贞　　洁

张晓峰　译

几乎没有任何东西能与一支高档雪茄的滋味相媲美。我年轻的时候很穷，只有偶尔别人送我一支我才能过过烟瘾。我当时下定决心要是有了钱，我一定要在每天午饭和晚饭后都美美地吸上一支雪茄。说起来，这还是我年轻时所做的决定中唯一坚持下来的一个，也是唯一一个我实现了并从未因幻灭而怨恨的抱负。我喜欢那种香味浓郁但又不太冲的雪茄，长度不能太短，太短的话，在你品出滋味前，烟就吸没了；也不能太长，太长的话又会让你感到厌烦。雪茄烟卷的松紧也要正好。过紧的话吸起来费力，过松的话，吸到最后，嘴边就会变得肮脏不堪。只有这样一支雪茄，吸完之后，你才会有一种意犹未尽的感觉。但是当你吸完最后一口，扔掉残剩的烟蒂，望着眼前渐渐消逝于周围空气中的最后一缕烟雾时，如果你是一个感性之人，一想到这支雪茄所经历的那些劳动、养护，还有苦心，以及为了提供给你这半小时的欢愉所必需的复杂工序随着雪茄的燃尽都化为乌有，你不难产生一种伤感之情。对常年在热带阳光的灼烤下汗流浃背，乘船走遍了七大洋的这类人而言，吃着一打牡蛎（就着半瓶干白葡萄酒），这种伤感就更加强烈了。如果将牡蛎换成羊排，这种感伤之情就会强烈得让人难以承受。因为羊是一种动物。你不禁要想了，自打地球表面有了生物，又经过了亿万年的变迁，动物们经过无数代繁衍的结果就是它们最终被码放到盛满碎冰的盘子上，或置于银质烤肉架上。也许嘴里嚼着一只牡蛎难以让你产生这种极端严肃的联想。我们通过生物进化的知识知道，这种双壳类生物千百万年来几乎没有变化，因而难以获得人类的同情。这种生物以一种超然的态度生活在地球上，简直就是对我们人类进取精神的一种冒犯；这种生物志得意满地躺在那里，让我们自负的人类顿生厌恶之情。但如果眼前是一盘羊排，恐怕所有人都会被激发出无限的遐思：毕竟在羊这种动物的进化历史中，处处可见我们人类的影子，我们在餐桌上温柔的一小口与这种动物密不可分。

有时想想，即使我们人类的命运也同样令人难以捉摸。看看身边那些不起眼的普通人，不论他们是银行职员、清洁工还是站在合唱团第二排人到中年的老姑娘，都会让人产生一种好奇之感。我们不禁想到，人类是怎样从原生浆液开始，经过冗长的历史变迁与生命的演化，经过一长串灾变事件，成了现在他们各自的样子？当这样巨大的兴衰变迁造就了此时的他们，你不禁要想，这些人的身上一定寄托着某种巨大的意义，你也一定会想，无论这些人的生活中遇到了什么难事，与生命精神或其他造就了他们生命的事物相比，都是小事一桩。思路突然中断了。正想着世界的起源，突然又想起了别的事情，似乎这两者之间没有任何联系。这简直就是个白痴在讲故事！如果不是这件事情有些稀奇古怪，情节又颇具戏剧性，谁还能在这里听我啰里啰唆讲这些琐碎之事呢？

一件本来也许不会发生的小事却产生了重大的后果，这真是谁也无法料到。看起来所有的事情都全靠运气。我们一个最细微的活动也许就能对他人的一生产生重大的影响，而这些人却和我们毫不相干。如果不是某天我走到了街对面，我在这里要讲的故事根本就不会发生。生活有时真的很不可思议，只有具备特别的幽默感的人才能品味出其中的乐趣。

一个春日的上午，我正在邦德大街上无所事事地闲逛。到中午的时候，我突然想起应该到索斯比拍卖行去看看，看是否有自己感兴趣的东西在拍卖。现在街上正堵车，我穿过拥堵的车辆，走到街道另一侧时，碰到了一个我在婆罗洲时认识的男人。他刚刚从一家衣帽店走出来。

“你好啊，莫顿，”我向他打招呼道，“什么时候回的国啊？”

“我回国大约有一星期了吧。”

他是一个地方官员。英属北婆罗洲总督给我写了一封介绍信去见他。我在信中告诉他，我打算在他那里待上一个星期，应该是住在政府开办的招待所。当我乘船到达那里的时候，他到船上接我，让我同他住。我不同意他的安排，我无法同一个完全陌生的人在一起待一个星期，我也不想让他为我破费。此外，我想自己一个人住招待所会更自由一些。但他不听我的解释。

“我家有很多空房间，”他说道，“而且招待所的条件很糟糕。我已经整整六个月没有跟一个白种人说话了，我周围那帮人让我烦透了。”

当我跟莫顿乘坐汽艇上岸，回到他住的平房后，他请我喝了一杯。面对我这个客人，他有些手足无措。他突然感到有些窘迫，说话的语气也不自然了。我尽力让他感觉像在家一样（但这是他自己的家，原本不该由我来这样做）。我问他有没有新唱片，他打开留声机，拉格泰姆的曲调响了起来，他这才恢复了自信。

他的平房可以俯瞰蜿蜒而过的河流，他的客厅设在一个大阳台上。客厅内的家具陈设非常呆板，与房主经常变换工作地点的政府官员的身份相衬。墙上挂着一些装饰品，包括当地人戴的各种帽子，还有各种动物的角、吹管和长矛；书架上则搁着侦探小说和旧杂志。客厅内还有一架立式小钢琴，琴键已经有些发黄了。客厅内虽说非常凌乱，但待着还算舒服。

不幸的是，我记不太清他当时是什么模样了。他很年轻，我后来了解到他当时只有二十八岁。他笑起来像个大男孩，很是迷人。我同他在一起待了一个星期，感觉很愉快。我俩沿着河来回溜达，一起去爬山。一天，我俩还同几个种植园主一起吃了午饭，这些种植园主居住在离这里二十英里远的地方。每天晚上我们都去俱乐部玩。这家俱乐部仅有的会员是当地一家鞣酸加工厂的经理和他的助手。但他们之间关系密切，很少与外人往来。只是在莫顿提出抗议，说他带了客人来，他们不能让他没面子的情况下，他们才同意与我俩打一局桥牌，但气氛并不友好。我俩从俱乐部回到住处吃晚饭，听听音乐，之后就上床睡觉了。莫顿很少待在办公室办公。你会以为他的生活一定很沉闷，但他却一天到晚精力充沛、情绪高昂。他是第一次出任这类职务，很高兴自己能够独立完成一项工作。他唯一感到焦虑的是在他督建的这条公路完工前，自己就会被调到其他地方去。他是发自内心地喜爱这项工作。是他提议修建这条公路，然后哄着当局拿出钱来让他督建这条公路的。他亲自勘察、测绘，独自解决了施工中出现的技术难题。每天早上去办公室之前，他都要开着那辆快要散架的旧福特车到施工现场转转，查看前一天的施工进度。他心无旁骛，甚至连晚上做梦都梦到这条路。他预计这条公路能在一年内完工，在完工之前他不想被调离。即便是画家或雕刻家创作一件艺术作品时也没有他现在这么高的热情。我想，正是他的这股热情让我喜欢上了他。我喜欢他对工作的热情，喜欢他的诚恳朴实。他为了完成这项工作已经达到了忘我的地步，孤独的生活，是否能得到提拔，甚至连回国的事，对他而言都无关紧要了。我忘了这段公路有多长，大概有十五到二十英里吧；我也忘了修这条公路的目的是什么，我想莫顿也不大关心修这条公路的目的。他对这项工作的热情就像艺术家的热情一样，他是抱着征服大自然的目的去完成这项工作的，而在这个过程中他学到了知识。他要与热带雨林抗争，倾盆暴雨会将几个星期的施工顷刻冲毁，道路测量时也会出现种种问题。他要负责招募和组织施工队，而且还要面对资金短缺的难题。他靠想象力支撑着自己。他的工作就如同一部宏大的史诗，工作中的酸甜苦辣如同一部有着无数情节的英雄传奇故事。

他唯一抱怨的事情是白日太短。白天他有公务。他是法官，也是收税员；在他满二十八岁后还成了所属教区的教父和教母，他要不时离开家到各处去走访。除非他盯在施工现场，否则工程根本不会有进展。他恨不得一天二十四个小时都待在工地上督促那些一心磨洋工的劳工更加卖力地工作。碰巧我到那里的前不久就发生了一件使他非常高兴的事。他曾提出将这条道路的一段分包给一个中国人，但这个包工头要价太高，超过了莫顿的预算。经过漫长的讨价还价之后，他们还是无法达成协议。眼看着道路施工的进度无法完成，莫顿心中火冒三丈，但却无计可施。然而一天早上来到办公室后，他听说昨天晚上在一家中国人开办的赌场中发生了一起斗殴事件。一名中国苦力在斗殴中受了重伤，肇事者已经被逮捕，而这名肇事者正是那个包工头。包工头被起诉了，证据确凿，莫顿判了他服劳役八个月。

“现在他还得去修这条该死的路，而且一分钱也拿不到了。”莫顿告诉我这个故事的时候，两眼闪闪发光。

一天上午，我们看见了这个正在干活的家伙。他身着犯人们穿的纱笼，冷漠地干着活儿。他泰然地接受了自己这种倒霉的命运。

“我告诉过他，如果道路能早日完成，我就免除他剩余的刑期，”莫顿说道，“他非常高傲，竟然拒绝了。其实这对我来说不是小事一桩吗，是不是？”

当我与莫顿告别时，我让他回国后一定要和我联系。他向我保证一回国就立马给我写信。一个人可能会在一时冲动之下发出这类邀请，而另一人可能完全是非常真诚地对待这件事。但是当后者真把这件事当真了，则前者多少会感到有些惊愕。人们经常在回国后与他们在海外时完全判若两人。在海外时他们表现得平易近人、热忱不做作。他们会有很多有趣的事告诉你，他们会对你非常友好。你会非常急于做点儿什么，以此来表示自己对所受的热情款待的感激之情。但真要回报起来却很难。有些人很善于当东家，他们会让客人有种宾至如归的感觉。但他们却可能是些让人乏味的客人。他们会紧张，很腼腆。当你把他们介绍给自己的朋友时，你的朋友们会认为他们乏味至极。你的朋友们会尽量表现得礼貌一些。但这些陌生人一走，朋友们就会宽慰地舒一口气，谈话也会再次恢复到往常那种轻松的氛围。我想，那些早早就参加了工作，生活在边远地区的人对此会感受更深一些，因为他们从中得到的是苦涩和羞辱感。因为我发现，那些居住在深林边缘，在远离总部的分支机构工作的人很少接受别人的邀请。尽管这些邀请非常诚挚，他们自己当初也是非常真心地接受了邀请，但他们还是不会践约。但莫顿不同，他是一个年轻的单身汉。通常这些人的妻子更难参与社交活动。其他女人只要扫一眼她们身上穿的土气服装，看看她们的神态，就能知道她们是外省人，然后用冷漠的态度将她们晾在一边。但一个男人还可以玩玩桥牌、打打网球、跳跳舞。莫顿的气质很迷人，只要有一两天时间，他就能适应这种环境，对此我毫不怀疑。

“你回国了怎么不告诉我呢？”我问他道。

“我想，你可能并不想被我打扰。”他笑着说。

“真是胡说八道。”

我们就这样站在邦德大街的路边说了一会儿话，当然在我看来他变化很大。我在他那里的时候，他从来都只穿卡其色的短裤和一件网球衫，只有在晚上我俩从俱乐部回到住处后，他才会换上一件睡衣上装，和一条纱笼来吃晚饭。这身装束可以说是迄今为止人类所发明的服装中，穿着最舒适的晚间服装了。现在他身穿一身蓝哔叽西装，显得有些拘束。在雪白衬衣领子的衬托下，他的面孔更显黝黑了。

“那条路修得怎么样了？”我问道。

“修完了。我一直担心工程不能按时完工，耽误我回国的行程。快完工的时候遇到了一两个障碍，但我督促他们往前抢进度。我在回国的前一天开着那辆福特车在这条路上从头跑到尾，一路都没有停车。”

我大笑起来。他高兴的样子很迷人。

“你回伦敦后都在忙些什么？”

“买衣服。”

“玩得开心吗？”

“很开心。就是有点儿孤单，这你知道。但我并不在意。我每晚都去看一场演出。帕尔默一家就要回伦敦了。我想你在沙捞越[1]时见过他们。我们打算一起玩玩。但他俩要先回苏格兰，因为帕尔默夫人的母亲病了。”

他的话虽然是轻描淡写，但却刺到了我的痛处。他们这类人都有这样共同的经历。这种经历让人想想就心碎。离回国还有好几个月的时间，他们就开始制订回国的计划；当他们离船踏上伦敦的土地时，他们会兴奋得难以自制。伦敦！这里到处都是商店、俱乐部、剧院和餐厅。伦敦！他们将在这里生活下去了。伦敦！他们将淹没于其中。伦敦对他们而言是一个陌生而混乱的城市，没有敌意，但充满了冷漠，而他们迷失在了这里。他们在这里没有朋友，他们与在这里结交的熟人没有任何共同之处。他们在这里比在丛林中更感孤独。如果在剧院碰上了一个他们在东方认识的熟人，他们会感到十分欣慰（或许对方却对此深感厌烦，极为反感）。他们也许会约好在某个晚上见面，在欢声笑语中回味他们在一起时的快乐时光，谈论共同的朋友，最后还会相互透露一点儿自己当年的小秘密。当然过后也不会为此而后悔。当他们要分手的时候，他们还会约定下次见面的时间。他们会相互拜访对方的家庭，当然也很高兴见到彼此的家人。但今非昔比，环境已经不同了，他们会感到自己有点儿像是个局外人。你最终意识到伦敦人的生活就是这样死气沉沉。回国的确令人兴趣盎然，但现在你真的无法再忍受这里的生活了。有时你会想念自己俯瞰河流的平房，想念自己当初在那里旅游的生活。那些在蓝色的月光下造访山打根[2]、古晋[3]或新加坡的日子是多么快乐呀。

我想起当初莫顿对我倾吐的期望。当时他说，一旦公路完工，了却了心事，他就要请假回国。而现在他回到了伦敦，但他却是一个人凄凉地坐在一家没有任何熟人的俱乐部里吃晚饭，或者孤单单地在苏活区的一家餐厅，吃完饭就去看电影。看电影也是自己一个人，甚至没有人在放映间隙里陪他喝上一杯。想到这里，我的心中泛起一阵剧痛。与此同时，我也想到，即使我知道他回到了伦敦，我也帮不上什么忙。上个星期我忙得不可开交。就在我要出国的头天晚上，我还陪朋友吃了饭，看了一场电影。

“今晚你怎么安排的？”我问他道。

“我打算上布莱顿酒店去吃饭。那里经常是人满为患，难得订到一个座位。但路对过有一个很有本事的家伙，他给我预订了一个座位。当然那是别人推掉的。你知道，即使难于弄到两个退座，弄到一张退座还是不难。”

“你为什么不过来和我一起吃晚饭呢？今晚我要跟几个朋友一起在干草市场饭店吃饭。饭后我们要去席罗兹俱乐部玩。”

“那好啊。”

我们约定十一点见面。然后我与他分手去赴一个约会。

我有些担心今晚我让莫顿见的那些朋友不太能让他尽兴，因为他们全都是清一色的中年人。但我实在想不出在一年中的这个季节还有哪个年轻人能被我抓来应应急，也想不出有哪个我熟识的姑娘乐于答应我，去陪一个腼腆的从马来亚来的年轻人吃饭和跳舞。不过我相信毕肖普夫妇能够尽他们所能来帮他。不管怎么说，能有几个人在一家俱乐部里陪他吃晚饭，还能在那里看美女们跳舞，应该能讨他开心，这比他自己一个人在半夜十一点就回家上床睡觉强多了。因为他在这里也没有其他地方可去了。当我还是一个医学院的学生时，我就认识了查理·毕肖普。他那时长得又瘦又小，一头浅褐色头发，相貌平平。他虽然有一双又黑又亮的漂亮眼睛，却戴了一副眼镜。他红红的圆脸盘总是一副快乐模样。他非常喜爱美女。我想他应该自有办法和莫顿相处，因为即便没钱没长相，他却总能设法召集一帮年轻人，随他一起到各地去旅游。他人很聪明，但颇为自负，而且好争论，性子急，说话很刻薄。回过头来想想，我敢说当时的他是一个不那么好处的年轻人，但我并不觉得他很讨厌。现在他已经五十五岁了，身材见胖，光头一个，但金边眼镜下的一双眼睛依然机敏有神。说话还是那么武断，甚至有些自以为是；依旧好争论，一嘴的刻薄；但他脾气很好，而且言语幽默。当这样一个人成了你的老朋友后，他的这些习性就不会再惹恼你了。你会容忍他的这些毛病，就如同容忍自己的身体缺陷一样。他是一个病理学家。他时不时会送我一本他刚刚出版的、薄薄的书。书的内容非常专业，配有大量的细菌照片做插图。这些书我都没有读过。从我时不时听来的消息来看，查理的学术观点是错误的。我想他不怎么受他同行们的待见。他毫不掩饰自己对同行们的看法，认为他们都是一些不称职的傻瓜。但他一直做着病理学家这份工作，这让他一年有六百至八百英镑的收入。我想，他并不在乎别人对他的看法。

我喜欢查理·毕肖普这个人，因为我已经与他相识三十年了；我也喜欢他妻子马热丽，因为她人非常好。当他告诉我他打算结婚的时候，我感到非常惊讶。当时他四十出头，且用情不专。因此我当时断定，他恐怕要打一辈子光棍了。他非常喜欢女人，但绝不感情用事，他也并不特别在意要哪一类型的女人。他对女性的评价在理想主义盛行的当今会被认为是粗俗的。他知道自己需要什么，也会去争取。无论是出于爱还是出于金钱，如果无法得到他想要的，他就会耸耸肩膀，一走了之。简言之，他并不需要女人来满足自己精神上的理想，只要提供给他肉体上的欢愉即可。奇怪的是，尽管他又瘦又小，相貌平平，却能找到如此多心甘情愿让他遂意的女人。至于精神上的需求，他能够从单细胞生物中得到满足。他是一个说话切中要害的人。当他告诉我要与一个叫马热丽·霍布森的年轻女人结婚时，我当即问他为什么。他咧嘴一笑。

“有三方面原因，”他说，“首先，我不跟她结婚，她就不跟我上床；其次，她能让我笑得像土狗一样；第三，她在这个世界无依无靠，没有一个亲人，必须有人来照顾她。”

“第一个理由你只是在炫耀，第二个理由是空话，第三个才是真正的原因。看来你已经任由她摆布了。”

他的双眼在他那副大眼镜下温和地闪烁着。

“你这家伙，什么事都能一眼看穿。”

“你现在不仅对她百依百顺，而且还为此扬扬得意。”

“明天过来吃午饭，认识认识她。她长得挺好看的。”

查理是一家不限男女的俱乐部的会员。那时我也经常出入这家俱乐部。我们约定明天在那里吃饭。我发现马热丽是一个非常吸引人的年轻女人，那时她快满三十了，很有修养。这让我很满意，同时也有几分吃惊。因为查理通常只对那些不太有教养的女人感兴趣，这一点逃不过我的眼睛。她的长相虽说不上多好，但挺标致，有一头漂亮的黑发和一双漂亮的眼睛。肤色白皙，看起来很健康。她说话非常率直，让人听起来很舒服。她看起来是一个诚实、单纯、可信任的人。我立马就喜欢上了她。她很容易交谈，对于别人所说的，虽然她并没有什么独到见解，但她马上就能领悟其中的可笑之处，而且她还是一个爽朗之人。她留给人们的印象是能干和务实。她的快活平和说明她有一个好脾气，而且悟性很高。

他们俩似乎对彼此非常满意。我第一次见到她时，曾自问：为什么马热丽要嫁给这样一个脾气暴躁的小个子男人？他不仅已经开始谢顶，而且也不年轻了。但我很快就发现了答案，她爱这个男人。他俩经常互相揶揄，然后哈哈大笑；他俩的目光不时相对，眼神意味深长，似乎在传递只有他俩才能理解的信息。这真是令人感动呢。

一个星期后，他俩就在一家结婚登记处办理了结婚手续。这桩婚姻非常美满。十六年后的现在回味起来，想到嬉闹使他俩结合在一起，我还禁不住要同情地窃笑一番。我从未见过如此恩爱有加的一对夫妇，虽然经济上始终不很宽裕，但却其乐融融。他们没有什么远大的抱负，生活对他们而言就像一次永远不会结束的野餐。他俩住在潘通大街的一处公寓内，是我所见过的最小的公寓，包括一间小卧室、一间小客厅和一间厨卫并用的房间。但他俩没有家的观念。他们通常去饭馆吃饭，只有早点才在公寓吃。这里只是他俩睡觉的地方。他们的小家布置得很舒适，只是来个客人喝杯掺苏打水的威士忌时，房间就会显得有点儿拥挤了。马热丽雇了一个按日付薪的清洁女工，将房间打扫得非常整洁。只是查理邋遢惯了，对此感到有些不大适应。室内的所有设施几乎都是两人共用的。他俩还有一辆微型轿车，只要查理休假，他俩就会钻进汽车穿过海峡，开始旅行。每人一个大袋子就能把所有的行李都打包好，想上哪儿就上哪儿。如果路上车坏了他俩也从不烦恼，遇到了坏天气也当作一件开心的事，就是轮胎爆了，他们也只当是又出了一桩笑话，如果迷了路，不得不在野外过夜，他俩就会把这视为最快活的一天。

查理仍然是好争论，脾气暴躁，但马热丽总能保持着平和的态度。她一句话就能使他冷静下来，再说几句就能使他笑起来。她为他关于鲜为人知的细菌的专著打字，从科学杂志中寻找资料。有一次我问他们吵过架没有。

“没有，”她回答道，“我俩似乎从来没有什么要吵的。查理的脾气好极了。”

“胡说，”我反驳道，“他是个蛮横、好斗、脾气暴躁的家伙，他一直都是这样。”

她看看自己的丈夫，咯咯地笑了。我明白她认为我是在开玩笑。

“让他胡言乱语，”查理说道，“他是个无知透顶的笨蛋，他甚至都不知道自己在胡说些什么。”

他俩在一起的时候非常甜蜜，非常享受对方的陪伴。他俩尽可能地待在一起。即使在结婚很久之后，查理依旧每天中午开车到城西，与马热丽在一家餐厅一起用餐。如果有人请他俩到乡间去度个周末，马热丽就会写信给女主人，询问是否能为他俩准备一张双人床。如果行的话，他俩就会欣然接受邀请。人们常常为此有点儿阴阳怪气地善意取笑他俩。他俩在一起睡了这么多年，但还是不能分床睡。一般人可能都会对此感到有点儿尴尬。通常来说，丈夫与妻子不仅会在各自的卧室睡觉，如果要让他们共用一个卫生间，他们恐怕都会不高兴。现在一般人家的卧室都是单人间，但如果你要邀请毕肖普夫妇到你家做客暂住的话，一定要准备一个有双人床的客房。这在他俩的朋友圈子中已经人所共知。当然有些人认为他俩这样做不大合适，但满足他俩的这个要求并不麻烦。而且他们夫妇俩都讨人喜欢，满足他们的这个怪癖还是值得的。查理总是精神头十足，刻薄的说话方式很是风趣，马热丽娴静而随和，能请到他俩来做客，是一件让人感到快活的事情。而对他俩而言，没有什么能比两人在乡间漫步更惬意的了，他俩常常会走很远。

一个男人结婚后，他的妻子迟早会使他疏远他的老朋友，但马热丽反而使查理与朋友们的关系更近了。她不仅使他变得更能容忍别人，也使他成为一个更合群的人。让人忍俊不禁的是，他俩不像是一对已婚的夫妇，倒像是一对在一起生活的中年光棍。一般情况下都是六七个男人在争论和打趣，开着下流玩笑，而只有马热丽一个女人陪着他们。她在场不仅不会使他们感到拘束，反而使他们更开心。只要我回到英国，我肯定会去看望他俩。他们一般都在我前面提到的俱乐部吃饭。如果我有空的话，我就会与他俩一起用餐。

那天傍晚我与他们夫妇俩一起用过点心，之后我们又一起玩了一会儿。我告诉他俩，我已经邀请莫顿过来吃晚饭。

“他这个人可能有点儿乏味，”我解释道，“但他是一个很不错的小伙子。我在婆罗洲的时候，他待我非常好。”

“你为什么不早点儿告诉我？”马热丽嚷道，“这样我就会带个姑娘来的。”

“找个姑娘来干吗？”查理说，“这里不有你嘛。”

“我想，让一个小伙子跟我这么大岁数的女人跳舞，他不会很开心。”马热丽说。

“胡说八道！你的岁数跟跳舞有什么关系！”查理转过身来对我说道，“跟你跳过舞的女人中，有比她跳得更好的吗？”

答案当然是肯定的了，但她跳舞跳得确实很好，舞步非常轻盈，而且节奏感把握得非常好。

“从来没有。”我语气诚恳地说道。

我们三人到达席罗兹俱乐部的时候，莫顿已经在那里等着我们了。他穿着晚礼服，显得肤色更黑了。也许是我知道这些西装已经在一口铁皮箱中，伴着樟脑丸躺了四年的缘故，我总觉得他穿着西装有些不自然。他肯定还是身着卡其布的短衣短裤更感轻松自在一些。查理·毕肖普是个健谈的人，喜欢一个人说个不停，而莫顿却有几分腼腆。我给他要了一杯鸡尾酒，还要了点儿香槟。我感觉他会很乐意跳舞，但不知他是否想到可以请马热丽跳。我深深地感觉到了我们之间的代沟。

“我想我应该告诉你，毕肖普夫人可是一位出色的舞者。”

“是吗？”他有点儿脸红，“能否请您跳支舞？”

她站了起来，两人开始跳舞。那天晚上她的衣着看起来不仅是时髦，简直可以用绝美一词来形容了。我估计她那身很普通的黑色服装价值顶多不过六个金币，但穿在她身上，却使她显得像个贵妇人。她的腿形非常好看，而当时流行穿非常短的裙子，因此她得以受益其中。我想她可能化了点儿淡妆，但与其他女人相比，她看起来非常自然。她很适合短发，头发乌黑锃亮，没有一根白发夹杂其中。她的长相称不上漂亮，但她待人的亲切态度，她精神饱满的神态，她健康的身体都给你一种感觉，即便你没觉得她是一个漂亮的女人，至少也会认为她漂不漂亮都无关紧要。她跳完舞回到座位上后，双眼闪闪发光，脸色绯红。

“他跳得怎么样？”她丈夫问道。

“好极了。”

“您的舞也跳得很好，与您搭配非常轻松。”莫顿说道。

查理继续他滔滔不绝的演讲。他说起话来幽默讽刺，他之所以让人感到有趣，就是因为连他都对自己说的话兴趣盎然。但莫顿对他所说的话一无所知，尽管他出于礼貌摆出一副感兴趣的样子，但我可以看得出，欢快的气氛让他非常激动，他更关注音乐和香槟，而不是谈话。当舞曲声再次响起来的时候，他立即探寻地瞅瞅马热丽。查理捕捉到了他的目光，微笑起来。

“再跟他跳一曲，马热丽。看你跳舞对我的身体也有好处。”

他俩又去跳舞了。查理用爱恋的眼神瞅了她一眼。

“马热丽今天很开心。她非常喜欢跳舞，可我跟她跳舞就喘不上气来。这个小伙子不错。”

我的小派对很成功。当我和莫顿同毕肖普夫妇告别后，我俩一同步行前往皮卡迪利广场。在路上他非常真切地对我表示了感谢，他说他过得真的很愉快。我同他道了别。第二天早上，我就出国了。

我很遗憾自己没法为莫顿做多点儿事。我知道等我回到英国的时候，他可能正在返回婆罗洲的路上。我不时会想起他。但等到秋天我回到英国后，我已经完全忘记他了。大约在我回到伦敦一个星期后的一天晚上，我偶然到查理·毕肖普也是会员的那家俱乐部去玩，看到查理正与三四个我认识的男人坐在一起，我便走上前去。我这次回来后还没见过他们。其中一个人叫比尔·马什，他的妻子珍妮特是我的老朋友。他邀请我一起喝一杯。

“你上哪儿去了？”查理问道，“最近一直没有看到你。”

我立刻注意到查理喝醉了，我非常吃惊。查理喜欢喝酒，但他很有分寸，从来都不会喝过头。我俩都很年轻的时候，他偶尔也喝醉过，或许这件事比任何事都能说明他是一个多么伟大的人，况且把一个人年轻时偶尔喝过量的事翻出来是不公平的。但在我的记忆中，查理只要喝醉了就会丑态百出，他会更具攻击性，会变成一个声如洪钟的话痨，很容易跟人吵起来。他现在就是这样，说话武断，拒绝听取任何关于他鲁莽言辞的反对意见。其他人知道他喝醉了，一方面对他无理搅三分的劲儿感到生气，一方面又觉得既然他喝醉了，就不要与他计较了。他是一个很难相处的家伙。他这么大岁数了，有点儿发福，还秃了顶，戴着一副眼镜，却醉得一塌糊涂。他通常都是一副衣冠楚楚的模样，但现在却如此衣衫不整，全身沾满了烟灰。查理叫了服务生，又点了一杯威士忌。这个服务生已经在这家俱乐部工作了三十年。

“您桌上还有一杯呢，先生。”

“让你干啥你就干啥，”查理·毕肖普说道，“马上给我拿两杯威士忌来，否则我就要投诉你怠慢客人。”

“好吧，先生。”服务生说道。

查理端起桌上那杯威士忌，一饮而尽。但他的手有些颤抖，因此洒了一些酒在身上。

“好了，查理，老伙计，咱们该走了。”比尔·马什说道，然后他转身对我说，“查理今天来这里的时间不长。”

现在我感到更惊讶了，但我觉得有些地方不对劲儿，想着最好还是什么都不说。

“我这就走，”查理说，“但我走之前要再喝一杯。这样我今晚就能睡个好觉了。”

在我看来这个聚会没有马上散伙的意思，因此我站了起来，说我想走着回家了。

“我说，”看我要走，比尔说道，“明天晚上你过来跟我们一起吃饭，好不好？就我、珍妮特和查理三个人。”

“好的，我很高兴过来。”我答应道。

显然出了什么岔子。

马什夫妇住在摄政公园东侧的一排住房内，为我开门的女佣让我到马什先生的书房去，他正在那里等我。

“我想我最好还是在你上楼前跟你唠几句，”他一面与我握手一面说道，“你知道马热丽把查理给甩了吗？”

“当然不知道！”

“他对这始终不能释怀。珍妮特认为让他自己一个人郁郁寡欢地待在那套小公寓里太残酷了，因此我俩邀请了他到我们这里住一段时间。我们尽可能地为他料理好一切。他现在酗酒成狂，他已经失眠两个星期了。”

“她不会永远离开他吧？”

我感到非常震惊。

“她是要这样。为了一个叫莫顿的家伙，她简直疯了。”

“莫顿？哪个莫顿？”

我压根儿没想到他会是我在婆罗洲认识的那个朋友。

“该死的，就是你介绍的他，看你做的好事。现在咱俩上楼去，我想最好还是让你先明白一下自己的处境。”

他推开门，我俩走出了书房。我彻底糊涂了。

“可是，听我说。”我说。

“去问珍妮特，她了解整件事情。这件事真让我莫名其妙。我现在真受不了马热丽，查理这下肯定垮了。”

他引着我走进客厅。我进屋后，珍妮特·马什站起身，走上前来欢迎我。查理正坐在窗边看晚报，看我正朝他走去，他就把报纸放到一边，同我握握手。他十分清醒，说话依然是那种快活的语气，但我注意到他看起来状态很差。我们喝了一杯雪利酒，然后走下楼去吃饭。珍妮特是个精力十足的女人，她个子高挑，容貌姣好，她机警地使谈话持续进行下去。当我们几个男人要去喝杯葡萄酒的时候，她命令我们不许超过十分钟。比尔平时是一个沉默寡言的人，现在却在千方百计找话说。我恍然大悟。我刚才光顾着想到底出了什么事，却没有意会到他们夫妇的苦心。显然，马什夫妇是不想让查理陷入沉思，因此，我也尽力说些有趣的事。查理似乎也愿意尽量配合我们，他总是喜欢滔滔不绝地说个没完。现在，他正站在一个病理学家的角度，探讨最近公众热议的一起谋杀案，但他的话听起来干巴巴的。看来他现在干什么都没有心思了。你会感觉到他为了回应主人的好意正强迫自己说话，但他的心思却在别的地方。头顶上的地板令人欣慰地跺响了，这是珍妮特不耐烦的信号。这种场合最需要一个女人来缓解气氛了。我们走上楼去，一起打了会儿桥牌。时间很晚了，当我要与他们告别的时候，查理说他要送我到马里波恩路。

“查理，现在太晚了，你最好还是上床睡觉吧。”珍妮特说道。

“我睡觉前散散步，能睡得实一些。”他回答道。

她有些担心地瞅瞅他。但一个年岁已到中年的病理学教授要想出去走走，你是拦不住的。她眼睛一亮，瞥了一眼她丈夫。

“我想让比尔去散散步也无妨。”

我想这句话不大明智，女人们通常有点儿太爱管事。查理不高兴地瞅了她一眼。

“完全没必要把比尔也拖出去。”他口气坚决地说道。

“我一点儿也不想出去。”比尔笑着说道，“我累坏了，我要上床睡觉了。”

我想，我俩出去后，比尔·马什跟他妻子一定会拌几句嘴。

“他们俩对我真是太好了。”当我俩沿着栅栏向前走去的时候，查理对我说，“如果没有他们，我真不知道自己会干出什么蠢事来。我有两个星期没有合眼了。”

我对此表示遗憾，但并没有询问原因。我俩就这样静静地走了一段路。我猜他和我一起出来是想要告诉我这件事的来龙去脉，但我感觉他并不急于讲述。我渴望表达我的同情，但又担心说错话，我不想让自己看上去就像要从他那里获取信心一样。我不知道该怎样引导他说这件事，我相信他也不需要别人去引导，他不是一个说话爱绕圈子的人。我想他是在考虑怎么说才好。我们走到了街道的拐角处。

“你可以在前面的教堂打到出租车，”他说，“我要再溜达一会儿。晚安。”

他点点头，然后没精打采地走了。我大吃一惊，却又无可奈何，只能继续向前走，直到打到一辆出租车。第二天早上我正在洗澡，电话铃声响了起来。我在身上裹了一条毛巾，浑身湿漉漉地跑出来接了电话。电话是珍妮特打来的。

“好吧，你对这一切怎么看？”她问道，“看样子昨晚你跟查理一起待了很长时间啊。我听说他回家的时候已经凌晨三点了。”

“他在马里波恩大街就跟我分手了，”我回答道，“他什么也没跟我说。”

“是吗？”

珍妮特的语气中透露出她想要跟我长唠一阵，我猜她用的是床边的电话。

“听着，”我赶紧说，“我正洗澡呢。”

“噢，你在洗澡间安了一部电话？”她热情地问道，我甚至觉得她还有点儿羡慕。

“没有。”我斩钉截铁地说，言语有点儿鲁莽，“我把地毯都弄湿了。”

“哦！”我感到她的语气中有些失望，还有一点儿不高兴，“好吧，什么时候我可以见你？你能在十二点的时候来一趟吗？”

这个时间不太方便，但我不打算跟她争辩了。

“可以，再见。”

我不容她再说什么就把电话挂断了。天堂里的人们打电话时肯定也是一句废话也没有。

我很喜欢珍妮特，但我知道没什么事比她的朋友遭遇不幸更能让她兴奋的了。她只是太急于帮助他们，但她总想深入参与到他们的不幸之中。她是那种患难之交，她愿意卷入别人遇上的麻烦事，乐此不疲。如果你卷入了一场风流韵事，你会发现不知怎的她就成了你的红颜知己，或者如果你在闹离婚，你也会发现她多半会插一手。加之她的确是一个很不错的女人。第二天中午，当我被领进珍妮特的客厅时，她急不可耐地接待我的样子，让我不禁心中暗笑。她为毕肖普所遭遇的不幸大感悲痛，但这件事很刺激，能有一个让她把整件事的来龙去脉都一一相告的人，她简直高兴得要死。珍妮特期待这场谈话，就像一个母亲期待与家庭医生讨论她已婚女儿的第一次分娩一样。珍妮特知道这件事很严重，她也从未轻看这件事，她打定主意要从这件事中挖掘出所有的快乐。

“我想，当马热丽告诉我，她已经打定主意要与查理分手时，没有谁比我更感震惊了。”她非常流利地说道。一个人只有一字不落地把这句话至少说上十来遍，才能达到这种流利程度。“他俩是我所认识的人中关系最密切的一对了。他们一见如故，缔结了一桩美满的婚姻。当然，比尔和我的关系很不错，但我俩也要不时地大吵一顿。我想，我有时真想杀了他。”

“我对你与比尔的关系一点儿兴趣都没有，”我说道，“跟我说说毕肖普夫妇的关系吧。我过来就是想听这个的。”

“我只是感觉得要见见你，毕竟你是唯一能把这件事解释清楚的人。”

“噢，上帝，千万别这么说。如果不是前天晚上比尔告诉我，我对这件事一无所知。”

“是我让他先告诉你的。我突然想到你也许还不知道这件事，我担心你冒冒失失地说错话。”

“你就从头说起吧。”我说道。

“好吧，就从你开始吧。不管怎么说，你是这场麻烦的始作俑者，你向他俩介绍了那个年轻人，这也是我为什么急着见你的原因。你非常了解这个人，而我从来没有见过他，我对他的了解全来自于马热丽告诉我的那些话。”

“你几点吃午饭？”我问道。

“一点半。”

“我也是。接着讲这个故事吧。”

但我的话使珍妮特有了一个主意。

“听我说，如果我退掉我的午餐的话，你会退掉你的吗？我们可以在这里吃点儿便餐。我这里还有一些冷盘肉，这样我们就不用着急了。我三点钟去做头发，这样我们就有的是时间了。”

“别，别，别。”我连忙拒绝，“我不同意这个主意。我至多只能待到一点二十分。”

“那我就只能简单说了。你认为格里这个人怎么样？”

“谁是格里？”

“格里·莫顿。他的名字叫杰拉尔德。”

“这我哪知道？”

“你跟他在一起待过。他的住处没有什么信件吗？”

“可能有，但我不可能碰巧去读这些信。”我有些尖锐地回答道。

“别说这样的蠢话了，我指的是信封。他是一个什么样的人？”

“好吧。他有点儿像吉卜林，你知道这个类型的人是什么样。他工作非常卖力，为人真诚，是为大英帝国扩张疆土立下汗马功劳的人。”

“我说的不是这个意思。”珍妮特有点儿不耐烦地大声喊道，“我是说，他长得怎么样？”

“我想，他长得很普通。当然，如果我再次见到他，我应该还能认出他来，但我无法非常清晰地把他描绘出来。他看起来很干净。”

“噢，上帝，”珍妮特喊道，“你还是不是一个小说家了？他的眼睛是什么颜色的？”

“我不知道。”

“你肯定知道。你跟任何一个人在一起待上一个星期，都不可能不知道他的眼睛是蓝色还是棕色，他的皮肤是黑还是白？”

“既不太黑，也不太白。”

“他的个子是高还是矮？”

“我想应该算中等个儿吧。”

“你是故意想惹我发火吗？”

“绝对不是。他就是很普通，他身上没有任何地方能引起你的注意。他长得既不丑，也算不上英俊。他看起来很正派，像是个绅士。”

“马热丽说他长得很可爱，笑起来很迷人。”

“可能是这样。”

“他疯狂地爱上了她。”

“你是怎么得出这个结论的？”我冷淡地问道。

“我看过他写的信了。”

“你是说她把他写的信都给你看了？”

“这有什么奇怪吗？当然是了。”

对于一个男人来讲，他们很难忍受女人们将他们的隐私泄露给他人。这些女人真是不知廉耻，她们可以在一起谈论男女间最私密的事情而丝毫不感到尴尬。庄重是男性特有的美德，尽管一个男人知道这一点，但每逢女人们做出缺乏矜持之事的时候，他还是感到极为震惊。不仅是他的信件被马热丽和珍妮特·马什读了，而且连他迷恋于她的状况马丽热也逐日随时告知了珍妮特，我真想知道莫顿要是知道了这个情况，他会怎么想。根据珍妮特的描述，他对马热丽是一见钟情。他俩在席罗兹俱乐部我的那个小型晚餐聚会上相识后的第二天早上，他就给她打电话，邀请她过来，找一个能跳舞的地方跟他一起喝茶。我一边听着珍妮特的故事，一边想，她的叙述显然是根据马热丽的描述而来。我决定不带偏见地听下去。让我感兴趣的是，珍妮特同情的一方居然是马热丽。当马热丽抛弃了她的丈夫后，让查理过来跟他们一起住两三个星期是她的主意，她说免得他孤零零地待在那个小公寓内黯然伤神。珍妮特对查理照顾得也确实非常到位，几乎每天都陪他吃午饭，因为他已经习惯了每天都与马热丽一起吃午饭。她每天都陪他到摄政公园散步，让比尔在周日陪他打高尔夫球。她非常耐心地听他讲自己不幸的故事，尽可能地给他抚慰。她为他感到非常难过，但她照样明确地站在马热丽一边。当我表示不赞成她这样的做法时，她狠狠地训了我一顿。这件事让她非常兴奋。从一开始马热丽面有得色又犹疑不决地到她这里，微笑着告诉她，自己有了一个相好的年轻人，到最后马热丽怒气冲冲又心神不宁地来到她这里，宣布自己再也无法忍受这种压力，已经带着自己的行李离开了公寓，她都参与其中。

“当然，起初我也无法相信自己的耳朵。”她解释道，“你非常了解查理与马热丽，他俩简直就是形影不离，关系亲密到连别人都禁不住要笑话他们了。他这样一个矮小的男人，我从来都不认为有什么吸引力，但我无法不喜欢他，因为他对马热丽太好了。我有时甚至有些嫉妒她。他们没有钱，住的地方也是一片混乱，但他们非常快活。当然，我从没想过他俩的关系会出现问题。马热丽也只是把这当作一件有趣的事而已。‘我自然没有非常认真地对待这件事。’她对我说，‘但到了我这个年龄还能和一个年轻人在一起真的很有趣。已经有好多年没人给我送鲜花了。我告诉他不要再送了，因为查理会认为这样太愚蠢了。他在伦敦没有任何亲人和朋友，而且他喜欢跳舞。他说跟我跳舞就像在做一场梦。他总是自己一个人去电影院，真是太凄惨了。我俩一起看了两次日场电影。每次我答应与他一起出去时，他那副感激的样子真是太可怜了。’‘我得说，’我说，‘他听起来像只小羊羔。’‘没错，’她说，‘我知道你能理解我。你不会责怪我的，对吧？’‘当然不会，亲爱的。’我这样回答她，‘你对我还不了解吗？我要是处在你这样的情况下，也会这样做的。’”

马热丽并没有向她丈夫隐瞒她与莫顿出去游玩的事，而查理也只是打趣她对他的小男友温厚有加，但他认为莫顿是一个非常彬彬有礼、讲话讨人喜欢的小伙子，并且很高兴在自己忙碌的时候，能有个人陪着马热丽一起玩。他从未吃过莫顿的醋。他们三人还一起吃过几次饭，一起看了一场演出。但不久后，格里·莫顿恳求马热丽跟他独处一晚上。马热丽说这不可能，但他不断恳求，让她不得安宁。最后，有一天她找到珍妮特，让她帮忙给查理打电话，叫他晚上过来吃饭，并告诉他要打桥牌，独缺他一人。查理从不在晚上撇开妻子，一个人外出。但马什夫妇是他的老朋友了，而珍妮特又特别重视这件事。珍妮特编造了一些荒诞无稽的借口，让这个聚会看起来很重要，使查理无法缺席。第二天马热丽与她见了面，告诉她昨晚妙极了。他俩一起在梅登黑德饭店吃的饭，还跳了舞，然后在夏日的深夜开车回家。

“他说他疯狂地迷上了我。”马热丽这样告诉她。

“他吻你了吗？”珍妮特问道。

“当然吻了。”马热丽咯咯地笑道，“别说傻话了，珍妮特。他非常可爱，性格非常好。当然，我并不全信他对我说的话。”

“亲爱的，你不会爱上他了吧？”

“我已经爱上他了。”马热丽回答说。

“亲爱的，这不是要有点儿难办了吗？”

“这场恋情不会很长的，他秋天就要返回婆罗洲。”

“噢，你现在看上去确实年轻了好几岁。”

“这我知道，我也感觉自己年轻了好几岁。”

没过多久他俩就每天见面了。他俩在上午见面，然后一起到公园去散步，或者一起去美术馆。中午时分他俩就会分开，因为马热丽要陪她丈夫一起吃午饭。午餐后他俩又会一起开车去郊外兜风，或者开到河边的一处地方。这些事马热丽没有告诉她丈夫，她很自然地认为他无法理解。

“你怎么就从来没有见过莫顿呢？”我问珍妮特。

“哦，是她不让我见。你看，我跟马热丽属于同一代人，我完全能理解她的这个做法。”

“我明白了。”

“当然，我是尽可能帮她的忙。只要她跟格里出去时，她总是借口上我这儿来。”

我是一个非常注重细节的人。

“他们俩就没有做出轨的事吗？”我问道。

“哦，没有。马热丽不是那种人。”

“你怎么知道的？”

“如果真有这种事，她会告诉我的。”

“我猜她应该干了这样的事。”

“我当然问过她，但她断然否认了。我相信她对我说的是实话。他俩之间从来没有发生这类事。”

“对我来说这似乎有点儿难以理解。”

“好吧，你要知道，马热丽是一个很好的女人。”

我耸了耸肩膀。

“她对查理绝对忠诚，无论如何她都不会欺骗他，她不能忍受自己有任何瞒着查理的念头。当她意识到自己爱上了格里时，她马上就想把这件事告诉查理。我当然恳求她别这样做，我告诉她，这样做没有任何好处，只会让查理伤心。不管怎么说，这个小伙子两个月后就要走了，把一件不会持续很长时间的事闹得满城风雨不会有什么好处。”

但格里返程的日子越来越近，这促使了这个事件的爆发。毕肖普夫妇早已计划像往常一样出国去旅行，他们这次打算驾车穿越比利时、荷兰和德国北部。查理忙着寻找各地的地图和旅游手册，他从朋友们那里收集有关旅馆和道路的信息。他盼着自己的这个假期，像一个中学生一样兴奋不已。马热丽沮丧地听着他议论这次旅行。他俩要离开四个星期，而格里九月份就要乘船走了。她与格里在一起的时间本来就不长了，现在又要浪费掉这么长一段时间，这让她难以忍受。她一想起这趟驾车旅行就满腔怒火，随着假期一天天逼近，她的情绪也越来越不安。最终，她决定只能跟他摊牌了。

“查理，我不想进行这次旅行了。”一天，他正在跟她谈论刚听人说起的一家餐厅时，她突然打断了他的话，“我希望你找别人跟你一起去。”

他目瞪口呆地望着她。她也对自己刚才脱口而出的话感到吃惊，她的嘴唇微微颤抖起来。

“为什么？出什么事了吗？”

“没什么事，我就是不想去了，我想自己一个人待一段时间。”

“你生病了吗？”

她从他的眼神中看到了突然降临的恐惧，他的关心使她更加难以忍受。

“没有，我的人生中从未这么好过。我爱上了一个人。”

“你？你爱上谁了？”

“格里。”

他极为震惊地看着她，无法相信自己的耳朵。而她误解了他的表情。

“责怪我也没有用，我不由自主地就爱上了他。他几个星期后就要走了，我不想把这点儿宝贵的时间浪费掉。”他突然大笑起来。

“马热丽，你怎么这么傻呀？你的岁数差不多可以做他的母亲了。”她的脸红了。

“他也同样爱我。”

“他是这样告诉你的吗？”

“他这样说了无数遍。”

“他是一个该死的骗子，就是这么回事。”

他咯咯地笑个不停，他的胖肚子乐得直抖，他认为这是一个天大的笑话。我猜查理没有以恰当的方式对待他的妻子。珍妮特似乎认为查理应该表现出体贴和同情的态度，他应该理解这件事。我看到了她内心所想的场景：查理嘴唇紧绷，默默地伤心，最后宣布两人断绝关系。女人对他人表现出来的自我牺牲之美总是非常敏感。如果他勃然大怒，打碎一两件家什（当然，他还会买一件新的补上），或者朝马热丽的下巴重重地打上一拳，珍妮特也会对他表示同情。但嘲笑她却是不可原谅的错误。我没有指出，对于一个矮胖的、年龄已达五十五岁的病理学教授而言，要让他像一个洞穴人一样对突然的变故做出反应，这也太难了一点儿。不管怎么说，他俩预定去荷兰的旅行取消了，毕肖普夫妇在伦敦度过了八月份。他俩都不怎么开心。他俩的中饭和晚饭依然在一起吃，因为这么多年来他们早已习惯如此。而其余的时间马热丽都与格里一起度过。她与他在一起的时间极大地弥补了她所忍受的痛苦。查理喜欢开粗俗的玩笑，对她和格里百般挖苦、千般嘲弄，以此为乐事。他坚持拒绝严肃地对待这件事情。他很生马热丽的气，因为她如此愚蠢，但显然他从未想过她会不忠于自己。对此，我与珍妮特有不同的看法。

“他甚至从未怀疑这一点。”她说，“他太了解马热丽了。”

几个星期过去了，格里终于搭船离开了。他是从蒂尔伯里[4]上的船，马热丽为他送了行。她回来后哭了两天两夜。查理看着她，愈来愈生气，他的脾气变得非常暴躁。

“听我说，马热丽，”最后他说道，“我对你一直很有耐心，但现在你必须重新振作起来。这件事已经超过开玩笑的限度了。”

“你就不能让我自己待一会儿吗？”她喊道，“我什么都没有了，生活对我而言已经没有什么意义了。”

“别再犯傻了。”他说。

我不知道他还说了些别的什么话，但他将自己对格里的评价说给她听真是太不明智了。我推测他一定是用极其恶毒的语言描述了格里。他俩大吵了一架。以前他俩从未这样激烈地争吵过。她过去之所以能够忍受查理的冷嘲热讽，是因为她知道，再过一个小时或一天，她就又能见到格里了。而现在她永远也见不到格里了，她再也无法忍受这样的语言刺激了。她已经忍耐了几个星期，现在，她把自我控制抛到九霄云外去了，也许她根本就不知道自己都对查理喊了些什么。他本来就是一个脾气暴躁的人，最后他动手打了她一巴掌。这一巴掌将两人都吓了一跳。他抓起帽子，转身冲出了公寓。婚后尽管生活艰辛，但他们始终共享着一张床。但当他后半夜返回家中后，他发现她在客厅的沙发上为自己搭了一个地铺。

“你不能睡在这儿，”他说道，“别犯傻了，到床上睡去。”

“不，我不会去的。别管我。”

这一晚他俩接着争吵。但她已经打定主意，以后每晚都在沙发上睡。但公寓这么小，他俩谁也逃离不了对方，甚至对方的一举一动自己都能看见，对方说的话也都会灌进自己的耳朵里。他俩在一起亲密无间地生活了这么多年，出于本能他俩也要待在一起。他试图跟她讲清道理。他认为她傻得令人不可思议，不断跟她争吵，想要让她知道自己是多么执迷不悟。他不让她自己一个人待着，也不让她睡觉。他一讲就讲到后半夜，直到两人都筋疲力尽为止。他认为他能通过讲道理让她摆脱这场爱情。有一次，他俩两三天时间彼此都没有说话。一天，他回家后发现她正在痛哭。看到她在流泪，他乱了方寸。他告诉她，自己多么爱她。他回忆起两人这么多年来所度过的幸福时光，试图用这个办法来感动她。他想让这件事就这样过去。他许诺再也不提起格里了。他俩真的能忘记经历的这场噩梦吗？但这种隐含和解的想法使她感到恶心了。她对他说，自己头痛欲裂，让他给她拿瓶安眠药水来。第二天早上他出门的时候，她还假装在睡着。但他一离开家门，她就将自己的东西打包好，离开了公寓。她有几件继承来的廉价首饰，变卖掉这些首饰后，她手上有了一小笔钱。她在一家廉价寄宿公寓内租了一间屋，没有告诉查理自己的住址。

查理发现马热丽离开自己后就垮了，她的逃离所带来的打击彻底击溃了他。他告诉珍妮特，自己无法忍受这种孤独。他给马热丽写信，乞求她回来；他请珍妮特为他求情，他愿意做出任何保证，他卑躬屈膝，但马热丽执拗地不愿回去。

“你认为她终有一天会回去吗？”我问珍妮特。

“她说绝不回去。”

现在已经是近一点半了，我必须走了。我驾车向伦敦城另一端驶去。

两三天后，我收到了一通马热丽的电话留言，她问我能否见她一面，提议到我的住处来。我招待她喝了茶。我尽量对她表现得友好一些，虽说她的风流韵事与我无关，但我发自内心地认为她是一个愚蠢的女人。我猜自己的态度挺冷漠的。她的长相从来也称不上漂亮，流逝的岁月也改变不了这一点。她的一双黑眼睛还是那样好看，让人感到吃惊的是，她脸上一点儿皱纹都没有。她的穿着很普通，要是化了妆的话，那就太在行了，反正我没有看出来。她仍然透着那么一种魅力，让你觉得她是一个非常自然的人，一个和蔼中带着幽默的人。

“如果你愿意的话，我想请你为我做件事。”她开门见山，一点儿也不拐弯抹角。

“什么事？”

“查理今天就要离开马什夫妇的家，回到自己的公寓了，我担心他头几天会很难过，如果你能请他吃晚饭或陪他活动活动，那就太好了。”

“我得看看我的书。”

“据说他现在喝酒喝得很凶。他是在作践自己。我希望你能提醒提醒他。”

“据我所知，他最近是在为家里的事烦恼。”我说话的语气可能有几分讥讽的味道。

马热丽的脸红了，她痛苦地看了我一眼。她的脸部扭曲着，就好像我刚才给了她一拳似的。

“当然，你认识他的时间要远远超过认识我的时间，所以你自然会站在他的一边。”

“天哪，告诉你实话吧。这些年来我之所以熟悉了他，主要还是你的缘故呢。我从来都不太喜欢他，但我认为你的为人非常好。”

她对我笑了，她的笑容很甜。她知道我这个人说一不二。

“你认为对他而言我算是个好妻子吗？”

“绝对。”

“他经常惹得别人不高兴，很多人都不喜欢他，但我从来都没觉得他难处。”

“他非常喜欢你。”

“这我知道。我俩在一起的时候很美好。十六年来我俩都过得很幸福。”她停顿了一下，目光渐渐下移，“我不得不离开他，我俩不可能再在一起了，这种鸡犬不宁的生活太可怕了。”

“我从来都不明白为什么不想一起生活的两个人还要继续一起生活下去。”

“你瞧，这对我俩来说太可怕了。我俩的关系一直都非常亲密，从来都是难舍难弃。结果，现在我却不愿多看他一眼。”

“我想，目前你俩的处境都不容易。”

“我爱上了他人，这并非我的过错。你瞧，这与我对查理的爱完全不同。我对格里的爱包含着母爱，意在对他进行保护。我比查理要理性得多。他这个人很难相处，但我跟他相处得一直都很好。但格里不同。”她的声音变得温柔起来，她的面容也出现了光彩，因而显得有些漂亮了，“他让我重返青春了。对他来说我是个女孩，跟他在一起我有一种可以依靠的感觉，感到很安全。”

“我也认为他是一个不错的小伙子。”我语速很慢地说道，“我想他以后会过得很好的。我遇见他的时候，他的年纪于他所从事的工作而言着实太年轻了。他现在也才刚二十九岁，是不是？”

她温柔地笑了。她知道我说的是什么意思。

“我从未对他隐瞒过自己的年龄，他说这没有关系。”

我知道她说的是实情，她不是那种刻意隐瞒自己年龄的女人。她在告诉格里自己年龄的时候，曾感到这是一件极为快乐的事情。

“你今年多大了？”

“四十四岁。”

“现在你打算怎么办呢？”

“我已经给格里写了信，告诉他我已经离开了查理。只要我一收到他的回信，我就打算去跟他一起生活。”

“你要知道，他住在一个非常原始的小部落。我恐怕你会发现自己处于一个极为尴尬的位置。”

“他向我保证，如果在他离开之后我无法找到自己的生活，就去找他。”

“你将一个年轻人在爱的冲动下所说的话当真，做出了如此重大的决定，你确信这样明智吗？”

极度兴奋的表情又出现在她脸上，让她看起来真的很漂亮了。“是的，当这个年轻人碰巧是格里的时候。”

我的心情很沉重，我沉默了一会儿，然后向她讲了格里·莫顿督建那条公路的故事。我讲的有点儿夸张，我想这样效果会更好一些。

“你给我讲这个故事想说明什么呢？”我讲完后她这样问我。

“我只是想，这是一个不错的故事。”

她摇摇头，笑了。

“不，你是想通过这个故事来告诉我，他非常年轻，非常有热情。他是个工作狂，因此，他不会在其他兴趣上浪费太多时间。我不会影响他的工作。你对他的了解不如我，他非常浪漫，他将自己看成了一个开拓者，他对于自己亲自参与了一个新国家的开发而激动不已，连我都被他感染了。这难道不是一桩宏伟的事业吗？与之相比，我们在这里的生活真的很无聊和平庸。当然，那里的生活非常孤独，甚至连有一个中年妇女陪伴都变得很不错。”

“你打算嫁给他吗？”我问道。

“我完全听他的，我不想做任何他不愿意做的事。”

她说的话非常简洁，但她委曲求全的态度深深地打动了我。她走后，我感到自己已经不怨恨她了。当然，我依然认为她很愚蠢。但如果愚蠢的男人将一个女人惹怒了，那么这个女人将终其一生都处于长期愤怒的状态。我想一切都会过去的。她说格里非常浪漫，他确实如此，但在这个平凡的世界里，浪漫只是他们胡说八道的托词，因为他们实际上拥有一种敏锐的现实感，而最易受骗的则是那些只注重浪漫的表面意义而一意孤行的人。英国人很浪漫，所以其他国家的人都认为英国人虚伪。但英国人绝非都是些伪君子，他们是真心实意地想建立一个理想的天国。但这个过程是艰难的，英国人有理由在这个过程中学会任何能找到的稳当投资。英国人的心灵就像威灵顿将军旗下的大军一样，需要充足的物资保障。我想格里收到马热丽的信后会度过糟糕的十五分钟。我并非多么同情他，我只是想看他如何摆脱他所面临的这个困境。我想马热丽会经历一次痛不欲生的失望，好吧，这并不会对她造成太大的伤害，然后她就会回到她丈夫的身边。我相信经过这场磨难之后，他们俩会在一片和平、安宁和幸福之中度过余生。

这件事却不同寻常。碰巧最近几天我没可能与查理·毕肖普进行任何形式的约会，但我有写信给他，邀请他于下周的某个晚上跟我一起吃晚饭。虽然有些犹疑，但我还是提议饭后一起去看场戏剧。我知道他是个大酒鬼，如果喝高了，就会唠唠叨叨个没完。我希望他不会在剧院里被人讨厌。我们约定在我们所属的俱乐部碰头，七点左右开始吃饭。之所以定在这个时间，是因为我俩想去看的那场戏将在八点一刻开始演。我到了那里，坐下来等着他。但他没有来。我打电话到他公寓，也没人接，所以我估计他可能正在路上。我很烦错过戏剧的开头。我焦急地站在俱乐部的大厅等着，这样只要他一到，我俩就可以直接上楼了。为了节省时间，我已经点好了菜。时钟指向了七点半，然后是七点四十五。我认为没有必要再等下去了，因此就上楼进了餐厅，自己一个人吃了晚饭。他还是没有出现。我要了一个从餐厅接到马什夫妇家的电话，很快一个服务员过来告诉我，是比尔·马什接的电话。

“我说，你知道查理·毕肖普在哪里吗？”我说道，“我俩约好一起吃晚饭，然后去看戏，但他没来。”

“他今天下午死了。”

“什么？”

我大吃一惊，说话的语气引得周围两三个人都抬头看我。今天餐厅爆满，服务员都在不停地忙碌。电话放在收银员的柜台上。一名负责送酒水的服务员托着一个盘子走过来，盘子上放着一瓶霍克酒[5]和两个高脚玻璃杯，他递给收银员一张记账单。一个大块头服务员正引着两个男人前往一张餐桌，他挤了我一下。

“你在哪里打电话呢？”比尔问道。

我猜他听到了我周围盆盘刀叉撞击发出的声音。我告诉他后，他要我一吃完饭就马上到他那里去，说珍妮特有话要对我说。

“我马上过去。”我答应道。

我到达时比尔跟珍妮特正坐在客厅里，比尔在看报，珍妮特在玩单人纸牌游戏。当女佣把我领入后，她马上走了过来。她迈着跳跃的步伐，稍有点儿下蹲，但脚下不出动静，就像一头美洲狮在逼近猎物。我立即就看出来，她现在是如鱼得水，非常适应这种情况。她握住我的手，把脸扭到了一边，以免让我看到她溢满了眼泪的双眼。她说话的声音低沉，充满了悲痛之情。

“我把马热丽带回了我家，让她上床睡了。医生给她开了一剂安眠药，她全都服了进去。这件事太可怕了，是不是？”她说话的声音介于喘息和抽泣之间，“真不知为什么我的身边总出现这类事情。”

毕肖普夫妇一直没有雇做家务的用人，只是找了一个钟点工，每天早上过来打扫房间，清洗早饭后用过的刀叉碗碟等。钟点工有房门的钥匙。这天早上，她一如既往地打开房门，清扫客厅。自从他的妻子离开了他，查理的作息时间就变得非常混乱，因而看到他还在睡觉，她也没有感到意外。但上班的时间到了，她知道他需要去上班，还有工作等着他完成。她在卧室的门上敲了敲，但没有回答声。她认为自己听到他在呻吟，便急忙推开房门。他面朝上地躺在床上，打着呼噜。他还在睡着。她叫他，他身上的某些症状让她感到害怕。她来到对门的公寓，那里住着一名记者，她按门铃的时候他还在床上，穿着睡衣给她开了门。

“打搅您了，先生，”她说道，“您能不能过来一下，看看我的东家怎么了。我想他不大对劲。”

这个记者穿过过道，来到查理的公寓内。一个安眠药的空瓶子正放在床边。

“我想你最好还是找个警察来。”他说。

一个警察来了，他立即用电话向警局要了辆救护车。他们把毕肖普送到了查令十字街医院，但他再也没有恢复意识。他咽气的时候，马热丽陪在他的身边。

“警方当然要进行一番调查了，”珍妮特说道，“但这件事情很明显。最近三四个星期他严重失眠，我猜他一直在服用安眠药。他一定是意外地服用过量了。”

“马热丽也是这么认为的吗？”

“她的情绪非常不稳，脑子乱成了一锅粥，但我告诉她，我确信他不是自杀身亡的。我的意思是说，他不是这样想不开的人。我说得对吗，比尔？”

“没错，亲爱的。”

“他留下遗书没有？”

“没有，一个字都没有。奇怪的是，马热丽今天早上收到了他寄给她的一封信。哦，那几乎称不上一封信，就是一个字条。字条上只有一行字，‘亲爱的，没有你我太孤单了。’就这样。这张字条当然说明不了什么，她向我保证不对警察提这张字条的事。我的意思是说，让别人联想起其他事情来有什么好处？人人都知道，只要是扯上了安眠药，事情就说不清道不明了。不管出了什么事，我今后都不会服用安眠药了。这件事明显是个意外事故。我说得对吗，比尔？”

“没错，亲爱的。”他答道。

我看得出来，珍妮特坚信查理·毕肖普不是自杀而亡，但她内心里有几分相信她想去相信的事呢？我不是一个够格的女性心理学家，对此我分析不出来。当然，也许她是对的。一个中年科学家由于中年发妻离开了自己而自杀，这种假设太荒谬了。极有可能的情况是，由于饱受失眠的折磨，在极不理智的情况下，他服用了比他所想的剂量要大的安眠药。不管怎么说，验尸官的结论就是这样。他被告知，最近查理·毕肖普酗酒成瘾，导致了他妻子的离家出走。很明显，他求死心切。验尸官对死者的遗孀表达了同情，并反复强调了滥用安眠药的危险。

我不喜欢参加葬礼，但珍妮特恳求我这次一定要参加查理的葬礼。他生前所在医院的几个同事都意欲参加这个葬礼，但由于马热丽不同意，他们被劝阻了。参加葬礼的只有珍妮特、比尔、马热丽和我。我们要到太平间去接灵车。他们提议我就在家等着，他们上路后再打电话给我。我留意着车，当我看到车开过来时，就下了楼，但比尔下车后在我家门口堵住了我。

“稍候片刻，”他说，“我要跟你说点儿事。珍妮特要你在葬礼后到我家来吃茶点，她说让马热丽闷闷不乐地待着不好，我们可以一起打打桥牌。你能来吗？”

“就这些吗？”我问道。

我穿着燕尾服和晚礼服裤，系着一条黑领带。

“哦，就这些。这样可以让马热丽分分心。”

“好吧。”

但我们最后并没有打桥牌。一头美丽秀发的珍妮特相当聪明地展现了她的深切哀悼，她以高超的技巧扮演着一个富有同情心的朋友角色。她也流了一点儿泪，然后小心翼翼地擦了擦眼睛，以免碰到涂了睫毛膏的眼睫毛。当马热丽肝胆欲裂地哭泣的时候，珍妮特温柔地搂着她。当别人遇到麻烦的时候，她确实能帮帮忙。我们在葬礼后回到马什夫妇的家。这时有一封给马热丽的电报，她拿过电报上了楼。我以为这是查理的一位刚刚听说了他死讯的朋友发来的唁电。比尔去换衣服了，珍妮特和我来到客厅，我俩把桥牌桌抬了出来，她摘下帽子，并将它放到了钢琴上。

“虚伪过头没什么好处。”她说道，“虽说马热丽的情绪非常不稳，但她现在必须要振作起来，打打桥牌能让她恢复到正常的状态。当然了，我也为可怜的查理深感悲痛，但就查理而言，我想他从来就没有从马热丽离开他这件事中恢复过来。不可否认的是，现在对于马热丽来说，事情简单多了。今天早上她给格里打电话了。”

“说了些什么？”

“告诉他关于可怜的查理死了的事。”

这时女佣走进客厅。

“你能到楼上毕肖普夫人那儿去吗，太太？她想要见您。”

“当然，我这就去。”

她迅速离开了房间，我一个人被撂在了客厅。不久比尔走了过来，我俩喝了杯酒。最后，珍妮特回来了，她递给我一封电报。电报上写着：

看在上帝的面上等着信。

格里

“你认为这句话是什么意思？”她问我。

“就是这个意思嘛。”我回答道。

“愚蠢！我当然已经告诉了马热丽这句话没有别的意思，但她还是很担心。她肯定是通过电话告诉他查理已经死了。我想，她现在可能不会有心情打桥牌了。我的意思是说，在她丈夫刚举行完葬礼的当天就进行这种游戏不大合适。”

“确实，我同意。”我说道。

“当然他会发电报来。他肯定会这么做的，对不对？我们唯一能做的事情就是挺直了坐着，等他的信。”

我看再继续这场谈话已经没有任何意义了，于是我便告辞了。两天后，珍妮特打来电话，告诉我莫顿给马热丽发来了唁电。她将电报的内容逐字读给我听。

惊悉噩耗，不胜悲哀。望你节哀，多多保重。

爱你的

格里

“你怎么看这封电报？”她问我。

“内容很恰当啊。”

“他当然不能说自己高兴得要跳起来了，对不对？”

“要是那样的话就太不深沉了。”

“但他还是用上了‘爱你的’这三个字。”

我在头脑中想象着这两个女人怎样反复揣度着这两封电报，她们仔细琢磨每一个字的含义，从各种角度来进行分析。我几乎可以听见她俩无休无止的交谈声。

“如果他现在让马热丽感到失望，我不知道马热丽会出什么事。”珍妮特继续说道，“当然了，他是否是个绅士还有待观察。”

“别胡说了。”我说完这句话后就挂断了电话。

接下来的几天，我与马什夫妇一起吃过两次饭。马热丽看起来憔悴不堪，我猜她正在心急如焚地等着那封还在路上的信。悲痛和害怕的双重折磨让她骨瘦如柴，她现在看上去极度脆弱，不得不去看心理医生。之前她从未有过这样的举动。她变得非常和蔼，别人对她表示关心，她会非常感激，她的笑容里也没有了自信，甚至有点儿怯懦，带着无边的哀婉。她无助的样子非常惹人同情，但莫顿远在数千英里之外。一天早上，珍妮特又给我打来电话。

“信到了，马热丽说可以让你看这封信。你能马上过来一趟吗？”

她紧张的语气已经让我大致知道了信的内容。当我到达她家后，珍妮特立即把信递给了我。我读完了信。这封信的用词很谨慎，我猜莫顿写这封信时一定反复修改过。信的内容充满了抚慰，显然他为了避免说任何可能伤及马热丽的话煞费苦心，但信中还是流露出他心中的恐惧。显然他被这种情况吓得浑身发抖，显然他觉得应付这种局面的最好办法是用点儿玩世不恭的语言。他对那块殖民地上的白种人肆意取笑了一番。如果马热丽突然出现，他们会说些什么呢？他可能很快就会被炒鱿鱼。人们往往认为在东方的生活自由自在，非常轻松，但事实并非如此。这里的生活比克拉珀姆[6]还要紧张。他太爱马热丽了，以至于一想到那些可怕的女人对马热丽嗤之以鼻的情景，他就无法忍受。此外，他现在被派往一个驻地，那里离周围其他地方有十天的路程。她绝对无法在他住的小屋内生活下去，那里当然也没有旅馆。他得深入丛林中去工作，一去就是好几天。这里绝不是一个适于女人生活的地方。他告诉她，她对他有多么重要，但她没必要为他操心。他不禁想到，她要是能回到她丈夫身边就好了。如果他认为自己成了她跟她丈夫之间的障碍，他将永远也不会饶恕自己。是的，我完全相信，写这样一封信真是不易。

“他写这封信的时候当然不知道查理死了。我曾告诉马热丽，他这一死把一切都改变了。”

“她同意你的说法吗？”

“我想她现在有点儿失去了理智。你怎么看这封信？”

“哦，写得很明白，他不打算要她。”

“两个月前他可是拼死拼活地追求她呀。”

“此一时彼一时了。人的变化之快真是难料啊。对他而言，离开伦敦的这段时间感觉起来得有一年了。他又回到了老朋友之中，又开始了他过去感兴趣的事情。亲爱的，马热丽自欺欺人没有什么益处。他已经回到属于他自己的生活中了，那里没有她的份儿。”

“我已经建议她不要管这封信，直接找他去。”

“我倒希望她做个明白人，不要让自己断然遭拒。”

“那她怎么办呢？噢，这也太残酷了。她是这个世界上最好的女人，她真的是非常优秀。”

“你这样想就可笑了，正是她的优秀惹来了这些麻烦，她为什么要跟莫顿来场婚外情？查理本来可以不知道这件事，那样也就没有这些糟糕的后果了；她与莫顿本来可以度过一段快活的时光，然后当他离开时，他们应该意识到一段让人舒心的插曲也要有一个优美的终结，然后就这样分手。这段故事也能成为两人愉快的回忆；她本来可以心满意足地回到查理身边继续过安稳的生活，继续做她的贤妻。”

珍妮特噘起了嘴唇，她轻蔑地瞅了我一眼。

“但还有贞洁的问题要考虑呢，你懂吗？”

“让贞洁见鬼去吧，贞洁只能造成毁灭和不幸，简直一文不值。如果你愿意，你可以称这种行为为贞洁，我管它叫怯懦。”

“她不会在与查理一起生活的时候背叛他。虽然有些女人能干得出来，但她对这种念头感到厌恶。”

“天哪，她本来可以在肉体上对他不忠的同时选择在精神上对他保持忠诚。这种骗术对女人来说易如反掌。”

“你真是一个可恶的玩世不恭者。”

“如果客观地看问题和按常识处理生活中遇到的问题被称作玩世不恭，那我的的确确是一个玩世不恭者。如果你喜欢的话，也可以说我可恶。现在我们就来客观地分析分析。马热丽是一个中年妇女，查理也五十五岁了，他俩已经结婚十六年了，当一个小伙子对她百般殷勤的时候，她自然会昏了头，但不要把这称作爱情，这是一种生理学现象。她如果把他所说的任何一句话当真，那她就是一个傻瓜。说出这些甜言蜜语的不是他本人，而是他如饥似渴的性本能。他一直在忍受着性饥渴，在四年的时间里他没有碰过女人，至少是没有碰过白种女人。他当时是说了一些疯话，许了一些诺言，但她竟然当真了，这会毁了他，这太可怕了。他看中马热丽只是一个巧合，他想要她，因为得不到她而更想要她。我猜他把这当成了爱情。但我可以肯定地说，这只是淫欲。如果他俩真的上了床，查理现在就不会死，正是她该死的贞洁才引出了这一系列后果。”

“你怎么这么蠢呢？你没看出来她是身不由己？她只是不想成为一个放荡的女人。”

“比起自私的女人，我更喜欢放荡的女人，比起愚蠢的女人，我也更青睐水性杨花的女人。”

“噢！住嘴。我请你到这里来不是让你来胡说八道，说这些恶毒话的。”

“那你让我过来干什么？”

“格里是你的朋友，是你把他介绍给了马热丽。假使她陷入了困境，那也是他造成的，但你是这一切麻烦的根源，你有责任给他写信，告诉他，他必须对她负责任。”

“我要是这样做了那我才该死呢。”我回答道。

“那你最好就离开这里。”

我转身准备离开。

“好吧，无论如何，万幸的是查理买了个生命保险。”珍妮特说道。

听了这句话，我转过身来，对她说道：

“你还敢管我叫玩世不恭者？”

在这里我就不重复我甩给她的那些骂人话了。我一面谩骂，一面摔门而去。但珍妮特依然是那个非常不错的女人，我经常想，娶她做妻子一定非常有意思。

[1]　马来西亚的一个州。

[2]　又译“仙那港”，马来西亚东部一港口城市。

[3]　沙捞越州的首府。

[4]　蒂尔伯里（Tilbury），伦敦和英格兰东南部的主要集装箱港口，位于泰晤士河北岸。

[5]　霍克酒，德国莱茵区产的一种干白葡萄酒。

[6]　克拉珀姆（Clapham），伦敦西南部兰贝斯区的一个地名。

The Verger

There had been a christening that afternoon at St Peter's, Neville Square, and Albert Edward Foreman still wore his verger's gown. He kept his new one, its folds as full and stiff as though it were made not of alpaca but of perennial bronze, for funerals and weddings (St Peter's, Neville Square, was a church much favoured by the fashionable for these ceremonies) and now he wore only his second-best. He wore it with complacence, for it was the dignified symbol of his office, and without it (when he took it off to go home) he had the disconcerting sensation of being somewhat insufficiently clad. He took pains with it; he pressed it and ironed it himself. During the sixteen years he had been verger of this church he had had a succession of such gowns, but he had never been able to throw them away when they were worn out and the complete series, neatly wrapped up in brown paper, lay in the bottom drawers of the wardrobe in his bedroom.

The verger busied himself quietly, replacing the painted wooden cover on the marble font, taking away a chair that had been brought for an infirm old lady, and waited for the vicar to have finished in the vestry so that he could tidy up in there and go home. Presently he saw him walk across the chancel, genuflect in front of the high altar, and come down the aisle; but he still wore his cassock.

"What's he 'anging about for?" the verger said to himself. "Don't 'e know I want my tea?"

The vicar had been but recently appointed, a red-faced energetic man in the early forties, and Albert Edward still regretted his predecessor, a clergyman of the old school who preached leisurely sermons in a silvery voice and dined out a great deal with his more aristocratic parishioners. He liked things in church to be just so, but he never fussed; he was not like this new man who wanted to have his finger in every pie. But Albert Edward was tolerant. St Peter's was in a very good neighbourhood and the parishioners were a very nice class of people. The new vicar had come from the East End and he couldn't be expected to fall in all at once with the discreet ways of his fashionable congregation.

"All this 'ustle," said Albert Edward. "But give 'im time, he'll learn."

When the vicar had walked down the aisle so far that he could address the verger without raising his voice more than was becoming in a place of worship he stopped.

"Foreman, will you come into the vestry for a minute. I have something to say to you."

"Very good, sir."

The vicar waited for him to come up and they walked up the church together.

"A very nice christening, I thought, sir. Funny 'ow the baby stopped cryin' the moment you took him."

"I've noticed they very often do," said the vicar, with a little smile. "After all I've had a good deal of practice with them."

It was a source of subdued pride to him that he could nearly always quiet a whimpering infant by the manner in which he held it and he was not unconscious of the amused admiration with which mothers and nurses watched him settle the baby in the crook of his surpliced arm. The verger knew that it pleased him to be complimented on his talent.

The vicar preceded Albert Edward into the vestry. Albert Edward was a trifle surprised to find the two churchwardens there. He had not seen them come in. They gave him pleasant nods.

"Good afternoon, my lord. Good afternoon, sir," he said to one after the other.

They were elderly men, both of them, and they had been churchwardens almost as long as Albert Edward had been verger. They were sitting now at a handsome refectory table that the old vicar had brought many years before from Italy and the vicar sat down in the vacant chair between them. Albert Edward faced them, the table between him and them, and wondered with slight uneasiness what was the matter. He remembered still the occasion on which the organist had got into trouble and the bother they had all had to hush things up. In a church like St Peter's, Neville Square, they couldn't afford a scandal. On the vicar's red face was a look of resolute benignity, but the others bore an expression that was slightly troubled.

"He's been naggin' them, he 'as," said the verger to himself. "He's jockeyed them into doin' something, but they don't 'alf like it. That's what it is, you mark my words."

But his thoughts did not appear on Albert Edward's clean-cut and distinguished features. He stood in a respectful but not obsequious attitude. He had been in service before he was appointed to his ecclesiastical office, but only in very good houses, and his deportment was irreproachable. Starting as a page-boy in the household of a merchant-prince, he had risen by due degrees from the position of fourth to first footman, for a year he had been single-handed butler to a widowed peeress, and, till the vacancy occurred at St Peter's, butler with two men under him in the house of a retired ambassador. He was tall, spare, grave, and dignified. He looked, if not like a duke, at least like an actor of the old school who specialized in dukes' parts. He had tact, firmness, and self-assurance. His character was unimpeachable.

The vicar began briskly.

"Foreman, we've got something rather unpleasant to say to you. You've been here a great many years and I think his lordship and the general agree with me that you've fulfilled the duties of your office to the satisfaction of everybody concerned."

The two churchwardens nodded.

"But a most extraordinary circumstance came to my knowledge the other day and I felt it my duty to impart it to the churchwardens. I discovered to my astonishment that you could neither read nor write."

The verger's face betrayed no sign of embarrassment.

"The last vicar knew that, sir," he replied. "He said it didn't make no difference. He always said there was a great deal too much education in the world for 'is taste."

"It's the most amazing thing I ever heard," cried the general. "Do you mean to say that you've been verger of this church for sixteen years and never learned to read or write?"

"I went into service when I was twelve, sir. The cook in the first place tried to teach me once, but I didn't seem to 'ave the knack for it, and then what with one thing and another I never seemed to 'ave the time. I've never really found the want of it. I think a lot of these young fellows waste a rare lot of time readin' when they might be doin' something useful."

"But don't you want to know the news?" said the other churchwarden. "Don't you ever want to write a letter?"

"No, me lord, I seem to manage very well without. And of late years now they've all these pictures in the papers I get to know what's goin' on pretty well. Me wife's quite a scholar and if I want to write a letter she writes it for me. It's not as if I was a bettin' man."

The two churchwardens gave the vicar a troubled glance and then looked down at the table.

"Well, Foreman, I've talked the matter over with these gentlemen and they quite agree with me that the situation is impossible. At a church like St Peter's, Neville Square, we cannot have a verger who can neither read nor write."

Albert Edward's thin, sallow face reddened and he moved uneasily on his feet, but he made no reply.

"Understand me, Foreman, I have no complaint to make against you. You do your work quite satisfactorily; I have the highest opinion both of your character and of your capacity; but we haven't the right to take the risk of some accident that might happen owing to your lamentable ignorance. It's a matter of prudence as well as of principle."

"But couldn't you learn, Foreman?" asked the general.

"No, sir, I'm afraid I couldn't, not now. You see, I'm not as young as I was and if I couldn't seem able to get the letters in me 'ead when I was a nipper I don't think there's much chance of it now."

"We don't want to be harsh with you, Foreman," said the vicar. "But the churchwardens and I have quite made up our minds. We'll give you three months and if at the end of that time you cannot read and write I'm afraid you'll have to go."

Albert Edward had never liked the new vicar. He'd said from the beginning that they'd made a mistake when they gave him St Peter's. He wasn't the type of man they wanted with a classy congregation like that. And now he straightened himself a little. He knew his value and he wasn't going to allow himself to be put upon.

"I'm very sorry, sir, I'm afraid it's no good. I'm too old a dog to learn new tricks. I've lived a good many years without knowin' 'ow to read and write, and without wishin' to praise myself, self-praise is no recommendation, I don't mind sayin' I've done my duty in that state of life in which it 'as pleased a merciful providence to place me, and if I could learn now I don't know as I'd want to."

"In that case, Foreman, I'm afraid you must go."

"Yes, sir, I quite understand. I shall be 'appy to 'and in my resignation as soon as you've found somebody to take my place."

But when Albert Edward with his usual politeness had closed the church door behind the vicar and the two churchwardens he could not sustain the air of unruffled dignity with which he had borne the blow inflicted upon him and his lips quivered. He walked slowly back to the vestry and hung up on its proper peg his verger's gown. He sighed as he thought of all the grand funerals and smart weddings it had seen. He tidied everything up, put on his coat, and hat in hand walked down the aisle. He locked the church door behind him. He strolled across the square, but deep in his sad thoughts he did not take the street that led him home, where a nice strong cup of tea awaited him; he took the wrong turning. He walked slowly along. His heart was heavy. He did not know what he should do with himself. He did not fancy the notion of going back to domestic service; after being his own master for so many years, for the vicar and churchwardens could say what they liked, it was he that had run St Peter's, Neville Square, he could scarcely demean himself by accepting a situation. He had saved a tidy sum, but not enough to live on without doing something, and life seemed to cost more every year. He had never thought to be troubled with such questions. The vergers of St Peter's, like the popes of Rome, were there for life. He had often thought of the pleasant reference the vicar would make in his sermon at evensong the first Sunday after his death to the long and faithful service, and the exemplary character of their late verger, Albert Edward Foreman. He sighed deeply. Albert Edward was a non-smoker and a total abstainer, but with a certain latitude; that is to say he liked a glass of beer with his dinner and when he was tired he enjoyed a cigarette. It occurred to him now that one would comfort him and since he did not carry them he looked about him for a shop where he could buy a packet of Gold Flake. He did not at once see one and walked on a little. It was a long street, with all sorts of shops in it, but there was not a single one where you could buy cigarettes.

"That's strange," said Albert Edward.

To make sure he walked right up the street again. No, there was no doubt about it. He stopped and looked reflectively up and down.

"I can't be the only man as walks along this street and wants a fag," he said. "I shouldn't wonder but what a fellow might do very well with a little shop here. Tobacco and sweets, you know."

He gave a sudden start.

"That's an idea," he said. "Strange 'ow things come to you when you least expect it."

He turned, walked home, and had his tea.

"You're very silent this afternoon, Albert," his wife remarked.

"I'm thinkin'," he said.

He considered the matter from every point of view and next day he went along the street and by good luck found a little shop to let that looked as though it would exactly suit him. Twenty-four hours later he had taken it, and when a month after that he left St Peter's, Neville Square, for ever, Albert Edward Foreman set up in business as a tobacconist and newsagent. His wife said it was a dreadful come-down after being verger of St Peter's, but he answered that you had to move with the times, the church wasn't what it was, and 'enceforward he was going to render unto Caesar what was Caesar's. Albert Edward did very well. He did so well that in a year or so it struck him that he might take a second shop and put a manager in. He looked for another long street that hadn't got a tobacconist in it and when he found it, and a shop to let, took it and stocked it. This was a success too. Then it occurred to him that if he could run two he could run half a dozen, so he began walking about London, and whenever he found a long street that had no tobacconist and a shop to let he took it. In the course of ten years he had acquired no less than ten shops and he was making money hand over fist. He went round to all of them himself every Monday, collected the week's takings, and took them to the bank.

One morning when he was there paying in a bundle of notes and a heavy bag of silver the cashier told him that the manager would like to see him. He was shown into an office and the manager shook hands with him.

"Mr. Foreman, I wanted to have a talk to you about the money you've got on deposit with us. d'you know exactly how much it is?"

"Not within a pound or two, sir; but I've got a pretty rough idea."

"Apart from what you paid in this morning it's a little over thirty thousand pounds. That's a very large sum to have on deposit and I should have thought you'd do better to invest it."

"I wouldn't want to take no risk, sir. I know it's safe in the bank."

"You needn't have the least anxiety. We'll make you out a list of absolutely gilt-edged securities. They'll bring you in a better rate of interest than we can possibly afford to give you."

A troubled look settled on Mr. Foreman's distinguished face. "I've never 'ad anything to do with stocks and shares and I'd 'ave to leave it all in your 'ands," he said.

The manager smiled. "We'll do everything. All you'll have to do next time you come in is just to sign the transfers."

"I could do that all right," said Albert uncertainly. "But 'ow should I know what I was signin'?"

"I suppose you can read," said the manager a trifle sharply.

Mr. Foreman gave him a disarming smile.

"Well, sir, that's just it. I can't. I know it sounds funny-like, but there it is, I can't read or write, only me name, an' I only learnt to do that when I went into business."

The manager was so surprised that he jumped up from his chair.

"That's the most extraordinary thing I ever heard."

"You see, it's like this, sir, I never 'ad the opportunity until it was too late and then some'ow I wouldn't. I got obstinate-like."

The manager stared at him as though he were a prehistoric monster.

"And do you mean to say that you've built up this important business and amassed a fortune of thirty thousand pounds without being able to read or write? Good God, man, what would you be now if you had been able to?"

"I can tell you that, sir," said Mr. Foreman, a little smile on his still aristocratic features. "I'd be verger of St Peter's, Neville Square."

The Facts of Life

It was Henry Garnet's habit on leaving the city of an afternoon to drop in at his club and play bridge before going home to dinner. He was a pleasant man to play with. He knew the game well and you could be sure that he would make the best of his cards. He was a good loser; and when he won he was more inclined to ascribe his success to his luck than to his skill. He was indulgent, and if his partner made a mistake he could be trusted to find an excuse for him. It was surprising then on this occasion to hear him telling his partner with unnecessary sharpness that he had never seen a hand worse played; and it was more surprising still to see him not only make a grave error himself, an error of which you would never have thought him capable, but when his partner, not unwilling to get a little of his own back, pointed it out, insist against all reason and with considerable heat that he was perfectly right. But they were all old friends, the men he was playing with, and none of them took his ill-humour very seriously. Henry Garnet was a broker, a partner in a firm of repute, and it occurred to one of them that something had gone wrong with some stock he was interested in.

"How's the market today?" he asked.

"Booming. Even the suckers are making money."

It was evident that stocks and shares had nothing to do with Henry Garnet's vexation; but something was the matter; that was evident too. He was a hearty fellow, who enjoyed excellent health; he had plenty of money; he was fond of his wife, and devoted to his children. As a rule he had high spirits, and he laughed easily at the nonsense they were apt to talk while they played; but today he sat glum and silent. His brows were crossly puckered and there was a sulky look about his mouth. Presently, to ease the tension, one of the others mentioned a subject upon which they all knew Henry Garnet was glad to speak.

"How's your boy, Henry? I see he's done pretty well in the tournament."

Henry Garnet's frown grew darker.

"He's done no better than I expected him to."

"When does he come back from Monte?"

"He got back last night."

"Did he enjoy himself?"

"I suppose so; all I know is that he made a damned fool of himself."

"Oh. How?"

"I'd rather not talk about it if you don't mind."

The three men looked at him with curiosity. Henry Garnet scowled at the green baize.

"Sorry, old boy. You call."

The game proceeded in a strained silence. Garnet got his bid, and when he played his cards so badly that he went three down not a word was said. Another rubber was begun and in the second game Garnet denied a suit.

"Having none?" his partner asked him.

Garnet's irritability was such that he did not even reply, and when at the end of the hand it appeared that he had revoked, and that his revoke cost the rubber, it was not to be expected that his partner should let his carelessness go without remark.

"What's the devil's the matter with you, Henry?" he said. "You're playing like a fool."

Garnet was disconcerted. He did not so much mind losing a big rubber himself, but he was sore that his inattention should have made his partner lose too. He pulled himself together.

"I'd better not play any more. I thought a few rubbers would calm me, but the fact is I can't give my mind to the game. To tell you the truth I'm in a hell of a temper."

They all burst out laughing.

"You don't have to tell us that, old boy. It's obvious."

Garnet gave them a rueful smile.

"Well, I bet you'd be in a temper if what's happened to me had happened to you. As a matter of fact I'm in a damned awkward situation, and if any of you fellows can give me any advice how to deal with it I'd be grateful."

"Let's have a drink and you tell us all about it. With a K.C., a Home Office official and an eminent surgeon—if we can't tell you how to deal with a situation, nobody can."

The K.C. got up and rang the bell for a waiter.

"It's about that damned boy of mine," said Henry Garnet.

Drinks were ordered and brought. And this is the story that Henry Garnet told them.

The boy of whom he spoke was his only son. His name was Nicholas and of course he was called Nicky. He was eighteen. The Garnets had two daughters besides, one of sixteen and the other of twelve, but however unreasonable it seemed, for a father is generally supposed to like his daughters best, and though he did all he could not to show his preference, there was no doubt that the greater share of Henry Garnet's affection was given to his son. He was kind, in a chaffing, casual way, to his daughters, and gave them handsome presents on their birthdays and at Christmas; but he doted on Nicky. Nothing was too good for him. He thought the world of him. He could hardly take his eyes off him. You could not blame him, for Nicky was a son that any parent might have been proud of. He was six foot two, lithe but muscular, with broad shoulders and a slim waist, and he held himself gallantly erect; he had a charming head, well placed on the shoulders, with pale brown hair that waved slightly, blue eyes with long dark lashes under well-marked eyebrows, a full red mouth, and a tanned, clean skin. When he smiled he showed very regular and very white teeth. He was not shy, but there was a modesty in his demeanour that was attractive. In social intercourse he was easy, polite, and quietly gay. He was the offspring of nice, healthy, decent parents, he had been well brought up in a good home, he had been sent to a good school, and the general result was as engaging a specimen of young manhood as you were likely to find in a long time. You felt that he was as honest, open, and virtuous as he looked. He had never given his parents a moment's uneasiness. As a child he was seldom ill and never naughty. As a boy he did everything that was expected of him. His school reports were excellent. He was wonderfully popular, and he ended his career, with a creditable number of prizes, as head of the school and captain of the football team. But this was not all. At the age of fourteen Nicky had developed an unexpected gift for lawn tennis. This was a game that his father not only was fond of, but played very well, and when he discerned in the boy the promise of a tennis-player he fostered it. During the holidays he had him taught by the best professionals and by the time he was sixteen he had won a number of tournaments for boys of his age. He could beat his father so badly that only parental affection reconciled the older player to the poor show he put up. At eighteen Nicky went to Cambridge and Henry Garnet conceived the ambition that before he was through with the university he should play for it. Nicky had all the qualifications for becoming a great tennis-player. He was tall, he had a long reach, he was quick on his feet, and his timing was perfect. He realized instinctively where the ball was coming and, seemingly without hurry, was there to take it. He had a powerful serve, with a nasty break that made it difficult to return, and his forehand drive, low, long, and accurate, was deadly. He was not so good on the backhand and his volleying was wild, but all through the summer before he went to Cambridge Henry Garnet made him work on these points under the best teacher in England. At the back of his mind, though he did not even mention it to Nicky, he cherished a further ambition, to see his son play at Wimbledon, and who could tell, perhaps be chosen to represent his country in the Davis Cup. A great lump came into Henry Garnet's throat as he saw in fancy his son leap over the net to shake hands with the American champion whom he had just defeated, and walk off the court to the deafening plaudits of the multitude.

As an assiduous frequenter of Wimbledon Henry Garnet had a good many friends in the tennis world, and one evening he found himself at a City dinner sitting next to one of them, a Colonel Brabazon, and in due course began talking to him of Nicky and what chance there might be of his being chosen to play for his university during the following season.

"Why don't you let him go down to Monte Carlo and play in the spring tournament there?" said the Colonel suddenly.

"Oh, I don't think he's good enough for that. He's not nineteen yet, he only went up to Cambridge last October; he wouldn't stand a chance against all those cracks."

"Of course, Austin and von Cramm and so on would knock spots off him, but he might snatch a game or two; and if he got up against some of the smaller fry there's no reason why he shouldn't win two or three matches. He's never been up against any of the first-rate players and it would be wonderful practice for him. He'd learn a lot more than he'll ever learn in the seaside tournaments you enter him for."

"I wouldn't dream of it. I'm not going to let him leave Cambridge in the middle of a term. I've always impressed upon him that tennis is only a game and it mustn't interfere with work."

Colonel Brabazon asked Garnet when the term ended.

"That's all right. He'd only have to cut about three days. Surely that could be arranged. You see, two of the men we were depending on have let us down, and we're in a hole. We want to send as good a team as we can. The Germans are sending their best players and so are the Americans."

"Nothing doing, old boy. In the first place Nicky's not good enough, and secondly, I don't fancy the idea of sending a kid like that to Monte Carlo without anyone to look after him. If I could get away myself I might think of it, but that's out of the question."

"I shall be there. I'm going as the non-playing captain of the English team. I'll keep an eye on him."

"You'll be busy, and besides, it's not a responsibility I'd like to ask you to take. He's never been abroad in his life, and to tell you the truth, I shouldn't have a moment's peace all the time he was there."

They left it at that and presently Henry Garnet went home. He was so flattered by Colonel Brabazon's suggestion that he could not help telling his wife.

"Fancy his thinking Nicky's as good as that. He told me he'd seen him play and his style was fine. He only wants more practice to get into the first flight. We shall see the kid playing in the semi-finals at Wimbledon yet, old girl."

To his surprise Mrs. Garnet was not so much opposed to the notion as he would have expected.

"After all the boy's eighteen. Nicky's never got into mischief yet and there's no reason to suppose he will now."

"There's his work to be considered; don't forget that. I think it would be a very bad precedent to let him cut the end of term."

"But what can three days matter? It seems a shame to rob him of a chance like that. I'm sure he'd jump at it if you asked him."

"Well, I'm not going to. I haven't sent him to Cambridge just to play tennis. I know he's steady, but it's silly to put temptation in his way. He's much too young to go to Monte Carlo by himself."

"You say he won't have a chance against these crack players, but you can't tell."

Henry Garnet sighed a little. On the way home in the car it had struck him that Austin's health was uncertain and that von Cramm had his off-days. Supposing, just for the sake of argument, that Nicky had a bit of luck like that—then there would be no doubt that he would be chosen to play for Cambridge. But of course that was all nonsense.

"Nothing doing, my dear. I've made up my mind and I'm not going to change it."

Mrs. Garnet held her peace. But next day she wrote to Nicky, telling him what had happened, and suggested to him what she would do in his place if, wanting to go, he wished to get his father's consent. A day or two later Henry Garnet received a letter from his son. He was bubbling over with excitement. He had seen his tutor, who was a tennis-player himself, and the Provost of his college, who happened to know Colonel Brabazon, and no objection would be made to his leaving before the end of term; they both thought it an opportunity that shouldn't be missed. He didn't see what harm he could come to, and if only, just this once, his father would stretch a point, well, next term, he promised faithfully, he'd work like blazes. It was a very pretty letter. Mrs. Garnet watched her husband read it at the breakfast table; she was undisturbed by the frown on his face. He threw it over to her.

"I don't know why you thought it necessary to tell Nicky something I told you in confidence. It's too bad of you. Now you've thoroughly unsettled him."

"I'm sorry. I thought it would please him to know that Colonel Brabazon had such a high opinion of him. I don't see why one should only tell people the disagreeable things that are said about them. Of course I made it quite clear that there could be no question of his going."

"You've put me in an odious position. If there's anything I hate it's for the boy to look upon me as a spoil-sport and a tyrant."

"Oh, he'll never do that. He may think you rather silly and unreasonable, but I'm sure he'll understand that it's only for his own good that you're being so unkind."

"Christ," said Henry Garnet.

His wife had a great inclination to laugh. She knew the battle was won. Dear, oh dear, how easy it was to get men to do what you wanted. For appearance sake Henry Garnet held out for forty-eight hours, but then he yielded, and a fortnight later Nicky came to London. He was to start for Monte Carlo next morning, and after dinner, when Mrs. Garnet and her elder daughter had left them, Henry took the opportunity to give his son some good advice.

"I don't feel quite comfortable about letting you go off to a place like Monte Carlo at your age practically by yourself," he finished, "but there it is and I can only hope you'll be sensible. I don't want to play the heavy father, but there are three things especially that I want to warn you against: one is gambling, don't gamble; the second is money, don't lend anyone money; and the third is women, don't have anything to do with women. If you don't do any of those three things you can't come to much harm, so remember them well."

"All right, father," Nicky smiled.

"That's my last word to you. I know the world pretty well and believe me, my advice is sound."

"I won't forget it. I promise you."

"That's a good chap. Now let's go up and join the ladies."

Nicky beat neither Austin nor von Cramm in the Monte Carlo tournament, but he did not disgrace himself. He snatched an unexpected victory over a Spanish player and gave one of the Austrians a closer match than anyone had thought possible. In the mixed doubles he got into the semi-finals. His charm conquered everyone and he vastly enjoyed himself. It was generally allowed that he showed promise, and Colonel Brabazon told him that when he was a little older and had had more practice with first-class players he would be a credit to his father. The tournament came to an end and the day following he was to fly back to London. Anxious to play his best he had lived very carefully, smoking little and drinking nothing, and going to bed early; but on his last evening he thought he would like to see something of the life in Monte Carlo of which he had heard so much. An official dinner was given to the tennis-players and after dinner with the rest of them he went into the Sporting Club. It was the first time he had been there. Monte Carlo was very full and the rooms were crowded. Nicky had never before seen roulette played except in the pictures; in a maze he stopped at the first table he came to; chips of different sizes were scattered over the green cloth in what looked like a hopeless muddle; the croupier gave the wheel a sharp turn and with a flick threw in the little white ball. After what seemed an endless time the ball stopped and another croupier with a broad, indifferent gesture raked in the chips of those who had lost.

Presently Nicky wandered over to where they were playing trente et quarante, but he couldn't understand what it was all about and he thought it dull. He saw a crowd in another room and sauntered in. A big game of baccarat was in progress and he was immediately conscious of the tension. The players were protected from the thronging bystanders by a brass rail; they sat round the table, nine on each side, with the dealer in the middle and the croupier facing him. Big money was changing hands. The dealer was a member of the Greek Syndicate. Nicky looked at his impassive face. His eyes were watchful, but his expression never changed whether he won or lost. It was a terrifying, strangely impressive sight. It gave Nicky, who had been thriftily brought up, a peculiar thrill to see someone risk a thousand pounds on the turn of a card and when he lost make a little joke and laugh. It was all terribly exciting. An acquaintance came up to him.

"Been doing any good?" he asked.

"I haven't been playing."

"Wise of you. Rotten game. Come and have a drink."

"All right."

While they were having it Nicky told his friends that this was the first time he had ever been in the rooms.

"Oh, but you must have one little flutter before you go. It's idiotic to leave Monte without having tried your luck. After all it won't hurt you to lose a hundred francs or so."

"I don't suppose it will, but my father wasn't any too keen on my coming at all and one of the three things he particularly advised me not to do was to gamble."

But when Nicky left his companion he strolled back to one of the tables where they were playing roulette. He stood for a while looking at the losers' money being raked-in by the croupier and the money that was won paid out to the winners. It was impossible to deny that it was thrilling. His friend was right, it did seem silly to leave Monte without putting something on the table just once. It would be an experience, and at his age you had to have all the experience you could get. He reflected that he hadn't promised his father not to gamble, he'd promised him not to forget his advice. It wasn't quite the same, was it? He took a hundred-franc note out of his pocket and rather shyly put it on number eighteen. He chose it because that was his age. With a wildly beating heart he watched the wheel turn; the little white ball whizzed about like a small demon of mischief; the wheel went round more slowly, the little white ball hesitated, it seemed about to stop, it went on again; Nicky could hardly believe his eyes when it fell into number eighteen. A lot of chips were passed over to him and his hands trembled as he took them. It seemed to amount to a lot of money. He was so confused that he never thought of putting anything on the following round; in fact he had no intention of playing any more, once was enough; and he was surprised when eighteen again came up. There was only one chip on it.

"By George, you've won again," said a man who was standing near to him.

"Me? I hadn't got anything on."

"Yes, you had. Your original stake. They always leave it on unless you ask for it back. Didn't you know?"

Another packet of chips was handed over to him. Nicky's head reeled. He counted his gains: seven thousand francs. A queer sense of power seized him; he felt wonderfully clever. This was the easiest way of making money that he had ever heard of. His frank, charming face was wreathed in smiles. His bright eyes met those of a woman standing by his side. She smiled.

"You're in luck," she said.

She spoke English, but with a foreign accent.

"I can hardly believe it. It's the first time I've ever played."

"That explains it. Lend me a thousand francs, will you? I've lost everything I've got. I'll give it you back in half an hour."

"All right."

She took a large red chip from his pile and with a word of thanks disappeared. The man who had spoken to him before grunted.

"You'll never see that again."

Nicky was dashed. His father had particularly advised him not to lend anyone money. What a silly thing to do! And to somebody he'd never seen in his life. But the fact was, he felt at that moment such a love for the human race that it had never occurred to him to refuse. And that big red chip, it was almost impossible to realize that it had any value. Oh well, it didn't matter, he still had six thousand francs, he'd just try his luck once or twice more and if he didn't win he'd go home. He put a chip on sixteen, which was his elder sister's age, but it didn't come up; then on twelve, which was his younger sister's, and that didn't come up either; he tried various numbers at random, but without success. It was funny, he seemed to have lost his knack. He thought he would try just once more and then stop; he won. He had made up all his losses and had something over. At the end of an hour, after various ups and downs, having experienced such thrills as he had never known in his life, he found himself with so many chips that they would hardly go in his pockets. He decided to go. He went to the changers' office and he gasped when twenty thousand-franc notes were spread out before him. He had never had so much money in his life. He put it in his pocket and was turning away when the woman to whom he had lent the thousand francs came up to him.

"I've been looking for you everywhere," she said. "I was afraid you'd gone. I was in a fever, I didn't know what you'd think of me. Here's your thousand francs and thank you so much for the loan."

Nicky, blushing scarlet, stared at her with amazement. How he had misjudged her! His father had said, don't gamble; well, he had, and he'd made twenty thousand francs; and his father had said, don't lend anyone money; well, he had, he'd lent quite a lot to a total stranger, and she'd returned it. The fact was that he wasn't nearly such a fool as his father thought: he'd had an instinct that he could lend her money with safety, and you see, his instinct was right. But he was so obviously taken aback that the little lady was forced to laugh.

"What is the matter with you?" she asked.

"To tell you the truth I never expected to see the money back."

"What did you take me for? Did you think I was a cocotte?"

Nicky reddened to the roots of his wavy hair.

"No, of course not."

"Do I look like one?"

"Not a bit."

She was dressed very quietly, in black, with a string of gold beads round her neck; her simple frock showed off a neat, slight figure; she had a pretty little face and a trim head. She was made up, but not excessively, and Nicky supposed that she was not more than three or four years older than himself. She gave him a friendly smile.

"My husband is in the administration in Morocco, and I've come to Monte Carlo for a few weeks because he thought I wanted a change."

"I was just going," said Nicky because he couldn't think of anything else to say.

"Already!"

"Well, I've got to get up early tomorrow. I'm going back to London by air."

"Of course. The tournament ended today, didn't it? I saw you play, you know, two or three times."

"Did you? I don't know why you should have noticed me."

"You've got a beautiful style. And you looked very sweet in your shorts."

Nicky was not an immodest youth, but it did cross his mind that perhaps she had borrowed that thousand francs in order to scrape acquaintance with him.

"Do you ever go to the Knickerbocker?" she asked.

"No. I never have."

"Oh, but you mustn't leave Monte Carlo without having been there. Why don't you come and dance a little? To tell you the truth, I'm starving with hunger and I should adore some bacon and eggs."

Nicky remembered his father's advice, not to have anything to do with women, but this was different; you had only to look at the pretty little thing to know at once that she was perfectly respectable. Her husband was in what corresponded, he supposed, to the Civil Service. His father and mother had friends who were Civil Servants and they and their wives sometimes came to dinner. It was true that the wives were neither so young nor so pretty as this one, but she was just as ladylike as they were. And after winning twenty thousand francs he thought it wouldn't be a bad idea to have a little fun.

"I'd love to go with you," he said. "But you won't mind if I don't stay very long. I've left instructions at my hotel that I'm to be called at seven."

"We'll leave as soon as ever you like."

Nicky found it very pleasant at the Knickerbocker. He ate his bacon and eggs with appetite. They shared a bottle of champagne. They danced, and the little lady told him he danced beautifully. He knew he danced pretty well, and of course she was easy to dance with. As light as a feather. She laid her cheek against his and when their eyes met there was in hers a smile that made his heart go pit-a-pat. A coloured woman sang in a throaty, sensual voice. The floor was crowded.

"Have you ever been told that you're very good-looking?" she asked.

"I don't think so," he laughed. "Gosh," he thought, "I believe she's fallen for me."

Nicky was not such a fool as to be unaware that women often liked him, and when she made that remark he pressed her to him a little more closely. She closed her eyes and a faint sigh escaped her lips.

"I suppose it wouldn't be quite nice if I kissed you before all these people," he said.

"What do you think they would take me for?"

It began to grow late and Nicky said that really he thought he ought to be going.

"I shall go too," she said. "Will you drop me at my hotel on your way?"

Nicky paid the bill. He was rather surprised at its amount, but with all that money he had in his pocket he could afford not to care, and they got into a taxi. She snuggled up to him and he kissed her. She seemed to like it.

"By Jove," he thought, "I wonder if there's anything doing."

It was true that she was a married woman, but her husband was in Morocco, and it certainly did look as if she'd fallen for him. Good and proper. It was true also that his father had warned him to have nothing to do with women, but, he reflected again, he hadn't actually promised he wouldn't, he'd only promised not to forget his advice. Well, he hadn't; he was bearing it in mind that very minute. But circumstances alter cases. She was a sweet little thing; it seemed silly to miss the chance of an adventure when it was handed to you like that on a tray. When they reached the hotel he paid off the taxi.

"I'll walk home," he said. "The air will do me good after the stuffy atmosphere of that place."

"Come up a moment," she said. "I'd like to show you the photo of my little boy."

"Oh, have you got a little boy?" he exclaimed, a trifle dashed.

"Yes, a sweet little boy."

He walked upstairs after her. He didn't in the least want to see the photograph of her little boy, but he thought it only civil to pretend he did. He was afraid he'd made a fool of himself; it occurred to him that she was taking him up to look at the photograph in order to show him in a nice way that he'd made a mistake. He'd told her he was eighteen.

"I suppose she thinks I'm just a kid."

He began to wish he hadn't spent all that money on champagne at the nightclub.

But she didn't show him the photograph of her little boy after all. They had no sooner got into her room than she turned to him, flung her arms round his neck, and kissed him full on the lips. He had never in all his life been kissed so passionately.

"Darling," she said.

For a brief moment his father's advice once more crossed Nicky's mind and then he forgot it.

Nicky was a light sleeper and the least sound was apt to wake him. Two or three hours later he awoke and for a moment could not imagine where he was. The room was not quite dark, for the door of the bathroom was ajar, and the light in it had been left on. Suddenly he was conscious that someone was moving about the room. Then he remembered. He saw that it was his little friend, and he was on the point of speaking when something in the way she was behaving stopped him. She was walking very cautiously, as though she were afraid of waking him; she stopped once or twice and looked over at the bed. He wondered what she was after. He soon saw. She went over to the chair on which he had placed his clothes and once more looked in his direction. She waited for what seemed to him an interminable time. The silence was so intense that Nicky thought he could hear his own heart beating. Then, very slowly, very quietly, she took up his coat, slipped her hand into the inside pocket and drew out all those beautiful thousand-franc notes that Nicky had been so proud to win. She put the coat back and placed some other clothes on it so that it should look as though it had not been disturbed, then, with the bundle of notes in her hand, for an appreciable time stood once more stock-still. Nicky had repressed an instinctive impulse to jump up and grab her, it was partly surprise that had kept him quiet, partly the notion that he was in a strange hotel, in a foreign country, and if he made a row he didn't know what might happen. She looked at him. His eyes were partly closed and he was sure that she thought he was asleep. In the silence she could hardly fail to hear his regular breathing. When she had reassured herself that her movements had not disturbed him she stepped, with infinite caution, across the room. On a small table in the window a cineraria was growing in a pot. Nicky watched her now with his eyes wide open. The plant was evidently placed quite loosely in the pot, for taking it by the stalks she lifted it out; she put the banknotes in the bottom of the pot and replaced the plant. It was an excellent hiding-place. No one could have guessed that anything was concealed under that richly-flowering plant. She pressed the earth down with her fingers and then, very slowly, taking care not to make the smallest noise, crept across the room and slipped back into bed.

"Chéri," she said, in a caressing voice.

Nicky breathed steadily, like a man immersed in deep sleep. The little lady turned over on her side and disposed herself to slumber. But though Nicky lay so still his thoughts worked busily. He was extremely indignant at the scene he had just witnessed, and to himself he spoke his thoughts with vigour.

"She's nothing but a damned tart. She and her dear little boy and her husband in Morocco. My eye! She's a rotten thief, that's what she is. Took me for a mug. If she thinks she's going to get away with anything like that, she's mistaken."

He had already made up his mind what he was going to do with the money he had so cleverly won. He had long wanted a car of his own, and had thought it rather mean of his father not to have given him one. After all, a feller doesn't always want to drive about in the family bus. Well, he'd just teach the old man a lesson and buy one himself. For twenty thousand francs, two hundred pounds roughly, he could get a very decent second-hand car. He meant to get the money back, but just then he didn't quite know how. He didn't like the idea of kicking up a row, he was a stranger, in a hotel he knew nothing of; it might very well be that the beastly woman had friends there, he didn't mind facing anyone in a fair fight, but he'd look pretty foolish if someone pulled a gun on him. He reflected besides, very sensibly, that he had no proof the money was his. If it came to a showdown and she swore it was hers, he might very easily find himself hauled off to a police-station. He really didn't know what to do. Presently by her regular breathing he knew that the little lady was asleep. She must have fallen asleep with an easy mind, for she had done her job without a hitch. It infuriated Nicky that she should rest so peacefully while he lay awake worried to death. Suddenly an idea occurred to him. It was such a good one that it was only by the exercise of all his self-control that he prevented himself from jumping out of bed and carrying it out at once. Two could play at her game. She'd stolen his money; well, he'd steal it back again, and they'd be all square. He made up his mind to wait quite quietly until he was sure that deceitful woman was sound asleep. He waited for what seemed to him a very long time. She did not stir. Her breathing was as regular as a child's.

"Darling," he said at last.

No answer. No movement. She was dead to the world. Very slowly, pausing after every movement, very silently, he slipped out of bed. He stood still for a while, looking at her to see whether he had disturbed her. Her breathing was as regular as before. During the time he was waiting he had taken note carefully of the furniture in the room so that in crossing it he should not knock against a chair or a table and make a noise. He took a couple of steps and waited, he took a couple of steps more; he was very light on his feet and made no sound as he walked; he took fully five minutes to get to the window, and here he waited again. He started, for the bed slightly creaked, but it was only because the sleeper turned in her sleep. He forced himself to wait till he had counted one hundred. She was sleeping like a log. With infinite care he seized the cineraria by the stalks and gently pulled it out of the pot; he put his other hand in, his heart beat nineteen to the dozen as his fingers touched the notes, his hand closed on them and he slowly drew them out. He replaced the plant and in turn carefully pressed down the earth. While he was doing all this he had kept one eye on the form lying in the bed. It remained still. After another pause he crept softly to the chair on which his clothes were lying. He first put the bundle of notes in his coat pocket and then proceeded to dress. It took him a good quarter of an hour, because he could afford to make no sound. He had been wearing a soft shirt with his dinner jacket, and he congratulated himself on this, because it was easier to put on silently than a stiff one. He had some difficulty in tying his tie without a looking-glass, but he very wisely reflected that it didn't really matter if it wasn't tied very well. His spirits were rising. The whole thing now began to seem rather a lark. At length he was completely dressed except for his shoes, which he took in his hand; he thought he would put them on when he got into the passage. Now he had to cross the room to get to the door. He reached it so quietly that he could not have disturbed the lightest sleeper. But the door had to be unlocked. He turned the key very slowly; it creaked.

"Who's that?"

The little woman suddenly sat up in bed. Nicky's heart jumped to his mouth. He made a great effort to keep his head.

"It's only me. It's six o'clock and I've got to go. I was trying not to wake you."

"Oh, I forgot."

She sank back on to the pillow.

"Now that you're awake I'll put on my shoes."

He sat down on the edge of the bed and did this.

"Don't make a noise when you go out. The hotel people don't like it. Oh, I'm so sleepy."

"You go right off to sleep again."

"Kiss me before you go." He bent down and kissed her. "You're a sweet boy and a wonderful lover. Bon voyage."

Nicky did not feel quite safe till he got out of the hotel. The dawn had broken. The sky was unclouded, and in the harbour the yachts and the fishing-boats lay motionless on the still water. On the quay fishermen were getting ready to start on their day's work. The streets were deserted. Nicky took a long breath of the sweet morning air. He felt alert and well. He also felt as pleased as Punch. With a swinging stride, his shoulders well thrown back, he walked up the hill and along the gardens in front of the Casino—the flowers in that clear light had a dewy brilliance that was delicious—till he came to his hotel. Here the day had already begun. In the hall porters with mufflers round their necks and berets on their heads were busy sweeping. Nicky went up to his room and had a hot bath. He lay in it and thought with satisfaction that he was not such a mug as some people might think. After his bath he did his exercises, dressed, packed, and went down to breakfast. He had a grand appetite. No continental breakfast for him! He had grapefruit, porridge, bacon and eggs, rolls fresh from the oven, so crisp and delicious they melted in your mouth, marmalade, and three cups of coffee. Though feeling perfectly well before, he felt better after that. He lit the pipe he had recently learnt to smoke, paid his bill and stepped into the car that was waiting to take him to the aerodrome on the other side of Cannes. The road as far as Nice ran over the hills and below him was the blue sea and the coastline. He couldn't help thinking it damned pretty. They passed through Nice, so gay and friendly in the early morning, and presently they came to a long stretch of straight road that ran by the sea. Nicky had paid his bill, not with the money he had won the night before, but with the money his father had given him; he had changed a thousand francs to pay for supper at the Knickerbocker, but that deceitful little woman had returned him the thousand francs he had lent her, so that he still had twenty thousand-franc notes in his pocket. He thought he would like to have a look at them. He had so nearly lost them that they had a double value for him. He took them out of his hip-pocket into which for safety's sake he had stuffed them when he put on the suit he was travelling in, and counted them one by one. Something very strange had happened to them. Instead of there being twenty notes as there should have been there were twenty-six. He couldn't understand it at all. He counted them twice more. There was no doubt about it; somehow or other he had twenty-six thousand francs instead of the twenty he should have had. He couldn't make it out. He asked himself if it was possible that he had won more at the Sporting Club than he had realized. But no, that was out of the question; he distinctly remembered the man at the desk laying the notes out in four rows of five, and he had counted them himself. Suddenly the explanation occurred to him; when he had put his hand into the flower-pot, after taking out the cineraria, he had grabbed everything he felt there. The flower-pot was the little hussy's money-box and he had taken out not only his own money, but her savings as well. Nicky leant back in the car and burst into a roar of laughter. It was the funniest thing he had ever heard in his life. And when he thought of her going to the flower-pot some time later in the morning when she awoke, expecting to find the money she had so cleverly got away with, and finding, not only that it wasn't there, but that her own had gone too, he laughed more than ever. And so far as he was concerned there was nothing to do about it; he neither knew her name, nor the name of the hotel to which she had taken him. He couldn't return her money even if he wanted to.

"It serves her damned well right," he said.

This then was the story that Henry Garnet told his friends over the bridge-table, for the night before, after dinner when his wife and daughter had left them to their port, Nicky had narrated it in full.

"And you know what infuriated me is that he's so damned pleased with himself. Talk of a cat swallowing a canary. And d'you know what he said to me when he'd finished? He looked at me with those innocent eyes of his and said: 'You know, father, I can't help thinking there was something wrong about the advice you gave me. You said, don't gamble; well, I did, and I made a packet; you said, don't lend money; well, I did, and I got it back; and you said, don't have anything to do with women; well, I did, and made six thousand francs on the deal.'"

It didn't make it any better for Henry Garnet that his three companions burst out laughing.

"It's all very well for you fellows to laugh, but you know, I'm in a damned awkward position. The boy looked up to me, he respected me, he took whatever I said as gospel truth, and now, I saw it in his eyes, he just looks upon me as a drivelling old fool. It's no good my saying one swallow doesn't make a summer; he doesn't see that it was just a fluke, he thinks the whole thing was due to his own cleverness. It may ruin him."

"You do look a bit of a damned fool, old man," said one of the others. "There's no denying that, is there?"

"I know I do, and I don't like it. It's so dashed unfair. Fate has no right to play one tricks like that. After all, you must admit that my advice was good."

"Very good."

"And the wretched boy ought to have burnt his fingers. Well, he hasn't. You're all men of the world, you tell me how I'm to deal with the situation now."

But they none of them could.

"Well, Henry, if I were you I wouldn't worry," said the lawyer. "My belief is that your boy's born lucky, and in the long run that's better than to be born clever or rich."

Lord Mountdrago

Dr Audlin looked at the clock on his desk. It was twenty minutes to six. He was surprised that his patient was late, for Lord Mountdrago prided himself on his punctuality; he had a sententious way of expressing himself which gave the air of an epigram to a commonplace remark, and he was in the habit of saying that punctuality is a compliment you pay to the intelligent and a rebuke you administer to the stupid. Lord Mountdrago's appointment was for five-thirty.

There was in Dr Audlin's appearance nothing to attract attention. He was tall and spare, with narrow shoulders and something of a stoop; his hair was grey and thin; his long, sallow face deeply lined. He was not more than fifty, but he looked older. His eyes, pale-blue and rather large, were weary. When you had been with him for a while you noticed that they moved very little; they remained fixed on your face, but so empty of expression were they that it was no discomfort. They seldom lit up. They gave no clue to his thoughts nor changed with the words he spoke. If you were of an observant turn it might have struck you that he blinked much less often than most of us. His hands were on the large side, with long, tapering fingers; they were soft, but firm, cool but not clammy. You could never have said what Dr Audlin wore unless you had made a point of looking. His clothes were dark. His tie was black. His dress made his sallow lined face paler, and his pale eyes more wan. He gave you the impression of a very sick man.

Dr Audlin was a psycho-analyst. He had adopted the profession by accident and practised it with misgiving. When the war broke out he had not been long qualified and was getting experience at various hospitals; he offered his services to the authorities, and after a time was sent out to France. It was then that he discovered his singular gift. He could allay certain pains by the touch of his cool, firm hands, and by talking to them often induce sleep in men who were suffering from sleeplessness. He spoke slowly. His voice had no particular colour, and its tone did not alter with the words he uttered, but it was musical, soft, and lulling. He told the men that they must rest, that they mustn't worry, that they must sleep; and rest stole into their jaded bones, tranquillity pushed their anxieties away, like a man finding a place for himself on a crowded bench, and slumber fell on their tired eyelids like the light rain of spring upon the fresh-turned earth. Dr Audlin found that by speaking to men with that low, monotonous voice of his, by looking at them with his pale, quiet eyes, by stroking their weary foreheads with his long firm hands, he could soothe their perturbations, resolve the conflicts that distracted them, and banish the phobias that made their lives a torment. Sometimes he effected cures that seemed miraculous. He restored speech to a man who, after being buried under the earth by a bursting shell, had been struck dumb, and he gave back the use of his limbs to another who had been paralysed after a crash in a plane. He could not understand his powers; he was of a sceptical turn, and though they say that in circumstances of this kind the first thing is to believe in yourself, he never quite succeeded in doing that; and it was only the outcome of his activities, patent to the most incredulous observer, that obliged him to admit that he had some faculty, coming from he knew not where, obscure and uncertain, that enabled him to do things for which he could offer no explanation. When the war was over he went to Vienna and studied there, and afterwards to Zürich; and then settled down in London to practise the art he had so strangely acquired. He had been practising now for fifteen years, and had attained, in the speciality he followed, a distinguished reputation. People told one another of the amazing things he had done, and though his fees were high, he had as many patients as he had time to see. Dr Audlin knew that he had achieved some very extraordinary results; he had saved men from suicide, others from the lunatic asylum, he had assuaged griefs that embittered useful lives, he had turned unhappy marriages into happy ones, he had eradicated abnormal instincts and thus delivered not a few from a hateful bondage, he had given health to the sick in spirit; he had done all this, and yet at the back of his mind remained the suspicion that he was little more than a quack.

It went against his grain to exercise a power that he could not understand, and it offended his honesty to trade on the faith of the people he treated when he had no faith in himself. He was rich enough now to live without working, and the work exhausted him; a dozen times he had been on the point of giving up practice. He knew all that Freud and Jung and the rest of them had written. He was not satisfied; he had an intimate conviction that all their theory was hocus-pocus, and yet there the results were, incomprehensible, but manifest. And what had he not seen of human nature during the fifteen years that patients had been coming to his dingy back room in Wimpole Street? The revelations that had been poured into his ears, sometimes only too willingly, sometimes with shame, with reservations, with anger, had long ceased to surprise him. Nothing could shock him any longer. He knew by now that men were liars, he knew how extravagant was their vanity; he knew far worse than that about them; but he knew that it was not for him to judge or to condemn. But year by year as these terrible confidences were imparted to him his face grew a little greyer, its lines a little more marked, and his pale eyes more weary. He seldom laughed, but now and again when for relaxation he read a novel he smiled. Did their authors really think the men and women they wrote of were like that? If they only knew how much more complicated they were, how much more unexpected, what irreconcilable elements coexisted within their souls and what dark and sinister contentions afflicted them!

It was a quarter to six. Of all the strange cases he had been called upon to deal with Dr Audlin could remember none stranger than that of Lord Mountdrago. For one thing the personality of his patient made it singular. Lord Mountdrago was an able and a distinguished man. Appointed Secretary of Foreign Affairs when still under forty, now after three years in office he had seen his policy prevail. It was generally acknowledged that he was the ablest politician in the Conservative Party and only the fact that his father was a peer, on whose death he would no longer be able to sit in the House of Commons, made it impossible for him to aim at the premiership. But if in these democratic times it is out of the question for a Prime Minister of England to be in the House of Lords, there was nothing to prevent Lord Mountdrago from continuing to be Secretary for Foreign Affairs in successive Conservative administrations and so for long directing the foreign policy of his country.

Lord Mountdrago had many good qualities. He had intelligence and industry. He was widely travelled, and spoke several languages fluently. From early youth he had specialized in foreign affairs, and had conscientiously made himself acquainted with the political and economic circumstances of other countries. He had courage, insight, and determination. He was a good speaker, both on the platform and in the House, clear, precise, and often witty. He was a brilliant debater and his gift of repartee was celebrated. He had a fine presence: he was a tall, handsome man, rather bald and somewhat too stout, but this gave him solidity and an air of maturity that were of service to him. As a young man he had been something of an athlete and had rowed in the Oxford boat, and he was known to be one of the best shots in England. At twenty-four he had married a girl of eighteen whose father was a duke and her mother a great American heiress, so that she had both position and wealth, and by her he had had two sons. For several years they had lived privately apart, but in public united, so that appearances were saved, and no other attachment on either side had given the gossips occasion to whisper. Lord Mountdrago indeed was too ambitious, too hard-working, and it must be added too patriotic, to be tempted by any pleasures that might interfere with his career. He had, in short, a great deal to make him a popular and successful figure. He had unfortunately great defects.

He was a fearful snob. You would not have been surprised at this if his father had been the first holder of the title. That the son of an ennobled lawyer, a manufacturer, or a distiller should attach an inordinate importance to his rank is understandable. The earldom held by Lord Mountdrago's father was created by Charles II, and the barony held by the first Earl dated from the Wars of the Roses. For three hundred years the successive holders of the title had allied themselves with the noblest families of England. But Lord Mountdrago was as conscious of his birth as a nouveau riche is conscious of his money. He never missed an opportunity of impressing it upon others. He had beautiful manners when he chose to display them, but this he did only with people whom he regarded as his equals. He was coldly insolent to those whom he looked upon as his social inferiors. He was rude to his servants and insulting to his secretaries. The subordinate officials in the government offices to which he had been successively attached feared and hated him. His arrogance was horrible. He knew that he was a great deal cleverer than most of the persons he had to do with, and never hesitated to apprise them of the fact. He had no patience with the infirmities of human nature. He felt himself born to command and was irritated with people who expected him to listen to their arguments or wished to hear the reasons for his decisions. He was immeasurably selfish. He looked upon any service that was rendered him as a right due to his rank and intelligence and therefore deserving of no gratitude. It never entered his head that he was called upon to do anything for others. He had many enemies: he despised them. He knew no one who merited his assistance, his sympathy, or his compassion. He had no friends. He was distrusted by his chiefs, because they doubted his loyalty; he was unpopular with his party, because he was overbearing and discourteous; and yet his merit was so great, his patriotism so evident, his intelligence so solid, and his management of affairs so brilliant that they had to put up with him. And what made it possible to do this was that on occasion he could be enchanting; when he was with persons whom he considered his equals, or whom he wished to captivate, in the company of foreign dignitaries or women of distinction, he could be gay, witty, and debonair; his manners then reminded you that in his veins ran the same blood as had run in the veins of Lord Chesterfield; he could tell a story with point, he could be natural, sensible, and even profound. You were surprised at the extent of his knowledge and the sensitiveness of his taste. You thought him the best company in the world; you forgot that he had insulted you the day before and was quite capable of cutting you dead the next.

Lord Mountdrago almost failed to become Dr Audlin's patient. A secretary rang up the doctor and told him that his lordship, wishing to consult him, would be glad if he would come to his house at ten o'clock on the following morning. Dr Audlin answered that he was unable to go to Lord Mountdrago's house, but would be pleased to give him an appointment at his consulting-room at five o'clock on the next day but one. The secretary took the message and presently rang back to say that Lord Mountdrago insisted on seeing Dr Audlin in his own house and the doctor could fix his own fee. Dr Audlin replied that he only saw patients in his consulting-room and expressed his regret that unless Lord Mountdrago was prepared to come to him he could not give him his attention. In a quarter of an hour a brief message was delivered to him that his lordship would come not next day but one, but next day, at five.

When Lord Mountdrago was then shown in he did not come forward, but stood at the door and insolently looked the doctor up and down. Dr Audlin perceived that he was in a rage; he gazed at him, silently, with still eyes. He saw a big heavy man, with greying hair, receding on the forehead so that it gave nobility to his brow, a puffy face with bold regular features and an expression of haughtiness. He had somewhat the look of one of the Bourbon sovereigns of the eighteenth century.

"It seems that it is as difficult to see you as a Prime Minister, Dr Audlin. I'm an extremely busy man."

"Won't you sit down?" said the doctor.

His face showed no sign that Lord Mountdrago's speech in any way affected him. Dr Audlin sat in his chair at the desk. Lord Mountdrago still stood and his frown darkened.

"I think I should tell you that I am His Majesty's Secretary for Foreign Affairs," he said acidly.

"Won't you sit down?" the doctor repeated.

Lord Mountdrago made a gesture, which might have suggested that he was about to turn on his heel and stalk out of the room; but if that was his intentionhe apparently thought better of it. He seated himself. Dr Audlin opened a large book and took up his pen. He wrote without looking at his patient.

"How old are you?"

"Forty-two."

"Are you married?"

"Yes."

"How long have you been married?"

"Eighteen years."

"Have you any children?"

"I have two sons."

Dr Audlin noted down the facts as Lord Mountdrago abruptly answered his questions. Then he leaned back in his chair and looked at him. He did not speak; he just looked, gravely, with pale eyes that did not move.

"Why have you come to see me?" he asked at length.

"I've heard about you. Lady Canute is a patient of yours, I understand. She tells me you've done her a certain amount of good."

Dr Audlin did not reply. His eyes remained fixed on the other's face, but they were so empty of expression that you might have thought he did not even see him.

"I can't do miracles," he said at length. Not a smile, but the shadow of a smile flickered in his eyes. "The Royal College of Physicians would not approve of it if I did."

Lord Mountdrago gave a brief chuckle. It seemed to lessen his hostility. He spoke more amiably.

"You have a very remarkable reputation. People seem to believe in you."

"Why have you come to me?" repeated Dr Audlin.

Now it was Lord Mountdrago's turn to be silent. It looked as though he found it hard to answer. Dr Audlin waited. At last Lord Mountdrago seemed to make an effort. He spoke.

"I'm in perfect health. Just as a matter of routine I had myself examined by my own doctor the other day, Sir Augustus Fitzherbert, I dare say you've heard of him, and he tells me I have the physique of a man of thirty. I work hard, but I'm never tired, and I enjoy my work. I smoke very little and I'm an extremely moderate drinker. I take a sufficiency of exercise and I lead a regular life. I am a perfectly sound, normal, healthy man. I quite expect you to think it very silly and childish of me to consult you."

Dr Audlin saw that he must help him.

"I don't know if I can do anything to help you. I'll try. You're distressed?"

Lord Mountdrago frowned.

"The work that I'm engaged in is important. The decisions I am called upon to make can easily affect the welfare of the country and even the peace of the world. It is essential that my judgement should be balanced and my brain clear. I look upon it as my duty to eliminate any cause of worry that may interfere with my usefulness."

Dr Audlin had never taken his eyes off him. He saw a great deal. He saw behind his patient's pompous manner and arrogant pride an anxiety that he could not dispel.

"I asked you to be good enough to come here because I know by experience that it's easier for someone to speak openly in the dingy surroundings of a doctor's consulting-room than in his accustomed environment."

"They're certainly dingy," said Lord Mountdrago acidly. He paused. It was evident that this man who had so much self-assurance, so quick and decided a mind that he was never at a loss, at this moment was embarrassed. He smiled in order to show the doctor that he was at his ease, but his eyes betrayed his disquiet. When he spoke again it was with unnatural heartiness.

"The whole thing's so trivial that I can hardly bring myself to bother you with it. I'm afraid you'll just tell me not to be a fool and waste your valuable time."

"Even things that seem very trivial may have their importance. They can be a symptom of a deep-seated derangement. And my time is entirely at your disposal."

Dr Audlin's voice was low and grave. The monotone in which he spoke was strangely soothing. Lord Mountdrago at length made up his mind to be frank.

"The fact is I've been having some very tiresome dreams lately. I know it's silly to pay any attention to them, but—well, the honest truth is that I'm afraid they've got on my nerves."

"Can you describe any of them to me?"

Lord Mountdrago smiled, but the smile that tried to be careless was only rueful.

"They're so idiotic, I can hardly bring myself to narrate them."

"Never mind."

"Well, the first I had was about a month ago. I dreamt that I was at a party at Connemara House. It was an official party. The King and Queen were to be there and of course decorations were worn. I was wearing my ribbon and my star. I went into a sort of cloakroom they have to take off my coat. There was a little man there called Owen Griffiths, who's a Welsh Member of Parliament, and to tell you the truth, I was surprised to see him. He's very common, and I said to myself: 'Really, Lydia Connemara is going too far, whom will she ask next?' I thought he looked at me rather curiously, but I didn't take any notice of him; in fact I cut the little bounder and walked upstairs. I suppose you've never been there?"

"Never."

"No, it's not the sort of house you'd ever be likely to go to. It's a rather vulgar house, but it's got a very fine marble staircase, and the Connemaras were at the top receiving their guests. Lady Connemara gave me a look of surprise when I shook hands with her, and began to giggle; I didn't pay much attention, she's a very silly, ill-bred woman and her manners are no better than those of her ancestor whom King Charles II made a duchess. I must say the reception rooms at Connemara House are stately. I walked through, nodding to a number of people and shaking hands; then I saw the German Ambassador talking with one of the Austrian Archdukes. I particularly wanted to have a word with him, so I went up and held out my hand. The moment the Archduke saw me he burst into a roar of laughter. I was deeply affronted. I looked him up and down sternly, but he only laughed the more. I was about to speak to him rather sharply, when there was a sudden hush and I realized that the King and Queen had come. Turning my back on the Archduke, I stepped forward, and then, quite suddenly, I noticed that I hadn't got any trousers on. I was in short silk drawers, and I wore scarlet sock-suspenders. No wonder Lady Connemara had giggled; no wonder the Archduke had laughed! I can't tell you what that moment was. An agony of shame. I awoke in a cold sweat. Oh, you don't know the relief I felt to find it was only a dream."

"It's the kind of dream that's not so very uncommon," said Dr Audlin.

"I dare say not. But an odd thing happened next day. I was in the lobby of the House of Commons, when that fellow Griffiths walked slowly past me. He deliberately looked down at my legs and then he looked me full in the face and I was almost certain he winked. A ridiculous thought came to me. He'd been there the night before and seen me make that ghastly exhibition of myself and was enjoying the joke. But of course I knew that was impossible because it was only a dream. I gave him an icy glare and he walked on. But he was grinning his head off."

Lord Mountdrago took his handkerchief out of his pocket and wiped the palms of his hands. He was making no attempt now to conceal his perturbation. Dr Audlin never took his eyes off him.

"Tell me another dream."

"It was the night after, and it was even more absurd than the first one. I dreamt that I was in the House. There was a debate on foreign affairs which not only the country, but the world, had been looking forward to with the gravest concern. The government had decided on a change in their policy which vitally affected the future of the Empire. The occasion was historic. Of course the House was crowded. All the ambassadors were there. The galleries were packed. It fell to me to make the important speech of the evening. I had prepared it carefully. A man like me has enemies, there are a lot of people who resent my having achieved the position I have at an age when even the cleverest men are content with situations of relative obscurity, and I was determined that my speech should not only be worthy of the occasion, but should silence my detractors. It excited me to think that the whole world was hanging on my lips. I rose to my feet. If you've ever been in the House you'll know how members chat to one another during a debate, rustle papers and turn over reports. The silence was the silence of the grave when I began to speak. Suddenly I caught sight of that odious little bounder on one of the benches opposite, Griffiths the Welsh member; he put out his tongue at me. I don't know if you've ever heard a vulgar music-hall song called A Bicycle Made for Two. It was very popular a great many years ago. To show Griffiths how completely I despised him I began to sing it. I sang the first verse right through. There was a moment's surprise, and when I finished they cried 'Hear, hear,' on the opposite benches. I put up my hand to silence them and sang the second verse. The House listened to me in stony silence and I felt the song wasn't going down very well. I was vexed, for I have a good baritone voice, and I was determined that they should do me justice. When I started the third verse the members began to laugh; in an instant the laughter spread; the ambassadors, the strangers in the Distinguished Strangers' Gallery, the ladies in the Ladies' Gallery, the reporters, they shook, they bellowed, they held their sides, they rolled in their seats; everyone was overcome with laughter except the ministers on the Front Bench immediately behind me. In that incredible, in that unprecedented uproar, they sat petrified. I gave them a glance, and suddenly the enormity of what I had done fell upon me. I had made myself the laughing-stock of the whole world. With misery I realized that I should have to resign. I woke and knew it was only a dream."

Lord Mountdrago's grand manner had deserted him as he narrated this, and now having finished he was pale and trembling. But with an effort he pulled himself together. He forced a laugh to his shaking lips.

"The whole thing was so fantastic that I couldn't help being amused. I didn't give it another thought, and when I went into the House on the following afternoon I was feeling in very good form. The debate was dull, but I had to be there, and I read some documents that required my attention. For some reason I chanced to look up and I saw that Griffiths was speaking. He has an unpleasant Welsh accent and an unprepossessing appearance. I couldn't imagine that he had anything to say that it was worth my while to listen to, and I was about to return to my papers when he quoted two lines from A Bicycle Made for Two. I couldn't help glancing at him and I saw that his eyes were fixed on me with a grin of bitter mockery. I faintly shrugged my shoulders. It was comic that a scrubby little Welsh member should look at me like that. It was an odd coincidence that he should quote two lines from that disastrous song that I'd sung all through in my dream. I began to read my papers again, but I don't mind telling you that I found it difficult to concentrate on them. I was a little puzzled. Owen Griffiths had been in my first dream, the one at Connemara House, and I'd received a very definite impression afterwards that he knew the sorry figure I'd cut. Was it a mere coincidence that he had just quoted those two lines? I asked myself if it was possible that he was dreaming the same dreams as I was. But of course the idea was preposterous and I determined not to give it a second thought."

There was a silence. Dr Audlin looked at Lord Mountdrago and Lord Mountdrago looked at Dr Audlin.

"Other people's dreams are very boring. My wife used to dream occasionally and insist on telling me her dreams next day with circumstantial detail. I found it maddening."

Dr Audlin faintly smiled.

"You're not boring me."

"I'll tell you one more dream I had a few days later. I dreamt that I went into a public-house at Limehouse. I've never been to Limehouse in my life and I don't think I've ever been in a public-house since I was at Oxford, and yet I saw the street and the place I went into as exactly as if I were at home there. I went into a room, I don't know whether they call it the saloon bar or the private bar; there was a fireplace and a large leather arm-chair on one side of it, and on the other a small sofa; a bar ran the whole length of the room and over it you could see into the public bar. Near the door was a round marble-topped table and two arm-chairs beside it. It was a Saturday night and the place was packed. It was brightly lit, but the smoke was so thick that it made my eyes smart. I was dressed like a rough, with a cap on my head and a handkerchief round my neck. It seemed to me that most of the people there were drunk. I thought it rather amusing. There was a gramophone going, or the radio, I don't know which, and in front of the fireplace two women were doing a grotesque dance. There was a little crowd round them, laughing, cheering, and singing. I went up to have a look and some man said to me: ''Ave a drink, Bill?' There were glasses on the table full of a dark liquid which I understand is called brown ale. He gave me a glass and not wishing to be conspicuous I drank it. One of the women who were dancing broke away from the other and took hold of the glass. 'Ere, what's the idea?' she said. 'That's my beer you're putting away.' 'Oh, I'm so sorry,' I said, 'this gentleman offered it me and I very naturally thought it was his to offer.' 'All right, mate,' she said, 'I don't mind. You come an' 'ave a dance with me.' Before I could protest she'd caught hold of me and we were dancing together. And then I found myself sitting in the arm-chair with the woman on my lap and we were sharing a glass of beer. I should tell you that sex has never played any great part in my life. I married young because in my position it was desirable that I should marry, but also in order to settle once for all the question of sex. I had the two sons I had made up my mind to have, and then I put the whole matter on one side. I've always been too busy to give much thought to that kind of thing, and living so much in the public eye as I do it would have been madness to do anything that might give rise to scandal. The greatest asset a politician can have is a blameless record as far as women are concerned. I have no patience with the men who smash up their careers for women. I only despise them. The woman I had on my knees was drunk; she wasn't pretty and she wasn't young; in fact, she was just a blowsy old prostitute. She filled me with disgust, and yet when she put her mouth to mine and kissed me, though her breath stank of beer and her teeth were decayed, though I loathed myself, I wanted her—I wanted her with all my soul. Suddenly I heard a voice. 'That's right, old boy, have a good time.' I looked up and there was Owen Griffiths. I tried to spring out of the chair, but that horrible woman wouldn't let me. 'Don't you pay no attention to 'im,' she said, ''e's only one of them nosy-parkers.' 'You go to it,' he said. 'I know Moll. She'll give you your money's worth all right.' You know, I wasn't so much annoyed at his seeing me in that absurd situation as angry that he should address me as 'old boy'. I pushed the woman aside and stood up and faced him. 'I don't know you and I don't want to know you,' I said. 'I know you all right,' he said. 'And my advice to you, Molly, is, see that you get your money, he'll bilk you if he can.' There was a bottle of beer on the table close by. Without a word I seized it by the neck and hit him over the head with it as hard as I could. I made such a violent gesture that it woke me up."

"A dream of that sort is not incomprehensible," said Dr Audlin. "It is the revenge nature takes on persons of unimpeachable character."

"The story's idiotic. I haven't told it you for its own sake. I've told it you for what happened next day. I wanted to look up something in a hurry and I went into the library of the House. I got the book and began reading. I hadn't noticed when I sat down that Griffiths was sitting in a chair close by me. Another of the Labour Members came in and went up to him. 'Hullo, Owen,' he said to him, 'you're looking pretty dicky today.' 'I've got an awful headache,' he answered. 'I feel as if I'd been cracked over the head with a bottle.'"

Now Lord Mountdrago's face was grey with anguish.

"I knew then that the idea I'd had and dismissed as preposterous was true. I knew that Griffiths was dreaming my dreams and that he remembered them as well as I did."

"It may also have been a coincidence."

"When he spoke he didn't speak to his friend, he deliberately spoke to me. He looked at me with sullen resentment."

"Can you offer any suggestion why this same man should come into your dreams?"

"None."

Dr Audlin's eyes had not left his patient's face and he saw that he lied. He had a pencil in his hand and he drew a straggling line or two on his blotting-paper. It often took a long time to get people to tell the truth, and yet they knew that unless they told it he could do nothing for them.

"The dream you've just described to me took place just over three weeks ago. Have you had any since?"

"Every night."

"And does this man Griffiths come into them all?"

"Yes."

The doctor drew more lines on his blotting-paper. He wanted the silence, the drabness, the dull light of that little room to have its effect on Lord Mountdrago's sensibility. Lord Mountdrago threw himself back in his chair and turned his head away so that he should not see the other's grave eyes.

"Dr Audlin, you must do something for me. I'm at the end of my tether. I shall go mad if this goes on. I'm afraid to go to sleep. Two or three nights I haven't. I've sat up reading and when I felt drowsy put on my coat and walked till I was exhausted. But I must have sleep. With all the work I have to do I must be at concert pitch; I must be in complete control of all my faculties. I need rest; sleep brings me none. I no sooner fall asleep than my dreams begin, and he's always there, that vulgar little cad, grinning at me, mocking me, despising me. It's a monstrous persecution. I tell you, doctor, I'm not the man of my dreams; it's not fair to judge me by them. Ask anyone you like. I'm an honest, upright, decent man. No one can say anything against my moral character either private or public. My whole ambition is to serve my country and maintain its greatness. I have money, I have rank, I'm not exposed to many of the temptations of lesser men, so that it's no credit to me to be incorruptible; but this I can claim, that no honour, no personal advantage, no thought of self would induce me to swerve by a hair's breadth from my duty. I've sacrificed everything to become the man I am. Greatness is my aim. Greatness is within my reach and I'm losing my nerve. I'm not that mean, despicable, cowardly, lewd creature that horrible little man sees. I've told you three of my dreams; they're nothing; that man has seen me do things that are so beastly, so horrible, so shameful, that even if my life depended on it I wouldn't tell them. And he remembers them. I can hardly meet the derision and disgust I see in his eyes and I even hesitate to speak because I know my words can seem to him nothing but utter humbug. He's seen me do things that no man with any self-respect would do, things for which men are driven out of the society of their fellows and sentenced to long terms of imprisonment; he's heard the foulness of my speech; he's seen me not only ridiculous, but revolting. He despises me and he no longer pretends to conceal it. I tell you that if you can't do something to help me I shall either kill myself or kill him."

"I wouldn't kill him if I were you," said Dr Audlin, coolly, in that soothing voice of his. "In this country the consequences of killing a fellow-creature are awkward."

"I shouldn't be hanged for it, if that's what you mean. Who would know that I'd killed him? That dream of mine has shown me how. I told you, the day after I'd hit him over the head with a beer-bottle he had such a headache that he couldn't see straight. He said so himself. That shows that he can feel with his waking body what happens to his body asleep. It's not with a bottle I shall hit him next time. One night, when I'm dreaming, I shall find myself with a knife in my hand or a revolver in my pocket, I must because I want to so intensely, and then I shall seize my opportunity. I'll stick him like a pig; I'll shoot him like a dog. In the heart. And then I shall be free of this fiendish persecution."

Some people might have thought that Lord Mountdrago was mad; after all the years during which Dr Audlin had been treating the diseased souls of men he knew how thin a line divides those whom we call sane from those whom we call insane. He knew how often in men who to all appearance were healthy and normal, who were seemingly devoid of imagination, and who fulfilled the duties of common life with credit to themselves and with benefit to their fellows, when you gained their confidence, when you tore away the mask they wore to the world, you found not only hideous abnormality, but kinks so strange, mental extravagances so fantastic, that in that respect you could call them lunatic. If you put them in an asylum not all the asylums in the world would be large enough. Anyhow, a man was not certifiable because he had strange dreams and they had shattered his nerve. The case was singular, but it was only an exaggeration of others that had come under Dr Audlin's observation; he was doubtful, however, whether the methods of treatment that he had so often found efficacious would here avail.

"Have you consulted any other member of my profession?" he asked.

"Only Sir Augustus. I merely told him that I suffered from nightmares. He said I was overworked and recommended me to go for a cruise. That's absurd. I can't leave the Foreign Office just now when the international situation needs constant attention. I'm indispensable, and I know it. On my conduct at the present juncture my whole future depends. He gave me sedatives. They had no effect. He gave me tonics. They were worse than useless. He's an old fool."

"Can you give any reason why it should be this particular man who persists in coming into your dreams?"

"You asked me that question before. I answered it."

That was true. But Dr Audlin had not been satisfied with the answer.

"Just now you talked of persecution. Why should Owen Griffiths want to persecute you?"

"I don't know."

Lord Mountdrago's eyes shifted a little. Dr Audlin was sure that he was not speaking the truth.

"Have you ever done him an injury?"

"Never."

Lord Mountdrago made no movement, but Dr Audlin had a queer feeling that he shrank into his skin. He saw before him a large, proud man who gave the impression that the questions put to him were an insolence, and yet for all that, behind that facade, was something shifting and startled that made you think of a frightened animal in a trap. Dr Audlin leaned forward and by the power of his eyes forced Lord Mountdrago to meet them.

"Are you quite sure?"

"Quite sure. You don't seem to understand that our ways lead along different paths. I don't wish to harp on it, but I must remind you that I am a Minister of the Crown and Griffiths is an obscure member of the Labour Party. Naturally there's no social connection between us; he's a man of very humble origin, he's not the sort of person I should be likely to meet at any of the houses I go to; and politically our respective stations are so far separated that we could not possibly have anything in common."

"I can do nothing for you unless you tell me the complete truth."

Lord Mountdrago raised his eyebrows. His voice was rasping.

"I'm not accustomed to having my word doubted, Dr Audlin. If you're going to do that I think to take up any more of your time can only be a waste of mine. If you will kindly let my secretary know what your fee is he will see that a cheque is sent to you."

For all the expression that was to be seen on Dr Audlin's face you might have thought that he simply had not heard what Lord Mountdrago said. He continued to look steadily into his eyes and his voice was grave and low.

"Have you done anything to this man that he might look upon as an injury?"

Lord Mountdrago hesitated. He looked away, and then, as though there were in Dr Audlin's eyes a compelling force that he could not resist, looked back. He answered sulkily:

"Only if he was a dirty, second-rate little cad."

"But that is exactly what you've described him to be."

Lord Mountdrago sighed. He was beaten. Dr Audlin knew that the sigh meant he was going at last to say what he had till then held back. Now he had no longer to insist. He dropped his eyes and began again drawing vague geometrical figures on his blotting-paper. The silence lasted two or three minutes.

"I'm anxious to tell you everything that can be of any use to you. If I didn't mention this before, it's only because it was so unimportant that I didn't see how it could possibly have anything to do with the case. Griffiths won a seat at the last election and he began to make a nuisance of himself almost at once. His father's a miner, and he worked in a mine himself when he was a boy; he's been a schoolmaster in the board schools and a journalist. He's that half-baked, conceited intellectual, with inadequate knowledge, ill-considered ideas, and impracticable plans, that compulsory education has brought forth from the working-classes. He's a scrawny, grey-faced man, who looks half-starved, and he's always very slovenly in appearance; heaven knows members nowadays don't bother much about their dress, but his clothes are an outrage to the dignity of the House. They're ostentatiously shabby, his collar's never clean and his tie's never tied properly; he looks as if he hadn't had a bath for a month and his hands are filthy. The Labour Party have two or three fellows on the Front Bench who've got a certain ability, but the rest of them don't amount to much. In the kingdom of the blind the one-eyed man is king: because Griffiths is glib and has a lot of superficial information on a number of subjects, the Whips on his side began to put him up to speak whenever there was a chance. It appeared that he fancied himself on foreign affairs, and he was continually asking me silly, tiresome questions. I don't mind telling you that I made a point of snubbing him as soundly as I thought he deserved. From the beginning I hated the way he talked, his whining voice and his vulgar accent; he had nervous mannerisms that intensely irritated me. He talked rather shyly, hesitatingly, as though it were torture to him to speak and yet he was forced on by some inner passion, and often he used to say some very disconcerting things. I'll admit that now and again he had a sort of tub-thumping eloquence. It had a certain influence over the ill-regulated minds of the members of his party. They were impressed by his earnestness and they weren't, as I was, nauseated by his sentimentality. A certain sentimentality is the common coin of political debate. Nations are governed by self-interest, but they prefer to believe that their aims are altruistic, and the politician is justified if with fair words and fine phrases he can persuade the electorate that the hard bargain he is driving for his country's advantage tends to the good of humanity. The mistake people like Griffiths make is to take these fair words and fine phrases at their face value. He's a crank, and a noxious crank. He calls himself an idealist. He has at his tongue's end all the tedious blather that the intelligentsia have been boring us with for years. Non-resistance. The brotherhood of man. You know the hopeless rubbish. The worst of it was that it impressed not only his own party, it even shook some of the sillier, more sloppy-minded members of ours. I heard rumours that Griffiths was likely to get office when a Labour Government came in; I even heard it suggested that he might get the Foreign Office. The notion was grotesque but not impossible. One day I had occasion to wind up a debate on foreign affairs which Griffiths had opened. He'd spoken for an hour. I thought it a very good opportunity to cook his goose, and by God, sir, I cooked it. I tore his speech to pieces. I pointed out the faultiness of his reasoning and emphasized the deficiency of his knowledge. In the House of Commons the most devastating weapon is ridicule: I mocked him; I bantered him; I was in good form that day and the House rocked with laughter. Their laughter excited me and I excelled myself. The Opposition sat glum and silent, but even some of them couldn't help laughing once or twice; it's not intolerable, you know, to see a colleague, perhaps a rival, made a fool of. And if ever a man was made a fool of I made a fool of Griffiths. He shrank down in a seat, I saw his face go white, and presently he buried it in his hands. When I sat down I'd killed him. I'd destroyed his prestige for ever; he had no more chance of getting office when a Labour Government came in than the policeman at the door. I heard afterwards that his father, the old miner, and his mother had come up from Wales, with various supporters of his in the constituency, to watch the triumph they expected him to have. They had seen only his utter humiliation. He'd won the constituency by the narrowest margin. An incident like that might very easily lose him his seat. But that was no business of mine."

"Should I be putting it too strongly if I said you had ruined his career?" asked Dr Audlin.

"I don't suppose you would."

"That is a very serious injury you've done him."

"He brought it on himself."

"Have you never felt any qualms about it?"

"I think perhaps if I'd known that his father and mother were there I might have let him down a little more gently."

There was nothing further for Dr Audlin to say, and he set about treating his patient in such a manner as he thought might avail. He sought by suggestion to make him forget his dreams when he awoke; he sought to make him sleep so deeply that he would not dream. He found Lord Mountdrago's resistance impossible to break down. At the end of an hour he dismissed him. Since then he had seen Lord Mountdrago half a dozen times. He had done him no good. The frightful dreams continued every night to harass the unfortunate man, and it was clear that his general condition was growing rapidly worse. He was worn out. His irritability was uncontrollable. Lord Mountdrago was angry because he received no benefit from his treatment, and yet continued it, not only because it seemed his only hope, but because it was a relief to him to have someone with whom he could talk openly. Dr Audlin came to the conclusion at last that there was only one way in which Lord Mountdrago could achieve deliverance, but he knew him well enough to be assured that of his own free will he would never, never take it. If Lord Mountdrago was to be saved from the breakdown that was threatening he must be induced to take a step that must be abhorrent to his pride of birth and his self-complacency. Dr Audlin was convinced that to delay was impossible. He was treating his patient by suggestion, and after several visits found him more susceptible to it. At length he managed to get him into a condition of somnolence. With his low, soft, monotonous voice he soothed his tortured nerves. He repeated the same words over and over again. Lord Mountdrago lay quite still, his eyes closed; his breathing was regular, and his limbs were relaxed. Then Dr Audlin in the same quiet tone spoke the words he had prepared.

"You will go to Owen Griffiths and say that you are sorry that you caused him that great injury. You will say that you will do whatever lies in your power to undo the harm that you have done him."

The words acted on Lord Mountdrago like the blow of a whip across his face. He shook himself out of his hypnotic state and sprang to his feet. His eyes blazed with passion and he poured forth upon Dr Audlin a stream of angry vituperation such as even he had never heard. He swore at him. He cursed him. He used language of such obscenity that Dr Audlin, who had heard every sort of foul word, sometimes from the lips of chaste and distinguished women, was surprised that he knew it.

"Apologize to that filthy little Welshman? I'd rather kill myself."

"I believe it to be the only way in which you can regain your balance."

Dr Audlin had not often seen a man presumably sane in such a condition of uncontrollable fury. He grew red in the face and his eyes bulged out of his head. He did really foam at the mouth. Dr Audlin watched him coolly, waiting for the storm to wear itself out, and presently he saw that Lord Mountdrago, weakened by the strain to which he had been subjected for so many weeks, was exhausted.

"Sit down," he said then, sharply.

Lord Mountdrago crumpled up into a chair.

"Christ, I feel all in. I must rest a minute and then I'll go."

For five minutes perhaps they sat in complete silence. Lord Mountdrago was a gross, blustering bully, but he was also a gentleman. When he broke the silence he had recovered his self-control.

"I'm afraid I've been very rude to you. I'm ashamed of the things I've said to you and I can only say you'd be justified if you refused to have anything more to do with me. I hope you won't do that. I feel that my visits to you do help me. I think you're my only chance."

"You mustn't give another thought to what you said. It was of no consequence."

"But there's one thing you mustn't ask me to do, and that is to make excuses to Griffiths."

"I've thought a great deal about your case I don't pretend to understand it, but I believe that your only chance of release is to do what I proposed. I have a notion that we're none of us one self, but many, and one of the selves in you has risen up against the injury you did Griffiths and has taken on the form of Griffiths in your mind and is punishing you for what you cruelly did. If I were a priest I should tell you that it is your conscience that has adopted the shape and lineaments of this man to scourge you to repentance and persuade you to reparation."

"My conscience is clear. It's not my fault if I smashed the man's career. I crushed him like a slug in my garden. I regret nothing."

It was on these words that Lord Mountdrago had left him. Reading through his notes, while he waited, Dr Audlin considered how best he could bring his patient to the state of mind that, now that his usual methods of treatment had failed, he thought alone could help him. He glanced at his clock. It was six. It was strange that Lord Mountdrago did not come. He knew he had intended to because a secretary had rung up that morning to say that he would be with him at the usual hour. He must have been detained by pressing work. This notion gave Dr Audlin something else to think of: Lord Mountdrago was quite unfit for work and in no condition to deal with important matters of state. Dr Audlin wondered whether it behoved him to get in touch with someone in authority, the Prime Minister or the Permanent Under-Secretary for Foreign Affairs, and impart to him his conviction that Lord Mountdrago's mind was so unbalanced that it was dangerous to leave affairs of moment in his hands. It was a ticklish thing to do. He might cause needless trouble and get roundly snubbed for his pains. He shrugged his shoulders.

"After all," he reflected, "the politicians have made such a mess of the world during the last five-and-twenty years, I don't suppose it makes much odds if they're mad or sane."

He rang the bell.

"If Lord Mountdrago comes now will you tell him that I have another appointment at six-fifteen and so I'm afraid I can't see him."

"Very good, sir."

"Has the evening paper come yet?"

"I'll go and see."

In a moment the servant brought it in. A huge headline ran across the front page: Tragic Death of Foreign Minister.

"My God!" cried Dr Audlin.

For once he was wrenched out of his wonted calm. He was shocked, horribly shocked, and yet he was not altogether surprised. The possibility that Lord Mountdrago might commit suicide had occurred to him several times, for that it was suicide he could not doubt. The paper said that Lord Mountdrago had been waiting in a Tube station, standing on the edge of the platform, and as the train came in was seen to fall on the rail. It was supposed that he had had a sudden attack of faintness. The paper went on to say that Lord Mountdrago had been suffering for some weeks from the effects of overwork, but had felt it impossible to absent himself while the foreign situation demanded his unremitting attention. Lord Mountdrago was another victim of the strain that modern politics placed upon those who played the more important parts in it. There was a neat little piece about the talents and industry, the patriotism and vision, of the deceased statesman, followed by various surmises upon the Prime Minister's choice of his successor. Dr Audlin read all this. He had not liked Lord Mountdrago. The chief emotion that his death caused in him was dissatisfaction with himself because he had been able to do nothing for him.

Perhaps he had done wrong in not getting into touch with Lord Mountdrago's doctor. He was discouraged, as always when failure frustrated his conscientious efforts, and repulsion seized him for the theory and practice of this empiric doctrine by which he earned his living. He was dealing with dark and mysterious forces that it was perhaps beyond the powers of the human mind to understand. He was like a man blindfold trying to feel his way to he knew not whither. Listlessly he turned the pages of the paper. Suddenly he gave a great start, and an exclamation once more was forced from his lips. His eyes had fallen on a small paragraph near the bottom of a column. Sudden Death of an M.P., he read. Mr. Owen Griffiths, member for so-and-so, had been taken ill in Fleet Street that afternoon and when he was brought to Charing Cross Hospital life was found to be extinct. It was supposed that death was due to natural causes, but an inquest would be held. Dr Audlin could hardly believe his eyes. Was it possible that the night before Lord Mountdrago had at last in his dream found himself possessed of the weapon, knife or gun, that he had wanted, and had killed his tormentor, and had that ghostly murder, in the same way as the blow with the bottle had given him a racking headache on the following day, taken effect a certain number of hours later on the waking man? Or was it, more mysterious and more frightful, that when Lord Mountdrago sought relief in death, the enemy he had so cruelly wronged, unappeased, escaping from his own mortality, had pursued him to some other sphere there to torment him still? It was strange. The sensible thing was to look upon it merely as an odd coincidence. Dr Audlin rang the bell.

"Tell Mrs. Milton that I'm sorry I can't see her this evening. I'm not well."

It was true; he shivered as though of an ague. With some kind of spiritual sense he seemed to envisage a bleak, a horrible void. The dark night of the soul engulfed him, and he felt a strange, primeval terror of he knew not what.

The Letter

Outside on the quay the sun beat fiercely. A stream of motors, lorries and buses, private cars and hirelings, sped up and down the crowded thoroughfare, and every chauffeur blew his horn; rickshaws threaded their nimble path amid the throng, and the panting coolies found breath to yell at one another; coolies, carrying heavy bales, sidled along with their quick jog-trot and shouted to the passer-by to make way; itinerant vendors proclaimed their wares. Singapore is the meeting-place of a hundred peoples; and men of all colours, black Tamils, yellow Chinks, brown Malays, Armenians, Jews, and Bengalis, called to one another in raucous tones. But inside the office of Messrs Ripley, Joyce, and Naylor it was pleasantly cool; it was dark after the dusty glitter of the street and agreeably quiet after its unceasing din. Mr. Joyce sat in his private room, at the table, with an electric fan turned full on him. He was leaning back, his elbows on the arms of the chair, with the tips of the outstretched fingers of one hand resting neatly against the tips of the outstretched fingers of the other. His gaze rested on the battered volumes of the Law Reports which stood on a long shelf in front of him. On the top of a cupboard were square boxes of japanned tin, on which were painted the names of various clients.

There was a knock at the door.

"Come in."

A Chinese clerk, very neat in his white ducks, opened it.

"Mr. Crosbie is here, sir."

He spoke beautiful English, accenting each word with precision, and Mr. Joyce had often wondered at the extent of his vocabulary. Ong Chi Seng was a Cantonese, and he had studied law at Gray's Inn. He was spending a year or two with Messrs Ripley, Joyce, and Naylor in order to prepare himself for practice on his own account. He was industrious, obliging, and of exemplary character.

"Show him in," said Mr. Joyce.

He rose to shake hands with his visitor and asked him to sit down. The light fell on him as he did so. The face of Mr. Joyce remained in shadow. He was by nature a silent man, and now he looked at Robert Crosbie for quite a minute without speaking. Crosbie was a big fellow, well over six feet high, with broad shoulders, and muscular. He was a rubber-planter, hard with the constant exercise of walking over the estate, and with the tennis which was his relaxation when the day's work was over. He was deeply sunburned. His hairy hands, his feet in clumsy boots were enormous, and Mr. Joyce found himself thinking that a blow of that great fist could easily kill the fragile Tamil. But there was no fierceness in his blue eyes; they were confiding and gentle; and his face, with its big, undistinguished features, was open, frank, and honest. But at this moment it bore a look of deep distress. It was drawn and haggard.

"You look as though you hadn't had much sleep the last night or two," said Mr. Joyce.

"I haven't."

Mr. Joyce noticed now the old felt hat, with its broad double brim, which Crosbie had placed on the table; and then his eyes travelled to the khaki shorts he wore, showing his red hairy thighs, the tennis shirt open at the neck, without a tie, and the dirty khaki jacket with the ends of the sleeves turned up. He looked as though he had just come in from a long tramp among the rubber trees. Mr. Joyce gave a slight frown.

"You must pull yourself together, you know. You must keep your head."

"Oh, I'm all right."

"Have you seen your wife today?"

"No, I'm to see her this afternoon. You know, it is a damned shame that they should have arrested her."

"I think they had to do that," Mr. Joyce answered in his level, soft tone.

"I should have thought they'd have let her out on bail."

"It's a very serious charge."

"It is damnable. She did what any decent woman would do in her place. Only, nine women out of ten wouldn't have the pluck. Leslie's the best woman in the world. She wouldn't hurt a fly. Why, hang it all, man, I've been married to her for twelve years, do you think I don't know her? God, if I'd got hold of the man I'd have wrung his neck, I'd have killed him without a moment's hesitation. So would you."

"My dear fellow, everybody's on your side. No one has a good word to say for Hammond. We're going to get her off. I don't suppose either the assessors or the judge will go into court without having already made up their minds to bring in a verdict of not guilty."

"The whole thing's a farce," said Crosbie violently. "She ought never to have been arrested in the first place, and then it's terrible, after all the poor girl's gone through, to subject her to the ordeal of a trial. There's not a soul I've met since I've been in Singapore, man or woman, who hasn't told me that Leslie was absolutely justified. I think it's awful to keep her in prison all these weeks."

"The law is the law. After all, she confesses that she killed the man. It is terrible, and I'm dreadfully sorry for both you and her."

"I don't matter a hang," interrupted Crosbie.

"But the fact remains that murder has been committed, and in a civilized community a trial is inevitable."

"Is it murder to exterminate noxious vermin? She shot him as she would have shot a mad dog."

Mr. Joyce leaned back again in his chair and once more placed the tips of his ten fingers together. The little construction he formed looked like the skeleton of a roof. He was silent for a moment.

"I should be wanting in my duty as your legal adviser," he said at last, in an even voice, looking at his client with his cool, brown eyes, "if I did not tell you that there is one point which causes me just a little anxiety. If your wife had only shot Hammond once, the whole thing would be absolutely plain sailing. Unfortunately she fired six times."

"Her explanation is perfectly simple. In the circumstances anyone would have done the same."

"I dare say," said Mr. Joyce, "and of course I think the explanation is very reasonable. But it's no good closing our eyes to the facts. It's always a good plan to put yourself in another man's place, and I can't deny that if I were prosecuting for the Crown that is the point on which I should centre my inquiry."

"My dear fellow, that's perfectly idiotic."

Mr. Joyce shot a sharp glance at Robert Crosbie. The shadow of a smile hovered over his shapely lips. Crosbie was a good fellow, but he could hardly be described as intelligent.

"I dare say it's of no importance," answered the lawyer, "I just thought it was a point worth mentioning. You haven't got very long to wait now, and when it's all over I recommend you to go off somewhere with your wife on a trip, and forget all about it. Even though we are almost dead certain to get an acquittal, a trial of that sort is anxious work, and you'll both want a rest."

For the first time Crosbie smiled, and his smile strangely changed his face. You forgot the uncouthness and saw only the goodness of his soul.

"I think I shall want it more than Leslie. She's borne up wonderfully. By God, there's a plucky little woman for you."

"Yes, I've been very much struck by her self-control," said the lawyer. "I should never have guessed that she was capable of such determination."

His duties as her counsel had made it necessary for him to have a good many interviews with Mrs. Crosbie since her arrest. Though things had been made as easy as could be for her, the fact remained that she was in gaol, awaiting her trial for murder, and it would not have been surprising if her nerves had failed her. She appeared to bear her ordeal with composure. She read a great deal, took such exercise as was possible, and by favour of the authorities worked at the pillow lace which had always formed the entertainment of her long hours of leisure. When Mr. Joyce saw her, she was neatly dressed in cool, fresh, simple frocks, her hair was carefully arranged, and her nails were manicured. Her manner was collected. She was able even to jest upon the little inconveniences of her position. There was something casual about the way in which she spoke of the tragedy, which suggested to Mr. Joyce that only her good breeding prevented her from finding something a trifle ludicrous in a situation which was eminently serious. It surprised him, for he had never thought that she had a sense of humour.

He had known her off and on for a good many years. When she paid visits to Singapore she generally came to dine with his wife and himself, and once or twice she had passed a weekend with them at their bungalow by the sea. His wife had spent a fortnight with her on the estate, and had met Geoffrey Hammond several times. The two couples had been on friendly, if not on intimate, terms, and it was on this account that Robert Crosbie had rushed over to Singapore immediately after the catastrophe and begged Mr. Joyce to take charge personally of his unhappy wife's defence.

The story she told him the first time he saw her she had never varied in the smallest detail. She told it as coolly then, a few hours after the tragedy, as she told it now. She told it connectedly, in a level, even voice, and her only sign of confusion was when a slight colour came into her cheeks as she described one or two of its incidents. She was the last woman to whom one would have expected such a thing to happen. She was in the early thirties, a fragile creature, neither short nor tall, and graceful rather than pretty. Her wrists and ankles were very delicate, but she was extremely thin, and you could see the bones of her hands through the white skin, and the veins were large and blue. Her face was colourless, slightly sallow, and her lips were pale. You did not notice the colour of her eyes. She had a great deal of light brown hair, and it had a slight natural wave; it was the sort of hair that with a little touching-up would have been very pretty, but you could not imagine that Mrs. Crosbie would think of resorting to any such device. She was a quiet, pleasant, unassuming woman. Her manner was engaging, and if she was not very popular it was because she suffered from a certain shyness. This was comprehensible enough, for the planter's life is lonely, and in her own house, with people she knew, she was in her quiet way charming. Mrs. Joyce, after her fortnight's stay, had told her husband that Leslie was a very agreeable hostess. There was more in her, she said, than people thought; and when you came to know her you were surprised how much she had read and how entertaining she could be.

She was the last woman in the world to commit murder.

Mr. Joyce dismissed Robert Crosbie with such reassuring words as he could find and, once more alone in his office, turned over the pages of the brief. But it was a mechanical action, for all its details were familiar to him. The case was the sensation of the day, and it was discussed in all the clubs, at all the dinner tables, up and down the Peninsula, from Singapore to Penang. The facts that Mrs. Crosbie gave were simple. Her husband had gone to Singapore on business, and she was alone for the night. She dined by herself, late, at a quarter to nine, and after dinner sat in the sitting-room working at her lace. It opened on the veranda. There was no one in the bungalow, for the servants had retired to their own quarters at the back of the compound. She was surprised to hear a step on the gravel path in the garden, a booted step, which suggested a white man rather than a native, for she had not heard a motor drive up, and she could not imagine who could be coming to see her at that time of night. Someone ascended the few stairs that led up to the bungalow, walked across the veranda, and appeared at the door of the room in which she sat. At the first moment she did not recognize the visitor. She sat with a shaded lamp, and he stood with his back to the darkness.

"May I come in?" he said.

She did not even recognize the voice.

"Who is it?" she asked.

She worked with spectacles, and she took them off as she spoke.

"Geoff Hammond."

"Of course. Come in and have a drink."

She rose and shook hands with him cordially. She was a little surprised to see him, for though he was a neighbour neither she nor Robert had been lately on very intimate terms with him, and she had not seen him for some weeks. He was the manager of a rubber estate nearly eight miles from theirs, and she wondered why he had chosen this late hour to come and see them.

"Robert's away," she said. "He had to go to Singapore for the night."

Perhaps he thought his visit called for some explanation, for he said:

"I'm sorry. I felt rather lonely tonight, so I thought I'd just come along and see how you were getting on."

"How on earth did you come? I never heard a car."

"I left it down the road. I thought you might both be in bed and asleep."

This was natural enough. The planter gets up at dawn in order to take the roll-call of the workers, and soon after dinner he is glad to go to bed. Hammond's car was in point of fact found next day a quarter of a mile from the bungalow.

Since Robert was away there was no whisky and soda in the room. Leslie did not call the boy, who was probably asleep, but fetched it herself. Her guest mixed himself a drink and filled his pipe.

Geoff Hammond had a host of friends in the colony. He was at this time in the late thirties, but he had come out as a lad. He had been one of the first to volunteer on the outbreak of war, and had done very well. A wound in the knee caused him to be invalided out of the army after two years, but he returned to the Federated Malay States with a D.S.O. and an M.C. He was one of the best billiard-players in the colony. He had been a beautiful dancer and a fine tennis-player, but though able no longer to dance, and his tennis, with a stiff knee, was not so good as it had been, he had the gift of popularity and was universally liked. He was a tall, good-looking fellow, with attractive blue eyes and a fine head of black, curling hair. Old stagers said his only fault was that he was too fond of the girls, and after the catastrophe they shook their heads and vowed that they had always known this would get him into trouble.

He began now to talk to Leslie about the local affairs, the forthcoming races in Singapore, the price of rubber, and his chances of killing a tiger which had been lately seen in the neighbourhood. She was anxious to finish by a certain date a piece of lace on which she was working, for she wanted to send it home for her mother's birthday, and so put on her spectacles again, and drew towards her chair the little table on which stood the pillow.

"I wish you wouldn't wear those great horn-spectacles," he said. "I don't know why a pretty woman should do her best to look plain."

She was a trifle taken aback at this remark. He had never used that tone with her before. She thought the best thing was to make light of it.

"I have no pretensions to being a raving beauty, you know, and if you ask me point-blank, I'm bound to tell you that I don't care two pins if you think me plain or not."

"I don't think you're plain. I think you're awfully pretty."

"Sweet of you," she answered, ironically. "But in that case I can only think you half-witted."

He chuckled. But he rose from his chair and sat down in another by her side.

"You're not going to have the face to deny that you have the prettiest hands in the world," he said.

He made a gesture as though to take one of them. She gave him a little tap.

"Don't be an idiot. Sit down where you were before and talk sensibly, or else I shall send you home."

He did not move.

"Don't you know that I'm awfully in love with you?" he said.

She remained quite cool.

"I don't. I don't believe it for a minute, and even if it were true I don't want you to say it."

She was the more surprised at what he was saying, since during the seven years she had known him he had never paid her any particular attention. When he came back from the war they had seen a good deal of one another, and once when he was ill Robert had gone over and brought him back to their bungalow in his car. He had stayed with them for a fortnight. But their interests were dissimilar, and the acquaintance had never ripened into friendship. For the last two or three years they had seen little of him. Now and then he came over to play tennis, now and then they met him at some planter's who was giving a party, but it often happened that they did not set eyes on him for a month at a time.

Now he took another whisky and soda. Leslie wondered if he had been drinking before. There was something odd about him, and it made her a trifle uneasy. She watched him help himself with disapproval.

"I wouldn't drink any more if I were you," she said, good-humouredly still.

He emptied his glass and put it down.

"Do you think I'm talking to you like this because I'm drunk?" he asked abruptly.

"That is the most obvious explanation, isn't it?"

"Well, it's a lie. I've loved you ever since I first knew you. I've held my tongue as long as I could, and now it's got to come out. I love you, I love you, I love you."

She rose and carefully put aside the pillow.

"Good night," she said.

"I'm not going now."

At last she began to lose her temper.

"But, you poor fool, don't you know that I've never loved anyone but Robert, and even if I didn't love Robert you're the last man I should care for."

"What do I care? Robert's away."

"If you don't go away this minute I shall call the boys, and have you thrown out."

"They're out of earshot."

She was very angry now. She made a movement as though to go on to the veranda, from which the house-boy would certainly hear her, but he seized her arm.

"Let me go," she cried furiously.

"Not much. I've got you now."

She opened her mouth and called "Boy, boy," but with a quick gesture he put his hand over it. Then before she knew what he was about he had taken her in his arms and was kissing her passionately. She struggled, turning her lips away from his burning mouth.

"No, no, no," she cried. "Leave me alone. I won't."

She grew confused about what happened then. All that had been said before she remembered accurately, but now his words assailed her ears through a mist of horror and fear. He seemed to plead for her love. He broke into violent protestations of passion. And all the time he held her in his tempestuous embrace. She was helpless, for he was a strong, powerful man, and her arms were pinioned to her sides; her struggles were unavailing, and she felt herself grow weaker; she was afraid she would faint, and his hot breath on her face made her feel desperately sick. He kissed her mouth, her eyes, her cheeks, her hair. The pressure of his arms was killing her. He lifted her off her feet. She tried to kick him, but he only held her more closely. He was carrying her now. He wasn't speaking any more, but she knew that his face was pale and his eyes hot with desire. He was taking her into the bedroom. He was no longer a civilized man, but a savage. And as he ran he stumbled against a table which was in the way. His stiff knee made him a little awkward on his feet, and with the burden of the woman in his arms he fell. In a moment she had snatched herself away from him. She ran round the sofa. He was up in a flash, and flung himself towards her. There was a revolver on the desk. She was not a nervous woman, but Robert was to be away for the night, and she had meant to take it into her room when she went to bed. That was why it happened to be there. She was frantic with terror now. She did not know what she was doing. She heard a report. She saw Hammond stagger. He gave a cry. He said something, she didn't know what. He lurched out of the room on to the veranda. She was in a frenzy now, she was beside herself, she followed him out, yes, that was it, she must have followed him out, though she remembered nothing of it, she followed firing automatically, shot after shot, till the six chambers were empty. Hammond fell down on the floor of the veranda. He crumpled up into a bloody heap.

When the boys, startled by the reports, rushed up, they found her standing over Hammond with the revolver still in her hand and Hammond lifeless. She looked at them for a moment without speaking. They stood in a frightened, huddled bunch. She let the revolver fall from her hand, and without a word turned and went into the sitting-room. They watched her go into her bedroom and turn the key in the lock. They dared not touch the dead body, but looked at it with terrified eyes, talking excitedly to one another in undertones. Then the head-boy collected himself; he had been with them for many years, he was Chinese and a level-headed fellow. Robert had gone into Singapore on his motor-cycle, and the car stood in the garage. He told the seis to get it out; they must go at once to the Assistant District Officer and tell him what had happened. He picked up the revolver and put it in his pocket. The A.D.O., a man called Withers, lived on the outskirts of the nearest town, which was about thirty-five miles away. It took them an hour and a half to reach him. Everyone was asleep, and they had to rouse the boys. Presently Withers came out and they told him their errand. The head-boy showed him the revolver in proof of what he said. The A.D.O. went into his room to dress, sent for his car, and in a little while was following them back along the deserted road. The dawn was just breaking as he reached the Crosbies' bungalow. He ran up the steps of the veranda, and stopped short as he saw Hammond's body lying where he fell. He touched the face. It was quite cold.

"Where's mem?" he asked the house-boy.

The Chinese pointed to the bedroom. Withers went to the door and knocked. There was no answer. He knocked again.

"Mrs. Crosbie," he called.

"Who is it?"

"Withers."

There was another pause. Then the door was unlocked and slowly opened. Leslie stood before him. She had not been to bed, and wore the tea-gown in which she had dined. She stood and looked silently at the A.D.O.

"Your house-boy fetched me," he said. "Hammond. What have you done?"

"He tried to rape me, and I shot him."

"My God. I say, you'd better come out here. You must tell me exactly what happened."

"Not now. I can't. You must give me time. Send for my husband."

Withers was a young man, and he did not know exactly what to do in an emergency which was so out of the run of his duties. Leslie refused to say anything till at last Robert arrived. Then she told the two men the story, from which since then, though she had repeated it over and over again, she had never in the slightest degree diverged.

The point to which Mr. Joyce recurred was the shooting. As a lawyer he was bothered that Leslie had fired not once, but six times, and the examination of the dead man showed that four of the shots had been fired close to the body. One might almost have thought that when the man fell she stood over him and emptied the contents of the revolver into him. She confessed that her memory, so accurate for all that had preceded, failed her here. Her mind was blank. It pointed to an uncontrollable fury; but uncontrollable fury was the last thing you would have expected from this quiet and demure woman. Mr. Joyce had known her a good many years, and had always thought her an unemotional person; during the weeks that had passed since the tragedy her composure had been amazing.

Mr. Joyce shrugged his shoulders.

"The fact is, I suppose," he reflected, "that you can never tell what hidden possibilities of savagery there are in the most respectable of women."

There was a knock at the door.

"Come in."

The Chinese clerk entered and closed the door behind him. He closed it gently, with deliberation, but decidedly, and advanced to the table at which Mr. Joyce was sitting.

"May I trouble you, sir, for a few words' private conversation?" he said.

The elaborate accuracy with which the clerk expressed himself always faintly amused Mr. Joyce, and now he smiled.

"It's no trouble, Chi Seng," he replied.

"The matter on which I desire to speak to you, sir, is delicate and confidential."

"Fire away."

Mr. Joyce met his clerk's shrewd eyes. As usual Ong Chi Seng was dressed in the height of local fashion. He wore very shiny patent-leather shoes and gay silk socks. In his black tie was a pearl and ruby pin, and on the fourth finger of his left hand a diamond ring. From the pocket of his neat white coat protruded a gold fountain pen and a gold pencil. He wore a gold wrist-watch, and on the bridge of his nose invisible pince-nez. He gave a little cough.

"The matter has to do with the case R. V. Crosbie, sir."

"Yes?"

"A circumstance has come to my knowledge, sir, which seems to me to put a different complexion on it."

"What circumstance?"

"It has come to my knowledge, sir, that there is a letter in existence from the defendant to the unfortunate victim of the tragedy."

"I shouldn't be at all surprised. In the course of the last seven years I have no doubt that Mrs. Crosbie often had occasion to write to Mr. Hammond."

Mr. Joyce had a high opinion of his clerk's intelligence and his words were designed to conceal his thoughts.

"That is very probable, sir. Mrs. Crosbie must have communicated with the deceased frequently, to invite him to dine with her for example, or to propose a tennis game. That was my first thought when the matter was brought to my notice. This letter, however, was written on the day of the late Mr. Hammond's death."

Mr. Joyce did not flicker an eyelash. He continued to look at Ong Chi Seng with the smile of faint amusement with which he generally talked to him.

"Who has told you this?"

"The circumstances were brought to my knowledge, sir, by a friend of mine."

Mr. Joyce knew better than to insist.

"You will no doubt recall, sir, that Mrs. Crosbie has stated that until the fatal night she had had no communication with the deceased for several weeks."

"Have you got the letter?"

"No, sir."

"What are its contents?"

"My friend gave me a copy. Would you like to peruse it, sir?"

"I should."

Ong Chi Seng took from an inside pocket a bulky wallet. It was filled with papers, Singapore dollar notes and cigarette cards. From the confusion he presently extracted a half-sheet of thin notepaper and placed it before Mr. Joyce. The letter read as follows:

R. will be away for the night. I absolutely must see you. I shall expect you at eleven. I am desperate, and if you don't come I won't answer for the consequences. Don't drive up.—L.

It was written in the flowing hand which the Chinese were taught at the foreign schools. The writing, so lacking in character, was oddly incongruous with the ominous words.

"What makes you think that this note was written by Mrs. Crosbie?"

"I have every confidence in the veracity of my informant, sir," replied Ong Chi Seng. "And the matter can very easily be put to the proof. Mrs. Crosbie will, no doubt, be able to tell you at once whether she wrote such a letter or not."

Since the beginning of the conversation Mr. Joyce had not taken his eyes off the respectable countenance of his clerk. He wondered now if he discerned in it a faint expression of mockery.

"It is inconceivable that Mrs. Crosbie should have written such a letter," said Mr. Joyce.

"If that is your opinion, sir, the matter is of course ended. My friend spoke to me on the subject only because he thought, as I was in your office, you might like to know of the existence of this letter before a communication was made to the Deputy Public Prosecutor."

"Who has the original?" asked Mr. Joyce sharply.

Ong Chi Seng made no sign that he perceived in this question and its manner a change of attitude.

"You will remember, sir, no doubt, that after the death of Mr. Hammond it was discovered that he had had relations with a Chinese woman. The letter is at present in her possession."

That was one of the things which had turned public opinion most vehemently against Hammond. It came to be known that for several months he had had a Chinese woman living in his house.

For a moment neither of them spoke. Indeed everything had been said and each understood the other perfectly.

"I'm obliged to you, Chi Seng. I will give the matter my consideration."

"Very good, sir. Do you wish me to make a communication to that effect to my friend?"

"I dare say it would be as well if you kept in touch with him," Mr. Joyce answered with gravity.

"Yes, sir."

The clerk noiselessly left the room, shutting the door again with deliberation, and left Mr. Joyce to his reflections. He stared at the copy, in its neat, impersonal writing, of Leslie's letter. Vague suspicions troubled him. They were so disconcerting that he made an effort to put them out of his mind. There must be a simple explanation of the letter, and Leslie without doubt could give it at once, but, by heaven, an explanation was needed. He rose from his chair, put the letter in his pocket, and took his topee. When he went out Ong Chi Seng was busily writing at his desk.

"I'm going out for a few minutes, Chi Seng," he said.

"Mr. George Reed is coming by appointment at twelve o'clock, sir. Where shall I say you've gone?"

Mr. Joyce gave him a thin smile.

"You can say that you haven't the least idea."

But he knew perfectly well that Ong Chi Seng was aware that he was going to the gaol. Though the crime had been committed in Belanda and the trial was to take place at Belanda Bharu, since there was in the gaol no convenience for the detention of a white woman Mrs. Crosbie had been brought to Singapore.

When she was led into the room in which he waited she held out her thin, distinguished hand, and gave him a pleasant smile. She was as ever neatly and simply dressed, and her abundant, pale hair was arranged with care.

"I wasn't expecting to see you this morning," she said, graciously.

She might have been in her own house, and Mr. Joyce almost expected to hear her call the boy and tell him to bring the visitor a gin pahit.

"How are you?" he asked.

"I'm in the best of health, thank you." A flicker of amusement flashed across her eyes. "This is a wonderful place for a rest cure."

The attendant withdrew and they were left alone.

"Do sit down," said Leslie.

He took a chair. He did not quite know how to begin. She was so cool that it seemed almost impossible to say to her the thing he had come to say. Though she was not pretty there was something agreeable in her appearance. She had elegance, but it was the elegance of good breeding in which there was nothing of the artifice of society. You had only to look at her to know what sort of people she had and what kind of surroundings she had lived in. Her fragility gave her a singular refinement. It was impossible to associate her with the vaguest idea of grossness.

"I'm looking forward to seeing Robert this afternoon," she said, in her good-humoured, easy voice. (It was a pleasure to hear her speak, her voice and her accent were so distinctive of her class.) "Poor dear, it's been a great trial to his nerves. I'm thankful it'll all be over in a few days."

"It's only five days now."

"I know. Each morning when I awake I say to myself, 'one less.'" She smiled then. "Just as I used to do at school and the holidays were coming."

"By the way, am I right in thinking that you had no communication whatever with Hammond for several weeks before the catastrophe?"

"I'm quite positive of that. The last time we met was at a tennis-party at the MacFarrens. I don't think I said more than two words to him. They have two courts, you know, and we didn't happen to be in the same sets."

"And you haven't written to him?"

"Oh, no."

"Are you quite sure of that?"

"Oh, quite," she answered, with a little smile. "There was nothing I should write to him for except to ask him to dine or to play tennis, and I hadn't done either for months."

"At one time you'd been on fairly intimate terms with him. How did it happen that you had stopped asking him to anything?"

Mrs. Crosbie shrugged her thin shoulders.

"One gets tired of people. We hadn't anything very much in common. Of course, when he was ill Robert and I did everything we could for him, but the last year or two he'd been quite well, and he was very popular. He had a good many calls on his time, and there didn't seem to be any need to shower invitations upon him."

"Are you quite certain that was all?"

Mrs. Crosbie hesitated for a moment.

"Well, I may just as well tell you. It had come to our ears that he was living with a Chinese woman, and Robert said he wouldn't have him in the house. I had seen her myself."

Mr. Joyce was sitting in a straight-backed arm-chair, resting his chin on his hand, and his eyes were fixed on Leslie. Was it his fancy that, as she made this remark, her black pupils were filled on a sudden, for the fraction of a second, with a dull red light? The effect was startling. Mr. Joyce shifted in his chair. He placed the tips of his ten fingers together. He spoke very slowly, choosing his words.

"I think I should tell you that there is in existence a letter in your handwriting to Geoff Hammond."

He watched her closely. She made no movement, nor did her face change colour, but she took a noticeable time to reply.

"In the past I've often sent him little notes to ask him to something or other, or to get me something when I knew he was going to Singapore."

"This letter asks him to come and see you because Robert was going to Singapore."

"That's impossible. I never did anything of the kind."

"You'd better read it for yourself."

He took it out of his pocket and handed it to her. She gave it a glance and with a smile of scorn handed it back to him.

"That's not my handwriting."

"I know, it's said to be an exact copy of the original."

She read the words now, and as she read a horrible change came over her. Her colourless face grew dreadful to look at. It turned green. The flesh seemed on a sudden to fall away and her skin was tightly stretched over the bones. Her lips receded, showing her teeth, so that she had the appearance of making a grimace. She stared at Mr. Joyce with eyes that started from their sockets. He was looking now at a gibbering death's head.

"What does it mean?" she whispered.

Her mouth was so dry that she could utter no more than a hoarse sound. It was no longer a human voice.

"That is for you to say," he answered.

"I didn't write it. I swear I didn't write it."

"Be very careful what you say. If the original is in your handwriting it would be useless to deny it."

"It would be a forgery."

"It would be difficult to prove that. It would be easy to prove that it was genuine."

A shiver passed through her lean body. But great beads of sweat stood on her forehead. She took a handkerchief from her bag and wiped the palms of her hands. She glanced at the letter again and gave Mr. Joyce a sidelong look.

"It's not dated. If I had written it and forgotten all about it, it might have been written years ago. If you'll give me time, I'll try and remember the circumstances."

"I noticed there was no date. If this letter were in the hands of the prosecution they would cross-examine the boys. They would soon find out whether someone took a letter to Hammond on the day of his death."

Mrs. Crosbie clasped her hands violently and swayed in her chair so that he thought she would faint.

"I swear to you that I didn't write that letter."

Mr. Joyce was silent for a little while. He took his eyes from her distraught face, and looked down on the floor. He was reflecting.

"In these circumstances we need not go into the matter further," he said slowly, at last breaking the silence. "If the possessor of this letter sees fit to place it in the hands of the prosecution you will be prepared."

His words suggested that he had nothing more to say to her, but he made no movement of departure. He waited. To himself he seemed to wait a very long time. He did not look at Leslie, but he was conscious that she sat very still. She made no sound. At last it was he who spoke.

"If you have nothing more to say to me I think I'll be getting back to my office."

"What would anyone who read the letter be inclined to think that it meant?" she asked then.

"He'd know that you had told a deliberate lie," answered Mr. Joyce sharply.

"When?"

"You have stated definitely that you had had no communication with Hammond for at least three months."

"The whole thing has been a terrible shock to me. The events of that dreadful night have been a nightmare. It's not very strange if one detail has escaped my memory."

"It would be unfortunate, when your memory has reproduced so exactly every particular of your interview with Hammond, that you should have forgotten so important a point as that he came to see you in the bungalow on the night of his death at your express desire."

"I hadn't forgotten. After what happened I was afraid to mention it. I thought you'd none of you believe my story if I admitted that he'd come at my invitation. I dare say it was stupid of me; but I lost my head, and after I'd said once that I'd had no communication with Hammond I was obliged to stick to it."

By now Leslie had recovered her admirable composure, and she met Mr. Joyce's appraising glance with candour. Her gentleness was very disarming.

"You will be required to explain, then, why you asked Hammond to come and see you when Robert was away for the night."

She turned her eyes full on the lawyer. He had been mistaken in thinking them insignificant, they were rather fine eyes, and unless he was mistaken they were bright now with tears. Her voice had a little break in it.

"It was a surprise I was preparing for Robert. His birthday is next month. I knew he wanted a new gun and you know I'm dreadfully stupid about sporting things. I wanted to talk to Geoff about it. I thought I'd get him to order it for me."

"Perhaps the terms of the letter are not very clear to your recollection. Will you have another look at it?"

"No, I don't want to," she said quickly.

"Does it seem to you the sort of letter a woman would write to a somewhat distant acquaintance because she wanted to consult him about buying a gun?"

"I dare say it's rather extravagant and emotional. I do express myself like that, you know. I'm quite prepared to admit it's very silly." She smiled. "And after all, Geoff Hammond wasn't quite a distant acquaintance. When he was ill I'd nursed him like a mother. I asked him to come when Robert was away, because Robert wouldn't have him in the house."

Mr. Joyce was tired of sitting so long in the same position. He rose and walked once or twice up and down the room, choosing the words he proposed to say; then he leaned over the back of the chair in which he had been sitting. He spoke slowly in a tone of deep gravity.

"Mrs. Crosbie, I want to talk to you very, very seriously. This case was comparatively plain sailing. There was only one point which seemed to me to require explanation: as far as I could judge, you had fired no less than four shots into Hammond when he was lying on the ground. It was hard to accept the possibility that a delicate, frightened, and habitually self-controlled woman, of gentle nature and refined instincts, should have surrendered to an absolutely uncontrolled frenzy. But of course it was admissible. Although Geoffrey Hammond was much liked and on the whole thought highly of, I was prepared to prove that he was the sort of man who might be guilty of the crime which in justification of your act you accused him of. The fact, which was discovered after his death, that he had been living with a Chinese woman gave us something very definite to go upon. That robbed him of any sympathy which might have been felt for him. We made up our minds to make use of the odium which such a connexion cast upon him in the minds of all respectable people. I told your husband this morning that I was certain of an acquittal, and I wasn't just telling him that to give him heart. I do not believe the assessors would have left the court."

They looked into one another's eyes. Mrs. Crosbie was strangely still. She was like a little bird paralysed by the fascination of a snake. He went on in the same quiet tones.

"But this letter has thrown an entirely different complexion on the case. I am your legal adviser, I shall represent you in court. I take your story as you tell it me, and I shall conduct your defence according to its terms. It may be that I believe your statements, and it may be that I doubt them. The duty of counsel is to persuade the court that the evidence placed before it is not such as to justify it in bringing in a verdict of guilty, and any private opinion he may have of the guilt or innocence of his client is entirely beside the point."

He was astonished to see in Leslie's eyes the flicker of a smile. Piqued, he went on somewhat dryly:

"You're not going to deny that Hammond came to your house at your urgent, and I may even say, hysterical invitation?"

Mrs. Crosbie, hesitating for an instant, seemed to consider.

"They can prove that the letter was taken to his bungalow by one of the house-boys. He rode over on his bicycle."

"You mustn't expect other people to be stupider than you. The letter will put them on the track of suspicions which have entered nobody's head. I will not tell you what I personally thought when I saw the copy. I do not wish you to tell me anything but what is needed to save your neck."

Mrs. Crosbie gave a shrill cry. She sprang to her feet, white with terror.

"You don't think they'd hang me?"

"If they came to the conclusion that you hadn't killed Hammond in self-defence, it would be the duty of the assessors to bring in a verdict of guilty. The charge is murder. It would be the duty of the judge to sentence you to death."

"But what can they prove?" she gasped.

"I don't know what they can prove. You know. I don't want to know. But if their suspicions are aroused, if they begin to make inquiries, if the natives are questioned—what is it that can be discovered?"

She crumpled up suddenly. She fell on the floor before he could catch her. She had fainted. He looked round the room for water, but there was none there, and he did not want to be disturbed. He stretched her out on the floor, and kneeling beside her waited for her to recover. When she opened her eyes he was disconcerted by the ghastly fear that he saw in them.

"Keep quite still," he said. "You'll be better in a moment."

"You won't let them hang me," she whispered.

She began to cry, hysterically, while in undertones he sought to quieten her.

"For goodness sake pull yourself together," he said.

"Give me a minute."

Her courage was amazing. He could see the effort she made to regain her self-control, and soon she was once more calm.

"Let me get up now."

He gave her his hand and helped her to her feet. Taking her arm, he led her to the chair. She sat down wearily.

"Don't talk to me for a minute or two," she said.

"Very well."

When at last she spoke it was to say something which he did not expect. She gave a little sigh.

"I'm afraid I've made rather a mess of things," she said.

He did not answer, and once more there was a silence.

"Isn't it possible to get hold of the letter?" she said at last.

"I do not think anything would have been said to me about it if the person in whose possession it is was not prepared to sell it."

"Who's got it?"

"The Chinese woman who was living in Hammond's house."

A spot of colour flickered for an instant on Leslie's cheek-bones.

"Does she want an awful lot for it?"

"I imagine that she has a very shrewd idea of its value. I doubt if it would be possible to get hold of it except for a very large sum."

"Are you going to let me be hanged?"

"Do you think it's so simple as all that to secure possession of an unwelcome piece of evidence? It's no different from suborning a witness. You have no right to make any such suggestion to me."

"Then what is going to happen to me?"

"Justice must take its course."

She grew very pale. A little shudder passed through her body.

"I put myself in your hands. Of course I have no right to ask you to do anything that isn't proper."

Mr. Joyce had not bargained for the little break in her voice which her habitual self-restraint made quite intolerably moving. She looked at him with humble eyes, and he thought that if he rejected their appeal they would haunt him for the rest of his life. After all, nothing could bring poor Hammond back to life again. He wondered what really was the explanation of that letter. It was not fair to conclude from it that she had killed Hammond without provocation. He had lived in the East a long time and his sense of professional honour was not perhaps so acute as it had been twenty years before. He stared at the floor. He made up his mind to do something which he knew was unjustifiable, but it stuck in his throat and he felt dully resentful towards Leslie. It embarrassed him a little to speak.

"I don't know exactly what your husband's circumstances are?"

Flushing a rosy red, she shot a swift glance at him.

"He has a good many tin shares and a small share in two or three rubber estates. I suppose he could raise money."

"He would have to be told what it was for."

She was silent for a moment. She seemed to think.

"He's in love with me still. He would make any sacrifice to save me. Is there any need for him to see the letter?"

Mr. Joyce frowned a little, and, quick to notice, she went on.

"Robert is an old friend of yours. I'm not asking you to do anything for me, I'm asking you to save a rather simple, kind man who never did you any harm from all the pain that's possible."

Mr. Joyce did not reply. He rose to go and Mrs. Crosbie, with the grace that was natural to her, held out her hand. She was shaken by the scene, and her look was haggard, but she made a brave attempt to speed him with courtesy.

"It's so good of you to take all this trouble for me. I can't begin to tell you how grateful I am."

Mr. Joyce returned to his office. He sat in his own room, quite still, attempting to do no work, and pondered. His imagination brought him many strange ideas. He shuddered a little. At last there was the discreet knock on the door which he was expecting. Ong Chi Seng came in.

"I was just going out to have my tiffin, sir," he said.

"All right."

"I didn't know if there was anything you wanted before I went, sir."

"I don't think so. Did you make another appointment for Mr. Reed?"

"Yes, sir. He will come at three o'clock."

"Good."

Ong Chi Seng turned away, walked to the door, and put his long slim fingers on the handle. Then, as though on an afterthought, he turned back.

"Is there anything you wish me to say to my friend, sir?"

Although Ong Chi Seng spoke English so admirably he had still a difficulty with the letter R, and he pronounced it "fliend".

"What friend?"

"About the letter Mrs. Crosbie wrote to Hammond deceased, sir."

"Oh! I'd forgotten about that. I mentioned it to Mrs. Crosbie and she denies having written anything of the sort. It's evidently a forgery."

Mr. Joyce took the copy from his pocket and handed it to Ong Chi Seng. Ong Chi Seng ignored the gesture.

"In that case, sir, I suppose there would be no objection if my fliend delivered the letter to the Deputy Public Prosecutor."

"None. But I don't quite see what good that would do your friend."

"My fliend, sir, thought it was his duty in the interests of justice."

"I am the last man in the world to interfere with anyone who wishes to do his duty, Chi Seng."

The eyes of the lawyer and of the Chinese clerk met. Not the shadow of a smile hovered on the lips of either, but they understood each other perfectly.

"I quite understand, sir," said Ong Chi Seng, "but from my study of the case R. V. Crosbie I am of opinion that the production of such a letter would be damaging to our client."

"I have always had a very high opinion of your legal acumen, Chi Seng."

"It had occurred to me, sir, that if I could persuade my fliend to induce the Chinese woman who has the letter to deliver it into our hands it would save a great deal of trouble."

Mr. Joyce idly drew faces on his blotting-paper.

"I suppose your friend is a business man. In what circumstances do you think he would be induced to part with the letter?"

"He has not got the letter. The Chinese woman has the letter. He is only a relation of the Chinese woman. She is ignorant woman; she did not know the value of that letter till my friend told her."

"What value did he put on it?"

"Ten thousand dollars, sir."

"Good God! Where on earth do you suppose Mrs. Crosbie can get ten thousand dollars! I tell you the letter's a forgery."

He looked up at Ong Chi Seng as he spoke. The clerk was unmoved by the outburst. He stood at the side of the desk, civil, cool, and observant.

"Mr. Crosbie owns an eighth share of the Betong Rubber Estate and a sixth share of the Selantan River Rubber Estate. I have a fliend who will lend him the money on the security of—his property."

"You have a large circle of acquaintance, Chi Seng."

"Yes, sir."

"Well, you can tell them all to go to hell. I would never advise Mr. Crosbie to give a penny more than five thousand for a letter that can be very easily explained."

"The Chinese woman does not want to sell the letter, sir. My fliend took a long time to persuade her. It is useless to offer her less than the sum mentioned."

Mr. Joyce looked at Ong Chi Seng for at least three minutes. The clerk bore the searching scrutiny without embarrassment. He stood in a respectful attitude with downcast eyes. Mr. Joyce knew his man. Clever fellow, Chi Seng, he thought, I wonder how much he's going to get out of it.

"Ten thousand dollars is a very large sum."

"Mr. Crosbie will certainly pay it rather than see his wife hanged, sir."

Again Mr. Joyce paused. What more did Chi Seng know than he had said? He must be pretty sure of his ground if he was obviously so unwilling to bargain. That sum had been fixed because whoever it was that was managing the affair knew it was the largest amount that Robert Crosbie could raise.

"Where is the Chinese woman now?" asked Mr. Joyce.

"She is staying at the house of my fliend, sir."

"Will she come here?"

"I think it more better if you go to her, sir. I can take you to the house tonight and she will give you the letter. She is very ignorant woman, sir, and she does not understand cheques."

"I wasn't thinking of giving her a cheque. I will bring bank notes with me."

"It would only be waste of valuable time to bring less than ten thousand dollars, sir."

"I quite understand."

"I will go and tell my fliend after I have had my tiffin, sir."

"Very good. You'd better meet me outside the club at ten o'clock tonight."

"With pleasure, sir," said Ong Chi Seng.

He gave Mr. Joyce a little bow and left the room. Mr. Joyce went out to have luncheon, too. He went to the club and here, as he had expected, he saw Robert Crosbie. He was sitting at a crowded table, and as he passed him, looking for a place, Mr. Joyce touched him on the shoulder.

"I'd like a word or two with you before you go," he said.

"Right you are. Let me know when you're ready."

Mr. Joyce had made up his mind how to tackle him. He played a rubber of bridge after luncheon in order to allow time for the club to empty itself. He did not want on this particular matter to see Crosbie in his office. Presently Crosbie came into the card-room and looked on till the game was finished. The other players went on their various affairs, and the two were left alone.

"A rather unfortunate thing has happened, old man," said Mr. Joyce, in a tone which he sought to render as casual as possible. "It appears that your wife sent a letter to Hammond asking him to come to the bungalow on the night he was killed."

"But that's impossible," cried Crosbie. "She's always stated that she had had no communication with Hammond. I know from my own knowledge that she hadn't set eyes on him for a couple of months."

"The fact remains that the letter exists. It's in the possession of the Chinese woman Hammond was living with. Your wife meant to give you a present on your birthday, and she wanted Hammond to help her to get it. In the emotional excitement that she suffered from after the tragedy, she forgot all about it, and having once denied having any communication with Hammond she was afraid to say that she had made a mistake. It was, of course, very unfortunate, but I dare say it was not unnatural."

Crosbie did not speak. His large, red face bore an expression of complete bewilderment, and Mr. Joyce was at once relieved and exasperated by his lack of comprehension. He was a stupid man, and Mr. Joyce had no patience with stupidity. But his distress since the catastrophe had touched a soft spot in the lawyer's heart; and Mrs. Crosbie had struck the right note when she asked him to help her, not for her sake, but for her husband's.

"I need not tell you that it would be very awkward if this letter found its way into the hands of the prosecution. Your wife has lied, and she would be asked to explain the lie. It alters things a little if Hammond did not intrude, an unwanted guest, but came to your house by invitation. It would be easy to arouse in the assessors a certain indecision of mind."

Mr. Joyce hesitated. He was face to face now with his decision. If it had been a time for humour, he could have smiled at the reflection that he was taking so grave a step, and that the man for whom he was taking it had not the smallest conception of its gravity. If he gave the matter a thought, he probably imagined that what Mr. Joyce was doing was what any lawyer did in the ordinary run of business.

"My dear Robert, you are not only my client, but my friend. I think we must get hold of that letter. It'll cost a good deal of money. Except for that I should have preferred to say nothing to you about it."

"How much?"

"Ten thousand dollars."

"That's a devil of a lot. With the slump and one thing and another it'll take just about all I've got."

"Can you get it at once?"

"I suppose so. Old Charlie Meadows will let me have it on my tin shares and on those two estates I'm interested in."

"Then will you?"

"Is it absolutely necessary?"

"If you want your wife to be acquitted."

Crosbie grew very red. His mouth sagged strangely.

"But . . ." he could not find words, his face now was purple. "But I don't understand. She can explain. You don't mean to say they'd find her guilty? They couldn't hang her for putting a noxious vermin out of the way."

"Of course they wouldn't hang her. They might only find her guilty of manslaughter. She'd probably get off with two or three years."

Crosbie started to his feet and his red face was distraught with horror.

"Three years."

Then something seemed to dawn in that slow intelligence of his. His mind was darkness across which shot suddenly a flash of lightning, and though the succeeding darkness was as profound, there remained the memory of something not seen but perhaps just descried. Mr. Joyce saw that Crosbie's big red hands, coarse and hard with all the odd jobs he had set them to, trembled.

"What was the present she wanted to make me?"

"She says she wanted to give you a new gun."

Once more that great red face flushed a deeper red.

"When have you got to have the money ready?"

There was something odd in his voice now. It sounded as though he spoke with invisible hands clutching at his throat.

"At ten o'clock tonight. I thought you could bring it to my office at about six."

"Is the woman coming to you?"

"No, I'm going to her."

"I'll bring the money. I'll come with you."

Mr. Joyce looked at him sharply.

"Do you think there's any need for you to do that? I think it would be better if you left me to deal with this matter by myself."

"It's my money, isn't it? I'm going to come."

Mr. Joyce shrugged his shoulders. They rose and shook hands. Mr. Joyce looked at him curiously.

At ten o'clock they met in the empty club.

"Everything all right?" asked Mr. Joyce.

"Yes. I've got the money in my pocket."

"Let's go then."

They walked down the steps. Mr. Joyce's car was waiting for them in the square, silent at that hour, and as they came to it Ong Chi Seng stepped out of the shadow of a house. He took his seat beside the driver and gave him a direction. They drove past the Hotel de l"Europe and turned up by the Sailor's Home to get into Victoria Street. Here the Chinese shops were still open, idlers lounged about, and in the roadway rickshaws and motor-cars and gharries gave a busy air to the scene. Suddenly their car stopped and Chi Seng turned round.

"I think it more better if we walk here, sir," he said.

They got out and he went on. They followed a step or two behind. Then he asked them to stop.

"You wait here, sir. I go in and speak to my fliend."

He went into a shop, open to the street, where three or four Chinese were standing behind the counter. It was one of those strange shops where nothing was on view, and you wondered what it was they sold there. They saw him address a stout man in a duck suit with a large gold chain across his breast, and the man shot a quick glance out into the night. He gave Chi Seng a key and Chi Seng came out. He beckoned to the two men waiting and slid into a doorway at the side of the shop. They followed him and found themselves at the foot of a flight of stairs.

"If you wait a minute I will light a match," he said, always resourceful. "You come upstairs, please."

He held a Japanese match in front of them, but it scarcely dispelled the darkness and they groped their way up behind him. On the first floor he unlocked a door and going in lit a gas-jet.

"Come in, please," he said.

It was a small square room, with one window, and the only furniture consisted of two low Chinese beds covered with matting. In one corner was a large chest, with an elaborate lock, and on this stood a shabby tray with an opium pipe on it and a lamp. There was in the room the faint, acrid scent of the drug. They sat down and Ong Chi Seng offered them cigarettes. In a moment the door was opened by the fat Chinaman whom they had seen behind the counter. He bade them good evening in very good English, and sat down by the side of his fellow-countryman.

"The Chinese woman is just coming," said Chi Seng.

A boy from the shop brought in a tray with a teapot and cups and the Chinaman offered them a cup of tea. Crosbie refused. The Chinese talked to one another in undertones, but Crosbie and Mr. Joyce were silent. At last there was the sound of a voice outside; someone was calling in a low tone; and the Chinaman went to the door. He opened it, spoke a few words, and ushered a woman in. Mr. Joyce looked at her. He had heard much about her since Hammond's death, but he had never seen her. She was a stoutish person, not very young, with a broad, phlegmatic face, she was powdered and rouged and her eyebrows were a thin black line, but she gave you the impression of a woman of character. She wore a pale blue jacket and a white skirt, her costume was not quite European nor quite Chinese, but on her feet were little Chinese silk slippers. She wore heavy gold chains round her neck, gold bangles on her wrists, gold ear-rings, and elaborate gold pins in her black hair. She walked in slowly, with the air of a woman sure of herself, but with a certain heaviness of tread, and sat down on the bed beside Ong Chi Seng. He said something to her and nodding she gave an incurious glance at the two white men.

"Has she got the letter?" asked Mr. Joyce.

"Yes, sir."

Crosbie said nothing, but produced a roll of five-hundred-dollar notes. He counted out twenty and handed them to Chi Seng.

"Will you see if that is correct?"

The clerk counted them and gave them to the fat Chinaman.

"Quite correct, sir."

The Chinaman counted them once more and put them in his pocket. He spoke again to the woman and she drew from her bosom a letter. She gave it to Chi Seng who cast his eyes over it.

"This is the right document, sir," he said, and was about to give it to Mr. Joyce when Crosbie took it from him.

"Let me look at it," he said.

Mr. Joyce watched him read and then held out his hand for it.

"You'd better let me have it."

Crosbie folded it up deliberately and put it in his pocket.

"No, I'm going to keep it myself. It's cost me enough money."

Mr. Joyce made no rejoinder. The three Chinese watched the little passage, but what they thought about it, or whether they thought, it was impossible to tell from their impassive countenances. Mr. Joyce rose to his feet.

"Do you want me any more tonight, sir?" said Ong Chi Seng.

"No." He knew that the clerk wished to stay behind in order to get his agreed share of the money, and he turned to Crosbie. "Are you ready?"

Crosbie did not answer, but stood up. The Chinaman went to the door and opened it for them. Chi Seng found a bit of candle and lit it in order to light them down, and the two Chinese accompanied them to the street. They left the woman sitting quietly on the bed smoking a cigarette. When they reached the street the Chinese left them and went once more upstairs.

"What are you going to do with that letter?" asked Mr. Joyce.

"Keep it."

They walked to where the car was waiting for them and here Mr. Joyce offered his friend a lift. Crosbie shook his head.

"I'm going to walk." He hesitated a little and shuffled his feet. "I went to Singapore on the night of Hammond's death partly to buy a new gun that a man I knew wanted to dispose of. Good night."

He disappeared quickly into the darkness.

Mr. Joyce was quite right about the trial. The assessors went into court fully determined to acquit Mrs. Crosbie. She gave evidence on her own behalf. She told her story simply and with straightforwardness. The D.P.P. was a kindly man and it was plain that he took no great pleasure in his task. He asked the necessary questions in a deprecating manner. His speech for the prosecution might really have been a speech for the defence, and the assessors took less than five minutes to consider their popular verdict. It was impossible to prevent the great outburst of applause with which it was received by the crowd that packed the courthouse. The judge congratulated Mrs. Crosbie and she was a free woman.

No one had expressed a more violent disapprobation of Hammond's behaviour than Mrs. Joyce; she was a woman loyal to her friends and she had insisted on the Crosbies staying with her after the trial, for she in common with everyone else had no doubt of the result, till they could make arrangements to go away. It was out of the question for poor, dear, brave Leslie to return to the bungalow at which the horrible catastrophe had taken place.

The trial was over by half past twelve and when they reached the Joyces' house a grand luncheon was awaiting them. Cocktails were ready, Mrs. Joyce's million-dollar cocktail was celebrated through all the Malay States, and Mrs. Joyce drank Leslie's health. She was a talkative, vivacious woman, and now she was in the highest spirits. It was fortunate, for the rest of them were silent. She did not wonder; her husband never had much to say, and the other two were naturally exhausted from the long strain to which they had been subjected. During luncheon she carried on a bright and spirited monologue. Then coffee was served.

"Now, children," she said in her gay, bustling fashion, "you must have a rest and after tea I shall take you both for a drive to the sea."

Mr. Joyce, who lunched at home only by exception, had of course to go back to his office.

"I'm afraid I can't do that, Mrs. Joyce," said Crosbie. "I've got to get back to the estate at once."

"Not today?" she cried.

"Yes, now. I've neglected it for too long and I have urgent business. But I shall be very grateful if you will keep Leslie until we have decided what to do."

Mrs. Joyce was about to expostulate, but her husband prevented her.

"If he must go, he must, and there's an end of it."

There was something in the lawyer's tone which made her look at him quickly. She held her tongue and there was a moment's silence. Then Crosbie spoke again.

"If you'll forgive me, I'll start at once so that I can get there before dark." He rose from the table. "Will you come and see me off, Leslie?"

"Of course."

They went out of the dining-room together.

"I think that's rather inconsiderate of him," said Mrs. Joyce. "He must know that Leslie wants to be with him just now."

"I'm sure he wouldn't go if it wasn't absolutely necessary."

"Well, I'll just see that Leslie's room is ready for her. She wants a complete rest, of course, and then amusement."

Mrs. Joyce left the room and Joyce sat down again. In a short time he heard Crosbie start the engine of his motor-cycle and then noisily scrunch over the gravel of the garden path. He got up and went into the drawing-room. Mrs. Crosbie was standing in the middle of it, looking into space, and in her hand was an open letter. He recognized it. She gave him a glance as he came in and he saw that she was deathly pale.

"He knows," she whispered.

Mr. Joyce went up to her and took the letter from her hand. He lit a match and set the paper afire. She watched it burn. When he could hold it no longer he dropped it on the tiled floor and they both looked at the paper curl and blacken. Then he trod it into ashes with his foot.

"What does he know?"

She gave him a long, long stare and into her eyes came a strange look. Was it contempt or despair? Mr. Joyce could not tell.

"He knows that Geoff was my lover."

Mr. Joyce made no movement and uttered no sound.

"He'd been my lover for years. He became my lover almost immediately after he came back from the war. We knew how careful we must be. When we became lovers I pretended I was tired of him, and he seldom came to the house when Robert was there. I used to drive out to a place we knew and he met me, two or three times a week, and when Robert went to Singapore he used to come to the bungalow late, when the boys had gone for the night. We saw one another constantly, all the time, and not a soul had the smallest suspicion of it. And then lately, a year ago, he began to change. I didn't know what was the matter. I couldn't believe that he didn't care for me any more. He always denied it. I was frantic. I made him scenes. Sometimes I thought he hated me. Oh, if you knew what agonies I endured. I passed through hell. I knew he didn't want me any more and I wouldn't let him go. Misery! Misery! I loved him. I'd given him everything. He was my life. And then I heard he was living with a Chinese woman. I couldn't believe it. I wouldn't believe it. At last I saw her, I saw her with my own eyes, walking in the village, with her gold bracelets and her necklaces, an old, fat Chinese woman. She was older than I was. Horrible! They all knew in the kampong that she was his mistress. And when I passed her, she looked at me and I knew that she knew I was his mistress too. I sent for him. I told him I must see him. You've read the letter. I was mad to write it. I didn't know what I was doing. I didn't care. I hadn't seen him for ten days. It was a lifetime. And when last we'd parted he took me in his arms and kissed me, and told me not to worry. And he went straight from my arms to hers."

She had been speaking in a low voice, vehemently, and now she stopped and wrung her hands.

"That damned letter. We'd always been so careful. He always tore up any word I wrote to him the moment he'd read it. How was I to know he'd leave that one? He came, and I told him I knew about the Chinawoman. He denied it. He said it was only scandal. I was beside myself. I don't know what I said to him. Oh, I hated him then. I tore him limb from limb. I said everything I could to wound him. I insulted him. I could have spat in his face. And at last he turned on me. He told me he was sick and tired of me and never wanted to see me again. He said I bored him to death. And then he acknowledged that it was true about the Chinawoman. He said he'd known her for years, before the war, and she was the only woman who really meant anything to him, and the rest was just pastime. And he said he was glad I knew and now at last I'd leave him alone. And then I don't know what happened, I was beside myself, I saw red. I seized the revolver and I fired. He gave a cry and I saw I'd hit him. He staggered and rushed for the veranda. I ran after him and fired again. He fell and then I stood over him and I fired till the revolver went click, click, and I knew there were no more cartridges."

At last she stopped, panting. Her face was no longer human, it was distorted with cruelty, and rage and pain. You would never have thought that this quiet, refined woman was capable of such fiendish passion. Mr. Joyce took a step backwards. He was absolutely aghast at the sight of her. It was not a face, it was a gibbering, hideous mask. Then they heard a voice calling from another room, a loud, friendly, cheerful voice. It was Mrs. Joyce.

"Come along, Leslie darling, your room's ready. You must be dropping with sleep."

Mrs. Crosbie's features gradually composed themselves. Those passions, so clearly delineated, were smoothed away as with your hand you would smooth crumpled paper, and in a minute the face was cool and calm and unlined. She was a trifle pale, but her lips broke into a pleasant, affable smile. She was once more the well-bred and even distinguished woman.

"I'm coming, Dorothy dear. I'm sorry to give you so much trouble."

Before the Party

Mrs. Skinner liked to be in good time. She was already dressed, in black silk as befitted her age and the mourning she wore for her son-in-law, and now she put on her toque. She was a little uncertain about it, since the egrets' feathers which adorned it might very well arouse in some of the friends she would certainly meet at the party acid expostulations; and of course it was shocking to kill those beautiful white birds, in the mating season too, for the sake of their feathers; but there they were, so pretty and stylish, and it would have been silly to refuse them, and it would have hurt her son-in-law's feelings. He had brought them all the way from Borneo and he expected her to be so pleased with them. Kathleen had made herself rather unpleasant about them, she must wish she hadn't now, after what had happened, but Kathleen had never really liked Harold. Mrs. Skinner, standing at her dressing-table, placed the toque on her head, it was after all the only nice hat she had, and put in a pin with a large jet knob. If anybody spoke to her about the ospreys she had her answer.

"I know it's dreadful," she would say, "and I wouldn't dream of buying them, but my poor son-in-law brought them back the last time he was home on leave."

That would explain her possession of them and excuse their use. Everyone had been very kind. Mrs. Skinner took a clean handkerchief from a drawer and sprinkled a little Eau de Cologne on it. She never used scent, and she had always thought it rather fast, but Eau de Cologne was so refreshing. She was very nearly ready now, and her eyes wandered out of the window behind her looking-glass. Canon Heywood had a beautiful day for his garden-party. It was warm and the sky was blue; the trees had not yet lost the fresh green of the spring. She smiled as she saw her little granddaughter in the strip of garden behind the house busily raking her very own flower-bed. Mrs. Skinner wished Joan were not quite so pale, it was a mistake to have kept her so long in the tropics; and she was so grave for her age, you never saw her run about; she played quiet games of her own invention and watered her garden. Mrs. Skinner gave the front of her dress a little pat, took up her gloves, and went downstairs.

Kathleen was at the writing-table in the window busy with lists she was making, for she was honorary secretary of the Ladies' Golf Club, and when there were competitions had a good deal to do. But she too was ready for the party.

"I see you've put on your jumper after all," said Mrs. Skinner.

They had discussed at luncheon whether Kathleen should wear her jumper or her black chiffon. The jumper was black and white, and Kathleen thought it rather smart, but it was hardly mourning. Millicent, however, was in favour of it.

"There's no reason why we should all look as if we'd just come from a funeral," she said. "Harold's been dead eight months."

To Mrs. Skinner it seemed rather unfeeling to talk like that. Millicent was strange since her return from Borneo.

"You're not going to leave off your weeds yet, darling?" she asked.

Millicent did not give a direct answer.

"People don't wear mourning in the way they used," she said. She paused a little and when she went on there was a tone in her voice which Mrs. Skinner thought quite peculiar. It was plain that Kathleen noticed it too, for she gave her sister a curious look. "I'm sure Harold wouldn't wish me to wear mourning for him indefinitely."

"I dressed early because I wanted to say something to Millicent," said Kathleen in reply to her mother's observation.

"Oh?"

Kathleen did not explain. But she put her lists aside and with knitted brows read for the second time a letter from a lady who complained that the committee had most unfairly marked down her handicap from twenty-four to eighteen. It requires a good deal of tact to be honorary secretary to a ladies' golf club. Mrs. Skinner began to put on her new gloves. The sun-blinds kept the room cool and dark. She looked at the great wooden hornbill, gaily painted, which Harold had left in her safekeeping; and it seemed a little odd and barbaric to her, but he had set much store on it. It had some religious significance and Canon Heywood had been greatly struck by it. On the wall, over the sofa, were Malay weapons, she forgot what they were called, and here and there on occasional tables pieces of silver and brass which Harold at various times had sent to them. She had liked Harold and involuntarily her eyes sought his photograph which stood on the piano with photographs of her two daughters, her grandchild, her sister, and her sister's son.

"Why, Kathleen, where's Harold's photograph?" she asked.

Kathleen looked round. It no longer stood in its place.

"Someone's taken it away," said Kathleen.

Surprised and puzzled, she got up and went over to the piano. The photographs had been rearranged so that no gap should show.

"Perhaps Millicent wanted to have it in her bedroom," said Mrs. Skinner.

"I should have noticed it. Besides, Millicent has several photographs of Harold. She keeps them locked up."

Mrs. Skinner had thought it very peculiar that her daughter should have no photographs of Harold in her room. Indeed she had spoken of it once, but Millicent had made no reply. Millicent had been strangely silent since she came back from Borneo, and had not encouraged the sympathy Mrs. Skinner would have been so willing to show her. She seemed unwilling to speak of her great loss. Sorrow took people in different ways. Her husband had said the best thing was to leave her alone. The thought of him turned her ideas to the party they were going to.

"Father asked if I thought he ought to wear a top-hat," she said. "I said I thought it was just as well to be on the safe side."

It was going to be quite a grand affair. They were having ices, strawberry and vanilla, from Boddy, the confectioner, but the Hey-woods were making the iced coffee at home. Everyone would be there. They had been asked to meet the Bishop of Hong Kong, who was staying with the Canon, an old college friend of his, and he was going to speak on the Chinese missions. Mrs. Skinner, whose daughter had lived in the East for eight years and whose son-in-law had been Resident of a district in Borneo, was in a flutter of interest. Naturally it meant more to her than to people who had never had anything to do with the Colonies and that sort of thing.

"What can they know of England who only England know?" as Mr. Skinner said.

He came into the room at that moment. He was a lawyer, as his father had been before him, and he had offices in Lincoln's Inn Fields. He went up to London every morning and came down every evening. He was only able to accompany his wife and daughters to the Canon's garden-party because the Canon had very wisely chosen a Saturday to have it on. Mr. Skinner looked very well in his tail-coat and pepper-and-salt trousers. He was not exactly dressy, but he was neat. He looked like a respectable family solicitor, which indeed he was; his firm never touched work that was not perfectly above board, and if a client went to him with some trouble that was not quite nice, Mr. Skinner would look grave.

"I don't think this is the sort of case that we very much care to undertake," he said. "I think you'd do better to go elsewhere."

He drew towards him his writing-block and scribbled a name and address on it. He tore off a sheet of paper and handed it to his client.

"If I were you I think I would go and see these people. If you mention my name I believe they'll do anything they can for you."

Mr. Skinner was clean-shaven and very bald. His pale lips were tight and thin, but his blue eyes were shy. He had no colour in his cheeks and his face was much lined.

"I see you've put on your new trousers," said Mrs. Skinner.

"I thought it would be a good opportunity," he answered. "I was wondering if I should wear a buttonhole."

"I wouldn't, father," said Kathleen. "I don't think it's awfully good form."

"A lot of people will be wearing them," said Mrs. Skinner.

"Only clerks and people like that," said Kathleen. "The Heywoods have had to ask everybody, you know. And besides, we are in mourning."

"I wonder if there'll be a collection after the Bishop's address," said Mr. Skinner.

"I should hardly think so," said Mrs. Skinner.

"I think it would be rather bad form," agreed Kathleen.

"It's as well to be on the safe side," said Mr. Skinner. "I'll give for all of us. I was wondering if ten shillings would be enough or if I must give a pound."

"If you give anything I think you ought to give a pound, father," said Kathleen.

"I'll see when the time comes. I don't want to give less than anyone else, but on the other hand I see no reason to give more than I need."

Kathleen put away her papers in the drawer of the writing-table and stood up. She looked at her wrist-watch.

"Is Millicent ready?" asked Mrs. Skinner.

"There's plenty of time. We're only asked at four, and I don't think we ought to arrive much before half past. I told Davis to bring the car round at four-fifteen."

Generally Kathleen drove the car, but on grand occasions like this Davis, who was the gardener, put on his uniform and acted as chauffeur. It looked better when you drove up, and naturally Kathleen didn't much want to drive herself when she was wearing her new jumper. The sight of her mother forcing her fingers one by one into her new gloves reminded her that she must put on her own. She smelt them to see if any odour of the cleaning still clung to them. It was very slight. She didn't believe anyone would notice.

At last the door opened and Millicent came in. She wore her widow's weeds. Mrs. Skinner never could get used to them, but of course she knew that Millicent must wear them for a year. It was a pity they didn't suit her; they suited some people. She had tried on Millicent's bonnet once, with its white band and long veil, and thought she looked very well in it. Of course she hoped dear Alfred would survive her, but if he didn't she would never go out of weeds. Queen Victoria never had. It was different for Millicent; Millicent was a much younger woman; she was only thirty-six: it was very sad to be a widow at thirty-six. And there wasn't much chance of her marrying again. Kathleen wasn't very likely to marry now, she was thirty-five; last time Millicent and Harold had come home she had suggested that they should have Kathleen to stay with them; Harold had seemed willing enough, but Millicent said it wouldn't do. Mrs. Skinner didn't know why not. It would give her a chance. Of course they didn't want to get rid of her, but a girl ought to marry, and somehow all the men they knew at home were married already. Millicent said the climate was trying. It was true she was a bad colour. No one would think now that Millicent had been the prettier of the two. Kathleen had fined down as she grew older, of course some people said she was too thin, but now that she had cut her hair, with her cheeks red from playing golf in all weathers, Mrs. Skinner thought her quite pretty. No one could say that of poor Millicent; she had lost her figure completely; she had never been tall, and now that she had filled out she looked stocky. She was a good deal too fat; Mrs. Skinner supposed it was due to the tropical heat that prevented her from taking exercise. Her skin was sallow and muddy; and her blue eyes, which had been her best feature, had gone quite pale.

"She ought to do something about her neck," Mrs. Skinner reflected. "She's becoming dreadfully jowly."

She had spoken of it once or twice to her husband. He remarked that Millicent wasn't as young as she was; that might be, but she needn't let herself go altogether. Mrs. Skinner made up her mind to talk to her daughter seriously, but of course she must respect her grief, and she would wait till the year was up. She was just as glad to have this reason to put off a conversation the thought of which made her slightly nervous. For Millicent was certainly changed. There was something sullen in her face which made her mother not quite at home with her. Mrs. Skinner liked to say aloud all the thoughts that passed through her head, but Millicent when you made a remark (just to say something, you know) had an awkward habit of not answering, so that you wondered whether she had heard. Sometimes Mrs. Skinner found it so irritating, that not to be quite sharp with Millicent she had to remind herself that poor Harold had only been dead eight months.

The light from the window fell on the widow's heavy face as she advanced silently, but Kathleen stood with her back to it. She watched her sister for a moment.

"Millicent, there's something I want to say to you," she said. "I was playing golf with Gladys Heywood this morning."

"Did you beat her?" asked Millicent.

Gladys Heywood was the Canon's only unmarried daughter.

"She told me something about you which I think you ought to know."

Millicent's eyes passed beyond her sister to the little girl watering flowers in the garden.

"Have you told Annie to give Joan her tea in the kitchen, mother?" she said.

"Yes, she'll have it when the servants have theirs."

Kathleen looked at her sister coolly.

"The Bishop spent two or three days at Singapore on his way home," she went on. "He's very fond of travelling. He's been to Borneo, and he knows a good many of the people that you know."

"He'll be interested to see you, dear," said Mrs. Skinner. "Did he know poor Harold?"

"Yes, he met him at Kuala Solor. He remembers him very well. He says he was shocked to hear of his death."

Millicent sat down and began to put on her black gloves. It seemed strange to Mrs. Skinner that she received these remarks with complete silence.

"Oh, Millicent," she said, "Harold's photo has disappeared. Have you taken it?"

"Yes, I put it away."

"I should have thought you'd like to have it out."

Once more Millicent said nothing. It really was an exasperating habit.

Kathleen turned slightly in order to face her sister.

"Millicent, why did you tell us that Harold died of fever?"

The widow made no gesture, she looked at Kathleen with steady eyes, but her sallow skin darkened with a flush. She did not reply.

"What do you mean, Kathleen?" asked Mr. Skinner, with surprise.

"The Bishop says that Harold committed suicide."

Mrs. Skinner gave a startled cry, but her husband put out a deprecating hand.

"Is it true, Millicent?"

"It is."

"But why didn't you tell us?"

Millicent paused for an instant. She fingered idly a piece of Brunei brass which stood on the table by her side. That too had been a present from Harold.

"I thought it better for Joan that her father should be thought to have died of fever. I didn't want her to know anything about it."

"You've put us in an awfully awkward position," said Kathleen, frowning a little. "Gladys Heywood said she thought it rather nasty of me not to have told her the truth. I had the greatest difficulty in getting her to believe that I knew absolutely nothing about it. She said her father was rather put out. He says, after all the years we've known one another, and considering that he married you, and the terms we've been on, and all that, he does think we might have had confidence in him. And at all events, if we didn't want to tell him the truth we needn't have told him a lie."

"I must say I sympathize with him there," said Mr. Skinner, acidly.

"Of course I told Gladys that we weren't to blame. We only told them what you told us."

"I hope it didn't put you off your game," said Millicent.

"Really, my dear, I think that is a most improper observation," exclaimed her father.

He rose from his chair, walked over to the empty fireplace, and from force of habit stood in front of it with parted coat-tails.

"It was my business," said Millicent, "and if I chose to keep it to myself I didn't see why I shouldn't."

"It doesn't look as if you had any affection for your mother if you didn't even tell her," said Mrs. Skinner.

Millicent shrugged her shoulders.

"You might have known it was bound to come out," said Kathleen.

"Why? I didn't expect that two gossiping old parsons would have nothing else to talk about than me."

"When the Bishop said he'd been to Borneo it's only natural that the Heywoods should ask him if he knew you and Harold."

"All that's neither here nor there," said Mr. Skinner. "I think you should certainly have told us the truth, and we could have decided what was the best thing to do. As a solicitor I can tell you that in the long run it only makes things worse if you attempt to hide them."

"Poor Harold," said Mrs. Skinner, and the tears began to trickle down her raddled cheeks. "It seems dreadful. He was always a good son-in-law to me. Whatever induced him to do such a dreadful thing?"

"The climate."

"I think you'd better give us all the facts, Millicent," said her father.

"Kathleen will tell you."

Kathleen hesitated. What she had to say really was rather dreadful. It seemed terrible that such things should happen to a family like theirs.

"The Bishop says he cut his throat."

Mrs. Skinner gasped and she went impulsively up to her bereaved daughter. She wanted to fold her in her arms.

"My poor child," she sobbed.

But Millicent withdrew herself.

"Please don't fuss me, mother. I really can't stand being mauled about."

"Really, Millicent," said Mr. Skinner, with a frown.

He did not think she was behaving very nicely.

Mrs. Skinner dabbed her eyes carefully with her handkerchief and with a sigh and a little shake of the head returned to her chair. Kathleen fidgeted with the long chain she wore round her neck.

"It does seem rather absurd that I should have to be told the details of my brother-in-law's death by a friend. It makes us all look such fools. The Bishop wants very much to see you, Millicent; he wants to tell you how much he feels for you." She paused, but Millicent did not speak. "He says that Millicent had been away with Joan and when she came back she found poor Harold lying dead on his bed."

"It must have been a great shock," said Mr. Skinner.

Mrs. Skinner began to cry again, but Kathleen put her hand gently on her shoulder.

"Don't cry, mother," she said. "It'll make your eyes red and people will think it so funny."

They were all silent while Mrs. Skinner, drying her eyes, made a successful effort to control herself. It seemed very strange to her that this very moment she should be wearing in her toque the ospreys that poor Harold had given her.

"There's something else I ought to tell you," said Kathleen.

Millicent looked at her sister again, without haste, and her eyes were steady, but watchful. She had the look of a person who is waiting for a sound which he is afraid of missing.

"I don't want to say anything to wound you, dear," Kathleen went on, "but there's something else and I think you ought to know it. The Bishop says that Harold drank."

"Oh, my dear, how dreadful!" cried Mrs. Skinner. "What a shocking thing to say. Did Gladys Heywood tell you? What did you say?"

"I said it was entirely untrue."

"This is what comes of making secrets of things," said Mr. Skinner, irritably. "It's always the same. If you try and hush a thing up all sorts of rumours get about which are ten times worse than the truth."

"They told the Bishop in Singapore that Harold had killed himself while he was suffering from delirium tremens. I think for all our sakes you ought to deny that, Millicent."

"It's such a dreadful thing to have said about anyone who's dead," said Mrs. Skinner. "And it'll be so bad for Joan when she grows up."

"But what is the foundation of this story, Millicent?" asked her father. "Harold was always very abstemious."

"Here," said the widow.

"Did he drink?"

"Like a fish."

The answer was so unexpected, and the tone so sardonic, that all three of them were startled.

"Millicent, how can you talk like that of your husband when he's dead?" cried her mother, clasping her neatly gloved hands. "I can't understand you. You've been so strange since you came back. I could never have believed that a girl of mine could take her husband's death like that."

"Never mind about that, mother," said Mr. Skinner. "We can go into all that later."

He walked to the window and looked out at the sunny little garden, and then walked back into the room. He took his pince-nez out of his pocket, and though he had no intention of putting them on, wiped them with his handkerchief. Millicent looked at him and in her eyes, unmistakably, was a look of irony which was quite cynical. Mr. Skinner was vexed. He had finished his week's work and he was a free man till Monday morning. Though he had told his wife that this garden-party was a great nuisance and he would much sooner have tea quietly in his own garden, he had been looking forward to it. He did not care very much about Chinese missions, but it would be interesting to meet the Bishop. And now this! It was not the kind of thing he cared to be mixed up in; it was most unpleasant to be told on a sudden that his son-in-law was a drunkard and a suicide. Millicent was thoughtfully smoothing her white cuffs. Her coolness irritated him; but instead of addressing her he spoke to his younger daughter.

"Why don't you sit down, Kathleen? Surely there are plenty of chairs in the room."

Kathleen drew forward a chair and without a word seated herself. Mr. Skinner stopped in front of Millicent and faced her.

"Of course I see why you told us Harold had died of fever. I think it was a mistake, because that sort of thing is bound to come out sooner or later. I don't know how far what the Bishop has told the Heywoods coincides with the facts, but if you will take my advice you will tell us everything as circumstantially as you can, then we can see. We can't hope that it will go no further now that Canon Heywood and Gladys know. In a place like this people are bound to talk. It will make it easier for all of us if we at all events know the exact truth."

Mrs. Skinner and Kathleen thought he put the matter very well. They waited for Millicent's reply. She had listened with an impassive face; that sudden flush had disappeared and it was once more, as usual, pasty and sallow.

"I don't think you'll much like the truth if I tell it to you," she said.

"You must know that you can count on our sympathy and understanding," said Kathleen gravely.

Millicent gave her a glance and the shadow of a smile flickered across her set mouth. She looked slowly at the three of them. Mrs. Skinner had an uneasy impression that she looked at them as though they were mannequins at a dressmaker's. She seemed to live in a different world from theirs and to have no connexion with them.

"You know, I wasn't in love with Harold when I married him," she said reflectively.

Mrs. Skinner was on the point of making an exclamation when a rapid gesture of her husband, barely indicated, but after so many years of married life perfectly significant, stopped her. Millicent went on. She spoke with a level voice, slowly, and there was little change of expression in her tone.

"I was twenty-seven, and no one else seemed to want to marry me. It's true he was forty-four, and it seemed rather old, but he had a very good position, hadn't he? I wasn't likely to get a better chance."

Mrs. Skinner felt inclined to cry again, but she remembered the party.

"Of course I see now why you took his photograph away," she said dolefully.

"Don't, mother," exclaimed Kathleen.

It had been taken when he was engaged to Millicent and was a very good photograph of Harold. Mrs. Skinner had always thought him quite a fine man. He was heavily built, tall and perhaps a little too fat, but he held himself well, and his presence was imposing. He was inclined to be bald, even then, but men did go bald very early nowadays, and he said that topees, sun-helmets, you know, were very bad for the hair. He had a small dark moustache, and his face was deeply burned by the sun. Of course his best feature was his eyes; they were brown and large, like Joan's. His conversation was interesting. Kathleen said he was pompous, but Mrs. Skinner didn't think him so, she didn't mind it if a man laid down the law; and when she saw, as she very soon did, that he was attracted by Millicent she began to like him very much. He was always very attentive to Mrs. Skinner, and she listened as though she were really interested when he spoke of his district, and told her of the big game he had killed. Kathleen said he had a pretty good opinion of himself, but Mrs. Skinner came of a generation which accepted without question the good opinion that men had of themselves. Millicent saw very soon which way the wind blew, and though she said nothing to her mother, her mother knew that if Harold asked her she was going to accept him.

Harold was staying with some people who had been thirty years in Borneo and they spoke well of the country. There was no reason why a woman shouldn't live there comfortably; of course the children had to come home when they were seven; but Mrs. Skinner thought it unnecessary to trouble about that yet. She asked Harold to dine, and she told him they were always in to tea. He seemed to be at a loose end, and when his visit to his old friends was drawing to a close, she told him they would be very much pleased if he would come and spend a fortnight with them. It was towards the end of this that Harold and Millicent became engaged. They had a very pretty wedding, they went to Venice for their honeymoon, and then they started for the East. Millicent wrote from various ports at which the ship touched. She seemed happy.

"People were very nice to me at Kuala Solor," she said. Kuala Solor was the chief town of the state of Sembulu. "We stayed with the Resident and everyone asked us to dinner. Once or twice I heard men ask Harold to have a drink, but he refused; he said he had turned over a new leaf now he was a married man. I didn't know why they laughed. Mrs. Gray, the Resident's wife, told me they were all so glad Harold was married. She said it was dreadfully lonely for a bachelor on one of the outstations. When we left Kuala Solor Mrs. Gray said goodbye to me so funnily that I was quite surprised. It was as if she was solemnly putting Harold in my charge."

They listened to her in silence. Kathleen never took her eyes off her sister's impassive face; but Mr. Skinner stared straight in front of him at the Malay arms, krises and parangs, which hung on the wall above the sofa on which his wife sat.

"It wasn't till I went back to Kuala Solor a year and a half later, that I found out why their manner had seemed so odd." Millicent gave a queer little sound like the echo of a scornful laugh. "I knew then a good deal that I hadn't known before. Harold came to England that time in order to marry. He didn't much mind who it was. Do you remember how we spread ourselves out to catch him, mother? We needn't have taken so much trouble."

"I don't know what you mean, Millicent," said Mrs. Skinner, not without acerbity, for the insinuation of scheming did not please her. "I saw he was attracted by you."

Millicent shrugged her heavy shoulders.

"He was a confirmed drunkard. He used to go to bed every night with a bottle of whisky and empty it before morning. The Chief Secretary told him he'd have to resign unless he stopped drinking. He said he'd give him one more chance. He could take his leave then and go to England. He advised him to marry so that when he got back he'd have someone to look after him. Harold married me because he wanted a keeper. They took bets in Kuala Solor on how long I'd make him stay sober."

"But he was in love with you," Mrs. Skinner interrupted. "You don't know how he used to speak to me about you, and at that time you're speaking of, when you went to Kuala Solor to have Joan, he wrote me such a charming letter about you."

Millicent looked at her mother again and a deep colour dyed her sallow skin. Her hands, lying on her lap, began to tremble a little. She thought of those first months of her married life. The government launch took them to the mouth of the river, and they spent the night at the bungalow which Harold said jokingly was their seaside residence. Next day they went up-stream in a prahu. From the novels she had read she expected the rivers of Borneo to be dark and strangely sinister, but the sky was blue, dappled with little white clouds, and the green of the mangroves and the nipahs, washed by the flowing water, glistened in the sun. On each side stretched the pathless jungle, and in the distance, silhouetted against the sky, was the rugged outline of a mountain. The air in the early morning was fresh and buoyant. She seemed to enter upon a friendly, fertile land, and she had a sense of spacious freedom. They watched the banks for monkeys sitting on the branches of the tangled trees, and once Harold pointed out something that looked like a log and said it was a crocodile. The Assistant Resident, in ducks and a topee, was at the landing-stage to meet them, and a dozen trim little soldiers were lined up to do them honour. The Assistant Resident was introduced to her. His name was Simpson.

"By Jove, sir," he said to Harold. "I'm glad to see you back. It's been deuced lonely without you."

The Resident's bungalow, surrounded by a garden in which grew wildly all manner of gay flowers, stood on the top of a low hill. It was a trifle shabby and the furniture was sparse, but the rooms were cool and of generous size.

"The kampong is down there," said Harold, pointing.

Her eyes followed his gesture, and from among the coconut trees rose the beating of a gong. It gave her a queer little sensation in the heart.

Though she had nothing much to do the days passed easily enough. At dawn a boy brought them their tea and they lounged about the veranda, enjoying the fragrance of the morning (Harold in a singlet and a sarong, she in a dressing-gown) till it was time to dress for breakfast. Then Harold went to his office and she spent an hour or two learning Malay. After tiffin he went back to his office while she slept. A cup of tea revived them both, and they went for a walk or played golf on the nine-hole links which Harold had made on a level piece of cleared jungle below the bungalow. Night fell at six and Mr. Simpson came along to have a drink. They chatted till their late dinner hour, and sometimes Harold and Mr. Simpson played chess. The balmy evenings were enchanting. The fireflies turned the bushes just below the veranda into coldly-sparkling, tremulous beacons, and flowering trees scented the air with sweet odours. After dinner they read the papers which had left London six weeks before and presently went to bed. Millicent enjoyed being a married woman, with a house of her own, and she was pleased with the native servants, in their gay sarongs, who went about the bungalow, with bare feet, silent but friendly. It gave her a pleasant sense of importance to be the wife of the Resident. Harold impressed her by the fluency with which he spoke the language, by his air of command, and by his dignity. She went into the court-house now and then to hear him try cases. The multifariousness of his duties and the competent way in which he performed them aroused her respect. Mr. Simpson told her that Harold understood the natives as well as any man in the country. He had the combination of firmness, tact, and good-humour which was essential in dealing with that timid, revengeful, and suspicious race. Millicent began to feel a certain admiration for her husband.

They had been married nearly a year when two English naturalists came to stay with them for a few days on their way to the interior. They brought a pressing recommendation from the governor, and Harold said he wanted to do them proud. Their arrival was an agreeable change. Millicent asked Mr. Simpson to dinner (he lived at the Fort and only dined with them on Sunday nights) and after dinner the men sat down to play bridge. Millicent left them presently and went to bed, but they were so noisy that for some time she could not get to sleep. She did not know at what hour she was awakened by Harold staggering into the room. She kept silent. He made up his mind to have a bath before getting into bed; the bath-house was just below their room, and he went down the steps that led to it. Apparently he slipped, for there was a great clatter, and he began to swear. Then he was violently sick. She heard him sluice the buckets of water over himself and in a little while, walking very cautiously this time, he crawled up the stairs and slipped into bed. Millicent pretended to be asleep. She was disgusted. Harold was drunk. She made up her mind to speak about it in the morning. What would the naturalists think of him? But in the morning Harold was so dignified that she hadn't quite the determination to refer to the matter. At eight Harold and she, with their two guests, sat down to breakfast. Harold looked round the table.

"Porridge," he said. "Millicent, your guests might manage a little Worcester sauce for breakfast, but I don't think they'll much fancy anything else. Personally I shall content myself with a whisky and soda."

The naturalists laughed, but shamefacedly.

"Your husband's a terror," said one of them.

"I should not think I had properly performed the duties of hospitality if I sent you sober to bed on the first night of your visit," said Harold, with his round, stately way of putting things.

Millicent, smiling acidly, was relieved to think that her guests had been as drunk as her husband. The next evening she sat up with them and the party broke up at a reasonable hour. But she was glad when the strangers went on with their journey. Their life resumed its placid course. Some months later Harold went on a tour of inspection of his district and came back with a bad attack of malaria. This was the first time she had seen the disease of which she had heard so much, and when he recovered it did not seem strange to her that Harold was very shaky. She found his manner peculiar. He would come back from the office and stare at her with glazed eyes; he would stand on the veranda, swaying slightly, but still dignified, and make long harangues about the political situation in England; losing the thread of his discourse, he would look at her with an archness which his natural stateliness made somewhat disconcerting and say:

"Pulls you down dreadfully, this confounded malaria. Ah, little woman, you little know the strain it puts upon a man to be an empire builder."

She thought that Mr. Simpson began to look worried, and once or twice, when they were alone, he seemed on the point of saying something to her which his shyness at the last moment prevented. The feeling grew so strong that it made her nervous, and one evening when Harold, she knew not why, had remained later than usual at the office she tackled him.

"What have you got to say to me, Mr. Simpson?" she broke out suddenly.

He blushed and hesitated.

"Nothing. What makes you think I have anything in particular to say to you?"

Mr. Simpson was a thin, weedy youth of four and twenty, with a fine head of waving hair which he took great pains to plaster down very flat. His wrists were swollen and scarred with mosquito bites. Millicent looked at him steadily.

"If it's something to do with Harold don't you think it would be kinder to tell me frankly?"

He grew scarlet now. He shuffled uneasily on his rattan chair. She insisted.

"I'm afraid you'll think it awful cheek," he said at last. "It's rotten of me to say anything about my chief behind his back. Malaria's a rotten thing, and after one's had a bout of it one feels awfully down and out."

He hesitated again. The corners of his mouth sagged as if he were going to cry. To Millicent he seemed like a little boy.

"I'll be as silent as the grave," she said with a smile, trying to conceal her apprehension. "Do tell me."

"I think it's a pity your husband keeps a bottle of whisky at the office. He's apt to take a nip more often than he otherwise would."

Mr. Simpson's voice was hoarse with agitation. Millicent felt a sudden coldness shiver through her. She controlled herself, for she knew that she must not frighten the boy if she were to get out of him all there was to tell. He was unwilling to speak. She pressed him, wheedling, appealing to his sense of duty, and at last she began to cry. Then he told her that Harold had been drunk more or less for the last fortnight, the natives were talking about it, and they said that soon he would be as bad as he had been before his marriage. He had been in the habit of drinking a good deal too much then, but details of that time, notwithstanding all her attempts, Mr. Simpson resolutely declined to give her.

"Do you think he's drinking now?" she asked.

"I don't know."

Millicent felt herself on a sudden hot with shame and anger. The Fort, as it was called because the rifles and the ammunition were kept there, was also the court-house. It stood opposite the Resident's bungalow in a garden of its own. The sun was just about to set and she did not need a hat. She got up and walked across. She found Harold sitting in the office behind the large hall in which he administered justice. There was a bottle of whisky in front of him. He was smoking cigarettes and talking to three or four Malays who stood in front of him listening with obsequious and at the same time scornful smiles. His face was red.

The natives vanished.

"I came to see what you were doing," she said.

He rose, for he always treated her with elaborate politeness, and lurched. Feeling himself unsteady he assumed an elaborate stateliness of demeanour.

"Take a seat, my dear, take a seat. I was detained by press of work."

She looked at him with angry eyes.

"You're drunk," she said.

He stared at her, his eyes bulging a little, and a haughty look gradually traversed his large and fleshy face.

"I haven't the remotest idea what you mean," he said.

She had been ready with a flow of wrathful expostulation, but suddenly she burst into tears. She sank into a chair and hid her face. Harold looked at her for an instant, then the tears began to trickle down his own cheeks; he came towards her with outstretched arms and fell heavily on his knees. Sobbing, he clasped her to him.

"Forgive me, forgive me," he said. "I promise you it shall not happen again. It was that damned malaria."

"It's so humiliating," she moaned.

He wept like a child. There was something very touching in the self-abasement of that big dignified man. Presently Millicent looked up. His eyes, appealing and contrite, sought hers.

"Will you give me your word of honour that you'll never touch liquor again?"

"Yes, yes. I hate it."

It was then she told him that she was with child. He was overjoyed.

"That is the one thing I wanted. That'll keep me straight."

They went back to the bungalow. Harold bathed himself and had a nap. After dinner they talked long and quietly. He admitted that before he married her he had occasionally drunk more than was good for him; in outstations it was easy to fall into bad habits. He agreed to everything that Millicent asked. And during the months before it was necessary for her to go to Kuala Solor for her confinement, Harold was an excellent husband, tender, thoughtful, proud, and affectionate; he was irreproachable. A launch came to fetch her, she was to leave him for six weeks, and he promised faithfully to drink nothing during her absence. He put his hands on her shoulders.

"I never break a promise," he said in his dignified way. "But even without it, can you imagine that while you are going through so much, I should do anything to increase your troubles?"

Joan was born. Millicent stayed at the Resident's, and Mrs. Gray, his wife, a kindly creature of middle age, was very good to her. The two women had little to do during the long hours they were alone but to talk, and in course of time Millicent learnt everything there was to know of her husband's alcoholic past. The fact which she found most difficult to reconcile herself to was that Harold had been told that the only condition upon which he would be allowed to keep his post was that he should bring back a wife. It caused in her a dull feeling of resentment. And when she discovered what a persistent drunkard he had been, she felt vaguely uneasy. She had a horrid fear that during her absence he would not have been able to resist the craving. She went home with her baby and a nurse. She spent a night at the mouth of the river and sent a messenger in a canoe to announce her arrival. She scanned the landing-stage anxiously as the launch approached it. Harold and Mr. Simpson were standing there. The trim little soldiers were lined up. Her heart sank, for Harold was swaying slightly, like a man who seeks to keep his balance on a rolling ship, and she knew he was drunk.

It wasn't a very pleasant home-coming. She had almost forgotten her mother and father and her sister who sat there silently listening to her. Now she roused herself and became once more aware of their presence. All that she spoke of seemed very far away.

"I knew that I hated him then," she said. "I could have killed him."

"Oh, Millicent, don't say that," cried her mother. "Don't forget that he's dead, poor man."

Millicent looked at her mother, and for a moment a scowl darkened her impassive face. Mr. Skinner moved uneasily.

"Go on," said Kathleen.

"When he found out that I knew all about him he didn't bother very much more. In three months he had another attack of D.T.S."

"Why didn't you leave him?" said Kathleen.

"What would have been the good of that? He would have been dismissed from the service in a fortnight. Who was to keep me and Joan? I had to stay. And when he was sober I had nothing to complain of. He wasn't in the least in love with me, but he was fond of me; I hadn't married him because I was in love with him, but because I wanted to be married. I did everything I could to keep liquor from him; I managed to get Mr. Gray to prevent whisky being sent from Kuala Solor, but he got it from the Chinese. I watched him as a cat watches a mouse. He was too cunning for me. In a little while he had another outbreak. He neglected his duties. I was afraid complaints would be made. We were two days from Kuala Solor and that was our safeguard, but I suppose something was said, for Mr. Gray wrote a private letter of warning to me. I showed it to Harold. He stormed and blustered, but I saw he was frightened, and for two or three months he was quite sober. Then he began again. And so it went on till our leave became due.

"Before we came to stay here I begged and prayed him to be careful. I didn't want any of you to know what sort of a man I had married. All the time he was in England he was all right and before we sailed I warned him. He'd grown to be very fond of Joan, and very proud of her, and she was devoted to him. She always liked him better than she liked me. I asked him if he wanted to have his child grow up, knowing that he was a drunkard, and I found out that at last I'd got a hold on him. The thought terrified him. I told him that I wouldn't allow it, and if he ever let Joan see him drunk I'd take her away from him at once. Do you know, he grew quite pale when I said it. I fell on my knees that night and thanked God, because I'd found a way of saving my husband.

"He told me that if I would stand by him he would have another try. We made up our minds to fight the thing together. And he tried so hard. When he felt as though he must drink he came to me. You know he was inclined to be rather pompous; with me he was so humble, he was like a child; he depended on me. Perhaps he didn't love me when he married me, but he loved me then, me and Joan. I'd hated him, because of the humiliation, because when he was drunk and tried to be dignified and impressive he was loathsome; but now I got a strange feeling in my heart. It wasn't love, but it was a queer, shy tenderness. He was something more than my husband, he was like a child that I'd carried under my heart for long and weary months. He was so proud of me and, you know, I was proud too. His long speeches didn't irritate me any more, and I only thought his stately ways rather funny and charming. At last we won. For two years he never touched a drop. He lost his craving entirely. He was even able to joke about it.

"Mr. Simpson had left us then and we had another young man called Francis.

"'I'm a reformed drunkard, you know, Francis,' Harold said to him once. 'If it hadn't been for my wife I'd have been sacked long ago. I've got the best wife in the world, Francis.'

"You don't know what it meant to me to hear him say that. I felt that all I'd gone through was worth while. I was so happy."

She was silent. She thought of the broad, yellow and turbid river on whose banks she had lived so long. The egrets, white and gleaming in the tremulous sunset, flew down the stream in a flock, flew low and swift, and scattered. They were like a ripple of snowy notes, sweet and pure and spring-like, which an unseen hand drew forth, a divine arpeggio, from an unseen harp. They fluttered along between the green banks, wrapped in the shadows of evening, like the happy thoughts of a contented mind.

"Then Joan fell ill. For three weeks we were very anxious. There was no doctor nearer than Kuala Solor and we had to put up with the treatment of a native dispenser. When she grew well again I took her down to the mouth of the river in order to give her a breath of sea air. We stayed there a week. It was the first time I had been separated from Harold since I went away to have Joan.

"There was a fishing village, on piles, not far from us, but really we were quite alone. I thought a great deal about Harold, so tenderly, and all at once I knew that I loved him. I was so glad when the prahu came to fetch us back, because I wanted to tell him. I thought it would mean a good deal to him. I can't tell you how happy I was. As we rowed up-stream the headman told me that Mr. Francis had had to go up-country to arrest a woman who had murdered her husband. He had been gone a couple of days.

"I was surprised that Harold was not on the landing-stage to meet me; he was always very punctilious about that sort of thing; he used to say that husband and wife should treat one another as politely as they treated acquaintances; and I could not imagine what business had prevented him. I walked up the little hill on which the bungalow stood. The ayah brought Joan behind me. The bungalow was strangely silent. There seemed to be no servants about, and I could not make it out; I wondered if Harold hadn't expected me so soon and was out. I went up the steps. Joan was thirsty and the ayah took her to the servants' quarters to give her something to drink. Harold was not in the sitting-room. I called him, but there was no answer. I was disappointed because I should have liked him to be there. I went into our bedroom. Harold wasn't out after all; he was lying on the bed asleep. I was really very much amused, because he always pretended he never slept in the afternoon. He said it was an unnecessary habit that we white people got into. I went up to the bed softly. I thought I would have a joke with him. I opened the mosquito curtains. He was lying on his back, with nothing on but a sarong, and there was an empty whisky bottle by his side. He was drunk.

"It had begun again. All my struggles for so many years were wasted. My dream was shattered. It was all hopeless. I was seized with rage."

Millicent's face grew once again darkly red and she clenched the arms of the chair she sat in.

"I took him by the shoulders and shook him with all my might. 'You beast,' I cried, 'you beast.' I was so angry I don't know what I did, I don't know what I said. I kept on shaking him. You don't know how loathsome he looked, that large fat man, half naked; he hadn't shaved for days, and his face was bloated and purple. He was breathing heavily. I shouted at him, but he took no notice. I tried to drag him out of bed, but he was too heavy. He lay there like a log. 'Open your eyes,' I screamed. I shook him again. I hated him. I hated him all the more because for a week I'd loved him with all my heart. He'd let me down. He'd let me down. I wanted to tell him what a filthy beast he was. I could make no impression on him. 'You shall open your eyes,' I cried. I was determined to make him look at me."

The widow licked her dry lips. Her breath seemed hurried. She was silent.

"If he was in that state I should have thought it best to have let him go on sleeping," said Kathleen.

"There was a parang on the wall by the side of the bed. You know how fond Harold was of curios."

"What's a parang?" said Mrs. Skinner.

"Don't be silly, mother," her husband replied irritably. "There's one on the wall immediately behind you."

He pointed to the Malay sword on which for some reason his eyes had been unconsciously resting. Mrs. Skinner drew quickly into the corner of the sofa, with a little frightened gesture, as though she had been told that a snake lay curled up beside her.

"Suddenly the blood spurted out from Harold's throat. There was a great red gash right across it."

"Millicent," cried Kathleen, springing up and almost leaping towards her, "what in God's name do you mean?"

Mrs. Skinner stood staring at her with wide startled eyes, her mouth open.

"The parang wasn't on the wall any more. It was on the bed. Then Harold opened his eyes. They were just like Joan's."

"I don't understand," said Mr. Skinner. "How could he have committed suicide if he was in the state you describe?"

Kathleen took her sister's arm and shook her angrily.

"Millicent, for God's sake explain."

Millicent released herself.

"The parang was on the wall, I told you. I don't know what happened. There was all the blood, and Harold opened his eyes. He died almost at once. He never spoke, but he gave a sort of gasp."

At last Mr. Skinner found his voice.

"But, you wretched woman, it was murder."

Millicent, her face mottled with red, gave him such a look of scornful hatred that he shrank back. Mrs. Skinner cried out.

"Millicent, you didn't do it, did you?"

Then Millicent did something that made them all feel as though their blood were turned to ice in their veins. She chuckled.

"I don't know who else did," she said.

"My God," muttered Mr. Skinner.

Kathleen had been standing bolt upright with her hands to her heart, as though its beating were intolerable.

"And what happened then?" she said.

"I screamed. I went to the window and flung it open. I called for the ayah. She came across the compound with Joan. 'Not Joan,' I cried. 'Don't let her come.' She called the cook and told him to take the child. I cried to her to hurry. And when she came I showed her Harold. 'The Tuan's killed himself!' I cried. She gave a scream and ran out of the house.

"No one would come near. They were all frightened out of their wits. I wrote a letter to Mr. Francis, telling him what had happened and asking him to come at once."

"How do you mean you told him what had happened?"

"I said, on my return from the mouth of the river, I'd found Harold with his throat cut. You know, in the tropics you have to bury people quickly. I got a Chinese coffin, and the soldiers dug a grave behind the Fort. When Mr. Francis came, Harold had been buried for nearly two days. He was only a boy. I could do anything I wanted with him. I told him I'd found the parang in Harold's hand and there was no doubt he'd killed himself in an attack of delirium tremens. I showed him the empty bottle. The servants said he'd been drinking hard ever since I left to go to the sea. I told the same story at Kuala Solor. Everyone was very kind to me, and the government granted me a pension."

For a little while nobody spoke. At last Mr. Skinner gathered himself together.

"I am a member of the legal profession. I'm a solicitor. I have certain duties. We've always had a most respectable practice. You've put me in a monstrous position."

He fumbled, searching for the phrases that played at hide and seek in his scattered wits. Millicent looked at him with scorn.

"What are you going to do about it?"

"It was murder, that's what it was; do you think I can possibly connive at it?"

"Don't talk nonsense, father," said Kathleen sharply. "You can't give up your own daughter."

"You've put me in a monstrous position," he repeated.

Millicent shrugged her shoulders again.

"You made me tell you. And I've borne it long enough by myself. It was time that all of you bore it too."

At that moment the door was opened by the maid.

"Davis has brought the car round, sir," she said.

Kathleen had the presence of mind to say something, and the maid withdrew.

"We'd better be starting," said Millicent.

"I can't go to the party now," cried Mrs. Skinner, with horror. "I'm far too upset. How can we face the Heywoods? And the Bishop will want to be introduced to you."

Millicent made a gesture of indifference. Her eyes held their ironical expression.

"We must go, mother," said Kathleen. "It would look so funny if we stayed away." She turned on Millicent furiously. "Oh, I think the whole thing is such frightfully bad form."

Mrs. Skinner looked helplessly at her husband. He went to her and gave her his hand to help her up from the sofa.

"I'm afraid we must go, mother," he said.

"And me with the ospreys in my toque that Harold gave me with his own hands," she moaned.

He led her out of the room, Kathleen followed close on their heels, and a step or two behind came Millicent.

"You'll get used to it, you know," she said quietly. "At first I thought of it all the time, but now I forget it for two or three days together. It's not as if there was any danger."

They did not answer. They walked through the hall and out of the front door. The three ladies got into the back of the car and Mr. Skinner seated himself beside the driver. They had no self-starter; it was an old car, and Davis went to the bonnet to crank it up. Mr. Skinner turned round and looked petulantly at Millicent.

"I ought never to have been told," he said. "I think it was most selfish of you."

Davis took his seat and they drove off to the Canon's garden-party.

Jane

I remember very well the occasion on which I first saw Jane Fowler. It is indeed only because the details of the glimpse I had of her then are so clear that I trust my recollection at all, for, looking back, I must confess that I find it hard to believe that it has not played me a fantastic trick. I had lately returned to London from China and was drinking a dish of tea with Mrs. Tower. Mrs. Tower had been seized with the prevailing passion for decoration; and with the ruthlessness of her sex had sacrificed chairs in which she had comfortably sat for years, tables, cabinets, ornaments on which her eyes had dwelt in peace since she was married, pictures that had been familiar to her for a generation; and delivered herself into the hands of an expert. Nothing remained in her drawing-room with which she had any association, or to which any sentiment was attached; and she had invited me that day to see the fashionable glory in which she now lived. Everything that could be pickled was pickled and what couldn't be pickled was painted. Nothing matched, but everything harmonized.

"Do you remember that ridiculous drawing-room suite that I used to have?" asked Mrs. Tower.

The curtains were sumptuous yet severe; the sofa was covered with Italian brocade; the chair on which I sat was in petit point. The room was beautiful, opulent without garishness, and original without affectation; yet to me it lacked something; and while I praised with my lips I asked myself why I so much preferred the rather shabby chintz of the despised suite, the Victorian watercolours that I had known so long, and the ridiculous Dresden china that had adorned the chimney-piece. I wondered what it was that I missed in all these rooms that the decorators were turning out with a profitable industry. Was it heart? But Mrs. Tower looked about her happily.

"Don't you like my alabaster lamps?" she said. "They give such a soft light."

"Personally I have a weakness for a light that you can see by," I smiled.

"It's so difficult to combine that with a light that you can't be too much seen by," laughed Mrs. Tower.

I had no notion what her age was. When I was quite a young man she was a married woman a good deal older than I, but now she treated me as her contemporary. She constantly said that she made no secret of her age, which was forty, and then added with a smile that all women took five years off. She never sought to conceal the fact that she dyed her hair (it was a very pretty brown with reddish tints), and she said she did this because hair was hideous while it was going grey; as soon as hers was white she would cease to dye it.

"Then they'll say what a young face I have."

Meanwhile it was painted, though with discretion, and her eyes owed not a little of their vivacity to art. She was a handsome woman, exquisitely gowned, and in the sombre glow of the alabaster lamps did not look a day more than the forty she gave herself.

"It is only at my dressing-table that I can suffer the naked brightness of a thirty-two-candle electric bulb," she added with smiling cynicism. "There I need it to tell me the first hideous truth and then to enable me to take the necessary steps to correct it."

We gossiped pleasantly about our common friends and Mrs. Tower brought me up to date in the scandal of the day. After roughing it here and there it was very agreeable to sit in a comfortable chair, the fire burning brightly on the hearth, charming tea-things set out on a charming table, and talk with this amusing, attractive woman. She treated me as a prodigal returned from his husks and was disposed to make much of me. She prided herself on her dinnerparties; she took no less trouble to have her guests suitably assorted than to give them excellent food; and there were few persons who did not look upon it as a treat to be bidden to one of them. Now she fixed a date and asked me whom I would like to meet.

"There's only one thing I must tell you. If Jane Fowler is still here I shall have to put it off."

"Who is Jane Fowler?" I asked.

Mrs. Tower gave a rueful smile.

"Jane Fowler is my cross."

"Oh!"

"Do you remember a photograph that I used to have on the piano before I had my room done, of a woman in a tight dress with tight sleeves and a gold locket, with her hair drawn back from a broad forehead and her ears showing and spectacles on a rather blunt nose? Well, that was Jane Fowler."

"You had so many photographs about the room in your unregenerate days," I said, vaguely.

"It makes me shudder to think of them. I've made them into a huge brown-paper parcel and hidden them in an attic"

"Well, who is Jane Fowler?" I asked again, smiling.

"She's my sister-in-law. She was my husband's sister and she married a manufacturer in the North. She's been a widow for many years, and she's very well-to-do."

"And why is she your cross?"

"She's worthy, she's dowdy, she's provincial. She looks twenty years older than I do and she's quite capable of telling anyone she meets that we were at school together. She has an overwhelming sense of family affection and because I am her only living connexion she's devoted to me. When she comes to London it never occurs to her that she should stay anywhere but here—she thinks it would hurt my feelings—and she'll pay me visits of three or four weeks. We sit here and she knits and reads. And sometimes she insists on taking me to dine at Claridge's and she looks like a funny old charwoman and everyone I particularly don't want to be seen by is sitting at the next table. When we are driving home she says she loves giving me a little treat. With her own hands she makes me tea-cosies that I am forced to use when she is here and doilies and centrepieces for the dining-room table."

Mrs. Tower paused to take breath.

"I should have thought a woman of your tact would find a way to deal with a situation like that."

"Ah, but don't you see, I haven't a chance. She's so immeasurably kind. She has a heart of gold. She bores me to death, but I wouldn't for anything let her suspect it."

"And when does she arrive?"

"Tomorrow."

But the answer was hardly out of Mrs. Tower's mouth when the bell rang. There were sounds in the hall of a slight commotion and in a minute or two the butler ushered in an elderly lady.

"Mrs. Fowler," he announced.

"Jane," cried Mrs. Tower, springing to her feet. "I wasn't expecting you today."

"So your butler has just told me. I certainly said today in my letter."

Mrs. Tower recovered her wits.

"Well, it doesn't matter. I'm very glad to see you whenever you come. Fortunately I'm doing nothing this evening."

"You mustn't let me give you any trouble. If I can have a boiled egg for my dinner, that's all I shall want."

A faint grimace for a moment distorted Mrs. Tower's handsome features. A boiled egg!

"Oh, I think we can do a little better than that."

I chuckled inwardly when I recollected that the two ladies were contemporaries. Mrs. Fowler looked a good fifty-five. She was a rather big woman; she wore a black straw hat with a wide brim and from it a black lace veil hung over her shoulders, a cloak that oddly combined severity with fussiness, a long black dress, voluminous as though she wore several petticoats under it, and stout boots. She was evidently short-sighted, for she looked at you through large gold-rimmed spectacles.

"Won't you have a cup of tea?" asked Mrs. Tower.

"If it wouldn't be too much trouble. I'll take off my mantle."

She began by stripping her hands of the black gloves she wore, and then took off her cloak. Round her neck was a solid gold chain from which hung a large gold locket in which I felt certain was a photograph of her deceased husband. Then she took off her hat and placed it neatly with her gloves and cloak on the sofa corner. Mrs. Tower pursed her lips. Certainly those garments did not go very well with the austere but sumptuous beauty of Mrs. Tower's redecorated drawing-room. I wondered where on earth Mrs. Fowler had found the extraordinary clothes she wore. They were not old and the materials were expensive. It was astounding to think that dressmakers still made things that had not been worn for a quarter of a century. Mrs. Fowler's grey hair was very plainly done, showing all her forehead and her ears, with a parting in the middle. It had evidently never known the tongs of Monsieur Marcel. Now her eyes fell on the tea-table with its teapot of Georgian silver and its cups in Old Worcester.

"What have you done with the tea-cosy I gave you last time I came up, Marion?" she asked. "Don't you use it?"

"Yes, I used it every day, Jane," answered Mrs. Tower glibly. "Unfortunately we had an accident with it a little while ago. It got burnt."

"But the last one I gave you got burnt."

"I'm afraid you'll think us very careless."

"It doesn't really matter," smiled Mrs. Fowler. "I shall enjoy making you another. I'll go to Liberty's tomorrow and buy some silks."

Mrs. Tower kept her face bravely.

"I don't deserve it, you know. Doesn't your vicar's wife need one?"

"Oh, I've just made her one," said Mrs. Fowler brightly.

I noticed that when she smiled she showed white, small, and regular teeth. They were a real beauty. Her smile was certainly very sweet.

But I felt it high time for me to leave the two ladies to themselves, so I took my leave.

Early next morning Mrs. Tower rang me up and I heard at once from her voice that she was in high spirits.

"I've got the most wonderful news for you," she said. "Jane is going to be married."

"Nonsense."

"Her fiancé is coming to dine here tonight to be introduced to me and I want you to come too."

"Oh, but I shall be in the way."

"No, you won't. Jane suggested herself that I should ask you. Do come."

She was bubbling over with laughter.

"Who is he?"

"I don't know. She tells me he's an architect. Can you imagine the sort of man Jane would marry?"

I had nothing to do and I could trust Mrs. Tower to give me a good dinner.

When I arrived Mrs. Tower, very splendid in a tea-gown a little too young for her, was alone.

"Jane is putting the finishing touches to her appearance. I'm longing for you to see her. She's all in a flutter. She says he adores her. His name is Gilbert and when she speaks of him her voice gets all funny and tremulous. It makes me want to laugh."

"I wonder what he's like."

"Oh, I'm sure I know. Very big and massive, with a bald head and an immense gold chain across an immense tummy. A large, fat, clean-shaven, red face and a booming voice."

Mrs. Fowler came in. She wore a very stiff black silk dress with a wide skirt and a train. At the neck it was cut into a timid V and the sleeves came down to the elbows. She wore a necklace of diamonds set in silver. She carried in her hands a long pair of black gloves and a fan of black ostrich feathers. She managed (as so few people do) to look exactly what she was. You could never have thought her anything in the world but the respectable relict of a North-country manufacturer of ample means.

"You've really got quite a pretty neck, Jane," said Mrs. Tower with a kindly smile.

It was indeed astonishingly young when you compared it with her weather-beaten face. It was smooth and unlined and the skin was white. And I noticed then that her head was very well placed on her shoulders.

"Has Marion told you my news?" she said, turning to me with that really charming smile of hers as if we were already old friends.

"I must congratulate you," I said.

"Wait to do that till you've seen my young man."

"I think it's too sweet to hear you talk of your young man," smiled Mrs. Tower.

Mrs. Fowler's eyes certainly twinkled behind her preposterous spectacles.

"Don't expect anyone too old. You wouldn't like me to marry a decrepit old gentleman with one foot in the grave, would you?"

This was the only warning she gave us. Indeed there was no time for any further discussion, for the butler flung open the door and in a loud voice announced:

"Mr. Gilbert Napier."

There entered a youth in a very well-cut dinner jacket. He was slight, not very tall, with fair hair in which there was a hint of a natural wave, cleanshaven, and blue-eyed. He was not particularly good-looking, but he had a pleasant, amiable face. In ten years he would probably be wizened and sallow; but now, in extreme youth, he was fresh and clean and blooming. For he was certainly not more than twenty-four. My first thought was that this was the son of Jane Fowler's fiancé (I had not known he was a widower) come to say that his father was prevented from dining by a sudden attack of gout. But his eyes fell immediately on Mrs. Fowler, his face lit up, and he went towards her with both hands outstretched. Mrs. Fowler gave him hers, a demure smile on her lips, and turned to her sister-in-law.

"This is my young man, Marion," she said.

He held out his hand.

"I hope you'll like me, Mrs. Tower," he said. "Jane tells me you're the only relation she has in the world."

Mrs. Tower's face was wonderful to behold. I saw then to admiration how bravely good breeding and social usage could combat the instincts of the natural woman. For the astonishment and then the dismay that for an instant she could not conceal were quickly driven away, and her face assumed an expression of affable welcome. But she was evidently at a loss for words. It was not unnatural if Gilbert felt a certain embarrassment and I was too busy preventing myself from laughing to think of anything to say. Mrs. Fowler alone kept perfectly calm.

"I know you'll like him, Marion. There's no one enjoys good food more than he does." She turned to the young man. "Marion's dinners are famous."

"I know," he beamed.

Mrs. Tower made some quick rejoinder and we went downstairs. I shall not soon forget the exquisite comedy of that meal. Mrs. Tower could not make up her mind whether the pair of them were playing a practical joke on her or whether Jane by wilfully concealing her fiancé's age had hoped to make her look foolish. But then Jane never jested and she was incapable of doing a malicious thing. Mrs. Tower was amazed, exasperated, and perplexed. But she had recovered her self-control, and for nothing would she have forgotten that she was a perfect hostess whose duty it was to make her party go. She talked vivaciously; but I wondered if Gilbert Napier saw how hard and vindictive was the expression of her eyes behind the mask of friendliness that she turned to him. She was measuring him. She was seeking to delve into the secret of his soul. I could see that she was in a passion, for under her rouge her cheeks glowed with an angry red.

"You've got a very high colour, Marion," said Jane, looking at her amiably through her great round spectacles.

"I dressed in a hurry. I dare say I put on too much rouge."

"Oh, is it rouge? I thought it was natural. Otherwise I shouldn't have mentioned it." She gave Gilbert a shy little smile. "You know, Marion and I were at school together. You would never think it to look at us now, would you? But of course I've lived a very quiet life."

I do not know what she meant by these remarks; it was almost incredible that she made them in complete simplicity; but anyhow they goaded Mrs. Tower to such a fury that she flung her own vanity to the winds. She smiled brightly.

"We shall neither of us see fifty again, Jane," she said.

If the observation was meant to discomfit the widow it failed.

"Gilbert says I mustn't acknowledge to more than forty-nine for his sake," she answered blandly.

Mrs. Tower's hands trembled slightly, but she found a retort.

"There is of course a certain disparity of age between you," she smiled.

"Twenty-seven years," said Jane. "Do you think it's too much? Gilbert says I'm very young for my age. I told you I shouldn't like to marry a man with one foot in the grave."

I was really obliged to laugh and Gilbert laughed too. His laughter was frank and boyish. It looked as though he were amused at everything Jane said. But Mrs. Tower was almost at the end of her tether and I was afraid that unless relief came she would for once forget that she was a woman of the world. I came to the rescue as best I could.

"I suppose you're very busy buying your trousseau," I said.

"No. I wanted to get my things from the dressmaker in Liverpool I've been to ever since I was first married. But Gilbert won't let me. He's very masterful, and of course he has wonderful taste."

She looked at him with a little affectionate smile, demurely, as though she were a girl of seventeen.

Mrs. Tower went quite pale under her make-up.

"We're going to Italy for our honeymoon. Gilbert has never had a chance of studying Renaissance architecture and of course it's important for an architect to see things for himself. And we shall stop in Paris on the way and get my clothes there."

"Do you expect to be away long?"

"Gilbert has arranged with his office to stay away for six months. It will be such a treat for him, won't it? You see, he's never had more than a fortnight's holiday before."

"Why not?" asked Mrs. Tower in a tone that no effort of will could prevent from being icy.

"He's never been able to afford it, poor dear."

"Ah!" said Mrs. Tower, and into the exclamation put volumes.

Coffee was served and the ladies went upstairs. Gilbert and I began to talk in the desultory way in which men talk who have nothing whatever to say to one another; but in two minutes a note was brought in to me by the butler. It was from Mrs. Tower and ran as follows:

Come upstairs quickly and then go as soon as you can. Take him with you. Unless I have it out with Jane at once I shall have a fit.

I told a facile lie.

"Mrs. Tower has a headache and wants to go to bed. I think if you don't mind we'd better clear out."

"Certainly," he answered.

We went upstairs and five minutes later were on the doorstep. I called a taxi and offered the young man a lift.

"No, thanks," he answered. "I'll just walk to the corner and jump on a bus."

Mrs. Tower sprang to the fray as soon as she heard the front door close behind us.

"Are you crazy, Jane?" she cried.

"Not more than most people who don't habitually live in a lunatic asylum, I trust," Jane answered blandly.

"May I ask why you're going to marry this young man?" asked Mrs. Tower with formidable politeness.

"Partly because he won't take no for an answer. He's asked me five times. I grew positively tired of refusing him."

"And why do you think he's so anxious to marry you?"

"I amuse him."

Mrs. Tower gave an exclamation of annoyance.

"He's an unscrupulous rascal. I very nearly told him so to his face."

"You would have been wrong, and it wouldn't have been very polite."

"He's penniless and you're rich. You can't be such a besotted fool as not to see that he's marrying you for your money."

Jane remained perfectly composed. She observed her sister-in-law's agitation with detachment.

"I don't think he is, you know," she replied. "I think he's very fond of me."

"You're an old woman, Jane."

"I'm the same age as you are, Marion," she smiled.

"I've never let myself go. I'm very young for my age. No one would think I was more than forty. But even I wouldn't dream of marrying a boy twenty years younger than myself."

"Twenty-seven," corrected Jane.

"Do you mean to tell me that you can bring yourself to believe that it's possible for a young man to care for a woman old enough to be his mother?"

"I've lived very much in the country for many years. I dare say there's a great deal about human nature that I don't know. They tell me there's a man called Freud, an Austrian, I believe . . ."

But Mrs. Tower interrupted her without any politeness at all.

"Don't be ridiculous, Jane. It's so undignified. It's so ungraceful. I always thought you were a sensible woman. Really you're the last person I should ever have thought likely to fall in love with a boy."

"But I'm not in love with him. I've told him that. Of course I like him very much or I wouldn't think of marrying him. I thought it only fair to tell him quite plainly what my feelings were towards him."

Mrs. Tower gasped. The blood rushed to her head and her breathing oppressed her. She had no fan, but she seized the evening paper and vigorously fanned herself with it.

"If you're not in love with him why do you want to marry him?"

"I've been a widow a very long time and I've led a very quiet life. I thought I'd like a change."

"If you want to marry just to be married why don't you marry a man of your own age?"

"No man of my own age has asked me five times. In fact no man of my own age has asked me at all."

Jane chuckled as she answered. It drove Mrs. Tower to the final pitch of frenzy.

"Don't laugh, Jane, I won't have it. I don't think you can be right in your mind. It's dreadful."

It was altogether too much for her and she burst into tears. She knew that at her age it was fatal to cry, her eyes would be swollen for twenty-four hours and she would look a sight. But there was no help for it. She wept. Jane remained perfectly calm. She looked at Marion through her large spectacles and reflectively smoothed the lap of her black silk dress.

"You're going to be so dreadfully unhappy," Mrs. Tower sobbed, dabbing her eyes cautiously in the hope that the black on her lashes would not smudge.

"I don't think so, you know," Jane answered in those equable, mild tones of hers, as if there were a little smile behind the words. "We've talked it over very thoroughly. I always think I'm a very easy person to live with. I think I shall make Gilbert very happy and comfortable. He's never had anyone to look after him properly. We're only marrying after mature consideration. And we've decided that if either of us wants his liberty the other will place no obstacles in the way of his getting it."

Mrs. Tower had by now recovered herself sufficiently to make a cutting remark.

"How much has he persuaded you to settle on him?"

"I wanted to settle a thousand a year on him, but he wouldn't hear of it. He was quite upset when I made the suggestion. He says he can earn quite enough for his own needs."

"He's more cunning than I thought," said Mrs. Tower acidly.

Jane paused a little and looked at her sister-in-law with kindly but resolute eyes.

"You see, my dear, it's different for you," she said. "You've never been so very much a widow, have you?"

Mrs. Tower looked at her. She blushed a little. She even felt slightly uncomfortable. But of course Jane was much too simple to intend an innuendo. Mrs. Tower gathered herself together with dignity.

"I'm so upset that I really must go to bed," she said. "We'll resume the conversation tomorrow morning."

"I'm afraid that won't be very convenient, dear. Gilbert and I are going to get the licence tomorrow morning."

Mrs. Tower threw up her hands in a gesture of dismay, but she found nothing more to say.

The marriage took place at a registrar's office. Mrs. Tower and I were the witnesses. Gilbert in a smart blue suit looked absurdly young and he was obviously nervous. It is a trying moment for any man. But Jane kept her admirable composure. She might have been in the habit of marrying as frequently as a woman of fashion. Only a slight colour on her cheeks suggested that beneath her calm was some faint excitement. It is a thrilling moment for any woman. She wore a very full dress of silvery grey velvet in the cut of which I recognized the hand of the dressmaker in Liverpool (evidently a widow of unimpeachable character) who had made her gowns for so many years; but she had so far succumbed to the frivolity of the occasion as to wear a large picture hat covered with blue ostrich feathers. Her gold-rimmed spectacles made it extraordinarily grotesque.

When the ceremony was over the registrar (somewhat taken aback, I thought, by the difference of age between the pair he was marrying) shook hands with her, tendering his strictly official congratulations; and the bridegroom, blushing slightly, kissed her. Mrs. Tower, resigned but implacable, kissed her; and then the bride looked at me expectantly. It was evidently fitting that I should kiss her too. I did. I confess that I felt a little shy as we walked out of the registrar's office past loungers who waited cynically to see the bridal pairs, and it was with relief that I stepped into Mrs. Tower's car. We drove to Victoria Station, for the happy couple were to go over to Paris by the two o'clock train, and Jane had insisted that the wedding-breakfast should be eaten at the station restaurant. She said it always made her nervous not to be on the platform in good time. Mrs. Tower, present only from a strong sense of family duty, was able to do little to make the party go off well; she ate nothing (for which I could not blame her, since the food was execrable, and anyway I hate champagne at luncheon) and talked in a strained voice. But Jane went through the menu conscientiously.

"I always think one should make a hearty meal before starting out on a journey," she said.

We saw them off, and I drove Mrs. Tower back to her house.

"How long do you give it?" she said. "Six months?"

"Let's hope for the best," I smiled.

"Don't be so absurd. There can be no 'best'. You don't think he's marrying her for anything but her money, do you? Of course it can't last. My only hope is that she won't have to go through as much suffering as she deserves."

I laughed. The charitable words were spoken in such a tone as to leave me in small doubt of Mrs. Tower's meaning.

"Well, if it doesn't last you'll have the consolation of saying: 'I told you so,'" I said.

"I promise you I'll never do that."

"Then you'll have the satisfaction of congratulating yourself on your self-control in not saying: 'I told you so.'"

"She's old and dowdy and dull."

"Are you sure she's dull?" I said. "It's true she doesn't say very much, but when she says anything it's very much to the point."

"I've never heard her make a joke in my life."

I was once more in the Far East when Gilbert and Jane returned from their honeymoon and this time I remained away for nearly two years. Mrs. Tower was a bad correspondent and though I sent her an occasional picture-postcard I received no news from her. But I met her within a week of my return to London; I was dining out and found that I was seated next to her. It was an immense party, I think we were four-and-twenty, like the blackbirds in the pie, and, arriving somewhat late, I was too confused by the crowd in which I found myself to notice who was there. But when we sat down, looking round the long table I saw that a good many of my fellow-guests were well known to the public from their photographs in the illustrated papers. Our hostess had a weakness for the persons technically known as celebrities and this was an unusually brilliant gathering.

When Mrs. Tower and I had exchanged the conventional remarks that two people make when they have not seen one another for a couple of years I asked about Jane.

"She's very well," said Mrs. Tower with a certain dryness.

"How has the marriage turned out?"

Mrs. Tower paused a little and took a salted almond from the dish in front of her.

"It appears to be quite a success."

"You were wrong then?"

"I said it wouldn't last and I still say it won't last. It's contrary to human nature."

"Is she happy?"

"They're both happy."

"I suppose you don't see very much of them."

"At first I saw quite a lot of them. But now . . ." Mrs. Tower pursed her lips a little. "Jane is becoming very grand."

"What do you mean?" I laughed.

"I think I should tell you that she's here tonight."

"Here?"

I was startled. I looked round the table again. Our hostess was a delightful and an entertaining woman, but I could not imagine that she would be likely to invite to a dinner such as this the elderly and dowdy wife of an obscure architect. Mrs. Tower saw my perplexity and was shrewd enough to see what was in my mind. She smiled thinly.

"Look on the left of our host."

I looked. Oddly enough the woman who sat there had by her fantastic appearance attracted my attention the moment I was ushered into the crowded drawing-room. I thought I noticed a gleam of recognition in her eye, but to the best of my belief I had never seen her before. She was not a young woman, for her hair was iron-grey; it was cut very short and clustered thickly round her well-shaped head in tight curls. She made no attempt at youth, for she was conspicuous in that gathering by using neither lipstick, rouge, nor powder. Her face, not a particularly handsome one, was red and weather-beaten; but because it owed nothing to artifice had a naturalness that was very pleasing. It contrasted oddly with the whiteness of her shoulders. They were really magnificent. A woman of thirty might have been proud of them. But her dress was extraordinary. I had not often seen anything more audacious. It was cut very low, with short skirts, which were then the fashion, in black and yellow; it had almost the effect of fancy-dress and yet so became her that though on anyone else it would have been outrageous, on her it had the inevitable simplicity of nature. And to complete the impression of an eccentricity in which there was no pose and of an extravagance in which there was no ostentation she wore, attached by a broad black ribbon, a single eyeglass.

"You're not going to tell me that is your sister-in-law," I gasped.

"That is Jane Napier," said Mrs. Tower icily.

At that moment she was speaking. Her host was turned towards her with an anticipatory smile. A baldish white-haired man, with a sharp, intelligent face, who sat on her left, was leaning forward eagerly, and the couple who sat opposite, ceasing to talk with one another, listened intently. She said her say and they all, with a sudden movement, threw themselves back in their chairs and burst into vociferous laughter. From the other side of the table a man addressed Mrs. Tower: I recognized a famous statesman.

"Your sister-in-law has made another joke, Mrs. Tower," he said.

Mrs. Tower smiled.

"She's priceless, isn't she?"

"Let me have a long drink of champagne and then for heaven's sake tell me all about it," I said.

Well, this is how I gathered it had all happened. At the beginning of their honeymoon Gilbert took Jane to various dressmakers in Paris and he made no objection to her choosing a number of "gowns" after her own heart; but he persuaded her to have a "frock" or two made according to his own design. It appeared that he had a knack for that kind of work. He engaged a smart French maid. Jane had never had such a thing before. She did her own mending and when she wanted "doing up" was in the habit of ringing for the housemaid. The dresses Gilbert had devised were very different from anything she had worn before; but he had been careful not to go too far too quickly, and because it pleased him she persuaded herself, though not without misgivings, to wear them in preference to those she had chosen herself. Of course she could not wear them with the voluminous petticoats she had been in the habit of using, and these, though it cost her an anxious moment, she discarded.

"Now if you please," said Mrs. Tower, with something very like a sniff of disapproval, "she wears nothing but thin silk tights. It's a wonder to me she doesn't catch her death of cold at her age."

Gilbert and the French maid taught her how to wear her clothes, and, unexpectedly enough, she was very quick at learning. The French maid was in raptures over Madame's arms and shoulders. It was a scandal not to show anything so fine.

"Wait a little, Alphonsine," said Gilbert. "The next lot of clothes I design for Madame we'll make the most of her."

The spectacles of course were dreadful. No one could look really well in gold-rimmed spectacles. Gilbert tried some with tortoiseshell rims. He shook his head.

"They'd look all right on a girl," he said. "You're too old to wear spectacles, Jane." Suddenly he had an inspiration. "By George, I've got it. You must wear an eyeglass."

"Oh, Gilbert, I couldn't."

She looked at him and his excitement, the excitement of the artist, made her smile. He was so sweet to her she wanted to do what she could to please him.

"I'll try," she said.

When they went to an optician and, suited with the right size, she placed an eyeglass jauntily in her eye Gilbert clapped his hands. There and then, before the astonished shopman, he kissed her on both cheeks.

"You look wonderful," he cried.

So they went down to Italy and spent happy months studying Renaissance and Baroque architecture. Jane not only grew accustomed to her changed appearance, but found she liked it. At first she was a little shy when she went into the dining-room of an hotel and people turned round to stare at her, no one had ever raised an eyelid to look at her before, but presently she found that the sensation was not disagreeable. Ladies came up to her and asked her where she got her dress.

"Do you like it?" she answered demurely. "My husband designed it for me."

"I should like to copy it if you don't mind."

Jane had certainly for many years lived a very quiet life, but she was by no means lacking in the normal instincts of her sex. She had her answer ready.

"I'm so sorry, but my husband's very particular and he won't hear of anyone copying my frocks. He wants me to be unique."

She had an idea that people would laugh when she said this, but they didn't; they merely answered:

"Oh, of course I quite understand. You are unique."

But she saw them making mental notes of what she wore, and for some reason this quite "put her about". For once in her life that she wasn't wearing what everybody else did, she reflected, she didn't see why everybody else should want to wear what she did.

"Gilbert," said she, quite sharply for her, "next time you're designing dresses for me I wish you'd design things that people can't copy."

"The only way to do that is to design things that only you can wear."

"Can't you do that?"

"Yes, if you'll do something for me."

"What is it?"

"Cut off your hair."

I think this was the first time that Jane jibbed. Her hair was long and thick and as a girl she had been quite vain of it; to cut it off was a very drastic proceeding. This really was burning her boats behind her. In her case it was not the first step that cost so much, it was the last; but she took it ("I know Marion will think me a perfect fool, and I shall never be able to go to Liverpool again," she said), and when they passed through Paris on their way home Gilbert led her (she felt quite sick, her heart was beating so fast) to the best hairdresser in the world. She came out of this shop with a jaunty, saucy, impudent head of crisp grey curls. Pygmalion had finished his fantastic masterpiece: Galatea was come to life.

"Yes," I said, "but that isn't enough to explain why Jane is here tonight amid this crowd of duchesses, Cabinet Ministers, and suchlike; nor why she is sitting on one side of her host with an Admiral of the Fleet on the other."

"Jane is a humorist," said Mrs. Tower. "Didn't you see them all laughing at what she said?"

There was no doubt now of the bitterness in Mrs. Tower's heart.

"When Jane wrote and told me they were back from their honeymoon I thought I must ask them both to dinner. I didn't much like the idea, but I felt it had to be done. I knew the party would be deadly and I wasn't going to sacrifice any of the people who really mattered. On the other hand I didn't want Jane to think I hadn't any nice friends. You know I never have more than eight, but on this occasion I thought it would make things go better if I had twelve. I'd been too busy to see Jane until the evening of the party. She kept us all waiting a little—that was Gilbert's cleverness—and at last she sailed in. You could have knocked me down with a feather. She made the rest of the women look dowdy and provincial. She made me feel like a painted old trollop."

Mrs. Tower drank a little champagne.

"I wish I could describe the frock to you. It would have been quite impossible on anyone else; on her it was perfect. And the eyeglass! I'd known her for thirty-five years and I'd never seen her without spectacles."

"But you knew she had a good figure."

"How should I? I'd never seen her except in the clothes you first saw her in. Did you think she had a good figure? She seemed not to be unconscious of the sensation she made but to take it as a matter of course. I thought of my dinner and I heaved a sigh of relief. Even if she was a little heavy in hand, with that appearance it didn't so very much matter. She was sitting at the other end of the table and I heard a good deal of laughter. I was glad to think that the other people were playing up well; but after dinner I was a good deal taken aback when no less than three men came up to me and told me that my sister-in-law was priceless, and did I think she would allow them to call on her? I didn't quite know whether I was standing on my head or my heels. Twenty-four hours later our hostess of tonight rang me up and said she had heard my sister-in-law was in London and she was priceless and would I ask her to luncheon to meet her? She has an infallible instinct, that woman: in a month everyone was talking about Jane. I am here tonight, not because I've known our hostess for twenty years and have asked her to dinner a hundred times, but because I'm Jane's sister-in-law."

Poor Mrs. Tower. The position was galling, and though I could not help being amused, for the tables were turned on her with a vengeance, I felt that she deserved my sympathy.

"People never can resist those who make them laugh," I said, trying to console her.

"She never makes me laugh."

Once more from the top of the table I heard a guffaw and guessed that Jane had said another amusing thing.

"Do you mean to say that you are the only person who doesn't think her funny?" I asked, smiling.

"Had it struck you that she was a humorist?"

"I'm bound to say it hadn't."

"She says just the same things as she's said for the last thirty-five years, I laugh when I see everyone else does because I don't want to seem a perfect fool, but I am not amused."

"Like Queen Victoria," I said.

It was a foolish jest and Mrs. Tower was quite right sharply to tell me so. I tried another tack.

"Is Gilbert here?" I asked, looking down the table.

"Gilbert was asked because she won't go out without him, but tonight he's at a dinner of the Architects' Institute or whatever it's called."

"I'm dying to renew my acquaintance with her."

"Go and talk to her after dinner. She'll ask you to her Tuesdays."

"Her Tuesdays?"

"She's at home every Tuesday evening. You'll meet there everyone you ever heard of. They're the best parties in London. She's done in one year what I've failed to do in twenty."

"But what you tell me is really miraculous. How has it been done?"

Mrs. Tower shrugged her handsome but adipose shoulders.

"I shall be glad if you'll tell me," she replied.

After dinner I tried to make my way to the sofa on which Jane was sitting, but I was intercepted and it was not till a little later that my hostess came up to me and said:

"I must introduce you to the star of my party. Do you know Jane Napier? She's priceless. She's much more amusing than your comedies."

I was taken up to the sofa. The admiral who had been sitting beside her at dinner was with her still. He showed no sign of moving and Jane, shaking hands with me, introduced me to him.

"Do you know Sir Reginald Frobisher?"

We began to chat. It was the same Jane as I had known before, perfectly simple, homely and unaffected, but her fantastic appearance certainly gave a peculiar savour to what she said. Suddenly I found myself shaking with laughter. She had made a remark, sensible and to the point, but not in the least witty, which her manner of saying and the bland look she gave me through her eyeglass made perfectly irresistible. I felt light-hearted and buoyant. When I left her she said to me:

"If you've got nothing better to do, come and see us on Tuesday evening. Gilbert will be so glad to see you."

"When he's been a month in London he'll know that he can have nothing better to do," said the admiral.

So, on Tuesday but rather late, I went to Jane's. I confess I was a little surprised at the company. It was quite a remarkable collection of writers, painters and politicians, actors, great ladies and great beauties: Mrs. Tower was right, it was a grand party; I had seen nothing like it in London since Stafford House was sold. No particular entertainment was provided. The refreshments were adequate without being luxurious. Jane in her quiet way seemed to be enjoying herself; I could not see that she took a great deal of trouble with her guests, but they seemed to like being there and the gay, pleasant party did not break up till two in the morning. After that I saw much of her. I not only went often to her house, but seldom went out to luncheon or to dinner without meeting her. I am an amateur of humour and I sought to discover in what lay her peculiar gift. It was impossible to repeat anything she said, for the fun, like certain wines, would not travel. She had no gift for epigram. She never made a brilliant repartee. There was no malice in her remarks nor sting in her rejoinders. There are those who think that impropriety, rather than brevity, is the soul of wit; but she never said a thing that could have brought a blush to a Victorian cheek. I think her humour was unconscious and I am sure it was unpremeditated. It flew like a butterfly from flower to flower, obedient only to its own caprice and pursuivant of neither method nor intention. It depended on the way she spoke and on the way she looked. Its subtlety gained by the flaunting and extravagant appearance that Gilbert had achieved for her; but her appearance was only an element in it. Now of course she was the fashion and people laughed if she but opened her mouth. They no longer wondered that Gilbert had married a wife so much older than himself. They saw that Jane was a woman with whom age did not count. They thought him a devilish lucky young fellow. The admiral quoted Shakespeare to me: "Age cannot wither her, nor custom stale her infinite variety." Gilbert was delighted with her success. As I came to know him better I grew to like him. It was quite evident that he was neither a rascal nor a fortune-hunter. He was not only immensely proud of Jane but genuinely devoted to her. His kindness to her was touching. He was a very unselfish and sweet-tempered young man.

"Well, what do you think of Jane now?" he said to me once, with boyish triumph.

"I don't know which of you is more wonderful," I said. "You or she."

"Oh, I'm nothing."

"Nonsense. You don't think I'm such a fool as not to see that it's you, and you only, who've made Jane what she is."

"My only merit is that I saw what was there when it wasn't obvious to the naked eye," he answered.

"I can understand your seeing that she had in her the possibility of that remarkable appearance, but how in the world have you made her into a humorist?"

"But I always thought the things she said a perfect scream. She was always a humorist."

"You're the only person who ever thought so."

Mrs. Tower, not without magnanimity, acknowledged that she had been mistaken in Gilbert. She grew quite attached to him. But notwithstanding appearances she never faltered in her opinion that the marriage could not last. I was obliged to laugh at her.

"Why, I've never seen such a devoted couple," I said.

"Gilbert is twenty-seven now. It's just the time for a pretty girl to come along. Did you notice the other evening at Jane's that pretty little niece of Sir Reginald's? I thought Jane was looking at them both with a good deal of attention, and I wondered to myself."

"I don't believe Jane fears the rivalry of any girl under the sun."

"Wait and see," said Mrs. Tower.

"You gave it six months."

"Well, now I give it three years."

When anyone is very positive in an opinion it is only human nature to wish him proved wrong. Mrs. Tower was really too cocksure. But such a satisfaction was not mine, for the end that she had always and confidently predicted to the ill-assorted match did in point of fact come. Still, the fates seldom give us what we want in the way we want it, and though Mrs. Tower could flatter herself that she had been right, I think after all she would sooner have been wrong. For things did not happen at all in the way she expected.

One day I received an urgent message from her and fortunately went to see her at once. When I was shown into the room Mrs. Tower rose from her chair and came towards me with the stealthy swiftness of a leopard stalking his prey. I saw that she was excited.

"Jane and Gilbert have separated," she said.

"Not really? Well, you were right after all."

Mrs. Tower looked at me with an expression I could not understand.

"Poor Jane," I muttered.

"Poor Jane!" she repeated, but in tones of such derision that I was dumbfounded.

She found some difficulty in telling me exactly what had occurred.

Gilbert had left her a moment before she leaped to the telephone to summon me. When he entered the room, pale and distraught, she saw at once that something terrible had happened. She knew what he was going to say before he said it.

"Marion, Jane has left me."

She gave him a little smile and took his hand.

"I knew you'd behave like a gentleman. It would have been dreadful for her for people to think that you had left her."

"I've come to you because I knew I could count on your sympathy."

"Oh, I don't blame you, Gilbert," said Mrs. Tower, very kindly. "It was bound to happen." He sighed.

"I suppose so. I couldn't hope to keep her always. She was too wonderful and I'm a perfectly commonplace fellow."

Mrs. Tower patted his hand. He was really behaving beautifully.

"And what's going to happen now?"

"Well, she's going to divorce me."

"Jane always said she'd put no obstacle in your way if ever you wanted to marry a girl."

"You don't think it's likely I should ever be willing to marry anyone else after being Jane's husband," he answered.

Mrs. Tower was puzzled. "Of course you mean that you've left Jane."

"I? That's the last thing I should ever do."

"Then why is she divorcing you?"

"She's going to marry Sir Reginald Frobisher as soon as the decree is made absolute."

Mrs. Tower positively screamed. Then she felt so faint that she had to get her smelling salts.

"After all you've done for her?"

"I've done nothing for her."

"Do you mean to say you're going to allow yourself to be made use of like that?"

"We arranged before we married that if either of us wanted his liberty the other should put no hindrance in the way."

"But that was done on your account. Because you were twenty-seven years younger that she was."

"Well, it's come in very useful for her," he answered bitterly.

Mrs. Tower expostulated, argued, and reasoned; but Gilbert insisted that no rules applied to Jane, and he must do exactly what she wanted. He left Mrs. Tower prostrate. It relieved her a good deal to give me a full account of this interview. It pleased her to see that I was as surprised as herself and if I was not so indignant with Jane as she was she ascribed that to the criminal lack of morality incident to my sex. She was still in a state of extreme agitation when the door was opened and the butler showed in—Jane herself. She was dressed in black and white as no doubt befitted her slightly ambiguous position, but in a dress so original and fantastic, in a hat so striking, that I positively gasped at the sight of her. But she was as ever bland and collected. She came forward to kiss Mrs. Tower, but Mrs. Tower withdrew herself with icy dignity.

"Gilbert has been here," she said.

"Yes, I know," smiled Jane. "I told him to come and see you. I'm going to Paris tonight and I want you to be very kind to him while I'm away. I'm afraid just at first he'll be rather lonely and I shall feel more comfortable if I can count on your keeping an eye on him."

Mrs. Tower clasped her hands.

"Gilbert has just told me something that I can hardly bring myself to believe. He tells me that you're going to divorce him to marry Reginald Frobisher."

"Don't you remember, before I married Gilbert you advised me to marry a man of my own age? The admiral is fifty-three."

"But, Jane, you owe everything to Gilbert," said Mrs. Tower indignantly. "You wouldn't exist without him. Without him to design your clothes, you'll be nothing."

"Oh, he's promised to go on designing my clothes," Jane answered blandly.

"No woman could want a better husband. He's always been kindness itself to you."

"Oh, I know he's been sweet."

"How can you be so heartless?"

"But I was never in love with Gilbert," said Jane. "I always told him that. I'm beginning to feel the need of the companionship of a man of my own age. I think I've probably been married to Gilbert long enough. The young have no conversation." She paused a little and gave us both a charming smile. "Of course I shan't lose sight of Gilbert. I've arranged that with Reginald. The admiral has a niece that would just suit him. As soon as we're married we'll ask them to stay with us at Malta—you know that the admiral is to have the Mediterranean Command—and I shouldn't be at all surprised if they fell in love with one another."

Mrs. Tower gave a little sniff.

"And have you arranged with the admiral that if you want your liberty neither should put any hindrance in the way of the other?"

"I suggested it," Jane answered with composure. "But the admiral says he knows a good thing when he sees it and he won't want to marry anyone else, and if anyone wants to marry me—he has eight twelve-inch guns on his flagship and he'll discuss the matter at short range." She gave us a look through her eyeglass which even the fear of Mrs. Tower's wrath could not prevent me from laughing at. "I think the admiral's a very passionate man."

Mrs. Tower gave me an angry frown.

"I never thought you funny, Jane," she said. "I never understood why people laughed at the things you said."

"I never thought I was funny myself, Marion," smiled Jane, showing her bright, regular teeth. "I am glad to leave London before too many people come round to our opinion."

"I wish you'd tell me the secret of your astonishing success," I said.

She turned to me with that bland, homely look I knew so well.

"You know, when I married Gilbert and settled in London and people began to laugh at what I said no one was more surprised than I was. I'd said the same things for thirty years and no one ever saw anything to laugh at. I thought it must be my clothes or my bobbed hair or my eyeglass. Then I discovered it was because I spoke the truth. It was so unusual that people thought it humorous. One of these days someone else will discover the secret and when people habitually tell the truth of course there'll be nothing funny in it."

"And why am I the only person not to think it funny?" asked Mrs. Tower.

Jane hesitated a little as though she were honestly searching for a satisfactory explanation.

"Perhaps you don't know the truth when you see it, Marion dear," she answered in her mild good-natured way.

It certainly gave her the last word. I felt that Jane would always have the last word. She was priceless.

Rain

IT was nearly bed-time and when they awoke next morning land would be in sight. Dr Macphail lit his pipe and, leaning over the rail, searched the heavens for the Southern Cross. After two years at the front and a wound that had taken longer to heal than it should, he was glad to settle down quietly at Apia for twelve months at least, and he felt already better for the journey. Since some of the passengers were leaving the ship next day at Pago-Pago they had had a little dance that evening and in his ears hammered still the harsh notes of the mechanical piano. But the deck was quiet at last. A little way off he saw his wife in a long chair talking with the Davidsons, and he strolled over to her. When he sat down under the light and took off his hat you saw that he had very red hair, with a bald patch on the crown, and the red, freckled skin which accompanies red hair; he was a man of forty, thin, with a pinched face, precise and rather pedantic; and he spoke with a Scots accent in a very low, quiet voice.

Between the Macphails and the Davidsons, who were missionaries, there had arisen the intimacy of shipboard, which is due to propinquity rather than to any community of taste. Their chief tie was the disapproval they shared of the men who spent their days and nights in the smoking-room playing poker or bridge and drinking. Mrs. Macphail was not a little flattered to think that she and her husband were the only people on board with whom the Davidsons were willing to associate, and even the doctor, shy but no fool, half unconsciously acknowledged the compliment. It was only because he was of an argumentative mind that in their cabin at night he permitted himself to carp.

"Mrs. Davidson was saying she didn't know how they'd have got through the journey if it hadn't been for us," said Mrs. Macphail, as she neatly brushed out her transformation. "She said we were really the only people on the ship they cared to know."

"I shouldn't have thought a missionary was such a big bug that he could afford to put on frills."

"It's not frills. I quite understand what she means. It wouldn't have been very nice for the Davidsons to have to mix with all that rough lot in the smoking-room."

"The founder of their religion wasn't so exclusive," said Dr Macphail with a chuckle.

"I've asked you over and over again not to joke about religion," answered his wife. "I shouldn't like to have a nature like yours, Alec. You never look for the best in people."

He gave her a sidelong glance with his pale, blue eyes, but did not reply. After many years of married life he had learned that it was more conducive to peace to leave his wife with the last word. He was undressed before she was, and climbing into the upper bunk he settled down to read himself to sleep.

When he came on deck next morning they were close to land. He looked at it with greedy eyes. There was a thin strip of silver beach rising quickly to hills covered to the top with luxuriant vegetation. The coconut trees, thick and green, came nearly to the water's edge, and among them you saw the grass houses of the Samoans; and here and there, gleaming white, a little church. Mrs. Davidson came and stood beside him. She was dressed in black and wore round her neck a gold chain, from which dangled a small cross. She was a little woman, with brown, dull hair very elaborately arranged, and she had prominent blue eyes behind invisible pince-nez. Her face was long, like a sheep's, but she gave no impression of foolishness, rather of extreme alertness; she had the quick movements of a bird. The most remarkable thing about her was her voice, high, metallic, and without inflection; it fell on the ear with a hard monotony, irritating to the nerves like the pitiless clamour of the pneumatic drill.

"This must seem like home to you," said Dr Macphail, with his thin, difficult smile.

"Ours are low islands, you know, not like these. Coral. These are volcanic. We've got another ten days' journey to reach them."

"In these parts that's almost like being in the next street at home," said Dr Macphail facetiously.

"Well, that's rather an exaggerated way of putting it, but one does look at distances differently in the South Seas. So far you're right."

Dr Macphail sighed faintly.

"I'm glad we're not stationed here," she went on. "They say this is a terribly difficult place to work in. The steamers' touching makes the people unsettled; and then there's the naval station; that's bad for the natives. In our district we don't have difficulties like that to contend with. There are one or two traders, of course, but we take care to make them behave, and if they don't we make the place so hot for them they're glad to go."

Fixing the glasses on her nose she looked at the green island with a ruthless stare.

"It's almost a hopeless task for the missionaries here. I can never be sufficiently thankful to God that we are at least spared that."

Davidson's district consisted of a group of islands to the North of Samoa; they were widely separated and he had frequently to go long distances by canoe. At these times his wife remained at their headquarters and managed the mission. Dr Macphail felt his heart sink when he considered the efficiency with which she certainly managed it. She spoke of the depravity of the natives in a voice which nothing could hush, but with a vehemently unctuous horror. Her sense of delicacy was singular. Early in their acquaintance she had said to him:

"You know, their marriage customs when we first settled in the islands were so shocking that I couldn't possibly describe them to you. But I'll tell Mrs. Macphail and she'll tell you."

Then he had seen his wife and Mrs. Davidson, their deck-chairs close together, in earnest conversation for about two hours. As he walked past them backwards and forwards for the sake of exercise, he had heard Mrs. Davidson's agitated whisper, like the distant flow of a mountain torrent, and he saw by his wife's open mouth and pale face that she was enjoying an alarming experience. At night in their cabin she repeated to him with bated breath all she had heard.

"Well, what did I say to you?" cried Mrs. Davidson, exultant, next morning. "Did you ever hear anything more dreadful? You don't wonder that I couldn't tell you myself, do you? Even though you are a doctor."

Mrs. Davidson scanned his face. She had a dramatic eagerness to see that she had achieved the desired effect.

"Can you wonder that when we first went there our hearts sank? You'll hardly believe me when I tell you it was impossible to find a single good girl in any of the villages."

She used the word good in a severely technical manner.

"Mr. Davidson and I talked it over, and we made up our minds the first thing to do was to put down the dancing. The natives were crazy about dancing."

"I was not averse to it myself when I was a young man," said Dr Macphail.

"I guessed as much when I heard you ask Mrs. Macphail to have a turn with you last night. I don't think there's any real harm if a man dances with his wife, but I was relieved that she wouldn't. Under the circumstances I thought it better that we should keep ourselves to ourselves."

"Under what circumstances?"

Mrs. Davidson gave him a quick look through her pince-nez, but did not answer his question.

"But among white people it's not quite the same," she went on, "though I must say I agree with Mr. Davidson, who says he can't understand how a husband can stand by and see his wife in another man's arms, and as far as I'm concerned I've never danced a step since I married. But the native dancing is quite another matter. It's not only immoral in itself, but it distinctly leads to immorality. However, I'm thankful to God that we stamped it out, and I don't think I'm wrong in saying that no one has danced in our district for eight years."

But now they came to the mouth of the harbour and Mrs. Macphail joined them. The ship turned sharply and steamed slowly in. It was a great land-locked harbour big enough to hold a fleet of battleships; and all around it rose, high and steep, the green hills. Near the entrance, getting such breeze as blew from the sea, stood the governor's house in a garden. The Stars and Stripes dangled languidly from a flagstaff. They passed two or three trim bungalows, and a tennis court, and then they came to the quay with its warehouses. Mrs. Davidson pointed out the schooner, moored two or three hundred yards from the side, which was to take them to Apia. There was a crowd of eager, noisy, and good-humoured natives come from all parts of the island, some from curiosity, others to barter with the travellers on their way to Sydney; and they brought pineapples and huge bunches of bananas, tapa cloths, necklaces of shells or sharks' teeth, kava-bowls, and models of war canoes. American sailors, neat and trim, clean-shaven and frank of face, sauntered among them, and there was a little group of officials. While their luggage was being landed the Macphails and Mrs. Davidson watched the crowd. Dr Macphail looked at the yaws from which most of the children and the young boys seemed to suffer, disfiguring sores like torpid ulcers, and his professional eyes glistened when he saw for the first time in his experience cases of elephantiasis, men going about with a huge, heavy arm or dragging along a grossly disfigured leg. Men and women wore the lava-lava.

"It's a very indecent costume," said Mrs. Davidson. "Mr. Davidson thinks it should be prohibited by law. How can you expect people to be moral when they wear nothing but a strip of red cotton round their loins?"

"It's suitable enough to the climate," said the doctor, wiping the sweat off his head.

Now that they were on land the heat, though it was so early in the morning, was already oppressive. Closed in by its hills, not a breath of air came in to Pago-Pago.

"In our islands," Mrs. Davidson went on in her high-pitched tones, "we've practically eradicated the lava-lava. A few old men still continue to wear it, but that's all. The women have all taken to the Mother Hubbard, and the men wear trousers and singlets. At the very beginning of our stay Mr. Davidson said in one of his reports: the inhabitants of these islands will never be thoroughly Christianised till every boy of more than ten years is made to wear a pair of trousers."

But Mrs. Davidson had given two or three of her birdlike glances at heavy grey clouds that came floating over the mouth of the harbour. A few drops began to fall.

"We'd better take shelter," she said.

They made their way with all the crowd to a great shed of corrugated iron, and the rain began to fall in torrents. They stood there for some time and then were joined by Mr. Davidson. He had been polite enough to the Macphails during the journey, but he had not his wife's sociability, and had spent much of his time reading. He was a silent, rather sullen man, and you felt that his affability was a duty that he imposed upon himself Christianly; he was by nature reserved and even morose. His appearance was singular. He was very tall and thin, with long limbs loosely jointed; hollow cheeks and curiously high cheek-bones; he had so cadaverous an air that it surprised you to notice how full and sensual were his lips. He wore his hair very long. His dark eyes, set deep in their sockets, were large and tragic; and his hands with their big, long fingers, were finely shaped; they gave him a look of great strength. But the most striking thing about him was the feeling he gave you of suppressed fire. It was impressive and vaguely troubling. He was not a man with whom any intimacy was possible.

He brought now unwelcome news. There was an epidemic of measles, a serious and often fatal disease among the Kanakas, on the island, and a case had developed among the crew of the schooner which was to take them on their journey. The sick man had been brought ashore and put in hospital on the quarantine station, but telegraphic instructions had been sent from Apia to say that the schooner would not be allowed to enter the harbour till it was certain no other member of the crew was affected.

"It means we shall have to stay here for ten days at least."

"But I'm urgently needed at Apia," said Dr Macphail.

"That can't be helped. If no more cases develop on board, the schooner will be allowed to sail with white passengers, but all native traffic is prohibited for three months."

"Is there a hotel here?" asked Mrs. Macphail.

Davidson gave a low chuckle.

"There's not."

"What shall we do then?"

"I've been talking to the governor. There's a trader along the front who has rooms that he rents, and my proposition is that as soon as the rain lets up we should go along there and see what we can do. Don't expect comfort. You've just got to be thankful if we get a bed to sleep on and a roof over our heads."

But the rain showed no sign of stopping, and at length with umbrellas and waterproofs they set out. There was no town, but merely a group of official buildings, a store or two, and at the back, among the coconut trees and plantains, a few native dwellings. The house they sought was about five minutes' walk from the wharf. It was a frame house of two storeys, with broad verandahs on both floors and a roof of corrugated iron. The owner was a half-caste named Horn, with a native wife surrounded by little brown children, and on the ground-floor he had a store where he sold canned goods and cottons. The rooms he showed them were almost bare of furniture. In the Macphails' there was nothing but a poor, worn bed with a ragged mosquito net, a rickety chair, and a washstand. They looked round with dismay. The rain poured down without ceasing.

"I'm not going to unpack more than we actually need," said Mrs. Macphail.

Mrs. Davidson came into the room as she was unlocking a portmanteau. She was very brisk and alert. The cheerless surroundings had no effect on her.

"If you'll take my advice you'll get a needle and cotton and start right in to mend the mosquito net," she said, "or you'll not be able to get a wink of sleep to-night."

"Will they be very bad?" asked Dr Macphail.

"This is the season for them. When you're asked to a party at Government House at Apia you'll notice that all the ladies are given a pillow-slip to put their—their lower extremities in."

"I wish the rain would stop for a moment," said Mrs. Macphail. "I could try to make the place comfortable with more heart if the sun were shining."

"Oh, if you wait for that, you'll wait a long time. Pago-Pago is about the rainiest place in the Pacific. You see, the hills, and that bay, they attract the water, and one expects rain at this time of year anyway."

She looked from Macphail to his wife, standing helplessly in different parts of the room, like lost souls, and she pursed her lips. She saw that she must take them in hand. Feckless people like that made her impatient, but her hands itched to put everything in the order which came so naturally to her.

"Here, you give me a needle and cotton and I'll mend that net of yours, while you go on with your unpacking. Dinner's at one. Dr Macphail, you'd better go down to the wharf and see that your heavy luggage has been put in a dry place. You know what these natives are, they're quite capable of storing it where the rain will beat in on it all the time."

The doctor put on his waterproof again and went downstairs. At the door Mr. Horn was standing in conversation with the quartermaster of the ship they had just arrived in and a second-class passenger whom Dr Macphail had seen several times on board. The quartermaster, a little, shrivelled man, extremely dirty, nodded to him as he passed.

"This is a bad job about the measles, doc," he said. "I see you've fixed yourself up already."

Dr Macphail thought he was rather familiar, but he was a timid man and he did not take offence easily.

"Yes, we've got a room upstairs."

"Miss Thompson was sailing with you to Apia, so I've brought her along here."

The quartermaster pointed with his thumb to the woman standing by his side. She was twenty-seven perhaps, plump, and in a coarse fashion pretty. She wore a white dress and a large white hat. Her fat calves in white cotton stockings bulged over the tops of long white boots in glacé kid. She gave Macphail an ingratiating smile.

"The feller's tryin' to soak me a dollar and a half a day for the meanest sized room," she said in a hoarse voice.

"I tell you she's a friend of mine, Jo," said the quartermaster. "She can't pay more than a dollar, and you've sure got to take her for that."

The trader was fat and smooth and quietly smiling.

"Well, if you put it like that, Mr. Swan, I'll see what I can do about it. I'll talk to Mrs. Horn and if we think we can make a reduction we will."

"Don't try to pull that stuff with me," said Miss Thompson. "We'll settle this right now. You get a dollar a day for the room and not one bean more."

Dr Macphail smiled. He admired the effrontery with which she bargained. He was the sort of man who always paid what he was asked. He preferred to be over-charged than to haggle. The trader sighed.

"Well, to oblige Mr. Swan I'll take it."

"That's the goods," said Miss Thompson. "Come right in and have a shot of hooch. I've got some real good rye in that grip if you'll bring it along, Mr. Swan. You come along too, doctor."

"Oh, I don't think I will, thank you," he answered. "I'm just going down to see that our luggage is all right."

He stepped out into the rain. It swept in from the opening of the harbour in sheets and the opposite shore was all blurred. He passed two or three natives clad in nothing but the lava-lava, with huge umbrellas over them. They walked finely, with leisurely movements, very upright; and they smiled and greeted him in a strange tongue as they went by.

It was nearly dinner-time when he got back, and their meal was laid in the trader's parlour. It was a room designed not to live in but for purposes of prestige, and it had a musty, melancholy air. A suite of stamped plush was arranged neatly round the walls, and from the middle of the ceiling, protected from the flies by yellow tissue paper, hung a gilt chandelier. Davidson did not come.

"I know he went to call on the governor," said Mrs. Davidson, "and I guess he's kept him to dinner."

A little native girl brought them a dish of Hamburger steak, and after a while the trader came up to see that they had everything they wanted.

"I see we have a fellow lodger, Mr. Horn," said Dr Macphail.

"She's taken a room, that's all," answered the trader. "She's getting her own board."

He looked at the two ladies with an obsequious air.

"I put her downstairs so she shouldn't be in the way. She won't be any trouble to you."

"Is it someone who was on the boat?" asked Mrs. Macphail.

"Yes, ma'am, she was in the second cabin. She was going to Apia. She has a position as cashier waiting for her."

"Oh!"

When the trader was gone Macphail said:

"I shouldn't think she'd find it exactly cheerful having her meals in her room."

"If she was in the second cabin I guess she'd rather," answered Mrs. Davidson. "I don't exactly know who it can be."

"I happened to be there when the quartermaster brought her along. Her name's Thompson."

"It's not the woman who was dancing with the quartermaster last night?" asked Mrs. Davidson.

"That's who it must be," said Mrs. Macphail. "I wondered at the time what she was. She looked rather fast to me."

"Not good style at all," said Mrs. Davidson.

They began to talk of other things, and after dinner, tired with their early rise, they separated and slept. When they awoke, though the sky was still grey and the clouds hung low, it was not raining and they went for a walk on the high road which the Americans had built along the bay.

On their return they found that Davidson had just come in.

"We may be here for a fortnight," he said irritably. "I've argued it out with the governor, but he says there is nothing to be done."

"Mr. Davidson's just longing to get back to his work," said his wife, with an anxious glance at him.

"We've been away for a year," he said, walking up and down the verandah. "The mission has been in charge of native missionaries and I'm terribly nervous that they've let things slide. They're good men, I'm not saying a word against them, God-fearing, devout, and truly Christian men—their Christianity would put many so-called Christians at home to the blush—but they're pitifully lacking in energy. They can make a stand once, they can make a stand twice, but they can't make a stand all the time. If you leave a mission in charge of a native missionary, no matter how trustworthy he seems, in course of time you'll find he's let abuses creep in."

Mr. Davidson stood still. With his tall, spare form, and his great eyes flashing out of his pale face, he was an impressive figure. His sincerity was obvious in the fire of his gestures and in his deep, ringing voice.

"I expect to have my work cut out for me. I shall act and I shall act promptly. If the tree is rotten it shall be cut down and cast into the flames."

And in the evening after the high tea which was their last meal, while they sat in the stiff parlour, the ladies working and Dr Macphail smoking his pipe, the missionary told them of his work in the islands.

"When we went there they had no sense of sin at all," he said. "They broke the commandments one after the other and never knew they were doing wrong. And I think that was the most difficult part of my work, to instil into the natives the sense of sin."

The Macphails knew already that Davidson had worked in the Solomons for five years before he met his wife. She had been a missionary in China, and they had become acquainted in Boston, where they were both spending part of their leave to attend a missionary congress. On their marriage they had been appointed to the islands in which they had laboured ever since.

In the course of all the conversations they had had with Mr. Davidson one thing had shone out clearly and that was the man's unflinching courage. He was a medical missionary, and he was liable to be called at any time to one or other of the islands in the group. Even the whaleboat is not so very safe a conveyance in the stormy Pacific of the wet season, but often he would be sent for in a canoe, and then the danger was great. In cases of illness or accident he never hesitated. A dozen times he had spent the whole night baling for his life, and more than once Mrs. Davidson had given him up for lost.

"I'd beg him not to go sometimes," she said, "or at least to wait till the weather was more settled, but he'd never listen. He's obstinate, and when he's once made up his mind, nothing can move him."

"How can I ask the natives to put their trust in the Lord if I am afraid to do so myself?" cried Davidson. "And I'm not, I'm not. They know that if they send for me in their trouble I'll come if it's humanly possible. And do you think the Lord is going to abandon me when I am on his business? The wind blows at his bidding and the waves toss and rage at his word."

Dr Macphail was a timid man. He had never been able to get used to the hurtling of the shells over the trenches, and when he was operating in an advanced dressing-station the sweat poured from his brow and dimmed his spectacles in the effort he made to control his unsteady hand. He shuddered a little as he looked at the missionary.

"I wish I could say that I've never been afraid," he said.

"I wish you could say that you believed in God," retorted the other.

But for some reason, that evening the missionary's thoughts travelled back to the early days he and his wife had spent on the islands.

"Sometimes Mrs. Davidson and I would look at one another and the tears would stream down our cheeks. We worked without ceasing, day and night, and we seemed to make no progress. I don't know what I should have done without her then. When I felt my heart sink, when I was very near despair, she gave me courage and hope."

Mrs. Davidson looked down at her work, and a slight colour rose to her thin cheeks. Her hands trembled a little. She did not trust herself to speak.

"We had no one to help us. We were alone, thousands of miles from any of our own people, surrounded by darkness. When I was broken and weary she would put her work aside and take the Bible and read to me till peace came and settled upon me like sleep upon the eyelids of a child, and when at last she closed the book she'd say: 'We'll save them in spite of themselves.' And I felt strong again in the Lord, and I answered: 'Yes, with God's help I'll save them. I must save them.'"

He came over to the table and stood in front of it as though it were a lectern.

"You see, they were so naturally depraved that they couldn't be brought to see their wickedness. We had to make sins out of what they thought were natural actions. We had to make it a sin, not only to commit adultery and to lie and thieve, but to expose their bodies, and to dance and not to come to church. I made it a sin for a girl to show her bosom and a sin for a man not to wear trousers."

"How?" asked Dr Macphail, not without surprise.

"I instituted fines. Obviously the only way to make people realise that an action is sinful is to punish them if they commit it. I fined them if they didn't come to church, and I fined them if they danced. I fined them if they were improperly dressed. I had a tariff, and every sin had to be paid for either in money or work. And at last I made them understand."

"But did they never refuse to pay?"

"How could they?" asked the missionary.

"It would be a brave man who tried to stand up against Mr. Davidson," said his wife, tightening her lips.

Dr Macphail looked at Davidson with troubled eyes. What he heard shocked him, but he hesitated to express his disapproval.

"You must remember that in the last resort I could expel them from their church membership."

"Did they mind that?"

Davidson smiled a little and gently rubbed his hands.

"They couldn't sell their copra. When the men fished they got no share of the catch. It meant something very like starvation. Yes, they minded quite a lot."

"Tell him about Fred Ohlson," said Mrs. Davidson.

The missionary fixed his fiery eyes on Dr Macphail.

"Fred Ohlson was a Danish trader who had been in the islands a good many years. He was a pretty rich man as traders go and he wasn't very pleased when we came. You see, he'd had things very much his own way. He paid the natives what he liked for their copra, and he paid in goods and whiskey. He had a native wife, but he was flagrantly unfaithful to her. He was a drunkard. I gave him a chance to mend his ways, but he wouldn't take it. He laughed at me."

Davidson's voice fell to a deep bass as he said the last words, and he was silent for a minute or two. The silence was heavy with menace.

"In two years he was a ruined man. He'd lost everything he'd saved in a quarter of a century. I broke him, and at last he was forced to come to me like a beggar and beseech me to give him a passage back to Sydney."

"I wish you could have seen him when he came to see Mr. Davidson," said the missionary's wife. "He had been a fine, powerful man, with a lot of fat on him, and he had a great big voice, but now he was half the size, and he was shaking all over. He'd suddenly become an old man."

With abstracted gaze Davidson looked out into the night. The rain was falling again.

Suddenly from below came a sound, and Davidson turned and looked questioningly at his wife. It was the sound of a gramophone, harsh and loud, wheezing out a syncopated tune.

"What's that?" he asked.

Mrs. Davidson fixed her pince-nez more firmly on her nose.

"One of the second-class passengers has a room in the house. I guess it comes from there."

They listened in silence, and presently they heard the sound of dancing. Then the music stopped, and they heard the popping of corks and voices raised in animated conversation.

"I daresay she's giving a farewell party to her friends on board," said Dr Macphail. "The ship sails at twelve, doesn't it?"

Davidson made no remark, but he looked at his watch.

"Are you ready?" he asked his wife.

She got up and folded her work.

"Yes, I guess I am," she answered.

"It's early to go to bed yet, isn't it?" said the doctor.

"We have a good deal of reading to do," explained Mrs. Davidson. "Wherever we are, we read a chapter of the Bible before retiring for the night and we study it with the commentaries, you know, and discuss it thoroughly. It's a wonderful training for the mind."

The two couples bade one another good night. Dr and Mrs. Macphail were left alone. For two or three minutes they did not speak.

"I think I'll go and fetch the cards," the doctor said at last.

Mrs. Macphail looked at him doubtfully. Her conversation with the Davidsons had left her a little uneasy, but she did not like to say that she thought they had better not play cards when the Davidsons might come in at any moment. Dr Macphail brought them and she watched him, though with a vague sense of guilt, while he laid out his patience. Below the sound of revelry continued.

It was fine enough next day, and the Macphails, condemned to spend a fortnight of idleness at Pago-Pago, set about making the best of things. They went down to the quay and got out of their boxes a number of books. The doctor called on the chief surgeon of the naval hospital and went round the beds with him. They left cards on the governor. They passed Miss Thompson on the road. The doctor took off his hat, and she gave him a "Good morning, doc." in a loud, cheerful voice. She was dressed as on the day before, in a white frock, and her shiny white boots with their high heels, her fat legs bulging over the tops of them, were strange things on that exotic scene.

"I don't think she's very suitably dressed, I must say," said Mrs. Macphail. "She looks extremely common to me."

When they got back to their house, she was on the verandah playing with one of the trader's dark children.

"Say a word to her," Dr Macphail whispered to his wife. "She's all alone here, and it seems rather unkind to ignore her."

Mrs. Macphail was shy, but she was in the habit of doing what her husband bade her.

"I think we're fellow lodgers here," she said, rather foolishly.

"Terrible, ain't it, bein' cooped up in a one-horse burg like this?" answered Miss Thompson. "And they tell me I'm lucky to have gotten a room. I don't see myself livin' in a native house, and that's what some have to do. I don't know why they don't have a hotel."

They exchanged a few more words. Miss Thompson, loud-voiced and garrulous, was evidently quite willing to gossip, but Mrs. Macphail had a poor stock of small talk and presently she said:

"Well, I think we must go upstairs."

In the evening when they sat down to their high-tea Davidson on coming in said:

"I see that woman downstairs has a couple of sailors sitting there. I wonder how she's gotten acquainted with them."

"She can't be very particular," said Mrs. Davidson.

They were all rather tired after the idle, aimless day.

"If there's going to be a fortnight of this I don't know what we shall feel like at the end of it," said Dr Macphail.

"The only thing to do is to portion out the day to different activities," answered the missionary. "I shall set aside a certain number of hours to study and a certain number to exercise, rain or fine—in the wet season you can't afford to pay any attention to the rain—and a certain number to recreation."

Dr Macphail looked at his companion with misgiving. Davidson's programme oppressed him. They were eating Hamburger steak again. It seemed the only dish the cook knew how to make. Then below the gramophone began. Davidson started nervously when he heard it, but said nothing. Men's voices floated up. Miss Thompson's guests were joining in a well-known song and presently they heard her voice too, hoarse and loud. There was a good deal of shouting and laughing. The four people upstairs, trying to make conversation, listened despite themselves to the clink of glasses and the scrape of chairs. More people had evidently come. Miss Thompson was giving a party.

"I wonder how she gets them all in," said Mrs. Macphail, suddenly breaking into a medical conversation between the missionary and her husband.

It showed whither her thoughts were wandering. The twitch of Davidson's face proved that, though he spoke of scientific things, his mind was busy in the same direction. Suddenly, while the doctor was giving some experience of practice on the Flanders front, rather prosily, he sprang to his feet with a cry.

"What's the matter, Alfred?" asked Mrs. Davidson.

"Of course! It never occurred to me. She's out of Iwelei."

"She can't be."

"She came on board at Honolulu. It's obvious. And she's carrying on her trade here. Here."

He uttered the last word with a passion of indignation.

"What's Iwelei?" asked Mrs. Macphail.

He turned his gloomy eyes on her and his voice trembled with horror.

"The plague spot of Honolulu. The Red Light district. It was a blot on our civilisation."

Iwelei was on the edge of the city. You went down side streets by the harbour, in the darkness, across a rickety bridge, till you came to a deserted road, all ruts and holes, and then suddenly you came out into the light. There was parking room for motors on each side of the road, and there were saloons, tawdry and bright, each one noisy with its mechanical piano, and there were barbers' shops and tobacconists. There was a stir in the air and a sense of expectant gaiety. You turned down a narrow alley, either to the right or to the left, for the road divided Iwelei into two parts, and you found yourself in the district. There were rows of little bungalows, trim and neatly painted in green, and the pathway between them was broad and straight. It was laid out like a garden-city. In its respectable regularity, its order and spruceness, it gave an impression of sardonic horror; for never can the search for love have been so systematised and ordered. The pathways were lit by a rare lamp, but they would have been dark except for the lights that came from the open windows of the bungalows. Men wandered about, looking at the women who sat at their windows, reading or sewing, for the most part taking no notice of the passers-by; and like the women they were of all nationalities. There were Americans, sailors from the ships in port, enlisted men off the gunboats, sombrely drunk, and soldiers from the regiments, white and black, quartered on the island; there were Japanese, walking in twos and threes; Hawaiians, Chinese in long robes, and Filipinos in preposterous hats. They were silent and as it were oppressed. Desire is sad.

"It was the most crying scandal of the Pacific," exclaimed Davidson vehemently. "The missionaries had been agitating against it for years, and at last the local press took it up. The police refused to stir. You know their argument. They say that vice is inevitable and consequently the best thing is to localise and control it. The truth is, they were paid. Paid. They were paid by the saloon-keepers, paid by the bullies, paid by the women themselves. At last they were forced to move."

"I read about it in the papers that came on board in Honolulu," said Dr Macphail.

"Iwelei, with its sin and shame, ceased to exist on the very day we arrived. The whole population was brought before the justices. I don't know why I didn't understand at once what that woman was."

"Now you come to speak of it," said Mrs. Macphail, "I remember seeing her come on board only a few minutes before the boat sailed. I remember thinking at the time she was cutting it rather fine."

"How dare she come here!" cried Davidson indignantly. "I'm not going to allow it."

He strode towards the door.

"What are you going to do?" asked Macphail.

"What do you expect me to do? I'm going to stop it. I'm not going to have this house turned into—into. . . ."

He sought for a word that should not offend the ladies' ears. His eyes were flashing and his pale face was paler still in his emotion.

"It sounds as though there were three or four men down there," said the doctor. "Don't you think it's rather rash to go in just now?"

The missionary gave him a contemptuous look and without a word flung out of the room.

"You know Mr. Davidson very little if you think the fear of personal danger can stop him in the performance of his duty," said his wife.

She sat with her hands nervously clasped, a spot of colour on her high cheek bones, listening to what was about to happen below. They all listened. They heard him clatter down the wooden stairs and throw open the door. The singing stopped suddenly, but the gramophone continued to bray out its vulgar tune. They heard Davidson's voice and then the noise of something heavy falling. The music stopped. He had hurled the gramophone on the floor. Then again they heard Davidson's voice, they could not make out the words, then Miss Thompson's, loud and shrill, then a confused clamour as though several people were shouting together at the top of their lungs. Mrs. Davidson gave a little gasp, and she clenched her hands more tightly. Dr Macphail looked uncertainly from her to his wife. He did not want to go down, but he wondered if they expected him to. Then there was something that sounded like a scuffle. The noise now was more distinct. It might be that Davidson was being thrown out of the room. The door was slammed. There was a moment's silence and they heard Davidson come up the stairs again. He went to his room.

"I think I'll go to him," said Mrs. Davidson.

She got up and went out.

"If you want me, just call," said Mrs. Macphail, and then when the other was gone: "I hope he isn't hurt."

"Why couldn't he mind his own business?" said Dr Macphail.

They sat in silence for a minute or two and then they both started, for the gramophone began to play once more, defiantly, and mocking voices shouted hoarsely the words of an obscene song.

Next day Mrs. Davidson was pale and tired. She complained of headache, and she looked old and wizened. She told Mrs. Macphail that the missionary had not slept at all; he had passed the night in a state of frightful agitation and at five had got up and gone out. A glass of beer had been thrown over him and his clothes were stained and stinking. But a sombre fire glowed in Mrs. Davidson's eyes when she spoke of Miss Thompson.

"She'll bitterly rue the day when she flouted Mr. Davidson," she said. "Mr. Davidson has a wonderful heart and no one who is in trouble has ever gone to him without being comforted, but he has no mercy for sin, and when his righteous wrath is excited he's terrible."

"Why, what will he do?" asked Mrs. Macphail.

"I don't know, but I wouldn't stand in that creature's shoes for anything in the world."

Mrs. Macphail shuddered. There was something positively alarming in the triumphant assurance of the little woman's manner. They were going out together that morning, and they went down the stairs side by side. Miss Thompson's door was open, and they saw her in a bedraggled dressing-gown, cooking something in a chafing-dish.

"Good morning," she called. "Is Mr. Davidson better this morning?"

They passed her in silence, with their noses in the air, as if she did not exist. They flushed, however, when she burst into a shout of derisive laughter. Mrs. Davidson turned on her suddenly.

"Don't you dare to speak to me," she screamed. "If you insult me I shall have you turned out of here."

"Say, did I ask Mr. Davidson to visit with me?"

"Don't answer her," whispered Mrs. Macphail hurriedly.

They walked on till they were out of earshot.

"She's brazen, brazen," burst from Mrs. Davidson.

Her anger almost suffocated her.

And on their way home they met her strolling towards the quay. She had all her finery on. Her great white hat with its vulgar, showy flowers was an affront. She called out cheerily to them as she went by, and a couple of American sailors who were standing there grinned as the ladies set their faces to an icy stare. They got in just before the rain began to fall again.

"I guess she'll get her fine clothes spoilt," said Mrs. Davidson with a bitter sneer.

Davidson did not come in till they were half way through dinner. He was wet through, but he would not change. He sat, morose and silent, refusing to eat more than a mouthful, and he stared at the slanting rain. When Mrs. Davidson told him of their two encounters with Miss Thompson he did not answer. His deepening frown alone showed that he had heard.

"Don't you think we ought to make Mr. Horn turn her out of here?" asked Mrs. Davidson. "We can't allow her to insult us."

"There doesn't seem to be any other place for her to go," said Macphail.

"She can live with one of the natives."

"In weather like this a native hut must be a rather uncomfortable place to live in."

"I lived in one for years," said the missionary.

When the little native girl brought in the fried bananas which formed the sweet they had every day, Davidson turned to her.

"Ask Miss Thompson when it would be convenient for me to see her," he said.

The girl nodded shyly and went out.

"What do you want to see her for, Alfred?" asked his wife.

"It's my duty to see her. I won't act till I've given her every chance."

"You don't know what she is. She'll insult you."

"Let her insult me. Let her spit on me. She has an immortal soul, and I must do all that is in my power to save it."

Mrs. Davidson's ears rang still with the harlot's mocking laughter.

"She's gone too far."

"Too far for the mercy of God?" His eyes lit up suddenly and his voice grew mellow and soft. "Never. The sinner may be deeper in sin than the depth of hell itself, but the love of the Lord Jesus can reach him still."

The girl came back with the message.

"Miss Thompson's compliments and as long as Rev. Davidson don't come in business hours she'll be glad to see him any time."

The party received it in stony silence, and Dr Macphail quickly effaced from his lips the smile which had come upon them. He knew his wife would be vexed with him if he found Miss Thompson's effrontery amusing.

They finished the meal in silence. When it was over the two ladies got up and took their work, Mrs. Macphail was making another of the innumerable comforters which she had turned out since the beginning of the war, and the doctor lit his pipe. But Davidson remained in his chair and with abstracted eyes stared at the table. At last he got up and without a word went out of the room. They heard him go down and they heard Miss Thompson's defiant "Come in" when he knocked at the door. He remained with her for an hour. And Dr Macphail watched the rain. It was beginning to get on his nerves. It was not like our soft English rain that drops gently on the earth; it was unmerciful and somehow terrible; you felt in it the malignancy of the primitive powers of nature. It did not pour, it flowed. It was like a deluge from heaven, and it rattled on the roof of corrugated iron with a steady persistence that was maddening. It seemed to have a fury of its own. And sometimes you felt that you must scream if it did not stop, and then suddenly you felt powerless, as though your bones had suddenly become soft; and you were miserable and hopeless.

Macphail turned his head when the missionary came back. The two women looked up.

"I've given her every chance. I have exhorted her to repent. She is an evil woman."

He paused, and Dr Macphail saw his eyes darken and his pale face grow hard and stern.

"Now I shall take the whips with which the Lord Jesus drove the usurers and the money changers out of the Temple of the Most High."

He walked up and down the room. His mouth was close set, and his black brows were frowning.

"If she fled to the uttermost parts of the earth I should pursue her."

With a sudden movement he turned round and strode out of the room. They heard him go downstairs again.

"What is he going to do?" asked Mrs. Macphail.

"I don't know." Mrs. Davidson took off her pince-nez and wiped them. "When he is on the Lord's work I never ask him questions."

She sighed a little.

"What is the matter?"

"He'll wear himself out. He doesn't know what it is to spare himself."

Dr Macphail learnt the first results of the missionary's activity from the half-caste trader in whose house they lodged. He stopped the doctor when he passed the store and came out to speak to him on the stoop. His fat face was worried.

"The Rev. Davidson has been at me for letting Miss Thompson have a room here," he said, "but I didn't know what she was when I rented it to her. When people come and ask if I can rent them a room all I want to know is if they've the money to pay for it. And she paid me for hers a week in advance."

Dr Macphail did not want to commit himself.

"When all's said and done it's your house. We're very much obliged to you for taking us in at all."

Horn looked at him doubtfully. He was not certain yet how definitely Macphail stood on the missionary's side.

"The missionaries are in with one another," he said, hesitatingly. "If they get it in for a trader he may just as well shut up his store and quit."

"Did he want you to turn her out?"

"No, he said so long as she behaved herself he couldn't ask me to do that. He said he wanted to be just to me. I promised she shouldn't have no more visitors. I've just been and told her."

"How did she take it?"

"She gave me Hell."

The trader squirmed in his old ducks. He had found Miss Thompson a rough customer.

"Oh, well, I daresay she'll get out. I don't suppose she wants to stay here if she can't have anyone in."

"There's nowhere she can go, only a native house, and no native'll take her now, not now that the missionaries have got their knife in her."

Dr Macphail looked at the falling rain.

"Well, I don't suppose it's any good waiting for it to clear up."

In the evening when they sat in the parlour Davidson talked to them of his early days at college. He had had no means and had worked his way through by doing odd jobs during the vacations. There was silence downstairs. Miss Thompson was sitting in her little room alone. But suddenly the gramophone began to play. She had set it on in defiance, to cheat her loneliness, but there was no one to sing, and it had a melancholy note. It was like a cry for help. Davidson took no notice. He was in the middle of a long anecdote and without change of expression went on. The gramophone continued. Miss Thompson put on one reel after another. It looked as though the silence of the night were getting on her nerves. It was breathless and sultry. When the Macphails went to bed they could not sleep. They lay side by side with their eyes wide open, listening to the cruel singing of the mosquitoes outside their curtain.

"What's that?" whispered Mrs. Macphail at last.

They heard a voice, Davidson's voice, through the wooden partition. It went on with a monotonous, earnest insistence. He was praying aloud. He was praying for the soul of Miss Thompson.

Two or three days went by. Now when they passed Miss Thompson on the road she did not greet them with ironic cordiality or smile; she passed with her nose in the air, a sulky look on her painted face, frowning, as though she did not see them. The trader told Macphail that she had tried to get lodging elsewhere, but had failed. In the evening she played through the various reels of her gramophone, but the pretence of mirth was obvious now. The ragtime had a cracked, heart-broken rhythm as though it were a one-step of despair. When she began to play on Sunday Davidson sent Horn to beg her to stop at once since it was the Lord's day. The reel was taken off and the house was silent except for the steady pattering of the rain on the iron roof.

"I think she's getting a bit worked up," said the trader next day to Macphail. "She don't know what Mr. Davidson's up to and it makes her scared."

Macphail had caught a glimpse of her that morning and it struck him that her arrogant expression had changed. There was in her face a hunted look. The half-caste gave him a sidelong glance.

"I suppose you don't know what Mr. Davidson is doing about it?" he hazarded.

"No, I don't."

It was singular that Horn should ask him that question, for he also had the idea that the missionary was mysteriously at work. He had an impression that he was weaving a net around the woman, carefully, systematically, and suddenly, when everything was ready would pull the strings tight.

"He told me to tell her," said the trader, "that if at any time she wanted him she only had to send and he'd come."

"What did she say when you told her that?"

"She didn't say nothing. I didn't stop. I just said what he said I was to and then I beat it. I thought she might be going to start weepin'."

"I have no doubt the loneliness is getting on her nerves," said the doctor. "And the rain—that's enough to make anyone jumpy," he continued irritably. "Doesn't it ever stop in this confounded place?"

"It goes on pretty steady in the rainy season. We have three hundred inches in the year. You see, it's the shape of the bay. It seems to attract the rain from all over the Pacific."

"Damn the shape of the bay," said the doctor.

He scratched his mosquito bites. He felt very short-tempered. When the rain stopped and the sun shone, it was like a hothouse, seething, humid, sultry, breathless, and you had a strange feeling that everything was growing with a savage violence. The natives, blithe and childlike by reputation, seemed then, with their tattooing and their dyed hair, to have something sinister in their appearance; and when they pattered along at your heels with their naked feet you looked back instinctively. You felt they might at any moment come behind you swiftly and thrust a long knife between your shoulder blades. You could not tell what dark thoughts lurked behind their wide-set eyes. They had a little the look of ancient Egyptians painted on a temple wall, and there was about them the terror of what is immeasurably old.

The missionary came and went. He was busy, but the Macphails did not know what he was doing. Horn told the doctor that he saw the governor every day, and once Davidson mentioned him.

"He looks as if he had plenty of determination," he said, "but when you come down to brass tacks he has no backbone."

"I suppose that means he won't do exactly what you want," suggested the doctor facetiously.

The missionary did not smile.

"I want him to do what's right. It shouldn't be necessary to persuade a man to do that."

"But there may be differences of opinion about what is right."

"If a man had a gangrenous foot would you have patience with anyone who hesitated to amputate it?"

"Gangrene is a matter of fact."

"And Evil?"

What Davidson had done soon appeared. The four of them had just finished their midday meal, and they had not yet separated for the siesta which the heat imposed on the ladies and on the doctor. Davidson had little patience with the slothful habit. The door was suddenly flung open and Miss Thompson came in. She looked round the room and then went up to Davidson.

"You low-down skunk, what have you been saying about me to the governor?"

She was spluttering with rage. There was a moment's pause. Then the missionary drew forward a chair.

"Won't you be seated, Miss Thompson? I've been hoping to have another talk with you."

"You poor low-life bastard."

She burst into a torrent of insult, foul and insolent. Davidson kept his grave eyes on her.

"I'm indifferent to the abuse you think fit to heap on me, Miss Thompson," he said, "but I must beg you to remember that ladies are present."

Tears by now were struggling with her anger. Her face was red and swollen as though she were choking.

"What has happened?" asked Dr Macphail.

"A feller's just been in here and he says I gotter beat it on the next boat."

Was there a gleam in the missionary's eyes? His face remained impassive.

"You could hardly expect the governor to let you stay here under the circumstances."

"You done it," she shrieked. "You can't kid me. You done it."

"I don't want to deceive you. I urged the governor to take the only possible step consistent with his obligations."

"Why couldn't you leave me be? I wasn't doin' you no harm."

"You may be sure that if you had I should be the last man to resent it."

"Do you think I want to stay on in this poor imitation of a burg? I don't look no busher, do I?"

"In that case I don't see what cause of complaint you have," he answered.

She gave an inarticulate cry of rage and flung out of the room. There was a short silence.

"It's a relief to know that the governor has acted at last," said Davidson finally. "He's a weak man and he shilly-shallied. He said she was only here for a fortnight anyway, and if she went on to Apia that was under British jurisdiction and had nothing to do with him."

The missionary sprang to his feet and strode across the room.

"It's terrible the way the men who are in authority seek to evade their responsibility. They speak as though evil that was out of sight ceased to be evil. The very existence of that woman is a scandal and it does not help matters to shift it to another of the islands. In the end I had to speak straight from the shoulder."

Davidson's brow lowered, and he protruded his firm chin. He looked fierce and determined.

"What do you mean by that?"

"Our mission is not entirely without influence at Washington. I pointed out to the governor that it wouldn't do him any good if there was a complaint about the way he managed things here."

"When has she got to go?" asked the doctor, after a pause.

"The San Francisco boat is due here from Sydney next Tuesday. She's to sail on that."

That was in five days' time. It was next day, when he was coming back from the hospital where for want of something better to do Macphail spent most of his mornings, that the half-caste stopped him as he was going upstairs.

"Excuse me, Dr Macphail, Miss Thompson's sick. Will you have a look at her."

"Certainly."

Horn led him to her room. She was sitting in a chair idly, neither reading nor sewing, staring in front of her. She wore her white dress and the large hat with the flowers on it. Macphail noticed that her skin was yellow and muddy under her powder, and her eyes were heavy.

"I'm sorry to hear you're not well," he said.

"Oh, I ain't sick really. I just said that, because I just had to see you. I've got to clear on a boat that's going to 'Frisco'."

She looked at him and he saw that her eyes were suddenly startled. She opened and clenched her hands spasmodically. The trader stood at the door, listening.

"So I understand," said the doctor.

She gave a little gulp.

"I guess it ain't very convenient for me to go to 'Frisco' just now. I went to see the governor yesterday afternoon, but I couldn't get to him. I saw the secretary, and he told me I'd got to take that boat and that was all there was to it. I just had to see the governor, so I waited outside his house this morning, and when he come out I spoke to him. He didn't want to speak to me, I'll say, but I wouldn't let him shake me off, and at last he said he hadn't no objection to my staying here till the next boat to Sydney if the Rev. Davidson will stand for it."

She stopped and looked at Dr Macphail anxiously.

"I don't know exactly what I can do," he said.

"Well, I thought maybe you wouldn't mind asking him. I swear to God I won't start anything here if he'll just only let me stay. I won't go out of the house if that'll suit him. It's no more'n a fortnight."

"I'll ask him."

"He won't stand for it," said Horn. "He'll have you out on Tuesday, so you may as well make up your mind to it."

"Tell him I can get work in Sydney, straight stuff, I mean. 'Tain't asking very much."

"I'll do what I can."

"And come and tell me right away, will you? I can't set down to a thing till I get the dope one way or the other."

It was not an errand that much pleased the doctor, and, characteristically perhaps, he went about it indirectly. He told his wife what Miss Thompson had said to him and asked her to speak to Mrs. Davidson. The missionary's attitude seemed rather arbitrary and it could do no harm if the girl were allowed to stay in Pago-Pago another fortnight. But he was not prepared for the result of his diplomacy. The missionary came to him straightway.

"Mrs. Davidson tells me that Thompson has been speaking to you."

Dr Macphail, thus directly tackled, had the shy man's resentment at being forced out into the open. He felt his temper rising, and he flushed.

"I don't see that it can make any difference if she goes to Sydney rather than to San Francisco, and so long as she promises to behave while she's here it's dashed hard to persecute her."

The missionary fixed him with his stern eyes.

"Why is she unwilling to go back to San Francisco?"

"I didn't enquire," answered the doctor with some asperity. "And I think one does better to mind one's own business."

Perhaps it was not a very tactful answer.

"The governor has ordered her to be deported by the first boat that leaves the island. He's only done his duty and I will not interfere. Her presence is a peril here."

"I think you're very harsh and tyrannical."

The two ladies looked up at the doctor with some alarm, but they need not have feared a quarrel, for the missionary smiled gently.

"I'm terribly sorry you should think that of me, Dr Macphail. Believe me, my heart bleeds for that unfortunate woman, but I'm only trying to do my duty."

The doctor made no answer. He looked out of the window sullenly. For once it was not raining and across the bay you saw nestling among the trees the huts of a native village.

"I think I'll take advantage of the rain stopping to go out," he said.

"Please don't bear me malice because I can't accede to your wish," said Davidson, with a melancholy smile. "I respect you very much, doctor, and I should be sorry if you thought ill of me."

"I have no doubt you have a sufficiently good opinion of yourself to bear mine with equanimity," he retorted.

"That's one on me," chuckled Davidson.

When Dr Macphail, vexed with himself because he had been uncivil to no purpose, went downstairs, Miss Thompson was waiting for him with her door ajar.

"Well," she said, "have you spoken to him?"

"Yes, I'm sorry, he won't do anything," he answered, not looking at her in his embarrassment.

But then he gave her a quick glance, for a sob broke from her. He saw that her face was white with fear. It gave him a shock of dismay. And suddenly he had an idea.

"But don't give up hope yet. I think it's a shame the way they're treating you and I'm going to see the governor myself."

"Now?"

He nodded. Her face brightened.

"Say, that's real good of you. I'm sure he'll let me stay if you speak for me. I just won't do a thing I didn't ought all the time I'm here."

Dr Macphail hardly knew why he had made up his mind to appeal to the governor. He was perfectly indifferent to Miss Thompson's affairs, but the missionary had irritated him, and with him temper was a smouldering thing. He found the governor at home. He was a large, handsome man, a sailor, with a grey toothbrush moustache; and he wore a spotless uniform of white drill.

"I've come to see you about a woman who's lodging in the same house as we are," he said. "Her name's Thompson."

"I guess I've heard nearly enough about her, Dr Macphail," said the governor, smiling. "I've given her the order to get out next Tuesday and that's all I can do."

"I wanted to ask you if you couldn't stretch a point and let her stay here till the boat comes in from San Francisco so that she can go to Sydney. I will guarantee her good behaviour."

The governor continued to smile, but his eyes grew small and serious.

"I'd be very glad to oblige you, Dr Macphail, but I've given the order and it must stand."

The doctor put the case as reasonably as he could, but now the governor ceased to smile at all. He listened sullenly, with averted gaze. Macphail saw that he was making no impression.

"I'm sorry to cause any lady inconvenience, but she'll have to sail on Tuesday and that's all there is to it."

"But what difference can it make?"

"Pardon me, doctor, but I don't feel called upon to explain my official actions except to the proper authorities."

Macphail looked at him shrewdly. He remembered Davidson's hint that he had used threats, and in the governor's attitude he read a singular embarrassment.

"Davidson's a damned busybody," he said hotly.

"Between ourselves, Dr Macphail, I don't say that I have formed a very favourable opinion of Mr. Davidson, but I am bound to confess that he was within his rights in pointing out to me the danger that the presence of a woman of Miss Thompson's character was to a place like this where a number of enlisted men are stationed among a native population."

He got up and Dr Macphail was obliged to do so too.

"I must ask you to excuse me. I have an engagement. Please give my respects to Mrs. Macphail."

The doctor left him crest-fallen. He knew that Miss Thompson would be waiting for him, and unwilling to tell her himself that he had failed, he went into the house by the back door and sneaked up the stairs as though he had something to hide.

At supper he was silent and ill-at-ease, but the missionary was jovial and animated. Dr Macphail thought his eyes rested on him now and then with triumphant good-humour. It struck him suddenly that Davidson knew of his visit to the governor and of its ill success. But how on earth could he have heard of it? There was something sinister about the power of that man. After supper he saw Horn on the verandah and, as though to have a casual word with him, went out.

"She wants to know if you've seen the governor," the trader whispered.

"Yes. He wouldn't do anything. I'm awfully sorry, I can't do anything more."

"I knew he wouldn't. They daren't go against the missionaries."

"What are you talking about?" said Davidson affably, coming out to join them.

"I was just saying there was no chance of your getting over to Apia for at least another week," said the trader glibly.

He left them, and the two men returned into the parlour. Mr. Davidson devoted one hour after each meal to recreation. Presently a timid knock was heard at the door.

"Come in," said Mrs. Davidson, in her sharp voice.

The door was not opened. She got up and opened it. They saw Miss Thompson standing at the threshold. But the change in her appearance was extraordinary. This was no longer the flaunting hussy who had jeered at them in the road, but a broken, frightened woman. Her hair, as a rule so elaborately arranged, was tumbling untidily over her neck. She wore bedroom slippers and a skirt and blouse. They were unfresh and bedraggled. She stood at the door with the tears streaming down her face and did not dare to enter.

"What do you want?" said Mrs. Davidson harshly.

"May I speak to Mr. Davidson?" she said in a choking voice.

The missionary rose and went towards her.

"Come right in, Miss Thompson," he said in cordial tones. "What can I do for you?"

She entered the room.

"Say, I'm sorry for what I said to you the other day an' for—for everythin' else. I guess I was a bit lit up. I beg pardon."

"Oh, it was nothing. I guess my back's broad enough to bear a few hard words."

She stepped towards him with a movement that was horribly cringing.

"You've got me beat. I'm all in. You won't make me go back to 'Frisco'?"

His genial manner vanished and his voice grew on a sudden hard and stern.

"Why don't you want to go back there?"

She cowered before him.

"I guess my people live there. I don't want them to see me like this. I'll go anywhere else you say."

"Why don't you want to go back to San Francisco?"

"I've told you."

He leaned forward, staring at her, and his great, shining eyes seemed to try to bore into her soul. He gave a sudden gasp.

"The penitentiary."

She screamed, and then she fell at his feet, clasping his legs.

"Don't send me back there. I swear to you before God I'll be a good woman. I'll give all this up."

She burst into a torrent of confused supplication and the tears coursed down her painted cheeks. He leaned over her and, lifting her face, forced her to look at him.

"Is that it, the penitentiary?"

"I beat it before they could get me," she gasped. "If the bulls grab me it's three years for mine."

He let go his hold of her and she fell in a heap on the floor, sobbing bitterly. Dr Macphail stood up.

"This alters the whole thing," he said. "You can't make her go back when you know this. Give her another chance. She wants to turn over a new leaf."

"I'm going to give her the finest chance she's ever had. If she repents let her accept her punishment."

She misunderstood the words and looked up. There was a gleam of hope in her heavy eyes.

"You'll let me go?"

"No. You shall sail for San Francisco on Tuesday."

She gave a groan of horror and then burst into low, hoarse shrieks which sounded hardly human, and she beat her head passionately on the ground. Dr Macphail sprang to her and lifted her up.

"Come on, you mustn't do that. You'd better go to your room and lie down. I'll get you something."

He raised her to her feet and partly dragging her, partly carrying her, got her downstairs. He was furious with Mrs. Davidson and with his wife because they made no effort to help. The half-caste was standing on the landing and with his assistance he managed to get her on the bed. She was moaning and crying. She was almost insensible. He gave her a hypodermic injection. He was hot and exhausted when he went upstairs again.

"I've got her to lie down."

The two women and Davidson were in the same positions as when he had left them. They could not have moved or spoken since he went.

"I was waiting for you," said Davidson, in a strange, distant voice. "I want you all to pray with me for the soul of our erring sister."

He took the Bible off a shelf, and sat down at the table at which they had supped. It had not been cleared, and he pushed the tea-pot out of the way. In a powerful voice, resonant and deep, he read to them the chapter in which is narrated the meeting of Jesus Christ with the woman taken in adultery.

"Now kneel with me and let us pray for the soul of our dear sister, Sadie Thompson."

He burst into a long, passionate prayer in which he implored God to have mercy on the sinful woman. Mrs. Macphail and Mrs. Davidson knelt with covered eyes. The doctor, taken by surprise, awkward and sheepish, knelt too. The missionary's prayer had a savage eloquence. He was extraordinarily moved, and as he spoke the tears ran down his cheeks. Outside, the pitiless rain fell, fell steadily, with a fierce malignity that was all too human.

At last he stopped. He paused for a moment and said:

"We will now repeat the Lord's prayer."

They said it and then; following him, they rose from their knees. Mrs. Davidson's face was pale and restful. She was comforted and at peace, but the Macphails felt suddenly bashful. They did not know which way to look.

"I'll just go down and see how she is now," said Dr Macphail.

When he knocked at her door it was opened for him by Horn. Miss Thompson was in a rocking-chair, sobbing quietly.

"What are you doing there?" exclaimed Macphail. "I told you to lie down."

"I can't lie down. I want to see Mr. Davidson."

"My poor child, what do you think is the good of it? You'll never move him."

"He said he'd come if I sent for him."

Macphail motioned to the trader.

"Go and fetch him."

He waited with her in silence while the trader went upstairs. Davidson came in.

"Excuse me for asking you to come here," she said, looking at him sombrely.

"I was expecting you to send for me. I knew the Lord would answer my prayer."

They stared at one another for a moment and then she looked away. She kept her eyes averted when she spoke.

"I've been a bad woman. I want to repent."

"Thank God! thank God! He has heard our prayers."

He turned to the two men.

"Leave me alone with her. Tell Mrs. Davidson that our prayers have been answered."

They went out and closed the door behind them.

"Gee whizz," said the trader.

That night Dr Macphail could not get to sleep till late, and when he heard the missionary come upstairs he looked at his watch. It was two o'clock. But even then he did not go to bed at once, for through the wooden partition that separated their rooms he heard him praying aloud, till he himself, exhausted, fell asleep.

When he saw him next morning he was surprised at his appearance. He was paler than ever, tired, but his eyes shone with an inhuman fire. It looked as though he were filled with an overwhelming joy.

"I want you to go down presently and see Sadie," he said. "I can't hope that her body is better, but her soul—her soul is transformed."

The doctor was feeling wan and nervous.

"You were with her very late last night," he said.

"Yes, she couldn't bear to have me leave her."

"You look as pleased as Punch," the doctor said irritably.

Davidson's eyes shone with ecstasy.

"A great mercy has been vouchsafed me. Last night I was privileged to bring a lost soul to the loving arms of Jesus."

Miss Thompson was again in the rocking-chair. The bed had not been made. The room was in disorder. She had not troubled to dress herself, but wore a dirty dressing-gown, and her hair was tied in a sluttish knot. She had given her face a dab with a wet towel, but it was all swollen and creased with crying. She looked a drab.

She raised her eyes dully when the doctor came in. She was cowed and broken.

"Where's Mr. Davidson?" she asked.

"He'll come presently if you want him," answered Macphail acidly. "I came here to see how you were."

"Oh, I guess I'm ok. You needn't worry about that."

"Have you had anything to eat?"

"Horn brought me some coffee."

She looked anxiously at the door.

"D'you think he'll come down soon? I feel as if it wasn't so terrible when he's with me."

"Are you still going on Tuesday?"

"Yes, he says I've got to go. Please tell him to come right along. You can't do me any good. He's the only one as can help me now."

"Very well," said Dr Macphail.

During the next three days the missionary spent almost all his time with Sadie Thompson. He joined the others only to have his meals. Dr Macphail noticed that he hardly ate.

"He's wearing himself out," said Mrs. Davidson pitifully. "He'll have a breakdown if he doesn't take care, but he won't spare himself."

She herself was white and pale. She told Mrs. Macphail that she had no sleep. When the missionary came upstairs from Miss Thompson he prayed till he was exhausted, but even then he did not sleep for long. After an hour or two he got up and dressed himself, and went for a tramp along the bay. He had strange dreams.

"This morning he told me that he'd been dreaming about the mountains of Nebraska," said Mrs. Davidson.

"That's curious," said Dr Macphail.

He remembered seeing them from the windows of the train when he crossed America. They were like huge mole-hills, rounded and smooth, and they rose from the plain abruptly. Dr Macphail remembered how it struck him that they were like a woman's breasts.

Davidson's restlessness was intolerable even to himself. But he was buoyed up by a wonderful exhilaration. He was tearing out by the roots the last vestiges of sin that lurked in the hidden corners of that poor woman's heart. He read with her and prayed with her.

"It's wonderful," he said to them one day at supper. "It's a true rebirth. Her soul, which was black as night, is now pure and white like the new-fallen snow. I am humble and afraid. Her remorse for all her sins is beautiful. I am not worthy to touch the hem of her garment."

"Have you the heart to send her back to San Francisco?" said the doctor. "Three years in an American prison. I should have thought you might have saved her from that."

"Ah, but don't you see? It's necessary. Do you think my heart doesn't bleed for her? I love her as I love my wife and my sister. All the time that she is in prison I shall suffer all the pain that she suffers."

"Bunkum," cried the doctor impatiently.

"You don't understand because you're blind. She's sinned, and she must suffer. I know what she'll endure. She'll be starved and tortured and humiliated. I want her to accept the punishment of man as a sacrifice to God. I want her to accept it joyfully. She has an opportunity which is offered to very few of us. God is very good and very merciful."

Davidson's voice trembled with excitement. He could hardly articulate the words that tumbled passionately from his lips.

"All day I pray with her and when I leave her I pray again, I pray with all my might and main, so that Jesus may grant her this great mercy. I want to put in her heart the passionate desire to be punished so that at the end, even if I offered to let her go, she would refuse. I want her to feel that the bitter punishment of prison is the thank-offering that she places at the feet of our Blessed Lord, who gave his life for her."

The days passed slowly. The whole household, intent on the wretched, tortured woman downstairs, lived in a state of unnatural excitement. She was like a victim that was being prepared for the savage rites of a bloody idolatry. Her terror numbed her. She could not bear to let Davidson out of her sight; it was only when he was with her that she had courage, and she hung upon him with a slavish dependence. She cried a great deal, and she read the Bible, and prayed. Sometimes she was exhausted and apathetic. Then she did indeed look forward to her ordeal, for it seemed to offer an escape, direct and concrete, from the anguish she was enduring. She could not bear much longer the vague terrors which now assailed her. With her sins she had put aside all personal vanity, and she slopped about her room, unkempt and dishevelled, in her tawdry dressing-gown. She had not taken off her night-dress for four days, nor put on stockings. Her room was littered and untidy. Meanwhile the rain fell with a cruel persistence. You felt that the heavens must at last be empty of water, but still it poured down, straight and heavy, with a maddening iteration, on the iron roof. Everything was damp and clammy. There was mildew on the walls and on the boots that stood on the floor. Through the sleepless nights the mosquitoes droned their angry chant.

"If it would only stop raining for a single day it wouldn't be so bad," said Dr Macphail.

They all looked forward to the Tuesday when the boat for San Francisco was to arrive from Sydney. The strain was intolerable. So far as Dr Macphail was concerned, his pity and his resentment were alike extinguished by his desire to be rid of the unfortunate woman. The inevitable must be accepted. He felt he would breathe more freely when the ship had sailed. Sadie Thompson was to be escorted on board by a clerk in the governor's office. This person called on the Monday evening and told Miss Thompson to be prepared at eleven in the morning. Davidson was with her.

"I'll see that everything is ready. I mean to come on board with her myself."

Miss Thompson did not speak.

When Dr Macphail blew out his candle and crawled cautiously under his mosquito curtains, he gave a sigh of relief.

"Well, thank God that's over. By this time to-morrow she'll be gone."

"Mrs. Davidson will be glad too. She says he's wearing himself to a shadow," said Mrs. Macphail. "She's a different woman."

"Who?"

"Sadie. I should never have thought it possible. It makes one humble."

Dr Macphail did not answer, and presently he fell asleep. He was tired out, and he slept more soundly than usual.

He was awakened in the morning by a hand placed on his arm, and, starting up, saw Horn by the side of his bed. The trader put his finger on his mouth to prevent any exclamation from Dr Macphail and beckoned to him to come. As a rule he wore shabby ducks, but now he was barefoot and wore only the lava-lava of the natives. He looked suddenly savage, and Dr Macphail, getting out of bed, saw that he was heavily tattooed. Horn made him a sign to come on to the verandah. Dr Macphail got out of bed and followed the trader out.

"Don't make a noise," he whispered. "You're wanted. Put on a coat and some shoes. Quick."

Dr Macphail's first thought was that something had happened to Miss Thompson.

"What is it? Shall I bring my instruments?"

"Hurry, please, hurry."

Dr Macphail crept back into the bedroom, put on a waterproof over his pyjamas, and a pair of rubber-soled shoes. He rejoined the trader, and together they tiptoed down the stairs. The door leading out to the road was open and at it were standing half a dozen natives.

"What is it?" repeated the doctor.

"Come along with me," said Horn.

He walked out and the doctor followed him. The natives came after them in a little bunch. They crossed the road and came on to the beach. The doctor saw a group of natives standing round some object at the water's edge. They hurried along, a couple of dozen yards perhaps, and the natives opened out as the doctor came up. The trader pushed him forwards. Then he saw, lying half in the water and half out, a dreadful object, the body of Davidson. Dr Macphail bent down—he was not a man to lose his head in an emergency—and turned the body over. The throat was cut from ear to ear, and in the right hand was still the razor with which the deed was done.

"He's quite cold," said the doctor. "He must have been dead some time."

"One of the boys saw him lying there on his way to work just now and came and told me. Do you think he did it himself?"

"Yes. Someone ought to go for the police."

Horn said something in the native tongue, and two youths started off.

"We must leave him here till they come," said the doctor.

"They mustn't take him into my house. I won't have him in my house."

"You'll do what the authorities say," replied the doctor sharply. "In point of fact I expect they'll take him to the mortuary."

They stood waiting where they were. The trader took a cigarette from a fold in his lava-lava and gave one to Dr Macphail. They smoked while they stared at the corpse. Dr Macphail could not understand.

"Why do you think he did it?" asked Horn.

The doctor shrugged his shoulders. In a little while native police came along, under the charge of a marine, with a stretcher, and immediately afterwards a couple of naval officers and a naval doctor. They managed everything in a businesslike manner.

"What about the wife?" said one of the officers.

"Now that you've come I'll go back to the house and get some things on. I'll see that it's broken to her. She'd better not see him till he's been fixed up a little."

"I guess that's right," said the naval doctor.

When Dr Macphail went back he found his wife nearly dressed.

"Mrs. Davidson's in a dreadful state about her husband," she said to him as soon as he appeared. "He hasn't been to bed all night. She heard him leave Miss Thompson's room at two, but he went out. If he's been walking about since then he'll be absolutely dead."

Dr Macphail told her what had happened and asked her to break the news to Mrs. Davidson.

"But why did he do it?" she asked, horror-stricken.

"I don't know."

"But I can't. I can't."

"You must."

She gave him a frightened look and went out. He heard her go into Mrs. Davidson's room. He waited a minute to gather himself together and then began to shave and wash. When he was dressed he sat down on the bed and waited for his wife. At last she came.

"She wants to see him," she said.

"They've taken him to the mortuary. We'd better go down with her. How did she take it?"

"I think she's stunned. She didn't cry. But she's trembling like a leaf."

"We'd better go at once."

When they knocked at her door Mrs. Davidson came out. She was very pale, but dry-eyed. To the doctor she seemed unnaturally composed. No word was exchanged, and they set out in silence down the road. When they arrived at the mortuary Mrs. Davidson spoke.

"Let me go in and see him alone."

They stood aside. A native opened a door for her and closed it behind her. They sat down and waited. One or two white men came and talked to them in undertones. Dr Macphail told them again what he knew of the tragedy. At last the door was quietly opened and Mrs. Davidson came out. Silence fell upon them.

"I'm ready to go back now," she said.

Her voice was hard and steady. Dr Macphail could not understand the look in her eyes. Her pale face was very stern. They walked back slowly, never saying a word, and at last they came round the bend on the other side of which stood their house. Mrs. Davidson gave a gasp, and for a moment they stopped still. An incredible sound assaulted their ears. The gramophone which had been silent for so long was playing, playing ragtime loud and harsh.

"What's that?" cried Mrs. Macphail with horror.

"Let's go on," said Mrs. Davidson.

They walked up the steps and entered the hall. Miss Thompson was standing at her door, chatting with a sailor. A sudden change had taken place in her. She was no longer the cowed drudge of the last days. She was dressed in all her finery, in her white dress, with the high shiny boots over which her fat legs bulged in their cotton stockings; her hair was elaborately arranged; and she wore that enormous hat covered with gaudy flowers. Her face was painted, her eyebrows were boldly black, and her lips were scarlet. She held herself erect. She was the flaunting quean that they had known at first. As they came in she broke into a loud, jeering laugh; and then, when Mrs. Davidson involuntarily stopped, she collected the spittle in her mouth and spat. Mrs. Davidson cowered back, and two red spots rose suddenly to her cheeks. Then, covering her face with her hands, she broke away and ran quickly up the stairs. Dr Macphail was outraged. He pushed past the woman into her room.

"What the devil are you doing?" he cried. "Stop that damned machine."

He went up to it and tore the record off. She turned on him.

"Say, doc, you can that stuff with me. What the hell are you doin' in my room?"

"What do you mean?" he cried. "What d'you mean?"

She gathered herself together. No one could describe the scorn of her expression or the contemptuous hatred she put into her answer.

"You men! You filthy, dirty pigs! You're all the same, all of you. Pigs! Pigs!"

Dr Macphail gasped. He understood.

Virtue

There are few things better than a good Havana. When I was young and very poor and smoked a cigar only when somebody gave me one, I determined that if ever I had money I would smoke a cigar every day after luncheon and after dinner. This is the only resolution of my youth that I have kept. It is the only ambition I have achieved that has never been embittered by disillusion. I like a cigar that is mild, but full-flavoured, neither so small that it is finished before you have become aware of it nor so large as to be irksome, rolled so that it draws without consciousness of effort on your part, with a leaf so firm that it doesn't become messy on your lips, and in such condition that it keeps its savour to the very end. But when you have taken the last pull and put down the shapeless stump and watched the final cloud of smoke dwindle blue in the surrounding air it is impossible, if you have a sensitive nature, not to feel a certain melancholy at the thought of all the labour, the care and pains that have gone, the thought, the trouble, the complicated organization that have been required to provide you with half an hour's delight. For this men have sweltered long years under tropical suns and ships have scoured the seven seas. These reflections become more poignant still when you are eating a dozen oysters (with half a bottle of dry white wine), and they become almost unbearable when it comes to a lamb cutlet. For these are animals and there is something that inspires awe in the thought that since the surface of the earth became capable of supporting life from generation to generation for millions upon millions of years creatures have come into existence to end at last upon a plate of crushed ice or on a silver grill. It may be that a sluggish fancy cannot grasp the dreadful solemnity of eating an oyster and evolution has taught us that the bivalve has through the ages kept itself to itself in a manner that inevitably alienates sympathy. There is an aloofness in it that is offensive to the aspiring spirit of man and a self-complacency that is obnoxious to his vanity. But I do not know how anyone can look upon a lamb cutlet without thoughts too deep for tears: here man himself has taken a hand and the history of the race is bound up with the tender morsel on your plate.

And sometimes even the fate of human beings is curious to consider. It is strange to look upon this man or that, the quiet ordinary persons of every day, the bank clerk, the dustman, the middle-aged girl in the second row of the chorus, and think of the interminable history behind them and of the long, long series of hazards by which from the primeval slime the course of events has brought them at this moment to such and such a place. When such tremendous vicissitudes have been needed to get them here at all one would have thought some huge significance must be attached to them; one would have thought that what befell them must matter a little to the Life Spirit or whatever else it is that has produced them. An accident befalls them. The thread is broken. The story that began with the world is finished abruptly and it looks as though it meant nothing at all. A tale told by an idiot. And is it not odd that this event, of an importance so dramatic, may be brought about by a cause so trivial?

An incident of no moment, that might easily not have happened, has consequences that are incalculable. It looks as though blind chance ruled all things. Our smallest actions may affect profoundly the whole lives of people who have nothing to do with us. The story I have to tell would never have happened if one day I had not walked across the street. Life is really very fantastic and one has to have a peculiar sense of humour to see the fun of it.

I was strolling down Bond Street one spring morning and having nothing much to do till lunch-time thought I would look in at Sotheby's, the auction rooms, to see whether there was anything on show that interested me. There was a block in the traffic and I threaded my way through the cars. When I reached the other side I ran into a man I had known in Borneo coming out of a hatter's.

"Hullo, Morton," I said. "When did you come home?"

"I've been back about a week."

He was a District Officer. The Governor had given me a letter of introduction to him and I wrote and told him I meant to spend a week at the place he lived at and should like to put up at the government rest-house. He met me on the ship when I arrived and asked me to stay with him. I demurred. I did not see how I could spend a week with a total stranger, I did not want to put him to the expense of my board, and besides I thought I should have more freedom if I were on my own. He would not listen to me.

"I've got plenty of room," he said, "and the rest-house is beastly. I haven't spoken to a white man for six months and I'm fed to the teeth with my own company."

But when Morton had got me and his launch had landed us at the bungalow and he had offered me a drink he did not in the least know what to do with me. He was seized on a sudden with shyness, and his conversation, which had been fluent and ready, ran dry. I did my best to make him feel at home (it was the least I could do, considering that it was his own house) and asked him if he had any new records. He turned on the gramophone and the sound of rag-time gave him confidence.

His bungalow overlooked the river and his living-room was a large veranda. It was furnished in the impersonal fashion that characterized the dwellings of government officials who were moved here and there at little notice according to the exigencies of the service. There were native hats as ornaments on the walls and the horns of animals, blow-pipes, and spears. In the book-shelf were detective novels and old magazines. There was a cottage piano with yellow keys. It was very untidy, but not uncomfortable.

Unfortunately I cannot very well remember what he looked like. He was young, twenty-eight, I learnt later, and he had a boyish and attractive smile. I spent an agreeable week with him. We went up and down the river and we climbed a mountain. We had tiffin one day with some planters who lived twenty miles away and every evening we went to the club. The only members were the manager of a kutch factory and his assistants, but they were not on speaking terms with one another and it was only on Morton's representations that they must not let him down when he had a visitor that we could get up a rubber of bridge. The atmosphere was strained. We came back to dinner, listened to the gramophone, and went to bed. Morton had little office work and one would have thought the time hung heavy on his hands, but he had energy and high spirits; it was his first post of the sort and he was happy to be independent. His only anxiety was lest he should be transferred before he had finished a road he was building. This was the joy of his heart. It was his own idea and he had wheedled the government into giving him the money to make it; he had surveyed the country himself and traced the path. He had solved unaided the technical problems that presented themselves. Every morning, before he went to his office, he drove out in a rickety old Ford to where the coolies were working and watched the progress that had been made since the day before. He thought of nothing else. He dreamt of it at night. He reckoned that it would be finished in a year and he did not want to take his leave till then. He could not have worked with more zest if he had been a painter or a sculptor creating a work of art. I think it was this eagerness that made me take a fancy to him. I liked his zeal. I liked his ingenuousness. And I was impressed by the passion for achievement that made him indifferent to the solitariness of his life, to promotion, and even to the thought of going home. I forget how long the road was, fifteen or twenty miles, I think, and I forget what purpose it was to serve. I don't believe Morton cared very much. His passion was the artist's and his triumph was the triumph of man over nature. He learnt as he went along. He had the jungle to contend against, torrential rains that destroyed the labour of weeks, accidents of topography; he had to collect his labour and hold it together; he had inadequate funds. His imagination sustained him. His labours gained a sort of epic quality and the vicissitudes of the work were a great saga that unrolled itself with an infinity of episodes.

His only complaint was that the day was too short. He had office duties, he was judge and tax collector, father and mother (at twenty-eight) of the people in his district; he had now and then to make tours that took him away from home. Unless he was on the spot nothing was done. He would have liked to be there twenty-four hours a day driving the reluctant coolies to further effort. It so happened that shortly before I arrived an incident had occurred that filled him with jubilation. He had offered a contract to a Chinese to make a certain section of the road and the Chinese had asked more than Morton could afford to pay. Notwithstanding interminable discussions they had been unable to arrive at an agreement and Morton with rage in his heart saw his work held up. He was at his wits' end. Then going down to his office one morning, he heard that there had been a row in one of the Chinese gambling houses the night before. A coolie had been badly wounded and his assailant was under arrest. This assailant was the contractor. He was brought into court, the evidence was clear, and Morton sentenced him to eighteen months' hard labour.

"Now he'll have to build the blasted road for nothing," said Morton, his eyes glistening when he told me the story.

We saw the fellow at work one morning, in the prison sarong, unconcerned. He was taking his misfortune in good part.

"I've told him I'll remit the rest of his sentence when the road's finished," said Morton, "and he's as pleased as Punch. Bit of a snip for me, eh, what?"

When I left Morton I asked him to let me know when he came to England and he promised to write to me as soon as he landed. On the spur of the moment one gives these invitations and one is perfectly sincere about them. But when one is taken at one's word a slight dismay seizes one. People are so different at home from what they are abroad. There they are easy, cordial, and natural. They have interesting things to tell you. They are immensely kind. You are anxious when your turn comes to do something in return for the hospitality you have received. But it is not easy. The persons who were so entertaining in their own surroundings are very dull in yours. They are constrained and shy. You introduce them to your friends and your friends find them a crashing bore. They do their best to be civil, but sigh with relief when the strangers go and the conversation can once more run easily in its accustomed channels. I think the residents in far places early in their careers understand the situation pretty well, as the result maybe of bitter and humiliating experiences, for I have found that they seldom take advantage of the invitation which on some outstation on the edge of the jungle has been so cordially extended to them and by them as cordially accepted. But Morton was different. He was a young man and single. It is generally the wives that are the difficulty; other women look at their drab clothes, in a glance take in their provincial air, and freeze them with their indifference. But a man can play bridge and tennis, and dance. Morton had charm. I had had no doubt that in a day or two he would find his feet.

"Why didn't you let me know you were back?" I asked him.

"I thought you wouldn't want to be bothered with me," he smiled.

"What nonsense!"

Of course now as we stood in Bond Street on the kerb and chatted for a minute he looked strange to me. I had never seen him in anything but khaki shorts and a tennis shirt, except when we got back from the club at night and he put on a pyjama jacket and a sarong for dinner. It is as comfortable a form of evening dress as has ever been devised. He looked a bit awkward in his blue serge suit. His face against a white collar was very brown.

"How about the road?" I asked him.

"Finished. I was afraid I'd have to postpone my leave, we struck one or two snags towards the end, but I made 'em hustle and the day before I left I drove the Ford to the end and back without stopping."

I laughed. His pleasure was charming.

"What have you been doing with yourself in London?"

"Buying clothes."

"Been having a good time?"

"Marvellous. A bit lonely, you know, but I don't mind that. I've been to a show every night. The Palmers, you know, I think you met them in Sarawak, were going to be in town and we were going to do the play together, but they had to go to Scotland because her mother's ill."

His words, said so breezily, cut me to the quick. His was the common experience. It was heartbreaking. For months, for long months before it was due, these people planned their leave, and when they got off the ship they were in such spirits they could hardly contain themselves. London. Shops and clubs and theatres and restaurants. London. They were going to have the time of their lives. London. It swallowed them. A strange turbulent city, not hostile but indifferent, and they were lost in it. They had no friends. They had nothing in common with the acquaintances they made. They were more lonely than in the jungle. It was a relief when at a theatre they ran across someone they had known in the East (and perhaps been bored stiff by or disliked) and they could fix up an evening together and have a good laugh and tell one another what a grand time they were having and talk of common friends and at last confide to one another a little shyly that they would not be sorry when their leave was up and they were once again in harness. They went to see their families and of course they were glad to see them, but it wasn't the same as it had been, they did feel a bit out of it, and when you came down to brass tacks the life people led in England was deadly. It was grand fun to come home, but you couldn't live there any more, and sometimes you thought of your bungalow overlooking the river and your tours of the district and what a lark it was to run over once in a blue moon to Sandakan or Kuching or Singapore.

And because I remembered what Morton had looked forward to when, the road finished and off his chest, he went on leave, I could not but feel a pang when I thought of him dining by himself in a dismal club where he knew nobody or alone in a restaurant in Soho and then going off to see a play with no one by his side with whom he could enjoy it and no one to have a drink with during the interval. And at the same time I reflected that even if I had known he was in London I could have done nothing much for him, for during the last week I had not had a moment free. That very evening I was dining with friends and going to a play, and the next day I was going abroad.

"What are you doing tonight?" I asked him.

"I'm going to the Pavilion. It's packed jammed full, but there's a fellow over the road who's wonderful and he's got me a ticket that had been returned. You can often get one seat, you know, when you can't get two."

"Why don't you come and have supper with me? I'm taking some people to the Haymarket and we're going on to Ciro's afterwards."

"I'd love to."

We arranged to meet at eleven and I left him to keep an engagement.

I was afraid the friends I had asked him to meet would not amuse Morton very much, for they were distinctly middle-aged, but I could not think of anyone young that at this season of the year I should be likely to get hold of at the last moment. None of the girls I knew would thank me for asking her to supper to dance with a shy young man from Malaya. I could trust the Bishops to do their best for him, and after all it must be jollier for him to have supper in a club with a good band where he could see pretty women dancing than to go home to bed at eleven because he had nowhere else in the world to go. I had known Charlie Bishop first when I was a medical student. He was then a thin fellow with sandy hair and blunt features; he had fine eyes, dark and gleaming, but he wore spectacles. He had a round, merry, red face. He was very fond of the girls. I suppose he had a way with him, for, with no money and no looks, he managed to pick up a succession of young persons who gratified his roving desires. He was clever and bumptious, argumentative and quick-tempered. He had a caustic tongue. Looking back, I should say he was a rather disagreeable young man, but I do not think he was a bore. Now, half-way through the fifties, he was inclined to be stout and he was very bald, but his eyes behind the gold-rimmed spectacles were still bright and alert. He was dogmatic and somewhat conceited, argumentative still and caustic, but he was good-natured and amusing. After you have known a person so long his idiosyncrasies cease to trouble you. You accept them as you accept your own physical defects. He was by profession a pathologist and now and then he sent me a slim book he had just published. It was severe and extremely technical and grimly illustrated with photographs of bacteria. I did not read it. I gathered from what I sometimes heard that Charlie's views on the subjects with which he dealt were unsound. I do not believe that he was very popular with the other members of his profession, he made no secret of the fact that he looked upon them as a set of incompetent idiots; but he had his job, it brought him in six or eight hundred a year, I think, and he was completely indifferent to other people's opinion of him.

I liked Charlie Bishop because I had known him for thirty years, but I liked Margery, his wife, because she was very nice. I was extremely surprised when he told me he was going to be married. He was hard on forty at the time and so fickle in his affections that I had made up my mind he would remain single. He was very fond of women, but he was not in the least sentimental, and his aims were loose. His views on the female sex would in these idealistic days be thought crude. He knew what he wanted and he asked for it, and if he couldn't get it for love or money he shrugged his shoulders and went his way. To be brief, he did not look to women to gratify his ideal but to provide him with fornication. It was odd that though small and plain he found so many who were prepared to grant his wishes. For his spiritual needs he found satisfaction in unicellular organisms. He had always been a man who spoke to the point, and when he told me he was going to marry a young woman called Margery Hobson I did not hesitate to ask him why. He grinned.

"Three reasons. First, she won't let me go to bed with her without. Second, she makes me laugh like a hyena. And third, she's alone in the world, without a single relation, and she must have someone to take care of her."

"The first reason is just swank and the second is eyewash. The third is the real one and it means that she's got you by the short hairs."

His eyes gleamed softly behind his large spectacles.

"I shouldn't be surprised if you weren't dead right."

"She's not only got you by the short hairs but you're as pleased as Punch that she has."

"Come and lunch tomorrow and have a look at her. She's easy on the eye."

Charlie was a member of a cock-and-hen club which at that time I used a good deal and we arranged to lunch there. I found Margery a very attractive young woman. She was then just under thirty. She was a lady. I noticed the fact with satisfaction, but with a certain astonishment, for it had not escaped my notice that Charlie was attracted as a rule by women whose breeding left something to be desired. She was not beautiful, but comely, with fine dark hair and fine eyes, a good colour and a look of health. She had a pleasant frankness and an air of candour that were very taking. She looked honest, simple, and dependable. I took an immediate liking to her. She was easy to talk to and though she did not say anything very brilliant she understood what other people were talking about; she was quick to see a joke and she was not shy. She gave you the impression of being competent and business-like. She had a happy placidity that suggested a good temper and an excellent digestion.

They seemed extremely pleased with one another. I had asked myself when I first saw her why Margery was marrying this irritable little man, baldish already and by no means young, but I discovered very soon that it was because she was in love with him. They chaffed one another a good deal and laughed a lot and every now and then their eyes met more significantly and they seemed to exchange a little private message. It was really rather touching.

A week later they were married at a registrar's office. It was a very successful marriage. Looking back now after sixteen years I could not but chuckle sympathetically at the thought of the lark they had made of their life together. I had never known a more devoted couple. They had never had very much money. They never seemed to want any. They had no ambitions. Their life was a picnic that never came to an end. They lived in the smallest flat I ever saw, in Panton Street, a small bedroom, a small sitting-room, and a bathroom that served also as a kitchen. But they had no sense of home, they ate their meals in restaurants, and only had breakfast in the flat. It was merely a place to sleep in. It was comfortable, though a third person coming in for a whisky and soda crowded it, and Margery with the help of a charwoman kept it as neat as Charlie's untidiness permitted, but there was not a single thing in it that had a personal note. They had a tiny car and whenever Charlie had a holiday they took it across the Channel and started off, with a bag each for all their luggage, to drive wherever the fancy took them. Breakdowns never disturbed them, bad weather was part of the fun, a puncture was no end of a joke, and if they lost their way and had to sleep out in the open they thought they were having the time of their lives.

Charlie continued to be irascible and contentious, but nothing he did ever disturbed Margery's lovely placidity. She could calm him with a word. She still made him laugh. She typed his monographs on obscure bacteria and corrected the proofs of his articles in the scientific magazines. Once I asked them if they ever quarrelled.

"No," she said, "we never seem to have anything to quarrel about. Charlie has the temper of an angel."

"Nonsense," I said, "he's an overbearing, aggressive, and cantankerous fellow. He always has been."

She looked at him and giggled and I saw that she thought I was being funny.

"Let him rave," said Charlie. "He's an ignorant fool and he uses words of whose meaning he hasn't the smallest idea."

They were sweet together. They were very happy in one another's company and were never apart if they could help it. Even after the long time they had been married Charlie used to get into the car every day at luncheon-time to come west and meet Margery at a restaurant. People used to laugh at them, not unkindly, but perhaps with a little catch in the throat, because when they were asked to go and spend a week-end in the country Margery would write to the hostess and say they would like to come if they could be given a double bed. They had slept together for so many years that neither of them could sleep alone. It was often a trifle awkward. Husbands and wives as a rule not only demanded separate rooms, but were inclined to be peevish if asked to share the same bathroom. Modern houses were not arranged for domestic couples, but among their friends it became an understood thing that if you wanted the Bishops you must give them a room with a double bed. Some people of course thought it a little indecent, and it was never convenient, but they were a pleasant pair to have to stay and it was worth while to put up with their crankiness. Charlie was always full of spirits and in his caustic way extremely amusing, and Margery was peaceful and easy. They were no trouble to entertain. Nothing pleased them more than to be left to go out together for a long ramble in the country.

When a man marries, his wife sooner or later estranges him from his old friends, but Margery on the contrary increased Charlie's intimacy with them. By making him more tolerant she made him a more agreeable companion. They gave you the impression not of a married couple, but, rather amusingly, of two middle-aged bachelors living together; and when Margery, as was the rule, found herself the only woman among half a dozen men, ribald, argumentative, and gay, she was not a bar to good-fellowship but an asset. Whenever I was in England I saw them. They generally dined at the club of which I have spoken and if I happened to be alone I joined them.

When we met that evening for a snack before going to the play I told them I had asked Morton to come to supper.

"I'm afraid you'll find him rather dull," I said. "But he's a very decent sort of boy and he was awfully kind to me when I was in Borneo."

"Why didn't you let me know sooner?" cried Margery. "I'd have brought a girl along."

"What do you want a girl for?" said Charlie. "There'll be you."

"I don't think it can be much fun for a young man to dance with a woman of my advanced years," said Margery.

"Rot. What's your age got to do with it?" He turned to me. "Have you ever danced with anyone who danced better?"

I had, but she certainly danced very well. She was light on her feet and she had a good sense of rhythm.

"Never," I said heartily.

Morton was waiting for us when we reached Ciro's. He looked very sunburned in his evening clothes. Perhaps it was because I knew that they had been wrapped away in a tin box with mothballs for four years that I felt he did not look quite at home in them. He was certainly more at ease in khaki shorts. Charlie Bishop was a good talker and liked to hear himself speak. Morton was shy. I gave him a cocktail and ordered some champagne. I had a feeling that he would be glad to dance, but was not quite sure whether it would occur to him to ask Margery. I was acutely conscious that we all belonged to another generation.

"I think I should tell you that Mrs. Bishop is a beautiful dancer," I said.

"Is she?" He flushed a little. "Will you dance with me?"

She got up and they took the floor. She was looking peculiarly nice that evening, not at all smart, and I do not think her plain black dress had cost more than six guineas, but she looked a lady. She had the advantage of having extremely good legs and at that time skirts were still being worn very short. I suppose she had a little make-up on, but in contrast with the other women there she looked very natural. Shingled hair suited her; it was not even touched with white and it had an attractive sheen. She was not a pretty woman, but her kindliness, her wholesome air, her good health gave you, if not the illusion that she was, at least the feeling that it didn't at all matter. When she came back to the table her eyes were bright and she had a heightened colour.

"How does he dance?" asked her husband.

"Divinely."

"You're very easy to dance with," said Morton.

Charlie went on with his discourse. He had a sardonic humour and he was interesting because he was himself so interested in what he said. But he spoke of things that Morton knew nothing about and though he listened with a civil show of interest I could see that he was too much excited by the gaiety of the scene, the music, and the champagne to give his attention to conversation. When the music struck up again his eyes immediately sought Margery's. Charlie caught the look and smiled.

"Dance with him, Margery. Good for my figure to see you take exercise."

They set off again and for a moment Charlie watched her with fond eyes.

"Margery's having the time of her life. She loves dancing and it makes me puff and blow. Not a bad youth."

My little party was quite a success and when Morton and I, having taken leave of the Bishops, walked together towards Piccadilly Circus he thanked me warmly. He had really enjoyed himself. I said good-bye to him. Next morning I went abroad.

I was sorry not to have been able to do more for Morton and I knew that when I returned he would be on his way back to Borneo. I gave him a passing thought now and then, but by the autumn when I got home he had slipped my memory. After I had been in London a week or so I happened to drop in one night at the club to which Charlie Bishop also belonged. He was sitting with three or four men I knew and I went up. I had not seen any of them since my return. One of them, a man called Bill Marsh, whose wife, Janet, was a great friend of mine, asked me to have a drink.

"Where have you sprung from?" asked Charlie. "Haven't seen you about lately."

I noticed at once that he was drunk. I was astonished. Charlie had always liked his liquor, but he carried it well and never exceeded. In years gone by, when we were very young, he got tight occasionally, but probably more than anything to show what a great fellow he was, and it is unfair to bring up against a man the excesses of his youth. But I remembered that Charlie had never been very nice when he was drunk: his natural aggressiveness was exaggerated then and he talked too much and too loud; he was very apt to be quarrelsome. He was very dogmatic now, laying down the law and refusing to listen to any of the objections his rash statements called forth. The others knew he was drunk and were struggling between the irritation his cantankerousness aroused in them and the good-natured tolerance which they felt his condition demanded. He was not an agreeable object. A man of that age, bald and fattish, with spectacles, is disgusting drunk. He was generally rather dapper, but he was untidy now and there was tobacco ash all over him. Charlie called the waiter and ordered another whisky. The waiter had been at the club for thirty years.

"You've got one in front of you, sir."

"Mind your own damned business," said Charlie Bishop. "Bring me a double whisky right away or I'll report you to the secretary for insolence."

"Very good, sir," said the waiter.

Charlie emptied his glass at a gulp, but his hand was unsteady and he spilled some of the whisky over himself.

"Well, Charlie, old boy, we'd better be toddling along," said Bill Marsh. He turned to me. "Charlie's staying with us for a bit."

I was more surprised still. But I felt that something was wrong and thought it safer not to say anything.

"I'm ready," said Charlie. "I'll just have another drink before I go. I shall have a better night if I do."

It did not look to me as though the party would break up for some time, so I got up and announced that I meant to stroll home.

"I say," said Bill, as I was about to go, "you wouldn't come and dine with us tomorrow night, would you, just me and Janet and Charlie?"

"Yes, I'll come with pleasure," I said.

It was evident that something was up.

The Marshes lived in a terrace on the East side of Regent's Park. The maid who opened the door for me asked me to go in to Mr. Marsh's study. He was waiting for me there.

"I thought I'd better have a word with you before you went upstairs," he said as he shook hands with me. "You know Margery's left Charlie?"

"No!"

"He's taken it very hard. Janet thought it was so awful for him alone in that beastly little flat that we asked him to stay here for a bit. We've done everything we could for him. He's been drinking like a fish. He hasn't slept a wink for a fortnight."

"But she hasn't left him for good?"

I was astounded.

"Yes. She's crazy about a fellow called Morton."

"Morton. Who's he?"

It never struck me it was my friend from Borneo.

"Damn it all, you introduced him and a pretty piece of work you did. Let's go upstairs. I thought I'd better put you wise."

He opened the door and we went out. I was thoroughly confused.

"But look here," I said.

"Ask Janet. She knows the whole thing. It beats me. I've got no patience with Margery, and he must be a mess."

He preceded me into the drawing-room. Janet Marsh rose as I entered and came forward to greet me. Charlie was sitting at the window, reading the evening paper; he put it aside as I went up to him and shook his hand. He was quite sober and he spoke in his usual rather perky manner, but I noticed that he looked very ill. We had a glass of sherry and went down to dinner. Janet was a woman of spirit. She was tall and fair and good to look at. She kept the conversation going with alertness. When she left us to drink a glass of port it was with instructions not to stay more than ten minutes. Bill, as a rule somewhat taciturn, exerted himself now to talk. I tumbled to the game. I was hampered by my ignorance of what exactly had happened, but it was plain that the Marshes wanted to prevent Charlie from brooding, and I did my best to interest him. He seemed willing to play his part, he was always fond of holding forth, and he discussed, from the pathologist's standpoint, a murder that was just then absorbing the public. But he spoke without life. He was an empty shell, and one had the feeling that though for the sake of his host he forced himself to speak, his thoughts were elsewhere. It was a relief when a knocking on the floor above indicated to us that Janet was getting impatient. This was an occasion when a woman's presence eased the situation. We went upstairs and played family bridge. When it was time for me to go Charlie said he would walk with me as far as the Marylebone Road.

"Oh, Charlie, it's so late, you'd much better go to bed," said Janet.

"I shall sleep better if I have a stroll before turning in," he replied.

She gave him a worried look. You cannot forbid a middle-aged professor of pathology from going for a little walk if he wants to. She glanced brightly at her husband.

"I daresay it'll do Bill no harm."

I think the remark was tactless. Women are often a little too managing. Charlie gave her a sullen look.

"There's absolutely no need to drag Bill out," he said with some firmness.

"I haven't the smallest intention of coming," said Bill, smiling. "I'm tired out and I'm going to hit the hay."

I fancy we left Bill Marsh and his wife to a little argument.

"They've been frightfully kind to me," said Charlie, as we walked along by the railings. "I don't know what I should have done without them. I haven't slept for a fortnight."

I expressed regret but did not ask the reason, and we walked for a little in silence. I presumed that he had come with me in order to talk to me of what had happened, but I felt that he must take his own time. I was anxious to show my sympathy, but afraid of saying the wrong things; I did not want to seem eager to extract confidences from him. I did not know how to give him a lead. I was sure he did not want one. He was not a man given to beating about the bush. I imagined that he was choosing his words. We reached the corner.

"You'll be able to get a taxi at the church," he said. "I'll walk on a bit further. Good night."

He nodded and slouched off. I was taken aback. There was nothing for me to do but to stroll on till I found a cab. I was having my bath next morning when a telephone call dragged me out of it, and with a towel round my wet body I took up the receiver. It was Janet.

"Well, what do you think of it all?" she said. "You seem to have kept Charlie up pretty late last night. I heard him come home at three."

"He left me at the Marylebone Road," I answered. "He said nothing to me at all."

"Didn't he?"

There was something in Janet's voice that suggested that she was prepared to have a long talk with me. I suspected she had a telephone by the side of her bed.

"Look here," I said quickly. "I'm having my bath."

"Oh, have you got a telephone in your bathroom?" she answered eagerly, and I think with envy.

"No, I haven't." I was abrupt and firm. "And I'm dripping all over the carpet."

"Oh!" I felt disappointment in her tone and a trace of irritation. "Well, when can I see you? Can you come here at twelve?"

It was inconvenient, but I was not prepared to start an argument.

"Yes, good-bye."

I rang off before she could say anything more. In heaven when the blessed use the telephone they will say what they have to say and not a word beside.

I was devoted to Janet, but I knew that there was nothing that thrilled her more than the misfortunes of her friends. She was only too anxious to help them, but she wanted to be in the thick of their difficulties. She was the friend in adversity. Other people's business was meat and drink to her. You could not enter upon a love affair without finding her somehow your confidante nor be mixed up in a divorce case without discovering that she too had a finger in the pie. Withal she was a very nice woman. I could not help then chuckling in my heart when at noon I was shown into Janet's drawing-room and observed the subdued eagerness with which she received me. She was very much upset by the catastrophe that had befallen the Bishops, but it was exciting, and she was tickled to death to have someone fresh whom she could tell all about it. Janet had just that business-like expectancy that a mother has when she is discussing with the family doctor her married daughter's first confinement. Janet was conscious that the matter was very serious, and she would not for a moment have been thought to regard it flippantly, but she was determined to get every ounce of value out of it.

"I mean, no one could have been more horrified than I was when Margery told me she'd finally made up her mind to leave Charlie," she said, speaking with the fluency of a person who has said the same thing in the same words a dozen times at least. "They were the most devoted couple I'd ever known. It was a perfect marriage. They got on like a house on fire. Of course Bill and I are devoted to one another, but we have awful rows now and then. I mean, I could kill him sometimes."

"I don't care a hang about your relations with Bill," I said. "Tell me about the Bishops. That's what I've come here for."

"I simply felt I must see you. After all you're the only person who can explain it."

"Oh, God, don't go on like that. Until Bill told me last night I didn't know a thing about it."

"That was my idea. It suddenly dawned on me that perhaps you didn't know and I thought you might put your foot in it too awfully."

"Supposing you began at the beginning," I said.

"Well, you're the beginning. After all you started the trouble. You introduced the young man. That's why I was so crazy to see you. You know all about him. I never saw him. All I know is what Margery has told me about him."

"At what time are you lunching?" I asked.

"Half past one."

"So am I. Get on with the story."

But my remark had given Janet an idea.

"Look here, will you get out of your luncheon if I get out of mine? We could have a snack here. I'm sure there's some cold meat in the house, and then we needn't hurry. I don't have to be at the hairdresser's till three."

"No, no, no," I said. "I hate the notion of that. I shall leave here at twenty minutes past one at the latest."

"Then I shall just have to race through it. What do you think of Gerry?"

"Who's Gerry?"

"Gerry Morton. His name's Gerald."

"How should I know that?"

"You stayed with him. Weren't there any letters lying about?"

"I daresay, but I didn't happen to read them," I answered somewhat tartly.

"Oh, don't be so stupid. I meant the envelopes. What's he like?"

"All right. Rather the Kipling type, you know. Very keen on his work. Hearty. Empire-builder and all that sort of thing."

"I don't mean that," cried Janet, not without impatience. "I mean, what does he look like?"

"More or less like everybody else, I think. Of course I should recognize him if I saw him again, but I can't picture him to myself very distinctly. He looks clean."

"Oh, my God," said Janet. "Are you a novelist or are you not? What's the colour of his eyes?"

"I don't know."

"You must know. You can't spend a week with anyone without knowing if their eyes are blue or brown. Is he fair or dark?"

"Neither."

"Is he tall or short?"

"Average, I should say."

"Are you trying to irritate me?"

"No. He's just ordinary. There's nothing in him to attract your attention. He's neither plain nor good-looking. He looks quite decent. He looks a gentleman."

"Margery says he has a charming smile and a lovely figure."

"I dare say."

"He's absolutely crazy about her."

"What makes you think that?" I asked dryly.

"I've seen his letters."

"Do you mean to say she's shown them to you?"

"Why, of course."

It is always difficult for a man to stomach the want of reticence that women betray in their private affairs. They have no shame. They will talk to one another without embarrassment of the most intimate matters. Modesty is a masculine virtue. But though a man may know this theoretically, each time he is confronted with women's lack of reserve he suffers a new shock. I wondered what Morton would think if he knew that not only were his letters read by Janet Marsh as well as by Margery, but that she had been kept posted from day to day with the progress of his infatuation. According to Janet he had fallen in love with Margery at first sight. The morning after they had met at my little supper party at Ciro's he had rung up and asked her to come and have tea with him at some place where they could dance. While I listened to Janet's story I was conscious of course that she was giving me Margery's view of the circumstances and I kept an open mind. I was interested to observe that Janet's sympathies were with Margery. It was true that when Margery left her husband it was her idea that Charlie should come to them for two or three weeks rather than stay on in miserable loneliness in the deserted flat and she had been extraordinarily kind to him. She lunched with him almost every day, because he had been accustomed to lunch every day with Margery; she took him for walks in Regent's Park and made Bill play golf with him on Sundays. She listened with wonderful patience to the story of his unhappiness and did what she could to console him. She was terribly sorry for him. But all the same she was definitely on Margery's side and when I expressed my disapproval of her she came down on me like a thousand of bricks. The affair thrilled her. She had been in it from the beginning when Margery, smiling, flattered, and a little doubtful, came and told her that she had a young man to the final scene when Margery, exasperated and distraught, announced that she could not stand the strain any more and had packed her things and moved out of the flat.

"Of course, at first I couldn't believe my ears," she said. "You know how Charlie and Margery were. They simply lived in one another's pockets. One couldn't help laughing at them, they were so devoted to one another. I never thought him a very nice little man and heaven knows he wasn't very attractive physically, but one couldn't help liking him because he was so awfully nice to Margery. I rather envied her sometimes. They had no money and they lived in a hugger-mugger sort of way, but they were frightfully happy. Of course I never thought anything would come of it. Margery was rather amused. 'Naturally I don't take it very seriously,' she told me, 'but it is rather fun to have a young man at my time of life. I haven't had any flowers sent me for years. I had to tell him not to send any more because Charlie would think it so silly. He doesn't know a soul in London and he loves dancing and he says I dance like a dream. It's miserable for him going to the theatre by himself all the time and we've done two or three matinees together. It's pathetic to see how grateful he is when I say I'll go out with him.' 'I must say,' I said, 'he sounds rather a lamb.' 'He is,' she said. 'I knew you'd understand. You don't blame me, do you?' 'Of course not, darling,' I said, 'surely you know me better than that. I'd do just the same in your place.'"

Margery made no secret of her outings with Morton and her husband chaffed her good-naturedly about her beau. But he thought him a very civil, pleasant-spoken young man and was glad that Margery had someone to play with while he was busy. It never occurred to him to be jealous. The three of them dined together several times and went to a show. But presently Gerry Morton begged Margery to spend an evening with him alone; she said it was impossible, but he was persuasive, he gave her no peace; and at last she went to Janet and asked her to ring up Charlie one day and ask him to come to dinner and make a fourth at bridge. Charlie would never go anywhere without his wife, but the Marshes were old friends, and Janet made a point of it. She invented some cock-and-bull story that made it seem important that he should consent. Next day Margery and she met. The evening had been wonderful. They had dined at Maidenhead and danced there and then had driven home through the summer night.

"He says he's crazy about me," Margery told her.

"Did he kiss you?" asked Janet.

"Of course," Margery chuckled. "Don't be silly, Janet. He is awfully sweet and, you know, he has such a nice nature. Of course I don't believe half the things he says to me."

"My dear, you're not going to fall in love with him."

"I have," said Margery.

"Darling, isn't it going to be rather awkward?"

"Oh, it won't last. After all he's going back to Borneo in the autumn."

"Well, one can't deny that it's made you look years younger."

"I know, and I feel years younger."

Soon they were meeting every day. They met in the morning and walked in the Park together or went to a picture gallery. They separated for Margery to lunch with her husband and after lunch met again and motored into the country or to some place on the river. Margery did not tell her husband. She very naturally thought he would not understand.

"How was it you never met Morton?" I asked Janet.

"Oh, she didn't want me to. You see, we belong to the same generation, Margery and I. I can quite understand that."

"I see."

"Of course I did everything I could. When she went out with Gerry she was always supposed to be with me."

I am a person who likes to cross a "t" and dot an "i".

"Were they having an affair?" I asked.

"Oh, no. Margery isn't that sort of woman at all."

"How do you know?"

"She would have told me."

"I suppose she would."

"Of course I asked her. But she denied it point-blank and I'm sure she was telling me the truth. There's never been anything of that sort between them at all."

"It seems rather odd to me."

"Well, you see, Margery is a very good woman."

I shrugged my shoulders.

"She was absolutely loyal to Charlie. She wouldn't have deceived him for anything in the world. She couldn't bear the thought of having any secret from him. As soon as she knew she was in love with Gerry she wanted to tell Charlie. Of course I begged her not to. I told her it wouldn't do any good and it would only make Charlie miserable. And after all, the boy was going away in a couple of months, it didn't seem much good to make a lot of fuss about a thing that couldn't possibly last."

But Gerry's imminent departure was the cause of the crash. The Bishops had arranged to go abroad as usual and proposed to motor through Belgium, Holland, and the North of Germany. Charlie was busy with maps and guides. He collected information from friends about hotels and roads. He looked forward to his holiday with the bubbling excitement of a schoolboy. Margery listened to him discussing it with a sinking heart. They were to be away four weeks and in September Gerry was sailing. She could not bear to lose so much of the short time that remained to them and the thought of the motor tour filled her with exasperation. As the interval grew shorter and shorter she grew more and more nervous. At last she decided that there was only one thing to do.

"Charlie, I don't want to come on this trip," she interrupted him suddenly, one day when he was talking to her of some restaurant he had just heard of. "I wish you'd get someone else to go with you."

He looked at her blankly. She was startled at what she had said and her lips trembled a little.

"Why, what's the matter?"

"Nothing's the matter. I don't feel like it. I want to be by myself for a bit."

"Are you ill?"

She saw the sudden fear in his eyes. His concern drove her beyond her endurance.

"No. I've never been better in my life. I'm in love."

"You? Whom with?"

"Gerry."

He looked at her in amazement. He could not believe his ears. She mistook his expression.

"It's no good blaming me. I can't help it. He's going away in a few weeks. I'm not going to waste the little time he has left." He burst out laughing.

"Margery, how can you make such a damned fool of yourself? You're old enough to be his mother." She flushed.

"He's just as much in love with me as I am with him."

"Has he told you so?"

"A thousand times."

"He's a bloody liar, that's all."

He chuckled. His fat stomach rippled with mirth. He thought it a huge joke. I daresay Charlie did not treat his wife in the proper way. Janet seemed to think he should have been tender and compassionate. He should have understood. I saw the scene that was in her mind's eye, the stiff upper lip, the silent sorrow, and the final renunciation. Women are always sensitive to the beauty of the self-sacrifice of others. Janet would have sympathized also if he had flown into a violent passion, broken one or two pieces of furniture (which he would have had to replace), or given Margery a sock in the jaw. But to laugh at her was unpardonable. I did not point out that it is very difficult for a rather stout and not very tall professor of pathology, aged fifty-five, to act all of a sudden like a cave-man. Anyhow, the excursion to Holland was given up and the Bishops stayed in London through August. They were not very happy. They lunched and dined together every day because they had been in the habit of doing so for so many years and the rest of the time Margery spent with Gerry. The hours she passed with him made up for all she had to put up with and she had to put up with a good deal. Charlie had a ribald and sarcastic humour and he made himself very funny at her expense and at Gerry's. He persisted in refusing to take the matter seriously. He was vexed with Margery for being so silly, but apparently it never occurred to him that she might have been unfaithful to him. I commented upon this to Janet.

"He never suspected it even," she said. "He knew Margery much too well."

The weeks passed and at last Gerry sailed. He went from Tilbury and Margery saw him off. When she came back she cried for forty-eight hours. Charlie watched her with increasing exasperation. His nerves were much frayed.

"Look here, Margery," he said at last, "I've been very patient with you, but now you must pull yourself together. This is getting past a joke."

"Why can't you leave me alone?" she cried. "I've lost everything that made life lovely to me."

"Don't be such a fool," he said.

I do not know what else he said. But he was unwise enough to tell her what he thought of Gerry and I gather that the picture he drew was virulent. It started the first violent scene they had ever had. She had borne Charlie's jibes when she knew that she would see Gerry in an hour or next day, but now that she had lost him for ever she could bear them no longer. She had held herself in for weeks: now she flung her self-control to the winds. Perhaps she never knew exactly what she said to Charlie. He had always been irascible and at last he hit her. They were both frightened when he had. He seized a hat and flung out of the flat. During all that miserable time they had shared the same bed, but when he came back, in the middle of the night, he found that she had made herself up a shake-down on the sofa in the sitting-room.

"You can't sleep there," he said. "Don't be so silly. Come to bed."

"No, I won't, let me alone."

For the rest of the night they wrangled, but she had her way and now made up her bed every night on the sofa. But in that tiny flat they could not get away from one another; they could not even get out of sight or out of hearing of one another. They had lived in such intimacy for so many years that it was an instinct for them to be together. He tried to reason with her. He thought her incredibly stupid and argued with her interminably in the effort to show her how wrong-headed she was. He could not leave her alone. He would not let her sleep, and he talked half through the night till they were both exhausted. He thought he could talk her out of love. For two or three days at a time they would not speak to one another. Then one day, coming home, he found her crying bitterly; the sight of her tears distracted him; he told her how much he loved her and sought to move her by the recollection of all the happy years they had spent together. He wanted to let bygones be bygones. He promised never to refer to Gerry again. Could they not forget the nightmare they had been through? But the thought of all that a reconciliation implied revolted her. She told him she had a racking headache and asked him to give her a sleeping draught. She pretended to be still asleep when he went out next morning, but the moment he was gone she packed up her things and left. She had a few trinkets that she had inherited and by selling them she got a little money. She took a room at a cheap boarding-house and kept her address a secret from Charlie.

It was when he found she had left him that he went all to pieces. The shock of her flight broke him. He told Janet that his loneliness was intolerable. He wrote to Margery imploring her to come back, and asked Janet to intercede for him; he was willing to promise anything; he abased himself. Margery was obdurate.

"Do you think she'll ever go back?" I asked Janet.

"She says not."

I had to leave then, for it was nearly half past one and I was bound for the other end of London.

Two or three days later I got a telephone message from Margery asking if I could see her. She suggested coming to my rooms. I asked her to tea. I tried to be nice to her; her affairs were no business of mine, but in my heart I thought her a very silly woman and I dare say my manner was cold. She had never been handsome and the passing years had changed her little. She had still those fine dark eyes and her face was astonishingly unlined. She was very simply dressed and if she wore make-up it was so cunningly put on that I did not perceive it. She had still the charm she had always had of perfect naturalness and of a kindly humour.

"I want you to do something for me if you will," she began without beating about the bush.

"What is it?"

"Charlie is leaving the Marshes today and going back to the flat. I'm afraid his first few days there will be rather difficult; it would be awfully nice of you if you'd ask him to dinner or something."

"I'll have a look at my book."

"I'm told he's been drinking heavily. It's such a pity. I wish you could give him a hint."

"I understand he's had some domestic worries of late," I said, perhaps acidly.

Margery flushed. She gave me a pained look. She winced as though I had struck her.

"Of course you've known him ever so much longer than you've known me. It's natural that you should take his part."

"My dear, to tell you the truth I've known him all these years chiefly on your account. I have never very much liked him, but I thought you were awfully nice."

She smiled at me and her smile was very sweet. She knew that I meant what I said.

"Do you think I was a good wife to him?"

"Perfect."

"He used to put people's backs up. A lot of people didn't like him, but I never found him difficult."

"He was awfully fond of you."

"I know. We had a wonderful time together. For sixteen years we were perfectly happy." She paused and looked down. "I had to leave him. It became quite impossible. That cat-and-dog life we were leading was too awful."

"I never see why two persons should go on living together if they don't want to."

"You see, it was awful for us. We'd always lived in such close intimacy. We could never get away from one another. At the end I hated the sight of him."

"I don't suppose the situation was easy for either of you."

"It wasn't my fault that I fell in love. You see, it was quite a different love from the one I'd felt for Charlie. There was always something maternal in that and protective. I was so much more reasonable than he was. He was unmanageable, but I could always manage him. Gerry was different." Her voice grew soft and her face was transfigured with glory. "He gave me back my youth. I was a girl to him and I could depend on his strength and be safe in his care."

"He seemed to me a very nice lad," I said slowly. "I imagine he'll do well. He was very young for the job he had when I ran across him. He's only twenty-nine now, isn't he?"

She smiled softly. She knew quite well what I meant.

"I never made any secret of my age to him. He says it doesn't matter."

I knew this was true. She was not the woman to have lied about her age. She had found a sort of fierce delight in telling him the truth about herself.

"How old are you?"

"Forty-four."

"What are you going to do now?"

"I've written to Gerry and told him I've left Charlie. As soon as I hear from him I'm going out to join him." I was staggered.

"You know, it's a very primitive little colony he's living in. I'm afraid you'll find your position rather awkward."

"He made me promise that if I found my life impossible after he left I'd go to him."

"Are you sure you're wise to attach so much importance to the things a young man says when he's in love?"

Again that really beautiful look of exaltation came into her face. "Yes, when the young man happens to be Gerry."

My heart sank. I was silent for a moment. Then I told her the story of the road Gerry Morton had built. I dramatized it, and I think I made it rather effective.

"What did you tell me that for?" she asked when I finished.

"I thought it rather a good story."

She shook her head and smiled.

"No, you wanted to show me that he was very young and enthusiastic, and so keen on his work that he hadn't much time to waste on other interests. I wouldn't interfere with his work. You don't know him as I do. He's incredibly romantic. He looks upon himself as a pioneer. I've caught from him something of his excitement at the idea of taking part in the opening up of a new country. It is rather splendid, isn't it? It makes life here seem very humdrum and commonplace. But of course it's very lonely there. Even the companionship of a middle-aged woman may be worth having."

"Are you proposing to marry him?" I asked.

"I leave myself in his hands. I want to do nothing that he does not wish."

She spoke with so much simplicity, there was something so touching in her self-surrender, that when she left me I no longer felt angry with her. Of course I thought her very foolish, but if the folly of men made one angry one would pass one's life in a state of chronic ire. I thought all would come right. She said Gerry was romantic. He was, but the romantics in this workaday world only get away with their nonsense because they have at bottom a shrewd sense of reality: the mugs are the people who take their vapourings at their face value. The English are romantic; that is why other nations think them hypocritical; they are not: they set out in all sincerity for the Kingdom of God, but the journey is arduous and they have reason to pick up any gilt-edged investment that offers itself by the way. The British soul, like Wellington's armies, marches on its belly. I supposed that Gerry would go through a bad quarter of an hour when he received Margery's letter. My sympathies were not deeply engaged in the matter and I was only curious to see how he would extricate himself from the pass he was in. I thought Margery would suffer a bitter disappointment; well, that would do her no great harm, and then she would go back to her husband and I had no doubt the pair of them, chastened, would live in peace, quiet, and happiness for the rest of their lives.

The event was different. It happened that it was quite impossible for me to make any sort of engagement with Charlie Bishop for some days, but I wrote to him and asked him to dine with me one evening in the following week. I proposed, though with misgiving, that we should go to a play; I knew he was drinking like a fish, and when tight he was noisy. I hoped he would not make a nuisance of himself in the theatre. We arranged to meet at our club and dine at seven because the piece we were going to began at a quarter past eight. I arrived. I waited. He did not come. I rang up his flat, but could get no reply, so concluded that he was on his way. I hate missing the beginning of a play and I waited impatiently in the hall so that when he came we could go straight upstairs. To save time I had ordered dinner. The clock pointed to half past seven, then a quarter to eight; I did not see why I should wait for him any longer, so walked up to the dining-room and ate my dinner alone. He did not appear. I put a call through from the dining-room to the Marshes and presently was told by a waiter that Bill Marsh was at the end of the wire.

"I say, do you know anything about Charlie Bishop?" I said. "We were dining together and going to a play and he hasn't turned up."

"He died this afternoon."

"What?"

My exclamation was so startled that two or three people within earshot looked up. The dining-room was full and the waiters were hurrying to and fro. The telephone was on the cashier's desk and a wine waiter came up with a bottle of hock and two long-stemmed glasses on a tray and gave the cashier a chit. The portly steward showing two men to a table jostled me.

"Where are you speaking from?" asked Bill.

I suppose he heard the clatter that surrounded me. When I told him he asked me if I could come round as soon as I had finished my dinner. Janet wanted to speak to me.

"I'll come at once," I said.

I found Janet and Bill sitting in the drawing-room. He was reading the paper and she was playing patience. She came forward swiftly when the maid showed me in. She walked with a sort of spring, crouching a little, on silent feet, like a panther stalking his prey. I saw at once that she was in her element. She gave me her hand and turned her face away to hide her eyes brimming with tears. Her voice was low and tragic.

"I brought Margery here and put her to bed. The doctor has given her a sedative. She's all in. Isn't it awful?" She gave a sound that was something between a gasp and a sob. "I don't know why these things always happen to me."

The Bishops had never kept a servant but a charwoman went in every morning, cleaned the flat, and washed up the breakfast things. She had her own key. That morning she had gone in as usual and done the sitting-room. Since his wife had left him Charlie's hours had been irregular and she was not surprised to find him asleep. But the time passed and she knew he had his work to go to. She went to the bedroom door and knocked. There was no answer. She thought she heard him groaning. She opened the door softly. He was lying in bed, on his back, and was breathing stertorously. He did not wake. She called him. Something about him frightened her. She went to the flat on the same landing. It was occupied by a journalist. He was still in bed when she rang, and opened the door to her in pyjamas.

"Beg pardon, sir," she said, "but would you just come and 'ave a look at my gentleman. I don't think he's well."

The journalist walked across the landing and into Charlie's flat. There was an empty bottle of veronal by the bed.

"I think you'd better fetch a policeman," he said.

A policeman came and rang through to the police station for an ambulance. They took Charlie to Charing Cross Hospital. He never recovered consciousness. Margery was with him at the end.

"Of course there'll have to be an inquest," said Janet. "But it's quite obvious what happened. He'd been sleeping awfully badly for the last three or four weeks and I suppose he'd been taking veronal. He must have taken an overdose by accident."

"Is that what Margery thinks?" I asked.

"She's too upset to think anything, but I told her I was positive he hadn't committed suicide. I mean, he wasn't that sort of a man. Am I right, Bill?"

"Yes, dear," he answered.

"Did he leave any letter?"

"No, nothing. Oddly enough Margery got a letter from him this morning, well, hardly a letter, just a line. 'I'm so lonely without you, darling.' That's all. But of course that means nothing and she's promised to say nothing about it at the inquest. I mean, what is the use of putting ideas in people's heads? Everyone knows that you never can tell with veronal, I wouldn't take it myself for anything in the world, and it was quite obviously an accident. Am I right, Bill?"

"Yes, dear," he answered.

I saw that Janet was quite determined to believe that Charlie Bishop had not committed suicide, but how far in her heart she believed what she wanted to believe I was not sufficiently expert in female psychology to know. And of course it might be that she was right. It is unreasonable to suppose that a middle-aged scientist should kill himself because his middle-aged wife leaves him and it is extremely plausible that, exasperated by sleeplessness, and in all probability far from sober, he took a larger dose of the sleeping-draught than he realized. Anyhow that was the view the coroner took of the matter. It was indicated to him that of late Charles Bishop had given way to habits of intemperance which had caused his wife to leave him, and it was quite obvious that nothing was further from his thoughts than to put an end to himself. The coroner expressed his sympathy with the widow and commented very strongly on the dangers of sleeping-draughts.

I hate funerals, but Janet begged me to go to Charlie's. Several of his colleagues at the hospital had intimated their desire to come, but at Margery's wish they were dissuaded; and Janet and Bill, Margery and I were the only persons who attended it. We were to fetch the hearse from the mortuary and they offered to call for me on their way. I was on the look-out for the car and when I saw it drive up went downstairs, but Bill got out and met me just inside the door.

"Half a minute," he said. "I've got something to say to you. Janet wants you to come back afterwards and have tea. She says it's no good Margery moping and after tea we'll play a few rubbers of bridge. Can you come?"

"Like this?" I asked.

I had a tail coat on and a black tie and my evening dress trousers.

"Oh, that's all right. It'll take Margery's mind off."

"Very well."

But we did not play bridge after all. Janet, with her fair hair, was very smart in her deep mourning and she played the part of the sympathetic friend with amazing skill. She cried a little, wiping her eyes delicately so as not to disturb the black on her eyelashes, and when Margery sobbed broken-heartedly put her arm tenderly through hers. She was a very present help in trouble. We returned to the house. There was a telegram for Margery. She took it and went upstairs. I presumed it was a message of condolence from one of Charlie's friends who had just heard of his death. Bill went to change and Janet and I went up to the drawing-room and got the bridge table out. She took off her hat and put it on the piano.

"It's no good being hypocritical." she said. "Of course Margery has been frightfully upset, but she must pull herself together now. A rubber of bridge will help her to get back to her normal state. Naturally I'm dreadfully sorry about poor Charlie, but as far as he was concerned I don't believe he'd ever have got over Margery's leaving him and one can't deny that it has made things much easier for her. She wired to Gerry this morning."

"What about?"

"To tell him about poor Charlie."

At that moment the maid came to the room.

"Will you go up to Mrs. Bishop, please, ma'am? She wants to see you."

"Yes, of course."

She went out of the room quickly and I was left alone. Bill joined me presently and we had a drink. At last Janet came back. She handed a telegram to me. It read as follows:

For God's sake await letter. Gerry

"What do you think it means?" she asked me. "What it says," I replied.

"Idiot! Of course I've told Margery that it doesn't mean anything, but she's rather worried. It must have crossed her cable telling him that Charles was dead. I don't think she feels very much like bridge after all. I mean, it would be rather bad form to play on the very day her husband has been buried."

"Quite," I said.

"Of course he may wire in answer to the cable. He's sure to do that, isn't he? The only thing we can do now is to sit tight and wait for his letter."

I saw no object in continuing the conversation. I left. In a couple of days Janet rang me up to tell me that Margery had received a telegram of condolence from Morton. She repeated it to me:

Dreadfully distressed to hear sad news. Deeply sympathize with your great grief.Love. Gerry

"What do you think of it?" she asked me.

"I think it's very proper."

"Of course he couldn't say he was as pleased as Punch, could he?"

"Not with any delicacy."

"And he did put in love."

I imagined how those women had examined the two telegrams from every point of view and scrutinized every word to press from it every possible shade of meaning. I almost heard their interminable conversations.

"I don't know what'll happen to Margery if he lets her down now," Janet went on. "Of course it remains to be seen if he's a gentleman."

"Rot," I said and rang off quickly.

In the course of the following days I dined with the Marshes a couple of times. Margery looked tired. I guessed that she awaited the letter that was on the way with sickening anxiety. Grief and fear had worn her to a shadow, she seemed very fragile now and she had acquired a spiritual look that I had never seen in her before. She was very gentle, very grateful for every kindness shown her, and in her smile, unsure and a little timid, was an infinite pathos. Her helplessness was very appealing. But Morton was several thousand miles away. Then one morning Janet rang me up.

"The letter has come. Margery says I can show it to you. Will you come round?"

Her tense voice told me everything. When I arrived Janet gave it to me. I read it. It was a very careful letter and I guessed that Morton had written it a good many times. It was very kind and he had evidently taken great pains to avoid saying anything that could possibly wound Margery; but what transpired was his terror. It was obvious that he was shaking in his shoes. He had felt apparently that the best way to cope with the situation was to be mildly facetious and he made very good fun of the white people in the colony. What would they say if Margery suddenly turned up? He would be given the order of the boot pretty damn quick. People thought the East was free and easy; it wasn't, it was more suburban than Clapham. He loved Margery far too much to bear the thoughts of those horrible women out there turning up their noses at her. And besides he had been sent to a station ten days from anywhere; she couldn't live in his bungalow exactly and of course there wasn't a hotel, and his work took him out into the jungle for days at a time. It was no place for a woman anyhow. He told her how much she meant to him, but she mustn't bother about him and he couldn't help thinking it would be better if she went back to her husband. He would never forgive himself if he thought he had come between her and Charlie. Yes, I am quite sure it had been a difficult letter to write.

"Of course he didn't know then that Charlie was dead. I've told Margery that changes everything."

"Does she agree with you?"

"I think she's being rather unreasonable. What do you make of the letter?"

"Well, it's quite plain that he doesn't want her."

"He wanted her badly enough two months ago."

"It's astonishing what a change of air and a change of scene will do for you. It must seem to him already like a year since he left London. He's back among his old friends and his old interests. My dear, it's no good Margery kidding herself; the life there has taken him back and there's no place for her."

"I've advised her to ignore the letter and go straight out to him."

"I hope she's too sensible to expose herself to a very terrible rebuff."

"But then what's to happen to her? Oh, it's too cruel. She's the best woman in the world. She has real goodness."

"It's funny if you come to think of it, it's her goodness that has caused all the trouble. Why on earth didn't she have an affair with Morton? Charlie would have known nothing about it and wouldn't have been a penny the worse. She and Morton could have had a grand time and when he went away they could have parted with the consciousness that a pleasant episode had come to a graceful end. It would have been a jolly recollection, and she could have gone back to Charlie satisfied and rested and continued to make him the excellent wife she had always been."

Janet pursed her lips. She gave me a look of disdain.

"There is such a thing as virtue, you know."

"Virtue be damned. A virtue that only causes havoc and unhappiness is worth nothing. You can call it virtue if you like. I call it cowardice."

"The thought of being unfaithful to Charlie while she was living with him revolted her. There are women like that, you know."

"Good gracious, she could have remained faithful to him in spirit while she was being unfaithful to him in the flesh. That is a feat of legerdemain that women find it easy to accomplish."

"What an odious cynic you are."

"If it's cynical to look truth in the face and exercise common sense in the affairs of life, then certainly I'm a cynic and odious if you like. Let's face it, Margery's a middle-aged woman, Charlie was fifty-five and they'd been married for sixteen years. It was natural enough that she should lose her head over a young man who made a fuss of her. But don't call it love. It was physiology. She was a fool to take anything he said seriously. It wasn't himself speaking, it was his starved sex, he'd suffered from sexual starvation, at least as far as white women are concerned, for four years; it's monstrous that she should seek to ruin his life by holding him to the wild promises he made then. It was an accident that Margery took his fancy; he wanted her, and because he couldn't get her wanted her more. I dare say he thought it love; believe me, it was only letch. If they'd gone to bed together Charlie would be alive today. It's her damned virtue that caused the whole trouble."

"How stupid you are. Don't you see that she couldn't help herself? She just doesn't happen to be a loose woman."

"I prefer a loose woman to a selfish one and a wanton to a fool."

"Oh, shut up. I didn't ask you to come here in order to make yourself absolutely beastly."

"What did you ask me to come here for?"

"Gerry is your friend. You introduced him to Margery. If she's in the soup it's on his account. But you are the cause of the whole trouble. It's your duty to write to him and tell him he must do the right thing by her."

"I'm damned if I will," I said.

"Then you'd better go."

I started to do so.

"Well, at all events it's a mercy that Charlie's life was insured," said Janet.

Then I turned on her.

"And you have the nerve to call me a cynic"

I will not repeat the opprobious word I flung at her as I slammed the door behind me. But Janet is all the same a very nice woman. I often think it would be great fun to be married to her.

重译本序

以效果而论，翻译应当像临画一样，所求的不在形似而在神似。以实际工作论，翻译比临画更难。临画与原画，素材相同（颜色、画布，或纸或绢），法则相同（色彩学、解剖学、透视学）。译本与原作，文字既不侔，规则又大异。各种文字各有特色，各有无可模仿的优点，各有无法补救的缺陷，同时又各有不能侵犯的戒律。像英、法，英、德那样接近的语言，尚且有许多难以互译的地方；中西文字的扞格远过于此，要求传神达意，铢两悉称，自非死抓字典，按照原文句法拼凑堆砌能济事。

各国的翻译文学，虽优劣不一，但从无法文式的英国译本，也没有英文式的法国译本[1]。假如破坏本国文字的结构与特性，就能传达异国文字的特性而获致原作的精神，那么翻译真是太容易了。不幸那种理论非但是刻舟求剑，而且是削足适履，两败俱伤[2]。两国文字词类的不同，句法构造的不同，文法与习惯的不同，修辞格律的不同，俗语的不同，即反映民族思想方式的不同，感觉深浅的不同，观点角度的不同，风俗传统信仰的不同，社会背景的不同，表现方法的不同。以甲国文字传达乙国文字所包含的那些特点，必须像伯乐相马，要“得其精而忘其粗，在其内而忘其外”。而即使是最优秀的译文，其韵味较之原文仍不免过或不及。翻译时只能尽量缩短这个距离，过则求其勿太过，不及则求其勿过于不及。

倘若认为译文标准不应当如是平易，则不妨假定理想的译文仿佛是原作者的中文写作。那么原文的意义与精神，译文的流畅与完整，都可以兼筹并顾，不至于再有以辞害意，或以意害辞的弊病了。

用这个尺度来衡量我的翻译，当然是眼高手低，还没有脱离学徒阶段。《高老头》初译（一九四四）对原作意义虽无大误[3]，但对话生硬死板，文气淤塞不畅，新文艺习气既刮除未尽，节奏韵味也没有照顾周到，更不必说作品的浑成了。这次以三阅月的工夫重译一遍，几经改削，仍未满意。艺术的境界无穷，个人的才能有限：心长力绌，唯有投笔兴叹而已。

译者

一九五一年九月

[1]《哈姆雷德》第一幕第一场有句：Not a mouse stirring，法国标准英法对照本《莎翁全集》译为：Pas un chat。岂法国莎士比亚学者不识mouse一字而误鼠为猫乎？此为译本不能照字面死译的最显著的例子。

[2]六年前，友人某君受苏联友人之托，以中国诗人李、杜等小传译成俄文。译稿中颇多中文化的俄文，为苏友指摘。某君以保持中国情调为辩，苏友谓此等文句既非俄文，尚何原作情调可言？以上为某君当时面述，录之为“削足适履，两败俱伤”二语作佐证。

[3]误译的事，有时即译者本人亦觉得莫名其妙。例如近译《贝姨》，书印之后，忽发现原文的蓝衣服译作绿衣服，不但正文错了，译者附注也跟着错了。这种文字上的色盲，真使译者为之大惊失“色”。

为吹号手吹响号角

有一个生活在十三世纪的男孩，他的勇气和爱国情怀直到今天还激荡在特定的铜号声中，那是一首“未完成”的曲子，因为就在他吹奏铜号的时候，入侵的鞑靼人一箭射中了他的胸膛。

有一个生活在十五世纪的男孩，在同一座塔楼，用同一个号角，不得不又吹响了那首曲子，这一次他吹完了，作为信号暗示另一队敌人的到来。

有一个生活在二十世纪的男人，他听到了那首每小时被准时吹响的古老的不完整乐曲，塑造了第二个男孩的形象，虚构了一个振奋人心的接近真实的故事，创作出当代最受欢迎的冒险小说。

这本书一定深深吸引着它的读者，因为人们完全不介意书名中的陌生名字——克拉科夫[1]——这个不为众人所知的城市，而且在一九二八年前它从未在儿童读物中出现过。学校的历史课或者传奇故事里也没有提到过一个名字与众不同的“卡济米尔·亚盖洛”国王。但凯利先生的作品让我们感受到了他对中世纪波兰的迷恋，那座古老而陌生的城市和形形色色的人物在他的笔下活灵活现、扣人心弦。我们被带入一个遍地炼金术士和铠甲骑士的世界，一个有着善良神父和可怕恶棍的国度，这个世界以小约瑟夫的视角展现在我们眼前。我们和他一起看到伟大的国王为他的家人平反，以及传世之宝“塔尔诺夫大水晶球”戏剧性的宿命。

这是一本好书，至少它为成长中的青少年打开了一扇了解波兰历史的窗户。一九二八年秋天出版后，它立即获得了评论界的广泛赞誉。孩子们和评论员一样渴望着阅读其中的内容。人们把这本书当作一个特别的发现，口口相传。这本书出版后的几个月内，一家图书馆写信告诉我，由于一遍又一遍地抄写，摆在他们书架上的这本书已经磨损破烂了。

本书在波兰也大受欢迎，并被称为“波兰人和英勇的美国人之间友谊和互相理解的标志”。克拉科夫的市议员满心感激，将至今仍然在圣玛利亚教堂吹响的一把历史悠久的银号借给了作者和出版商。凯利先生在纽约公共图书馆举办的图书周见面会上讲述了这本书的诞生过程，那时他常常光顾那座吹响“不完整乐曲”的教堂，拿着手表站在那里。

“当另一个号角在克拉科夫的上空吹响时，你会听到波兰人皆知的英雄主义的象征，这是克拉科夫为你而吹起的号角。”

他指向门口的位置，我带来的一位纽约警察乐队成员正站在那里。号声响起，嘹亮而澎湃。那是一个伟大的时刻！没有人知道，这位魁梧的警察之前并不懂得乐谱，我不得不匆忙把他带到地下室，教他反复练习吹奏这首曲子。

这把古老的号角之后继续被展出，盛放号角的天鹅绒盒子每侧都有一面国旗。这个号角一年内走遍美国，被陈列在书店里，在学校和图书馆被吹响。这个号角比那段时间古老塔楼所使用的号角还要珍贵。

当这本书一九二九年在华盛顿特区被授予纽伯瑞奖的时候，号声也响彻了美国图书馆协会会议的上空。凯利先生在领奖时，如是说：

“我不知道各位是否把这称作乐曲，在我看来，这是一种从克拉科夫城传来的震动，让我心潮涌动……在波兰重生后，我第一次来到克拉科夫，突然听到了巨大的钟声低沉地在我的头顶上空响起，然后是小钟发出的警报，我看到闲庭信步的鸽子被这声音吓到，像雪花一样四散而去。当一切回归平静，羽翼飘荡的高空响起了号声《海那圣歌》……我无法形容自己的感受。我兴奋地想要高声尖叫，想站到自己的头顶上唱歌跳舞。我的心脏开始轻柔却沉郁有力地跳动，似乎能溅起激动的火花。

“这种痴迷再未离我而去。在那之后，我又回到波兰修学。那时，我每天都会在教堂的高墙内待上一段时间。早上、中午、夜晚到深夜的每一个时间段，我都到过那里，有时候甚至凌晨就跑去……因为我爱着它。它见证了我灵魂所经历的每一种情绪，也传达了我心中的每一份欢乐。”

媒体人的敏锐观察力与诗意的情感表达相融合，造就了这部不同寻常的作品。

凯利先生对波兰的爱起源于第一次世界大战期间，那时他被派到法国，参加对波兰军队的抚恤工作。波兰解放后，他和军队一同回到波兰，在那里待了三年，并三次获得政府颁发的奖章。一九二四年，在纽约卡斯基斯科基金会（Kosciuszko Foundation）的赞助下，他再次来到波兰进行了为期一年的授课和研究。他原本想写一本严肃正统、贴合实际的书，但最终被这个地方和这个地方的人所感染，创作出了这部浪漫的小说。

这本书成功之后，他又创作了两则故事：一则关于波兰历史中的危机，也是儿童读物；另一则是圣诞节故事，名为《洁净的干草之中》（In Clean Hay）。他还创作了其他作品，在此不作赘述。他在达特茅斯教授英国文学和波兰历史，退休后在缅因海岸附近的一座岛上生活并进行写作。一九六零年，他在岛上去世。他的教学和他的作品将永远活在他所热爱的那两个国度。

路易·希曼·贝克特尔
一九六六年四月于基斯科山

[1]　本书名原文为The Trumpeter of Krakow。

A TRUMPET FOR THE TRUMPETER

There was a boy, in the thirteenth century, whose courage and patriotism live on today in a certain trumpet-call, a tune "unfinished" because, as he once blew it, the arrow of an invading Tartar pierced his breast.

There was a boy of the fifteenth century who had reason to blow that tune, in the same tower, on the same trumpet, and to finish it, as a signal of another sort of enemy.

A man of the twentieth century, hearing the old broken tune played every hour, invented the second boy, when he wrote this book, a story partly true, and so exciting that it has won a place among the best-loved adventure stories of our time.

It must hold its readers engrossed, for it has overcome that strange name on the cover, "Krakow," a city by no means well known to tourists and before 1928 never used in a book for boys and girls. And neither school histories nor legends had celebrated a king so oddly named as "Kazimir Jagiello." But Mr. Kelly makes us share his own fascination for medieval Poland; he makes that strange, ancient city as real and exciting as he does his colorful cast of people. We are transported into a world of alchemists and armored knights, of a kind priest and a fearful villain, all seen through the eyes of young Joseph with him, we watch the great king do justice to his family, and see the wildly dramatic end of that fateful, ancienttreasure, the "Great Tarnov Crystal."

It is good to have one book, at least, for growing youth that opens a window on Polish history. When published in the fall of 1928, it won immediate critical praise. Boys and girls were as keen about it as reviewers; it was the sort of book to pass on as a special discovery. Within a few months of its publication one library wrote me that copy after copy had been "worn to shreds" on its shelves.

In Poland it was welcomed as "a symbol of new understanding and friendship between Poles and the valiant American people." In gratitude, the city councilors of Krakow loaned the author and his publisher one of the oldest of the silver trumpets still blown from the tower of the Church of Our Lady. At the Book Week meeting at the New York Public Library, Mr. Kelly was the speaker. Having told how the idea of the book came to him, as he haunted the church where the "broken tune" of the ancient hymn rang out, he stood with watch in hand.

"Now at the very moment when another trumpet blows in Krakow, you will hear that symbol of heroism known to every Pole, blown for you by a trumpet from Krakow."

He motioned toward the door, where I had brought a member of the New York police band. The tune rang forth, loud and spine-chilling. It was a great moment! No one knew that I had had to rush that burly policeman to the cellar to teach him the tune, since he could not read music.

The old trumpet went on display in its velvet-lined case, with flags on each side. It traveled all over America for a year, was shown in bookshops, and was blown in schools and libraries. By then, other less precious trumpets were being used in the old tower, as they are today.

When the book was awarded the Newbery Medal in 1929, in Washington, D.C., of course the trumpet rang out over the American Library Association meeting. Mr. Kelly's acceptance speech said, in part:

"I don't know if you call it song exactly, but it's a kind of vibration that issues from this city of Krakow that arouses a very tumult in my heart.... As I first came into Krakow after that great day when Poland rose from the grave, I suddenly heard the great bell boom over my head with its deep accent, and then the tocsin, the smaller bell, which drove the pigeons scrambling and shook them into the light like white snowflakes. As all were settling and there was but the fluttering of wings high in the air, there came from above that call of the trumpet, the Heynal.... I can't describe my emotions. I was so happy that I wanted to scream aloud. I wanted to sing and dance and stand on my head. My heart started to beat, gently but without speed, and seemed to be throwing off sparks of fire.

"That intoxication never left me. And later when I came back to study I did not let one day pass without spending some time within the walls of that church. I went there morning, noon, and night; late night, too, and very early morning.... I love it. It has sheltered every mood that my spirit has known and it has expressed every joy that there is in me."

The keen observation of a newspaper man had been fused with poetic emotion to produce this most unusual book.

Mr. Kelly's love of Poland began during the first World War, when he was sent to do relief work for the Polish legions in France; he returned with them when Poland was freed, to stay for threeyears. He was awarded three decorations by the government. Then in 1924, he returned to Poland for a year of lecturing and study, on a fellowship from the Kosciuszko Foundation in New York. Instead of the serious factual book he had intended to do, he was impelled by the place and the people to write this romantic novel.

After its success, he wrote two more stories of crises in Polish history, also a story for younger children, set in Poland, a Christmas tale called in Clean Hay, and other books. He taught English literature and Polish history at Dartmouth until he retired to live and write on an island off the Maine coast. There he died, in 1960. His teaching and his books live on, in both the countries he loved.

LOUIS SEAMAN BECHTEL

Mt. Kisco, April, 1966

THE BROKEN NOTE

It was in the spring of the year 1241 that rumors began to travel along the highroad from Kiev in the land of Rus that the Tartars of the East were again upon the march. Men trembled when they heard that news and mothers held their children close to their breasts, for the name "Tartar" was one that froze folks' blood in their veins. As the weeks went on, the rumors grew thicker and there began to come through to Poland, our land of the fields, the news that the country lands of the Ukraine were ablaze. Then it was heard that Kiev had fallen, then Lvov, the city of the Lion, and now there was naught between the savage band of warriors and the fair city of Krakow save a few peaceful villages and fertile fields.

The Tartars came through the world like a horde of wild beasts. They left not one thing alive nor one green blade of wheat standing. They were short, dark men of shaggy beards and long hair twisted into little braids, and they rode on small horses which they covered with trophies that they had gained in war. Brave they were as lions, courageous they were as great dogs, but they had hearts of stone and knew not mercy, nor pity, nor tenderness, nor God. On their horses they carried round shields of leather and iron, and long spears often trailed from their saddles. About their shoulders and thighs they wore skins of animals. Some decorated their ears with golden rings—here and there one wore a gold ring in the nose. When theytraveled, the dust rose high into the sky from beneath the hoofs of their little horses, and the thunder of the hoof beats could be heard many miles away. They were so numerous that it took days for the whole horde to pass any one given point, and for miles behind the army itself rumbled carts bearing slaves, provisions, and booty— usually gold.

Before them went always a long, desperate procession of country people driven from their humble homes by the news of the coming terror; they had already said farewell to the cottages where they lived, the parting from which was almost as bitter as death. So it has always been in time of war that the innocent suffer most—these poor, helpless peasants with their carts and horses and geese and sheep trudging along through the dust to escape, if God so willed, the terrible fate which would befall them were they left behind. There were old people in that procession too feeble to be stirring even about a house, mothers nursing children, women weak with sickness, and men broken hearted at the loss of all that a lifetime of labor had brought. Children dragged themselves wearily along beside them, often bearing their pets in their arms.

To this company Krakow opened her gates, and prepared for defense. Many of the nobility and rich citizens had, in the meantime, fled to the west or taken refuge in monasteries far to the north. The brothers of the monastery at Zvierzyniec, a short distance outside the city, took in all the refugees that the building could accommodate, and then prepared to stand siege. But the great, weary, terror-mad mob that had fled ahead of the band of Tartars was content enough to make the city itself its destination. And once within its walls all turned their faces toward the south. For there, in the south of the city,towering on its rocky hill high over the Vistula River, was the great, irregular, turreted mass that was the Wawel—the fortress and castle of the kings of Poland from the time of Krakus, the legend king, and the home of the dukes and nobles who formed the king's court.

It had been decided to make no attempt to defend the city outside the castle gates, since that would entail a great loss of life; and so for several days the city dwellers who remained and these refugees from all the country about poured into the fortification and were housed inside its walls. The old castle gates which were then on Castle Highway opposite the Church of St. Andrew were at last shut and barricaded, and the walls were manned with citizen soldiery prepared to give their lives for the protection of the city and their families.

The Tartars fell upon the city in the night and, after burning the outlying villages, pillaged the districts that lay about the churches of St. Florian, St. John, and the Holy Cross. The whole night long was one of hideous sounds—the crackling and fury of flames, the snarling and yelling of the enemy when they found that the prey had fled, their roars of triumph when they came upon gold and treasure. As morning dawned the watchers from the Wawel looked out over the town and saw but three churches not already in flames. These were the Church of Our Lady Mary near the great market, the Church of St. Andrew, with its stalwart towers, at the Castle Gate, and the Church of St. Adaibert in the market place. Already a colony of Jews in the Black Village had perished, also those refugees and town dwellers who had not rushed inside the walls of defense. There remained but one man—or rather, a youth—still alive in the midst of all that destruction.

He was the trumpeter of the Church of Our Lady Mary, and he had taken solemn oath to sound the trumpet each hour of the day and night from a little balcony high up on the front of the church. As the first golden rays of the sun changed the Vistula from a dark line to a plash of dancing gold, he mounted this balcony to sound the Heynal—the hymn to Our Lady which every trumpeter in the church had in the past sworn to play each hour of the day and night—"until death." He felt with a strange joy the glow of the sun as it fell upon him that morning, for the night had been very dark both with its own shadow and with the gloomy blackness of men's ruthlessness.

About his feet, down in the town highway stood groups of short, fierce men gazing up at him curiously. Here and there the roof of a house was shooting upward in flames and belching forth clouds of black smoke. Hundreds of dwellings lay charred and ruined by the conflagration. He was alone in the midst of a terrible enemy—he might have fled on the previous day and gained the castle with the refugees and the town dwellers, but he had been true to his oath and remained at his post until he should be driven away. Now it was too late to retreat.

He was a very young man, perhaps nineteen or twenty, and wore a dark cloth suit that was caught at the knees with buckles, like the knickerbockers of a later generation; dark, thick hose extended from the knees to the tops of his soft, pointed sandals, and a short coat falling just below the waist was held together in front by a belt. The head covering was of leather and something like a cowl; it fell clear to his shoulders and ran up over the head in such a way that only his face and a bit of hair were visible.

My mother and sister are safe, he thought. May God be praisedfor that! They are gone these ten days and must be now with the cousins in Moravia.

It came to him then what a sweet thing life is. The sun over the Vistula was now reflected in the windows of the Cathedral of the Wawel, where the priests were already saying mass. At the tops of all the gates he could see guards in full armor, upon which the sunlight hashed. A banner with a white eagle hung in the air above the gate at the great draw.

Poland lives, he thought.

And then it came to him, young as he was, that he was part of the glorious company of Polish men that was fighting for all Christendom against brutal and savage invaders. He had not seen much of death before that minute—he had heard of it only as something vague. And now, he himself was perhaps going out to meet it, because of his oath, because of his love for the Church, because of his love for Poland.

I shall keep my word, he mused. If I die it shall be for that. My word is as good as my life.

Had a painter caught his expression then, he would have caught only the expression of a very great peace—an expression that signified somehow that God was very close. There was no moment of weakness, no faltering, no suffering even—for he did not think of what might come after his duty was performed. The sand in the hourglass already marked the hour for the trumpet to sound.

"Now, for Poland and Our Lady, I will sound the Heynal," he said, and raised the trumpet to his lips.

Softly he blew at first—then, thrilled with a sense of triumph, he felt in his heart a joy that was almost ecstatic. He seemed to seein a vision that though he might now die alone and for naught save what perhaps some scoffing ones might call a foolish honor, still that bravery was to descend as a heritage to the people to whom he belonged, and was to become a part of their spirit, their courage, their power of everlasting—all this that moment brought.

A Tartar below crouched to his bow and drew back the arrow as far as he could draw. The string whirred. The dark shaft flew like a swift bird straight for the mark. It pierced the breast of the young trumpeter when he was near the end of his song—it quivered there a moment and the song ceased. But, still holding to the trumpet, the youth fell back against the supporting wall and blew one last glorious note; it began strongly, trembled, and then ceased—broken like the young life that gave it birth—and at that moment those below applied the torch to the wooden church, and it, too, rose in flames to Heaven, with the soul of the youth among them.

I. THE MAN WHO WOULDN'T SELL HIS PUMPKIN

It was in late July of the year 1461 that the sun` rose one morning red and fiery as if ushering in midsummer's hottest day. His rays fell upon the old city of Krakow and the roads leading up to it, along which rolled and rocked a very caravan of peasants' wagons. They were drawn mostly by single horses hitched into place by the side of a rough pole that served for shaft; for wheels there were stout pieces of board nailed tightly together and cut round about, baked with fire at the rim to harden them; for body they had but rude cross boards as a floor, with sides and ends of plaited willow reeds, so that the wagons had the appearance of large baskets traveling on wheels. As they moved along a road often rough from holes and stones, out through fields sometimes, and even across streams, the wagons pitched about like little boats on a windswept sea.

In many cases the drivers were walking alongside the carts, flicking their long whips now and then above the horses' backs to give the animals a little encouragement, while upon the seats sat the patient figures of women and children.

In the wagon was all manner of merchandise—vegetables, flowers, ducks, hens and geese, pigs, butter and milk. Here a driver was conveying a load of skins, here one had nothing but black earth for enriching city gardens. Another, driving a load of poultry,wore around his neck, like beads, garland after garland of dried mushrooms strung upon strings. At the back of the picture rose the foothills of the Carpathians, misty and golden in the early sun, and at a distance the Vistula River curved like a silver bracelet about the Wawel Hill. All about was the early-morning smell of wet grass and fresh earth and growing things.

Market day had begun. All night some of these wagons had been traveling along the highways that spread out from the great highway that was the Krakow, Tarnov, Lvov, Kiev route. Some had been on the march for two days and two nights, so distant were the borders of the province. Here were men and women in town dress from the larger centers, here were barefooted peasants in long coats and round hats, here were peasant women in rough garments but with head scarfs and shawls of dazzling colors, here were the inhabitants of a Jewish village, twelve men in black robes and black hats, with the characteristic orthodox curls hanging down in front of their ears.

Here were boys belonging to the retinue of a local szlachcic, or country gentleman, their leather costumes showing up to advantage beside the rather dingy dress of the male portion of the peasantry. Here and there were women with little babies, here and there were old people trudging by the sides of their wagons up to market, as they had done for thirty or forty years past.

But every man in that caravan carried some sort of weapon, either a short knife at the belt, or quarter staff in the hand, or huge-headed ax at the bottom of the wagon. For thieves were abroad in great number at times of market, and it was even said that there were country gentlemen of ruined fortune who were not above recoupingthemselves now and then at the expense of some such caravan. Usually, however, it was on the return trip that the thieves were numerous, for then each villager and peasant had gold or silver as the result of the day's bargaining.

Although practically all these wagons carried cargoes of goods, there was one which seemed strangely empty for market day. It had two horses instead of the usual one, its shaft pole was stouter that those of the other wagons, its occupants were better dressed than the peasants and seemed somehow not like actual workers of the soil. In it rode the driver, a man of perhaps forty-five years, a woman—his wife—some ten years younger, and a boy, who sat at the open end of the wagon, dangling his legs above the dirt and mud of the highway.

"Now, wife," said the man, snapping a long whip at the off horse—his wife was sitting beside him on a rude seat at the front of the wagon—"that high tower you see is a watch tower on the Wawel Hill of Krakow. Should we go as flies the stork, we should reach there by the eighth hour. See, in the distance are the two towers of the Church of Our Lady. It is a welcome sight to my eyes after these three weeks on a rocking cart."

The woman threw back a gray hood from her face and looked ahead with longing eyes. "It is Krakow, then," she said, "the city of my mother. Often has she told me of its glory, and yet I never had hoped to see it. God knows I wish I might see it differently and with less pain in my heart. But God gives, and man receives, and we are here at last."

"Yes," said the man.

For a long time they traveled along in silence. The man was musing on his early experiences in Krakow, the woman on her losthome in the Ukraine, and the boy letting his imagination run riot in speculation as to the sights that he should see in the great city.

Their thoughts were brought suddenly from their own affairs to a commotion among the carts behind them. Drivers were reining in their horses and swinging them to the left of the road, narrow as it was, in order to let someone pass. The man whose thoughts had been thus interrupted turned around, trying to discern who it might be who was pushing forward through the long line of carts, and in a moment he saw that it was a rider on a small horse.

"Way, way," the rider was shouting. "Do you peasants think that the whole road belongs to you? ... Stay on your farm, where you belong," he shouted angrily at a peasant driver whose horse reared suddenly from the edge of the road to the middle. "Give me room to pass. You have no business on the highroad with an animal that jumps about like that."

"I had gone in the ditch else," replied the peasant without surliness.

The rider glanced sharply at the contents of the man's wagon, and being assured that it contained nothing but fresh straw to be sold to brick makers, dashed ahead until he was even with the cart which held the man and woman and boy.

The last named had been watching his advance curiously. Now this boy, Joseph Charnetski, was in his fifteenth year. He was not by any means handsome, though he could not be called ugly. His hair and his eyes were dark, and his face was somewhat round and very pleasant. He wore rather rich, though travel-soiled, nether garments, not leather like those of the retainers, nor of coarse sacking like the peasants' clothes, but of a good quality of homespun, and a thick,buttoned coat of the same material, which—fell skirt like nearly to the knees. On his feet were brown leather boots, whose tops were soft and loose, and so high that they reached almost to the bottom of the coat. On his head he wore a round hat like a turban.

The instant the rider perceived the boy, "Chlopak, chlopak [Boy, boy]," he exclaimed in a rather croaky voice, "tell your old man to hold his horses. You come and hold mine."

The boy obeyed, but as he leaped from the wagon and grasped at the horse's bit thong, he came to the conclusion that the stranger was no friend. In those days when the world was just emerging from a period of darkness and cruelty, it was a necessity that each man should be constantly upon his guard against other men. Robbers abounded—jealous friends often descended to mean tricks; men of noble birth and breeding thought nothing of defrauding poor peasants, and among the poor peasants themselves were those who would commit crimes for the sake of gold.

Therefore when Joseph grasped at the horse's bit rein he had already come to the conclusion, perhaps from something in the stranger's looks or speech or manner, that he was one to be treated with caution. He was attired in a retainer's suit of thick cloth. The jacket was short but concealed a coat of very light chain armor beneath. He wore for breeches not knickerbockers but a single leather garment that combined doublet and hose in one. The cap was round, with a hanging jewel, probably glass, dangling behind against his neck.

It was the face, however, that betrayed the soul beneath. It was a dark, oval, wicked face—the eyes were greenish and narrow and the eyebrow line above them ran straight across the bridge of thenose, giving the effect of a monkey rather than a man. One cheek was marked with a button like scar, the scar of the button plague that is so common in the lands east of the Volga, or even the Dnieper, and marks the bearer as a Tartar or a Cossack or a Mongol. The ears were low set and ugly. The mouth looked like the slit that boys make in the pumpkins they carry on the eve of Allhallows. Above the mouth was a cropped mustache, which hung down at the ends and straggled into a scanty beard. The man carried at his waist a short curved sword and from the inside of his jacket could be seen protruding the jeweled handle of an Oriental dagger.

No sooner had the boy caught at his rein than the man was off his horse and with a leap had gained the wagon. Joseph's father reached quickly under the wagon seat for a short cross-hilted sword.

"Not one step nearer," he shouted as the man came toward him with hand outstretched as if to take his hand. "Who you may he I know not, but I stand as a Christian till I find out what your errand is."

The stranger stopped, smiled at the ready sword still in its scabbard, though with a sudden respect in his smile, then pulled off his hat and made a bow. "I take it that you are Andrew Charnetski," he said.

"You take too much." answered the driver. "To strangers I am Pan[1] Andrew Charnetski."

The stranger bowed again. "I spoke as to an equal," he said. "I am Stefan Ostrovski of Chelm. But now I am come from Kiev, where I have been on state business. It is known that one Muscovite has some important business with our Lithuanian provinces, and I, though I may not say by whom, was sent to learn—" He broke off suddenly, as if wishing to give the impression that his business was such that he might not speak of it in public fashion. "Put on my way home, men told me that a band of Tartars had come north from the Krim, pillaging much of the country about. Among the houses which they had burned and the fields which they had destroyed were the house and fields of one Andrew Charnetski—nay, I ask pardon—of Pan Andrew Charnetski, who was reported to have escaped with his wife and son in the direction of Krakow, where they were said to have friends. This being true, and since I was traveling in the same direction, I sought a description of Pan Andrew and his family, and this morning when I saw a true Ukrainian cart, drawn by two horses and not by one, and bearing a man and woman and boy such as had been described to me, I took the assurance to present myself and make my greetings to you."

Pan Charnetski scrutinized the face, the clothing, and the figure of the stranger closely. "The half is not yet told," he said.

"Nay," answered the other, "but the rest is perhaps a tale for you and me behind some heavy door when we reach the city of Krakow just ahead. I have heard—" He spoke significantly; then with his hands he described a circle in the air.

Charnetski watched him with his eyelids drawn half shut so that he could focus his attention upon the man and see naught of the world outside. His heart was not so cold and steady, however, as one might think from looking at his calm, composed features. In truth, at the stranger's gesture his heart was beating a tattoo against his ribs. He knew that almost every word the man had uttered wasfalse; he knew that his name was not Ostrovski, even though there had been members of that family in Chelm—not one feature of the man's countenance was Polish. And there was that in the tone of the last words that had suggested a threat. Charnetski realized also that here was no chance meeting. It was fourteen days and more since they had left the border. This man, he reasoned, had followed them all that distance, or had perhaps been sent by some person of higher rank to intercept them before they gained entrance to the city.

"You have heard naught that concerns me," he answered shortly. "And now, since the carts are leaving me behind, will you kindly return to your horse? I have nothing to say that will be of importance to you, nor do you interest me in any way."

Charnetski spoke truly, for the carts ahead were already some distance away and the drivers behind were shouting at him angrily for blocking the traffic.

"On the contrary," answered the stranger, "you have that which interests me greatly. And I will not leave you until we are safe behind some door in the city. Here, boy," he shouted at Joseph, "lead my horse along behind the wagon, for I intend to ride the rest of the way."

Pan Charnetski's cheeks blazed. "Now, by the lightning, you make yourself too free here," he articulated. "State what business you have quickly and be done."

The man glanced around the cart and he saw on the wooden floor just in front of the driver's seat a huge yellow pumpkin. "Ha," he said, "a pumpkin, and at this time of the year. I suppose they raise pumpkins in the winter on the steppe. What shall be the price of that pumpkin?"

"It is not for sale," answered Charnetski.

"No?"

"I said no."

"What if I offer its weight in gold?"

"All's one."

"You will not sell?"

"I tell you, no."

"Then"—the stranger drew his sword quickly—"then you will fight for it!" And he stepped forward toward the driver.

Charnetski hesitated no longer. In the flash of an eye he had vaulted across the seat, dodged a blow of the saber, and caught the stranger's right wrist in a grip of steel. The sword dropped with a clang. Charnetski did not let the man go, however. He threw his left hand into the small of the stranger's leg and with clutch upon arm and leg hoisted him high and tossed him out of the cart. He fell in the mud, sputtering with rage and calling curses of every description upon Charnetski's head. And at this minute Joseph, with admirable foresight, swung the man's horse about and struck him smartly upon the right flank. The horse reared and capered, then dashed off down the road in the direction from which the wagons had come; at the same instant the boy leaped upon the cart and shouted to his father, who climbed back to the seat and swung the long lash over the horses' heads. They were off in a second, leaving the stranger in the middle of the highway, turning now to the right and now to the left as if uncertain whether to pursue his horse or his enemy. And Charnetski, swinging about, picked up the sword from the bottom of the cart and hurled it into the road.

Some time later they reached the Kazimierz, the Jewish cityfounded by King Kazimir more than one hundred years earlier. Passing through this, they came to the bridge across the Vistula which would admit them to the city of Krakow itself. Finding, however, that this bridge was undergoing repairs, they were forced to take the next bridge to the north; thence they proceeded to the fortified gate called Mikolayska, where they were challenged by the gatekeeper.

[1]　Pan is a formal Polish term signifying Sir or Mr.

II. KRAKOW

"Charnetski, Christian, wife and son," said Pan Andrew to a custodian who wore light armor and carried a halberd.

He gave them a quick glance and motioned for them to pass. Another man in black peered into the cart to see what was inside, and finding nothing, concluded that these were farm folk come up to the city to buy, and accordingly demanded but a few pieces of iron coin as tax. This paid, they took the road which ran from Mikolayska Gate to the Sukiennice, the old Cloth Hall, which stood then, as it does today, in the very center of the city.

Krakow was flooded with a golden sunlight. Joseph, who saw for the first time a large city, gaped in very astonishment as he glanced left and right about him.

Front and rear, their cart formed part of the long straight train of carts coming to the city loaded with products of the farms. Through this line were breaking from time to time splendid horsemen wearing breastplates of steel that shone like precious metal and carrying long swords dangling from the saddles. One of these men who pushed through the crowd just in front of their horses was so splendidly arrayed that the boy took him for a very high noble, or perhaps the king himself, the peace-loving king, Kazimir Jagiello, the fourth of the name of Kazimir, and he exclaimed:

"That must be the king, Father. See the shining armor and thejewels upon his saddle. And the sword must be of gold, for it shines like fire. And look"—he pointed eagerly—"see the Polish eagle worked in silver upon the saddlecloth. There beyond it is the white knight of Lithuania. Is he not indeed the king?"

"No, son, no. That is but one of the guard that waits on the nobles at the royal castle."

All about them rose in the bright sunlight palaces, churches, towers, battlement walls, and Gothic buildings, as yet for the most part unadorned by the rich sculpture that was to come in a few years under the influence of the Italian Renaissance. In the distance rose against the turquoise-blue sky the cathedral on the Wawel Hill, its Romanesque tower showing high above the city. Close at hand were the two towers of the Church of Our Lady Mary, not as they appear today since the hand of the master architect and of the renowned sculptor Wit Stwosz altered them, but rising unbelfried and uncrowned above the cemetery, where white gravestones clustered at the base of the church.

In the very middle of the market, surrounded by smaller wooden buildings, was the great Cloth Hall, used for the sale and exchange of cloth goods, already swarming with merchants who had been traveling all night, and for many nights perhaps, in order to close bargains early on market day before the money of purchasers had been spent elsewhere.

Camped in the square outside the Cloth Hall were a number of Tartars who had come from the distant East to sell fine swords and cloths and jewels plundered from Muscovites, or Bulgarians, or Creeks, or other travelers in the steppes. Facing the east as the rising sun had crept over Wawel Hill, they had chanted their morningprayer of praise to the great Allah. Their singing could have been heard mingling with the clashing of the great bell on the Church of Our Lady Mary and the chanted service of the Armenian merchants who had come in from Trebizond and the lands beyond the Black Sea with carpets and spices and fine rugs.

Here for the moment in this great international capital of East and West was worshiped every god that man knows; it might even be said that God himself was worshiped under many names and in many languages and dialects. Here were Turks, Cossacks, Ruthenians, Germans, Flemings, Czechs, and Slovaks, with their wares to sell, and Hungarians with their wines from the mellow plains of Transylvania.

As for money, there might be found zloty and guilder and groschen, silver in bars, and precious stones, also plenty of token "in kind"—that is to say, certain varieties of merchandise such as amber, dates bound in packages, or even vegetables in containers, each of which had a recognized value over all the trade routes of the Hanseatic League. For the League merchants were represented here as well—prosperous Germans or Dutchmen in long robes with fur collars—and they did business in every language known to man.

While the boy drank in these unusual sights on all sides, there suddenly floated down from above the sweet notes of a trumpet. Looking directly upward he could see the golden bell of a trumpet protruding from one of the tower windows of the Church of Our Lady Mary, and as he looked the full dignity of the church burst upon him, its quiet strength which appealed to the eye being strangely mingled in his senses with the trumpet song which fell upon his ears.

There were two towers rising high above the traffic of the street; rising unequally, he now noticed, for the nearer tower seemed a bit squat beside the farther one. It was from the higher tower that the trumpeter was playing.

The tune was a little morning hymn, the Heynal, brought into Poland, some said, in the earliest days of Christianity by missionaries who came from the south. It was a simple little air, intensely sweet and appealing, but at a certain place the trumpeter broke the tune off abruptly, leaving but the echo of an unfinished strain to float down from above. It was as if someone at that moment had taken the trumpet from his lips.

Joseph turned to his father in astonishment. "Isn't he going to finish the song?"

The father smiled. "It is a long story, my son, and one that I will tell you at a later time."

The trumpet sounded again, from another window, then from the farther side, and finally at the north side, toward the Florian Gate. Four times the trumpeter had sounded the Heynal, ending always with the broken note.

"He plays rather poorly," added Pan Charnetski.

Now, though Pan Charnetski was a country gentleman, he was accomplished in many crafts. After having graduated from the University of Krakow, he decided not to remain in one of the professions but rather to live on his father's estate and manage it, as had been the custom for the men in his family. He had retained a love of music, which he had studied in the university, and played well upon brass instruments, the straight trumpet, the curved trumpet, and the trumpet with keys. Therefore when he said that thetrumpeter in the tower had not played well he knew of what he was talking.

The cart was now passing close to the Cloth Hall, and Joseph ceased to question his father any further concerning the song with the broken note because of the strange scenes which claimed his attention.

Here stood a group of merchants in bright gowns. Wealthy they must have been because their long coats were of fine cloth, some lined with fur and trimmed with many silks. Beneath the coats were costumes of tight-fitting cloth. Joseph saw one man with the color of the cloth in the trouser of the right leg different from the color of the cloth of the left trouser, which to the boy had a ludicrous look. But when he noticed that many other men wore the same kind of garment, tight-fitting to leg and thigh, and of different color upon each leg, he ceased to smile and began to wonder. The wonder did not leave off for a while, either, for other curiosities in dress caught his eye. The hats and head coverings were in their way as remarkable as the tight garments. Turbans were worn uniformly, some with pointed peaks, others simply masses of gayly colored cloth heaped up high on the head in twists and folds; grotesque ornaments, too, were worn on the head—one man even had a stuffed or an imitation rooster, with legs and comb and all, perched on the crown of his high hat. The merchants wore curious leather footgear, most of the sandals being of soft leather with long, twisted points. One man had sticks thrust into the leather at the toes, making his sandals appear at least two feet long.

At the stalls around the Cloth Hall were all manner of wares, which the sellers were advertising with loud cries. Here was a graincounter with different colored grains in open sacks. A woman in a blue gown which hung from a yoke at the shoulder, and with a piece of cloth of the same color wound deftly around her head for a hat, was selling a few grains of corn to a traveling musician. He wore a long yellow garment all of a piece, including head covering like a cowl, and falling to the knees, below which the legs and feet were bare. This garment was caught at the waist by a bright yellow belt. He carried under one arm a bagpipe with three protruding tubes, two for music, if it might be called such, and one for his mouth. In one hand he held a pouch of leather into which the woman was slipping grains of corn.

The Charnetskis drove by the stalls and shops of the glove makers, where there were women working and buying, all dressed in bright-colored gowns; past the needle makers in leather aprons, who sprawled over benches; past the sword makers, with their neat forges and rows of shining steel blades; past the tub makers, who were assembling wooden staves into tub bodies; past the smiths in their long black aprons, leading horses into position where they could be shed. Here and there the red signs of the barber and bloodletter, here and there the huge flasks of green and blue denoting the stores of the apothecaries. True Catholics had upon the walls of their shops an ikon or a picture of the Holy Mother of God from the sacred shrine of Chenstohova; almost every merchant had some distinctive figure above the door of his shop to distinguish it from his neighbor's; for example there was a hatter with the sign "Under the White Elephant," and there was a shoemaker who had a stone head of Kazimir the Great for the satisfaction of himself and his customers. The numbering of public buildings was not known in that age, andbuildings were distinguished by some such emblem, which usually stood above the outer gate or door.

Everywhere could be heard the cries of vendors shouting or singing their wares or professions, the flower girls, the knife sharpener, the baker's boy, and the butcher's apprentice.

"Co brakuje, co brakuje?" they all shouted in a chorus. "What do you lack? What do you lack?"

Occasionally, to Joseph's delight, a monkey could be seen, brought here by traders from the east or south, one playing around a booth, another carried, much bedecked with ribbons, in the arms of some merchant's or perhaps burgomaster's lady.

Once or twice amid the clamor of the market rang the clanking of chains as poor wretches about to be fastened to the church walls by iron collars, or stuck in the pillory, or perhaps even to suffer a worse fate, were marched to the church for a last prayer before the sentence of the law was passed upon them. Life was a precarious thing in many ways in those days, and men and women for very slight offenses were beheaded or banished or thrown into prisons.

Now they passed a procession of pilgrims on the way to some shrine, men and women from the villages dressed in their good clothes with the parish priest marching ahead of them and leading the chant which they were singing. The cross bearer was a young man with stalwart shoulders and bright eyes; he had need of his strength, too, for he had sworn to carry the holy image of Our Lord from his native village to Chenstohova, which was many miles distant. This company had already been on the road about ten days. There were boys and girls, too, in the procession, and some had their minds upon serious things, but others were looking for the first timeupon the glory of medieval Krakow, and would no doubt in their prayers ask forgiveness for too much attention to worldly things.

The cart turned into Grodzka, or Castle, Street, after leaving the market place and went directly toward the Wawel. Near the Wawel Pan Andrew swung the horses to the right and passed through a city gate and into a meadowy lane. In front of a large rambling palace that stood there, he drew up by the side of the road and leaped to the ground not far from a pair of iron gates that marked the entrance. At these gates he was accosted by an armed guard who, with a rather hostile air, blocked the entrance completely with his spear.

"What do you want?" he asked sharply.

"I seek Pan Andrew Tenczynski."

The guard shouted something, whereat five men in armor came running from a little house near the gate.

"Surround him," said the guard. This was done much to the astonishment of Pan Andrew. "One of you run to the house and call the captain," next ordered the guard. "Tell him that a countryman is here demanding to see Pan Andrew Tenczynski."

Pan Charnetski, trying to force his way out of the circle, was pushed back into the center by one of the armed men. At that he raised his voice in anger: "Who are you that dare detain me here? I am Pan Andrew Charnetski, first cousin to the Tenczynskis and proprietor of an estate in the Ukraine. I demand that you confront me with an officer in authority and not treat me like one come here as an enemy."

The men of the guard looked at each other in astonishment. Was it possible that this man did not know the truth—the report of which had already spread over the greater portion of Poland?

The captain came in a moment with the returning soldier. He broke through the ring and walked straight up to Pan Charnetski. "What is your business here?" There was certain pleasantness and courtesy in his voice that made Pan Andrew forget his anger for the moment.

"You have a civil tongue, young man," he answered. "I take it that you are in command here?"

"I am."

"Then I will tell you, as I have told your soldiers, that I am Pan Andrew Charnetski, come this day from the Ukraine to see my cousin Pan Andrew Tenczynski on important business."

"You come too late," answered the captain. "It is strange that you have not heard, for this news is now all about the country. Pan Andrew Tenczynski lives no longer. His kin have departed from the city for a time, and may return I know not when. I am here for the observance of order, for the protection of the estate against enemies of the family."

Pan Andrew started. "My cousin is dead—and how?"

"It was like to nothing the city has seen these many years. For a long time there had been hot blood between the tradesmen and nobles. The issue came to a head through the dissatisfaction of Pan Tenczynski over some piece of armor that he had bidden a smith to make. He not only took the tradesman to task but refused to pay for the work he had done, whereat the whole guild rose against him. They pursued him through the streets and killed him in the Church of the Franciscans, where he had sought shelter. It was a sad and grievous thing, and his family for fear of the mob fled the city. The gentle Elizabeth, our queen—and may the blessing of Heaven beupon her!—hates all strife that may result in the shedding of blood, and she it was who persuaded our king to make peace between the townsfolk and nobles. He sent us here to protect this house, to be a guarantee against the shedding of any blood, for there are many who would willingly pillage this dwelling and kill the servants that are still here. We are but acting upon orders when we detain all persons who seek entrance here, and for the execution of these orders you must give us your pardon, since we seek but to avert further bloodshed."

It seemed to Pan Andrew at that moment as if heaven had fallen about his ears.

"Let me give to Pan one piece of advice," continued the captain.

"Most willingly will I receive it," said Pan Andrew thoughtfully.

"Get yourself from the city as quickly as possible if you be of any blood ties with the Tenczynskis, or else, if you stay, change your name and manner of speech lest some assassin make a mark of you for the benefit of his party.... I greet you then with a hail, as is befitting between equal Pans, and request that, for your own safety, you depart quickly."

"But—I must remain here. A band of pillagers, I know not whom exactly, though I think them the paid robbers of someone in high authority, have burned my house in the Ukraine and left not one stone upon another. My fields are ruined as well, and I am here to take refuge with my kinsmen, to bring them word of something very secret, which must go at once to the ears of the king himself."

"Alas," answered the captain, "I can give you but little help. The king is at this moment in Torun, where there are said to be plans against the military order of the Knights of the Cross—for he seeksthere in the north peace at all odds. When he will return I know not, perhaps in a month, perhaps in a year. If you would await him here, I would, if I were you, settle in this town and take another name. Later there will come a retribution for these dark deeds against the Tenczynski family, and there will be more crows about the gallows."

Saying which, he turned away and called the guard again to its post.

Pan Andrew, however, stood motionless for a few seconds. The thoughts fairly burned in his brain. His friends, protectors, gone! The king away, he himself a fugitive here no less than in the Ukraine. From every side enemies pressed upon him, and what had he done to deserve such a fate? He was in a predicament even without this complication, for here he was in a great city where he had not a single friend. He had but little money, for what he had gathered had been invested year by year in his house and lands in the Ukraine. There were his wife and his son to be put in a place of shelter, and not only were the means lacking but there was even peril at every hand. Behind him at the gates of the city had appeared one foe— here in the city there were apparently many others. What to do? ... Well.... Let God give.... There would be something.

Aimlessly he got into the wagon, turned it about, and made for the market again. There at least they might spend the day, procure water for the horses, and buy a little of something to eat. He found a place near one of the springs, unloosed the horses with the help of his son, and let them crop the short grass that grew near one edge of the market place, watering them with buckets that he filled at the spring.

Not until then did he seek comfort and counsel from his wife,who had always been his solace at such times; throwing himself down beside her on the wagon seat, he told her the story of his late discoveries, the absence of the king, the death of his kinsman. For a second the woman's heart quailed before the fresh difficulties, but she forgot self at the look in her husband's face. Her quiet reply, "We will wait, for God is in the waiting," filled him with courage again.

Joseph, however, was at that age when no sky remains long clouded. His heart had been beating fast with excitement ever since the sight of the city's towers had loomed before them in the early morning, and his legs had been itching to get out of the wagon and explore the place. He began by taking a short excursion over to a little building near by, which at first glance had seemed to be a market building, but, when he approached it, proved to be a church with a low dome and round side windows. Although the church was of much interest to those who favored historical lore as being one of the oldest churches in Poland, it did not interest the boy greatly. He scrutinized the beggars at the door, a young boy with but one leg, a woman with a back bent to a curve, an old man with sightless eyes, praying continually, and many other wretched alms seekers. Crossing himself and muttering a prayer for God's helpless creatures, Joseph turned and marched down Grodzka Street in the direction of the Wawel.

He had just come to a cross lane which led on the left to the Church of the Dominicans, and on the right to the Church of All Saints, when he noticed a Tartar boy in the street leading and constantly beatings a large Ukrainian wolf dog. The wolf dog was on a leash—he had a strong hand-wrought collar about the neck— and he was turning now and then to glance back at his tormentor,who was plying a short Cossack whip. Joseph watched the boy in amazement, wondering why he had the dog and why he was beating him—as a matter of fact, the boy was acting out of pure viciousness—but neither of these questions found satisfactory solution in Joseph's mind. In a very few minutes, however, another question rose with the suddenness of lightning, a question which required action for a solution, and this action Joseph was able to supply.

For at the moment that the boy and dog were crossing the church lane, there emerged from the farther foot walk a man dressed all in black like a priest, but wearing a collar which was not clerical, since it opened in the front. He did not, however, for the moment attract Joseph's attention; it was his companion that caught and held the boy's gaze. For the companion was a girl of perhaps the same age as Joseph—she was walking by the side of the man in black and now and then grasping at his hand.

Joseph saw the dog no longer. His eyes were riveted on the girl. She seemed to him like an angel taken out of a Christmas play, or a spirit from a Festival of the Three Kings—in truth, she might have been one of those beautiful figures come to life out of the wondrous stained-glass windows in the church. Her hair was light—Joseph's was dark. Her skin was as white as the finest linen, her eyes as blue as the skies above the Vistula; she wore a cloak like garment of red that fell from her shoulders to her ankles and was girdled at the waist. It was embroidered in blue, with lace at neck and wrists; in front it did not meet completely but showed the second garment that she wore beneath, a mantle of blue that fell in folds even below the outer coat. And as she looked up, the country boy thought that he had never seen anything prettier on earth—so daintily she trippedalong that she seemed to walk on clouds. Then for a moment he looked down at his hands, dirty, hard, and grimy; he looked at his clothes and found them dusty and worn after the long journey.

But if he had been in heaven at the sight of the girl, he came back to earth quickly. For the Tartar boy with the dog and the man in black with the girl were close together at the crossing of the roads when suddenly the maddened dog turned desperately at bay upon his tormentor and crouched for a powerful spring. Joseph shouted and rushed forward just as the dog leaped. The Tartar boy dropped the leather thong in a flash and darted down the walk out of reach of the dog's jaws, but leaving directly in his path the man in black and the girl. Blind with fury the dog sprang again, and in an instant he would have come down upon the girl, who happened to be on the outside, had not Joseph at the same moment leaped and caught at the dog's heavy collar.

He had dealt with dogs many times in the Ukraine, and he knew that no dog is vicious if healthy and well treated; therefore there had been no fear in this effort that he made, save for the peril, perhaps, that the dog might mistake him for the boy who had been beating him, and sink his teeth into his flesh.

His fingers caught the collar squarely. The grip held, and he went hurtling through the air like the tail of a skyrocket, as the dog's leap, weighted by this unexpected load, fell short and the girl drew back with a cry. But Joseph and the infuriated animal went rolling to and fro in a wild embrace on the hard surface of the road, he striving to make the beast pay attention to his words, the dog only becoming more and more frightened. But the boy knew, after the first second when all depended upon whether his grip held or not, that everythingwas safe and he could successfully avoid the paws and teeth of the dog. Thus at a favorable moment he released his hold quickly upon the animal's collar and scrambled to his feet while a very dusty and possibly ashamed wolf dog tore off like a streak of lightning in the direction of the Franciscans' church.

III. THE ALCHEMIST

Something heavy but kindly fell upon Joseph's shoulders and something light touched his cheek.

Looking up quickly from a survey of his garments, now more ragged and dusty than ever, he perceived that the weight was the hand of the man in black and that the lightness had been a kiss upon his cheek from the man's companion—her cheeks were Bushed and her eyes bright and her lips were still close to him. He was somewhat dazed from the shock of going to earth so quickly with the dog, but he thrilled with pleasure and happiness from the kindly touch and the kiss.

He stepped back to brush himself, and then gazed squarely at the man and girl.

His cheeks grew rosy with that first meeting of eyes. For in the man's there was an ocean of gratitude and a suggestion of a tear, and the girl's eyes blazed forth frank admiration.

"You were so quick," she exclaimed. "Would that I could spring like that. It was brave of you—"

His tongue found no words. Boys of fifteen, even if aged by experience, have little to say when praise is bestowed so freely.

Moreover the man gave him no opportunity. "Remarkable," he said, "remarkable. As swift a leap as I ever saw," and then blinking with his eyes as if the light hurt them, added, "or hope to see."

"It was nothing," Joseph stammered. "Often in the Ukraine I have dispersed dogs in a fight." And then thinking that this perhaps sounded like boasting, said further, "As do many boys of my age in that country."

"From the Ukraine?" The man in black looked at him with interest. "How do you happen to be so far from home?"

"Tartars or Cossacks burned our house. We have been traveling this day more than two weeks in a cart only to find ourselves homeless here. Father had kinsfolk in this city, but the head of the house is dead and the others are away."

"Where are your people now?"

"In the market place."

"H'm," the man muttered to himself, "homeless and in the market place. And what will they do?"

The boy shook his head. "I think that my father will find us some shelter," he said finally. "He was thinking—" He hesitated, for he had been taught never to speak of troubles before strangers, though the girl peered straight into his eyes with great kindness and sweetness.

There is something curious here, thought the man. The boy's face has a high degree of intelligence and his speech is the speech of one who has listened to good words. A noble action this—I think in good faith that the whelp might have had his teeth in the child's throat.

Looking down upon the boy he said, "You have rendered us a noteworthy service, you have saved my niece from much painful injury; will you not accompany us to our home that we may hear your whole story and perhaps in our turn—"

The boy's face reddened. "Nay," he said, "I wish no reward. What I did—"

The girl caught him up. "Indeed you do my uncle wrong. He meant but this: we live humbly, will you not come and rest for a moment until you may join your people?"

"I ask pardon," the boy said quickly.

Whereat the man laughed, for their speech and expression had been over serious for children, though it still was an age when children grew to be men and women often over a single night. In some provinces girls of fourteen or fifteen were considered grown women and even given in marriage. Boys at that age had seen much of the rough side of life, of war and battle and cruelty.

"I will go with you," Joseph added, kissing the cuff of the gown of the man in black as he had always been taught to do in his home.

They turned to the left past the Church of the Franciscans, to the right through a short lane, and then to the left again into the most curious street of the world of that day.

It was the Street of the Pigeons, famed throughout all Europe as the dwelling place of scholars, astrologers, magicians, students, and likewise doctors, brothers of the Church, and masters of the seven arts. In the worst end of the street, the upper end near the city wall, clustered the squalid dwelling places that were once the homes of Jewish refugees, fleeing from persecution in all parts of the world. Terrible poverty had existed there, and when the Jewish inhabitants finally moved to their own city, Kazimierz, across the river, the buildings which they left were scarcely fit for human beings to live in. They were, in the first place, very old and out of repair—they were built for the most part of wood, though the fronts on the streetswere sometimes of brick covered with rough cement or mortar. The upper stories usually overhung, and the roofs were covered with loose boards nailed in place, serving instead of tiles or shingles. Rickety staircases on the outside of these buildings led from the streets or from interior courts up to the dwelling places on the third and fourth floors, where, at the time of this story, lived family literally heaped upon family in terrible disorder and poverty.

Thieves and murderers crouched there in hiding during the day, bands of lawless men had their haunts there in cellar or attic or other den. A fire in the year 1407 had swept through this street and through St. Ann's, clearing out many of these undesirable places, but unfortunately not destroying all of them.

In the lower end of the streets on the side toward the University of Krakow there was more respectability, since students and masters of the university inhabited there. A large students' bursar, or dormitory, stood near the corner where Jagiellonska now meets the Street of the Pigeons. In this lived many students; others put up near by in groups or with private families, since it was not until late in the 1490's that the authorities compelled the students to live in university buildings.

The prestige of the various colleges and the reputation of the men who taught there had drawn to Krakow not only genuine students but also many of the craft that live by their wits in all societies, in all ages—fortune tellers and astrologers, magicians and palmists, charlatans, necromancers, and fly-by-nights who were forever eluding the authorities of the law. Here, somewhere on the Street of the Pigeons, they all found lodging.

In the rooms above the street, in the kitchens beneath the street,these men plied their trades. Self-termed astrologers read in the stars the destinies of the gullible; they foretold happiness to trusting peasant girls who came to them for advice in their love matters; they prophesied disaster to mer-chants who, held by fear, might be induced to part with much money; they cheated, they robbed, and often on provocation they killed, until after many years they gave the street a certain unsavory reputation. Against the machinations of these men the influence of the university was ever working, and the first great blow that many of these magic crafts and black arts received was struck by Nicholas Kopernik, better known as Copernicus, many years later, when Joseph Charnetski was a very old man; Copernicus, working with rough implements, even before the telescope had been invented, proved to men for the first time that the heavenly bodies, stars and planets, move in the skies according to well-fixed and definitely determined laws, subject only to the will of the Creator of the universe, and that they have nothing to do with the destinies of individuals.

All about them in the street flitted men dressed in long robes like that of the guardian of the little girl, though all the robes were not alike. Some were clerical, with closed front and collar; others were open and flowing, with great sleeves like a bishop's gown; some were of blue, some were of red, some were of green. Joseph noticed one robe of ermine over which was worn a chain of heavy gold, at the end of which hung suspended a great amethyst cross.

They passed a house, part wood and part stone, where were gathered at opened doors a great group of young men in plain black robes, much less sumptuous than some others which they had seen, all the members of the group engaged in a lively altercation, as theguardian informed the boy and girl, concerning the movement of the stars. One was contending that the firmament of stars moved for one hundred years to the west—another (and this was backed by a written argument from the old Alphonsian tables from Spain) that the stars moved constantly in one direction without change.

Passing this group they came to a dwelling the front of which was stone. The door was set back from the street and flanked by short projecting buttresses on either side, put there as if to caution the emerging inhabitant to look carefully to right and left before proceeding—a caution not unwise at night. The windows above were not only crossed by wooden shutters that opened and closed like doors, but also barred with iron. The man in black took from the folds of his gown a huge brass key, which he fitted into the outside door, turned it in the lock with some labor, and then threw the portal open.

They stepped over a small board which served as a threshold, and passed through a dark passageway which led to an open court. At the end of the court was the flat wall of a monastery, without windows or doors. On the right was a low, one-story building, and on the left rose a ramshackle structure of wood, four stories high. Outside this building, leading to the apartments on the second and third floors, was a wooden staircase hitched to the wall by wooden clutch supports and strengthened by a single wooden upright. In the middle of the court was an old well with a bucket on a rope attached to a wheel.

The staircase creaked as they ascended, and seemed to Joseph to swing just a little. It gave him such a dizzy sensation that he clutched at the wall, fearful lest the whole structure should becomeloose and topple down. But the man only smiled as he saw the boy's sudden movement and assured him that the staircase was safe enough. They went up one flight, past the first landing, and then on to the second. Here they stopped and the man reached into his gown for another key, a smaller one this time.

Just as they were entering the apartment on the third floor opposite this landing, Joseph noticed that there was still one more floor above them, even though the main staircase ended with the third floor. The entrance to this top door, which appeared to have been at one time a loft or storeroom, was gained by climbing a crude ladder like staircase with a single rail, which was fastened at a slight angle against the wall. The door to which these steps led was directly above the farther end of the landing, and to Joseph's surprise, appeared to be of metal. From its shape and size the boy decided that it was a window that had been changed into an entrance, while at its right a square aperture had been cut in the wall, probably for the purpose of giving light. In an instant they were in the apartment where the man and girl lived, and Joseph had no further chance to study the loft which in some unexplainable manner had aroused his curiosity.

This apartment was stuffy and poorly lighted, but the furnishings were not poor. There were tapestries and great oaken chairs, a heavy table in the middle of the room, several huge chests, and a sideboard upon which some silver glistened.

The girl ran quickly to a shutter and threw it open, where-upon the light streamed in through a myriad of small glass panes set in lead. Quickly she set before Joseph and the man in black, small goblets which she filled with wine; a few pieces of broken breadwere placed before them on the table, and they all ate, Joseph rather voraciously, although striving to disguise his hunger.

"Now tell us your story," the man bade him.

Joseph related it briefly, emphasizing for the most part the arrival of his father and mother and himself in the city that morning, and the dilemma that faced them in procuring lodgings.

The man in the black robe listened attentively, and when the boy had finished he struck the table a light blow. "I think I have it," he said. "Wait here for me and take what refreshment you will. I will be back in a few moments." He went out through the door and hurried down the stairs to one of the apartments below.

The girl pushed her chair closer to Joseph's and looked up into his eyes.

"What is your name?" she asked.

"I am Joseph Charnetski."

"Joseph," she said. "I like the name much. Mine is Elzbietka."

"My father is Andrew Charletski," continued Joseph, "and we lived in the country of the black lands in the Ukraine. It was lonely in our neighborhood, for the nearest neighbor was sixty staja away, yet we never felt fear of Cossack or Tartar, though others did, for my father always treated them well. We were therefore surprised not long ago when there came to us a former servant, a friendly Tartar, who said that we were in some danger, and although my father laughed, I know that he gave the report some credence, since he took the Tartar aside and talked with him privately for a long time. He is not one to reveal his fear, however, and we remained in our house as before, with the warning all but forgotten by my mother and me.

"Then one night before we went to bed, my mother, who wasworking upon some sewing, saw a man's face peeping in through the thatch at one corner of our house. It was a face that she had never seen before; it was not one of the servants of our place or any place next to ours; it was a villainous face and it made such an impression on her that she screamed aloud, alarming us all."

"Yes?" the blue eyes were full of interest.

"That night my father came into the room where I was sleeping, bade me dress quickly, and in a short time led me and my mother through a little door in the rear of the house that I had never seen opened before, since it had always been fastened with nails. Outside this door we found ourselves in a passageway dug out of the earth like a cave, and through this we crept until we emerged into a shed some distance from the other dwellings where two of our best horses were hitched to a cart. That my father had already taken such precautions unknown to us assured me that he had feared something, the nature of which he had kept from us."

"But you know now?"

"Nay-the most curious part is yet to come. My mother and I climbed into the wagon, where a goodly supply of food had been stored, while my father, moving swiftly, wielded a forked stick with such effect, in one corner of the shed, that he soon unearthed a pile of vegetables which had been covered over with tree branches and leaves in order to preserve them. I thought at the time that he was about to put some of them into our wagon for food, but to my surprise he chose only one."

"And that—"

"A pumpkin."

"A pumpkin! But why—"

"I know no more about it than you. When everything else in our wagon had been eaten, Father refused to give it up—this was ten days later, of course, when we were on the last stages of our journey; and once, indeed this very morning, a man who had evidently pursued us from the Ukraine offered my father the pumpkin's weight in gold in exchange for it—but my father refused."

"Did you learn whose face your mother saw in the thatch?"

"That I did not, but what came later proved that my father had acted wisely in leaving our house secretly and in a hurry. For when we stopped in a village a few days later to rest our horses, we saw a neighbor who had traveled from our part of the country on horseback. He had passed our place on the day after we left. Every building had been burned to the ground, he told us, and the land itself looked as if a battle had raged there; the wheat was down and the crops were burned, and holes had been dug everywhere, as if the invaders had hunted for hidden treasure."

"Your father has the pumpkin now?"

"It is safe in his possession—though why he refused its weight in gold I cannot see. But I think he would not be pleased that I have told all this about it, although I know that the secret is safe with you. Now tell me something of yourself. This man whom you called uncle—is he your father's brother?"

"That he is. My mother and father died in the plague that spread through the town when I was small. He is a master of arts in the university and a very great scholar," she added proudly. "His name is Nicholas Kreutz, and among those most famed in the university in alchemy he is indeed the greatest. He is not a servant of the Church, though a good Christian, and he seeks, as do many others, the secretsof his craft."

The scholar-alchemist appeared suddenly in the doorway and smiled at them.

"I have just ascertained," he said, seating himself at the table, "that if it pleases your father, there is a haven for you all here in this very house. There is not much to pay, and a shelter, however lowly, is better than the sky when light falls. Your father might sell his pair of horses—horses bring a good price at present, I hear—and he could live here until some suitable employment appears. Unless," he added, "the place is too humble—"

"Indeed that cannot be," said the boy eagerly. "Gladly at this minute will he welcome ally roof for the sake of my mother, who is somewhat tired after the long journey from the Ukraine. I cannot go too swiftly to tell him of this news. But only assure me that you are in sober earnest about this matter."

Elzbietka sprang up from her chair. "Did you but know him as well as I, you would not doubt."

At that the alchemist enveloped her with his long arms, from which hung the black sleeves of his gown, until she smiled out from the embrace at Joseph like one caught between the wings of a great raven or crow.

"Hurry and tell your people," she commanded him, "and bring them back here. Indeed, I never knew what a mother was. If I but please her—"

"That you will," shouted Joseph. "I will go as soon as Pan Kreutz unlocks the door for me below."

"Tell your people that it is the door beneath us that is unoccupied," directed the alchemist as he let the boy out through thegate. "There are only two rooms there, a large and a small one, but they will serve your purposes for the time, I believe."

Joseph thanked him with all his heart and set out on the run for the market place. The Street of the Pigeons seemed to unwind before him as he ran, and he was soon in the street leading directly to the Cloth Hall.

Turning there, past one corner of the Town Hall, he ran directly by the cloth markets and headed for the little church near which his father had unloosed the horses. But no sooner had his eyes fallen upon the wagon and his father and mother standing in it, than he stopped suddenly in astonishment. Then, like an arrow leaving a bow, he darted forward, for what he saw set his heart beating faster than it had beaten in all that eventful day.

The stranger that they had left in the mud by the roadside that morning stood by the side of the wagon with a crowd of ruffians at his heels, threatening and shouting at Pan Andrew and his wife. The stranger carried a huge club, and the ruffians, of whom he appeared to be the leader, were armed with staves and stones and were shouting angrily, as if intent on harming the man and woman above them. Pan Andrew, in facing them, had stepped in front of his wife, to shield her if stones were thrown; and the sight of the resistance, and the cries of the leader and his attackers, soon brought a huge crowd surging about the wagon, for it was now close on to noon, and the morning's business of the market was well-nigh finished and many citizens and farmers were eating or resting in the shade of the trees about the square.

Joseph darted through the crowd and leaped up on the wagon, to stand by his father's side.

"Ha, we have the cub as well," shouted the one who had boasted of the name Ostrovski in the early morning. "He is a wizard like unto the father, and a witch like the mother, for it was he who made my horse fly straight up to heaven this morning with a blow upon the flank."

At that, a great skulk in the crowd let fly a stone at the three, which missed Pan Andrew but narrowly.

"Magicians, wizards, witches," hooted the crowd.

"It is the man who is the worst," shouted the self-named Ostrovski. "It is he who hath bewitched my brother and cut off his head and changed the head into a pumpkin. If he be honest, let him deliver that pumpkin over to me in the sight of all, that I may give Christian burial to my brother's brains.... An' he will not, let him face my charge. He is a wizard, yea, and one condemned by Church and court and precept. At him! Kill him! But save me the pumpkin which is the head of my brother!"

Absurd as these accusations seem today, they did not seem so in the fifteenth century. For men were then but beginning to see the folly of many superstitions and cruelties that had been prevalent since the Dark Ages; they believed that certain persons had malign powers such as could transform others into strange animals; they thought that by magic, men could work out their spite upon others in horribly malicious ways; that food could be poisoned by charms and milk made sour.

And to raise the cry of wizard against a man, no matter how peace-loving and innocent he might be, was enough to start rough and brutal men, yes, and women, too, into active persecution and unlawful deeds.

This was the method that the stranger had adopted in order to get his revenge upon Pan Andrew, and not only revenge, but that which he sought even more keenly, the possession of the pumpkin that the country gentleman had refused to deliver to him early in the day. He had been about the city seeking out certain friends or followers in order to raise the cry of wizard, and then he had with them searched through the city until they came upon Pan Andrew and his wife.

"The pumpkin, the pumpkin—it is my brother's head," he kept shouting.

Pan Andrew, on his side, only smiled back derisively upon him, and gathered in the pumpkin where no man could seize it without taking as well a blow from his heavy sword, and the attackers, being more cowards than men, made no attempt to approach the wagon at the side that he was facing. Some, armed with large stones, were, however, sneaking around to get behind him, and others in front were preparing to send a volley of missiles upon him, when there rushed into the turmoil a man of venerable appearance, clad in a brown robe with large puffy sleeves and pointed hood. He was of moderate stature, firm of gait, and bore himself like a man in the prime of life.

A priest he might have been, a brother of some order he seemed, but a scholar he was certainly, for there was that in his face and a droop to the shoulders that proclaimed him a man of letters.

"Cease—cease—cowards all!" he shouted in a commanding tone of voice. "What persecution goes on here?"

"The man and the woman and boy are workers in magic, wizards and a witch," said the leader roughly. "Keep your hands off,for we are admonishing them."

"Wizards and witches—fiddlesticks!" shouted the newcomer, pulling himself up in the wagon until he stood beside Pan Andrew. "This is but an excuse for some such deed of violence as this city has seen too much of in the past twelve months. To attack an honest man—for to any but a blind man he appears as honest—a weak woman, and a defenseless boy—Cowards all, I say! Disperse, or I will call the king's guards to disperse you."

"It is Jan Kanty himself," said one of the rioters in a loud whisper that all about him heard. "I'm off, for one." And throwing his stick to the ground, he took to his heels.

If there had been no magic in Pan Andrew, his wife, or his boy, there was magic in the name of Jan Kanty, and a very healthy magic, too, for at once every hat in that crowd came off, and men began to look askance at each other as if caught in some shameful thing.

"The good Jan Kanty," was whispered on every side, and in the briefest second imaginable the crowd had melted until there remained not one person, not even the leader of the ruffians who had begun the attack.

IV. THE GOOD JAN KANTY

Among the most remarkable personages of Krakow's age of glory in the fifteenth century was a certain scholar-priest by the name of Jan Kanty. He had been educated at the University of Krakow in the period of late Scholasticism when the chief teachings were still mere expositions of the seven arts, of which grammar was the king. However, a full life and much contact with men had made Jan Kanty a well-rounded man. He loved learning for its own sake, but he honored most of all its precepts and its application to life, and he gave himself over in his cell-like quarters on the lower floor of the old university building (now long since destroyed by fire), to the creation of new points of view on old subjects, to comments on the conduct and opinions of the masters and doctors of the university at the great church councils of Europe, and to an intellectual chronicle of his age.

His life was saintly and his cell was as much visited, perhaps, as is his shrine in the magnificent old university library today. The peasants loved him especially, and this was rather curious since the men from the farms rarely sought the advice of the men of the university; they were, in fact, somewhat shy of the dispensers of higher learning. They were not shy of Jan Kanty, however. They came to Krakow to ask his opinion on the weather in the seasons of grains and vegetables, they called upon him for decisions in disputesbetween landowners, they consulted him concerning the proper kind of food for their livestock, they questioned him on all problems having to do with morals or religion, and they accepted his rulings with as much finality and satisfaction as if they had been the rulings of Heaven.

Therefore his name was one to be reckoned with everywhere, inside the city and out. He hated above all things cruelty of man against man, or of man against something helpless, a horse, or a dog, or a child. And when he saw one man and a woman and a boy of honest features and good appearance harassed by some hundred men, he did not hesitate but rushed into the midst of the flying stones without regard to his own safety or comfort.

"Peace be with you," he said to Pan Andrew when the crowd had scattered, "and with you, my daughter," putting his hand upon the woman's head. "What may be the cause of such mischance? You are strangers here?"

"Strangers and worse. Homeless," said Pan Andrew.

"You are come from a long distance?"

"The Ukraine."

The kind shoulders rocked in agitation. "My—my—but surely you have friends in town?"

"I have none. I had a friend here and sought him, but he is dead. My house is burned by Tartars, my wealth is gone. I am pursued by men who seek my life and the one possession that I have left." Here he touched the pumpkin with his foot.

"But why this accusation of magic?"

Pan Andrew smiled. "A trick it was to raise feelings against me in the public square and then to despoil me of this possession. Ithink that he who raised the storm against me here has followed me many miles across the border, and I believe that he is the agent of some more powerful person. There is much to this, my good—my good—You are a priest?"

"Men call me so. I am but a servant of the Father of us all."

"Then, good father, hear me! I seek to do no man wrong. I am helpless in a world of plotting and troubles, and I seek only a place where I may this night provide shelter for my good wife and my boy."

"Come with me then," said the scholar-priest. "I will at least offer you the hospitality that my cell affords.... Nay—hitch your horses to the wagon and drive through that lane yonder which leads to the Street of St. Ann."

Pan Andrew was already adjusting the harness when Joseph tugged at his sleeve. "Father," he urged, "Father, I know of a place where we can stay."

The father looked down at him in astonishment. "You," he answered, "you? And how did you find such a place?"

"A scholar and his niece live there. They took me to their house. There is a space below them at the head of a flight of stairs."

Jan Kanty interposed. "Come at any rate to my dwelling, and there we can make plans. If the boy has found a place, and his face and words seem truthful, then we can talk at better length there at our ease than here in the busy square."

A few minutes later they stopped in front of the largest of a number of buildings, which made up the university. On the way there Joseph had noted that almost every man they passed on the street had doffed his hat to Jan Kanty, and once a whole company ofknights had saluted him with drawn swords. He seemed to pay but little attention to these courtesies, however, for his mind was busy with the problem of the present, and when he alighted from the cart and led the three to his little cell on the ground floor just at the right of the door, he was still pondering.

Once inside the house, however, Pan Andrew, disregarding Joseph's information for the minute, begged an immediate audience with Jan Kanty alone, and while the boy and his mother were eating some food which the scholar had placed upon a table in the corridor just outside his cell, he began to address his host in a low tone.

Their voices buzzed as Joseph and his mother ate. Only once did the boy catch distinct syllables, and that was when the priest asked Pan Andrew, "That, then, is the pumpkin that you have brought from the Ukraine?"

Pan Andrew must have nodded, for be made no verbal answer. He had not dropped the precious vegetable from his hands during the entire conversation. Joseph heard no more of the talk, for he began at that moment to tell his mother of his own adventures of the morning.

As he progressed with his story she ceased eating and stared at him. "Why, this is a very miracle," she said. "As soon as Pan Andrew has finished with the good father in the next room, we will go straight about procuring the lodging of which the scholar told you.... And the poor child—she lost her father and mother in the plague? Indeed, I think that God must have sent us to her."

Jan Kanty at the farther end of the cell listened to Pan Andrew's tale to the very end. He asked a few questions, which the other answered, and then the two began to converse rapidly though in lowtones.

At length Jan Kanty passed his hand across his eyes as if thinking very deeply. Then he said, "It seems to me that there is one course open to you. You have enemies in the city, you believe, and therefore you must remain for the present unseen. I advise a change of name, for such subterfuge is no sin where the end to be gained is righteous. For your present needs you can obtain money by selling your horses and cart; if you wish, I will send a man with them to the horse market in the plain below the Wawel. They would be but an encumbrance to you at best, and moreover they will bring a pretty price since they are of good stock and well fed."

"This money will not last me forever," said Pan Andrew. "I must think of some employment besides."

"I have thought of that," continued Jan Kanty. "I know of employment which might suit your case even though it be a humble task."

"It cannot be too humble for me," answered the other quickly, "provided it brings enough return for the support of my wife and boy."

"Good! Excellent!" exclaimed the scholar. "Then I have just the thing. You were a hunter in the old days, I presume?"

"Why, yes," said Pan Andrew, wondering.

"And you can sound the horn?"

"That I can. And if I do say it, with more skill than any hunter in the Eastern Marches."

"Good! ... But yet one thing. This news which you have imparted to me should be for the ears of the king alone. The treasure which you guard should be returned to him; it should become theproperty of the commonwealth. I know not what harm it has already done in the world; I only hope that it may do-no more. Would you leave it with me for safekeeping, perhaps?"

"Would that I could. But it was the oath that I took to my father that it should never leave my hands while life remained—save to one person, and that person the king of Poland."

"Then God be with you. Rest here until the horses are sold and then after hearing your son's story we will think of tomorrow."

He called the mother and boy into his cell. "Why, here," he said on hearing the story of Joseph's adventure from his mother's lips, "is the thing arranged to perfection. I know the place you mention and I know the scholar Kreutz as well. A curious man, and of certain strange disposition, but honest and sincere and a seeker after light. He is, I think, feared by the common people, as are also many dwellers in the next street, which has been since olden times inhabited by sorcerers and their ilk, and the court of his house is but little frequented. They tell strange tales of him, sometimes, most of which I know to be false. But it is just the place for your dwelling at present, since there is little likelihood of your being disturbed there."

At this so great a feeling of thankfulness came upon Joseph's mother that she would have fallen to her knees and asked the good father for his blessing, but he restrained her.

"Nay, daughter," he said, "it is I who need thy blessing, since I know what fortitude and courage thy kind heart possesses."

She kissed his hand nevertheless, as did Joseph immediately afterward, and Pan Andrew turned away quickly lest they should see that his eyes were moist, for there is such power in kindness well bestowed that it touches the wells of human feeling. There was, too,something in this scholar-priest that went at once to the heart, some fine quality of feeling and spirituality that set him apart, though ever so sweetly and gently, from other men.

A servant of the university was dispatched to sell the horses and cart, and Joseph with his father and mother sat down to await the man's return.

While they were waiting, there came a knocking upon the outside door. Jan Kanty went to it at once. A woman stood there, with a baby in her arms, not in the attitude of one asking for alms but of one seeking advice. She came, it seemed, from the Black Village and was suffering much from pains that took her legs and arms and neck.

Jan Kanty questioned her quietly. "Where do you sleep?" he asked.

"On the floor, reverend sir," she answered. "And the aches and pains are so strong that I can stand them no longer. It is certain that a devil possesses me, and I would that you should pray him away."

"Is the door made of stones?"

"It is."

"Are the stones ever wet?"

"No, reverend sir, except in spring."

"Is the earth damp beneath the stones?"

"Why—yes—perhaps," she said. "Sometimes when the well water is not much used it overflows, for there is a source there, and sometimes when they have been drawing water carelessly the overflow leaks down beneath the stones."

"Then take heed to what I say and the aches and pains will pass. Take stones and build a low wall between the well and the side ofyour cottage. Make this waterproof and then dig a drain that will carry the water away from your house. Hang your bedclothes often in the sun and be sure that they are always dry. Change every week the boughs upon which you lie; thus will the pains go away."

She kissed his hand and departed.

Then came a peasant who complained that worms were coming up from the ground and were destroying the young shoots of his plants.

"Could you but say a prayer, father," the man supplicated, "the worms will cease."

"It is for you to prevent them," said Jan Kanty. "Sprinkle all the earth about the plants with ashes which you take from your stove. If this does not prevent the worms, then rise early in the morning and pour water about the plants. The worms will then come to the top where the water is, and you may kill them."

Then stooping over a high desk he began to write upon a long scroll of parchment, the end of which hung far over the desk almost to the floor. He used for writing the quill of a pigeon thrust into a piece of oak wood.

Joseph curled up on a bench that ran along beneath the windows and closed his eyes. What a day it had been! And what might the future hold?

His thoughts, which at first had begun to run slowly, suddenly became brisk and grew fantastic. He seemed to see himself bearing armor, a shield, and a sword, fighting desperately with a great dark-browed Tartar who had instead of a head a huge yellow pumpkin. Then the Tartar suddenly took off his head, and carrying it in his arms, climbed up a steep ladder to a room that seemed to hang fromthe stars. Out of it came lightning and flashes of strangely colored light, and suddenly the Tartar emerged, now with the head of a dog, and the pumpkin floating along beside him as if it were but a ball of feathers in the wind. The scratching of Jan Kanty's quill grew fainter and fainter, and the fantastic world dimmed slowly in blackness.

Joseph was fast asleep.

When he awoke the room was no longer filled with sunshine. A single candle lantern was burning at the farther end of the cell, and by its light he could see his father, Jan Kanty, and his mother busied with something that lay in front of them upon the table. He rubbed his eyes to make sure that he was awake—yes, it was the mysterious pumpkin, from which his father was slicing away the outer rind with a huge knife. It was a curious pumpkin, that vegetable—the rind was so hard and brittle that the knife scraped on it as if it were cutting or whittling away a piece of board. Joseph, fascinated, watched the process, almost afraid to breathe. Little by little the hard pieces dropped to the floor like bits of shell as the blade cut them through.

"I think," the father was saying in a low voice, "that I hold here in my hand the reason for the attack on my house in the Ukraine, and that the man who has hounded us today knew very well what this pumpkin shell contained. He had been told that I had it in my possession; he knew the exact size of my property, and he quickly put two and two together when he saw this pumpkin, and only this pumpkin, in my wagon. The reason that I made no effort to conceal it was, of course, to allay any suspicion concerning it."

"But," interrupted Jan Kanty, "a pumpkin at this time of year is likely to create some curiosity among those who give the matter a second thought. This is a late pumpkin, and I suppose that in allPoland it would be hard to find another such in midsummer."

"True," replied Pan Andrew, "but I had to risk that. Long ago when I was worried over this sacred charge and feared lest some enemy might discover its existence and attempt to rob me, there came to me the idea of a shell like this as an excellent means of concealment. Since that day there has never been a time, summer or winter, when there was not a pumpkin shell in readiness for an emergency, and many an experiment was I obliged to make, indeed, before I was able to preserve a shell in the good condition of this one."

At this moment he cut away the last piece of the rind.

The room was suddenly filled with the light of a thousand candles. Colors of the rainbow fell upon the walls—a huge center of radiance like the sun in the heavens blazed into being at the very place where the pumpkin shell had been but a moment before. Flickering, dancing flecks of light leaped about the room and transformed its gloom into the brilliancy of day—and then there was again but the light of the little lantern, for the father had placed that which the pumpkin contained in a bag furnished by Jan Kanty, and was busy tying up the open side when Joseph came rushing up to the table.

"Father," he cried, "what was it? What was the light which came from that which you took from the pumpkin?"

The father's voice was kindly but firm. "In time, Joseph, you shall know. It would be but a care to you, a matter of more worry than you suspect, if you knew what responsibility we are carrying here. If it is mere curiosity, be assured that knowledge will bring nothing but pain. If it is real interest, I will tell you plainly that indue time you shall be informed of all that has passed. Just now—it has cost me so much that I have not the heart to burden your young life with its secrets."

He broke off, and after a short silence, changed the subject.

"We will go now to that place which you have found for us. While you slept the reverend father and I have been to see your friends. He has seen to it that the rooms have been made comfortable, and there we shall stay, at least for the present."

V. IN THE STREET OF THE PIGEONS

St. Ann's Street was as black as pitch when they emerged from the habitation of the scholar-priest. He insisted on accompanying them and carried his little candle lantern for aid, which, though it threw a faint light upon the ground a step or two ahead, yet had not much more light than the stars which shone down from a moonless sky. Pan Andrew, with his wife on his right arm, followed Jan Kanty, and Joseph brought up the rear. They had taken but a few steps along the narrow footwalk by the side of the road when something damp and clammy was forced into the boy's right hand; he gave a little startled jump, but reassured himself at the next minute that it was nothing but the nose of a stray dog that had sought his hand as a token of friendly greeting.

And as I live, thought Joseph as he reached down and felt a great shaggy head, it's like the wolf dog that leaped at Elzbietka this very day. Yes—it's about the same size—and here: the collar is exactly the same that I had my fingers through. I know its feel by those little knobs that almost tear the flesh.

"Father! Father!" he called.

Pan Andrew turned about quickly. "What is it?"

"A dog," answered the boy, "a friendly dog."

"Bring him along with us," said the father with a laugh, "we can't have too many friends just now." And at that they continued ontheir way.

Now of all the creatures that God has put in the world a dog is the most curious, and sometimes, one might think, the most discerning. For when this same animal had broken loose in the morning, his first impulse, which he had followed, had been that of flight. His second impulse was to look for a friend, since no dog can live without a friend. The Tartar boy had already departed. The dog had seen too much of him as it was. Also by virtue of a rare instinct which dogs, and sometimes horses, possess, the wolf dog had realized fully that the boy who had leaped at his collar was not an enemy. Perhaps it was the boy's touch, perhaps it was some quality in the tone of his voice, but the animal knew that Joseph was used to dogs and knew as well that he was just in his treatment of them. Therefore he had searched all day throughout the city streets, and when he came upon this little group of people in the dark street his sense of smell told him that here was a dog lover, and marvel of marvels, it was the same dog lover that had sprung upon him earlier in the day!

They turned at length from St. Ann's Street into a side lane that is known today as Jagiellonska, and followed it for a short distance until they reached the Street of the Pigeons. Here they turned to the left and walked for a few steps until suddenly just before them rose a babel of subdued voices. Father Jan Kanty stood stock-still. The others also came to a halt and remained motionless, except for the dog, which strained at Joseph's hold upon his collar.

"Stay," said the scholar, "I will go forward to see what may be in the air." And holding his lantern at the height of his head, he plunged into a crowd of black-robed figures that had formed a circlein the very middle of the street.

"Students," he cried aloud, as he swung his lantern first to this face and then to that, "students. And what devilment make you here now?"

The crowd broke before him at a touch. Either he was much feared by them or greatly respected—that Pan Andrew could see— perhaps both.

"A duel," he exclaimed as he reached the center of the crowd, where a space lighted by a lantern upon the ground had previously been obscured by the bodies of the lookers-on, "and what means it?"

Two young men, both students, with their black university robes lying beside them on the ground, stood facing each other with unfastened under jackets. Slender Italian dueling swords, or foils, held firmly in the clasped fingers of their bared right arms, had clashed the instant before Jan Kanty entered the arena.

"A duel," he repeated. "Do you not know that dueling has been forbidden I know not how many times within these streets bounding the university? Do you not know that it is punishable by fine or imprisonment even, if the duelers are students?"

His hands groped fearlessly for the weapons. "This is no play duel," he cried, as he gathered them in.

Indeed it was not! The young men were fighting with naked rapiers! In most of the students' duels the points of the weapons were capped with buttons to make them less dangerous, or if the engagements were to be with broad-swords, the opponents wore breastplates and heavy gauntlets and helmets. But here stood two young men without a single precaution against injury, and it was quite evident that one of them would have been badly wounded hadnot the scholar brought the fight to an end.

"What means this?" he repeated. "Who may you be?" Holding the lantern close up to the face of the nearer, he cried out suddenly in astonishment. "Johann Tring! As much would I have thought of seeing you here as I would have of seeing our own lord cardinal. You whom I thought more a slave to a crucible than to a sword. And your name?" he thundered at the other.

"Conrad Mlynarki of Mazovia," answered the student, thrusting his weapon back into his girdle and letting his eyes drop for shame.

"A Mazovian! Well, it rejoices me that you are ashamed, and there was perhaps reason for your anger, since I hear that Mazovians are insulted without much thought these days. Go to your room! I will hear your story tomorrow. And you"—he turned to the remnants of the original crowd, those few who remained, maliciously hoping to see punishment meted out to the offenders—"betake yourselves to your bursars with all possible speed, for if I see one of you here when I return, I will notify the authorities in the morning."

"As to you, Johann Tring," he addressed the other student when he stood alone with him in the middle of the street, "are you not ashamed at such a public brawl?"

"I am not," said the student quickly and without flinching at the look which Jan Kanty gave him.

At this moment Pan Andrew and the others came up to them. In the light of the lantern Joseph glanced at the face of the student, Johann Tring, and received almost a shock—a feeling at least of violent repulsion. It was not that the face was distorted, indeed it was not, the eyes were bright and piercing, and the hair was black—the carriage of the body was erect, and the whiteness of theskin where the collar was rolled back stood in remarkable contrast to the hair and the blackness that lay about him. But the nose was thin and mean, the mouth was small and smug, and out of the eyes came a look that signified an utterly selfish spirit behind them. For one so young this expression was strange, and even more than strange; it was unnatural, and this unnaturalness was more apparent, even, to a boy of Joseph's age than it might have been to an older and maturer man who was used to much selfishness and meanness in the world.

"Now what caused this quarrel?" Joseph heard the scholar ask the question rather sharply.

"It is too long to tell at once—"

"Yes, but briefly."

"He insulted me."

"What did he say?"

"More things than one, but chiefly chided me about my studies. Asked me if I had learned yet how to make gold out of iron or brass or leather and said that he would collect old shoes all over the city if I would transmute them into precious metal."

"And this upon no provocation?"

The young man hesitated, yet there was something compelling about Jan Kanty that caused men to speak the truth to him. "I did ask him if the frogs in the north country spoke Mazovian," he answered in a rather sour voice.

"Yes, and I thought it was something like this," spoke Jan Kanty quickly. "Why must one always aggravate these Mazovians to their swords? I warn you here and now that, swordsman though you may be, the Mazovians are much more nimble with blades than with tongue."

"But he said further," went on Tring in self-justification, and being unable to express himself clearly in Polish, continued in German, much to Joseph's distress, for he could not understand a word.

"Have more caution, Tring," said the scholar at length. "Since you are not enrolled as a regular student of the university you must be even more careful in your conduct than if you were.... Since it is you who have first drawn your weapon, it must be you who make peace. Go tomorrow at dawn and kiss your opponent upon the cheek and sue him for pardon."

This advice sat hard upon Tring's temper, but he was so much influenced by the scholar that he finally bowed his head in consent.

"And further than this I might say, Johann Tring, that such occurrences bring you no credit. I know not much of your studies these days, though I think sometimes that you keep company more with necromancers and astrologers of little merit than with such worthy men as Pan Kreutz and his equals. These are dark days when men look with suspicion upon all who engage in investigation whether it be honest or dishonorable, godly or selfish. Are you still at Kreutz's?"

"I am."

"Then come with us, since we are bound for his dwelling. This Pan and his wife are taking the rooms below Kreutz's."

The young man tried to peer into the darkness beyond the lantern light to see who the new tenants might be, but none of the Charnetskis was visible.

They walked ahead a few steps until they came to the door where Joseph had been in the afternoon. Jan Kanty reached up andpulled the wire, which hung down from above the door, and in a few minutes an old bent woman with a lantern scrutinized their faces from the open doorway and admitted them.

"All will be well now," said Joseph's father. "We need not trouble you further."

"It has been otherwise than trouble," protested the scholar. "You will be well and comfortable, I am sure, for all the arrangements have been made. Tomorrow I shall send you the man who will tell you of your new duties. And now good night to you, Pan Andrew— Kovalski"—he hesitated a bit over the assumed name—"and may peace be with you."

"And with you." They all repeated it.

The kindly figure of the gentle, loving, saintly old man passed out into the darkness again. The woman slammed the door and bolted it heavily when the Charnetskis—now the Kovalskis—Johann Tring, and the dog were inside.

"At last," said Pan Andrew, "we are at home."

They passed through the passage with its pointed arches and emerged into the court, the woman leading the way with her lantern. Here Tring bade them good night and went to his room on the right-hand side of the court. Joseph felt at parting from him something of the same dislike that he had experienced when the lantern light had fallen upon his face in the street; the face was one that might easily come to haunt a man in his dreams, and yet it was in daylight but an ordinary face, like that of a thousand other students who possessed neither the gift of beauty nor the curse of ugliness—yet in that yellow gleam of the lantern there had been upon the features some indefinable threat of malignity.

The woman led them to the stairway on the left. As they ascended these same stairs that Joseph had climbed earlier in the day, the whole staircase seemed even more shaky and rickety than it had appeared in the light of day. The woman moved ahead of them freely, but Pan Andrew and his wife and Joseph clung to the railing as if for protection in case the boards should fall away beneath their feet.

At the first landing the door stood open. Out from this door came the welcome beam of a candle, lighted by the hands of Elzbietka Kreutz. The father with this candle in his hand at once inspected the little quarters. There were but two rooms, one of them fortunately large and of good shape, so that while one end of it must serve as a bedroom for Pan Andrew and his wife, there was ample room at the other end for the general living quarters of the family. The smaller room at the back Joseph would sleep in. The woman who had opened the door had been busy all the evening preparing the place for occupancy, expending some of the money which Pan Andrew had given her for bare necessities, a rug, wooden eating utensils, chairs, and beds.

He had left his name as Andrew Kovalski with the woman, the name which had been agreed upon with Jan Kanty, a name in itself one of the most common, since it signified a smith—and the alchemist and his niece having been advised of the kinship with the Tenczynskis, willingly pledged silence concerning the true name.

"Well, wife," said Pan Andrew when they were alone and the door fastened, "this is better than we dared hope." There upon he laid down upon the table in the large room the precious round parcel which had not left his hands at any time since they had set out fromJan Kanty's cell. "Best of all we are safe here; the door is heavy, the front of the building is of stone, and from the rear no one could climb over the wall without danger to himself. It is, indeed, the wall of a monastery to which none but monks have access. Above us is the alchemist Kreutz, and below on the ground floor are the old woman and her son, both of whom take care of the building and watch the gate at night. Across the way live a few students; one of them this Johann Tring who accompanied us. Those seeking us would never think of looking for us here; the change in name is also a protection. Here we may stay in comfort until such time as we may communicate with the king."

He intended to say more, but was interrupted by a curious sound that came from outside, as if a heavy body were dragging itself along. The mother uttered a little cry of fear; Pan Andrew reached for the handle of his short sword, but Joseph broke into a laugh.

"It is my dog rubbing against the door," he said. "He is tired and hungry, and no doubt wants a little water. There is a well in the court below from which I will draw it, and he can sleep then in the shelter of the wail. Tomorrow I must procure a chain or rope to fasten him with, for he is nearly wild and might cause trouble if he ran about." With this, Joseph searched in a basket for a bit of meat and a piece of bread, and finding them, descended to the court below. It was dark there but his mother held the lantern above him so that he could see to draw water and settle the dog in a corner of the wall.

When they returned his father was preparing for bed. The valuable package had been disposed of somewhere; with curious eyes Joseph scanned every inch of the large room and came to the conclusion that the only hiding place in the quarters was thatafforded by the bed, either in the shadowy place beneath it, or somewhere in the bedding or folded clothes beneath the headrest.

He ceased to wonder very long about it, however, for his eyelids were heavy, despite his sleep of the afternoon. The whole world drifted off into oblivion, it seemed, the minute that he laid his head on the stuffed bag that served for a pillow.

The next day all were astir early. The mother was at work polishing the woodwork, and the father was driving nails to strengthen the cheap chairs, or covering cracks in the wall, and later inspecting the old staircase outside the building to see if he might mend it. The daylight inspection brought with it some satisfaction, for while it confirmed his belief that the staircase was shaky, yet it revealed that the underpinnings were firmer than might be supposed. The staircase might last for some years if it did not have rough usage, and certainly there was no immediate danger, as Pan Andrew had feared the night before.

Joseph took an early opportunity, after he had eaten the breakfast brought by the old woman who lived below, to run forth into the Street of the Pigeons with the dog, whom he named at once Wolf. In the daytime the street wore little of the sinister aspect that it carried at night; the little oval windows that had seemed then like wicked eyes peering down, now were more like the eyes of merry gnomes or pixies. The buildings which in the twilight, or even in the nighttime when lights fell upon them, seemed grotesque or terrible, in the light of day seemed only curiously twisted out of shape and hung out and bent inward in every conceivable fashion. All the lower windows bore heavy iron bars; doors carried great metal hinges that spread like trees over the surface of the hard wood, andchains dangled and rattled when the house occupants went in or out. From some windows hung clothes—women's clothing, long hose worn by men, jackets, and here and there, a student's black gown. The novelty of the street attracted the boy, and for a long time he wandered through it curiously.

At the upper end, where it met a cross street that ran toward the Rynek, the Street of the Pigeons curved quite sharply. Joseph finally ran with the dog clear to this cross street, which bore the name Bracka, and then, retracing his steps, bore back to the house which had now become his home. Mounting the steps rather breathlessly, he threw open the door to the outer room and was about to shout a merry greeting, as was his usual custom, but checked himself at sight of a stranger who stood talking with his father. The newcomer, who had a pleasant face, was dressed in leathers somewhat like those of the night watch when the outer chain armor is removed. On the table in front of the men lay a long brass trumpet, made cunningly and polished until it resembled gold.

By the side of the trumpet lay two parchment scripts, one of them evidently a copy of a long piece of writing, the other—as Joseph could see—a set of musical notes worked carefully in red and black.

"This," said the stranger, pointing first to the script containing the writing, "is a copy of the oath that you have already sworn. This other is the music of the Heynal, the hymn which you must play from the church tower every hour of the night. The trumpeter whom you relieve tonight will give you the key to the tower room, and what information you may need. It is a noble piece of work, this sounding of the Heynal, and I am much pleased that Father Jan hasbeen able to find so good a Pole as you to carry out the night duties." With this, he kissed Pan Andrew upon the right cheek and departed.

Joseph stared in frank amazement. The Heynal! The church tower. And his father!

"I will tell you everything," said the father as they sat down to the noonday meal. "This oath which I have sworn is the customary oath taken by the watchman-trumpeter of the tower of the Church of Our Lady Mary. You may read it at your leisure. The music is the hymn with the broken note of which I have promised to tell you the story soon. It is played each hour from the windows in the octagon room at the top of the higher tower."

"And you are to be the trumpeter?" asked Joseph.

"I am, thanks to the good Jan Kanty," the father answered. "The trumpeter and the watchman as well, for it is from this tower that fires throughout the city are sighted and the alarm given with the big bell. For the present it must be for our own safety that we are known as the Kovalski family, a name which Father Jan has given us. As plain Andrew Kovalski I shall be a mere city dweller of Krakow. I shall be trumpeter, succeeding the man—God rest his soul!—who died but a week ago, since which time there has been a substitute who can play but badly."

"But the man said each hour of the night," exclaimed the boy. "Will you be there all night?"

"Yes," answered Pan Andrew. "It is for my own safety to be abroad in the city only after nightfall. None will recognize me then—and as for you, my son, the good father has arranged that you shall attend the Collegium Minus here, to complete your studies, which I and your tutors have already begun with you. But there mustbe caution employed even by you, for there are people who seek nothing better than to find us and despoil us of our treasure. You may take your exercises with the other boys very soon, however, and go abroad with discretion, for in the clothes, which I shall buy you there will be no danger, I think, that you may be recognized. A close mouth is necessary nevertheless. Tell no one of our adventures and be content for the time with the plain name Joseph Kovalski."

Thus, at the direction of the good Jan Kanty, Pan Andrew became Pan Kovalski—Joseph was to be sent to school—and the watchtower of the Church of Our Lady Mary was to see a new trumpeter.

At the moment that the father had ceased speaking, there came running into the room from the staircase the girl Elzbietka Kreutz, who made straight for Joseph's mother and was caught into her arms. "We shall be happy here," the woman exclaimed, "that I know, and here is one that needs a mother's love." The girl turned to smile to Pan Andrew, whose face grew gentle at the sight of her eyes, and he picked up her slim, dainty hand and kissed it—it was indeed a picture, that fragile white hand lying in his huge brown palm.

"Uncle has told me," she said, "that you are to play the trumpet at the church. Often at night, when I lie awake lonely and have strange fears, I listen for the music from the steeple. And now when I know that it is Joseph's father that is playing I shall go to sleep again and fear nothing."

"It is as if I had two children," said Pan Andrew, slipping one arm about the child and the other about his son. "It truly seems as if God has once more smiled upon us."

VI. THE TOWER OF THE TRUMPETER

One of the great sights of central Europe, even in those faraway days, which men came from all parts of the world to see, was the Church of Our Lady Mary in Krakow. Now, though this church rose majestically over the medieval city, its towers visible from afar, and its red brick walls as substantial and as solid as the very rock base of the Wawel Hill itself, it was not from the outside such an imposing sight as was its more aristocratic sister, the Wawel Cathedral. It lacked flying buttresses and distinct Gothic ornamentation, such as huge gargoyles and flowers and saints carved in stone, though its graceful form indicated a solid and magnificent strength. It was not a church such as one might gaze upon in sunny France, where the mild breezes and sweet sunshine permit delicate carvings and pinnacles upon the outside walls, but it was built like a solid fortress to withstand the mighty storms that sometimes sweep over Poland from the wild steppes or from the Baltic Sea. It was the interior of this church, however, that drew men to it, for within, it was a very miracle of beauty, a crystal hidden in a shapely stone.

It was to this church, then, that Pan Andrew and Joseph wended their way after darkness fell on their first day in the new dwelling. Pan Andrew carried the trumpet under his right arm. Near the base of the higher tower a watchman spied them as they approached, and unlocked a small, heavy door that led to the tower stairs. They wentup a narrow staircase, winding about in the darkness, until it reached a platform where the interior of the tower loomed suddenly above them. Just at the right, as they began their ascent in the main body of the tower, was a door that led to a little chapel in which, as Joseph learned afterward, prisoners condemned to death spent their last hours on earth.

A man carrying a lantern shouted to them from above; they waited then until he had descended—he was the day watchman whom Pan Andrew relieved. He paused to kiss Pan Andrew upon the cheek in welcome, and to speak a few words in explanation of his duties above. Then he placed in his hand the lantern and a key to the room, which the trumpeter was to occupy in the high tower. He wished them luck on their first night and then descended by the side staircase to the ground, where the watchman let him out. Joseph and his father in the meantime began to climb the steps of the scaffolding that led up into the tower. This scaffolding was held in place by crossbeams, and at its edge ran the steps, so built that as a man ascended he passed constantly from one of the four sides of the tower to another side. The staircase was steep and narrow, but very solid, so solid that the stairs did not creak as they ascended.

They climbed and climbed, past five levels of windows glassed in with small white globes of solid crystal. Up and up went father and son, until they reached the level where there was a room for the watchman. This octagonal room was divided into two sections, one being the room where the trumpeter might keep warm between watches, the other being the open space around it, from which the turret windows looked out over the city. Here hung extra trumpets, here were the ropes, which connected with the great bell hanging inthe lower tower, and here were the red flags and the lanterns, which were hung out when a fire was perceived from the tower.

For it was the duty of the trumpeter to watch constantly for fires. He was to watch also for troops approaching the city, for tumults or disturbances of any kind, but he was especially the guardian against fires. Conflagrations had done the city much harm in the past; many of the older buildings were of wood, although fronted with stone, and roofs were often of thatch or soft wood that easily caught fire from sparks. When a fire was discovered, the trumpeter or watchman, for he was both, hung a red flag from the window which faced the direction in which the blaze lay. At night he would hang out a lantern with a red glass front instead of the flag.

It was his duty also to sound the alarm bell if any danger whatever came to threaten the lives of citizens. In the very month previous to the coming of Pan Andrew and his family to Krakow, the watchman had rung loud and long upon the bell to alarm the watch and the city when the riot against the Tenczynski family took place. In the coming year the bell was to be tolled at the execution, in the Town Square just below the tower, of the four men charged with causing the riot. The tower was indeed the very center of Krakow activity.

Pan Andrew fitted his key to the lock of the door leading into the inner room and threw back the bolt. Entering after his father, Joseph found himself in a small comfortable room containing a table, a bed, a small stove, and a lighted lantern hanging on the wall. About the table were three chairs, wedged rather tightly because of the lack of space, and upon the table was a huge hourglass, one of the largest that Joseph had ever seen. The sand pouring through itin a fine stream had filled the lower section almost to a level graded on the glass with a Latin "X" to designate the tenth hour. The glass was in reality a twelve-hour glass, and lines and Latin numerals had been marked upon it just after the maker had blown it into shape, when the material was still soft. This was the trumpeter's official clock. There was on the south side of the nave roof, where the sun touched at all hours of the day, a large sundial which was read each noon, and on the north wall of the tower was a clock with one hand. This hand, which indicated the hours, was in truth a hand—a piece of metal shaped like a double fist—with fingers curled and the index pointing out to the hours.

When the sand had reached the level of the glass at which the "X" was cut, Pan Andrew hastened out to the open section of the tower and released a coil of rope that hung on a pillar in the center of the space. This rope ran down through a hole in the flooring, until it reached the level of the lower tower, when it swung about over a piece of round wood that served as a pulley

and leaped from there to the lower tower through an aperture that was originally designed as a narrow window through which to shoot arrows in time of defense. In the lower tower the rope was connected with one end of an iron hammer that was suspended above the great bell. When the rope was pulled the hammer descended, but it sprang quickly back to its original position when the rope was loosed, a spring of twisted metal and leather serving to draw it back. Pan Andrew pulled once—the hammer descended—boom—the stroke of the bell sounded over the whole city. He pulled again and again until the full quota of ten strokes was made.

Next he went to the side of the tower nearest the entrance to the little room and swung back a small glass window. Through this space he thrust the trumpet and began to play. It was on the West Side, the side toward the Cloth Hall, with the university in the distance. Then he moved to another window but one and began to play toward the south. Likewise he played toward the east, and finally toward the north, according to the instructions which he had received. Lights were twinkling now all over the city below him; the air was soft and smelled of the freshly cut grass which the peasants gather into piles. In the direction of the university a group of men were chanting a hymn. A clashing of iron hoofs on the stones of Grodzka Street betokened the presence of some armed men, perhaps the servitors of some nobles' houses at the castle, or perhaps members of the royal guard. Men of the night watch could be heard banging at doors of shops with the butts of their spears to be sure that no careless apprentice or servant had left the door ajar. Down below, in the graveyard, the white stones were just perceptible, dim and gray in the dusk; and over the way, the lamplighter was enkindling the huge wicks of the lamps that hung under the Cloth Hall roof. The stars were coming out, one after another, in the sky, where a touch of blue still lingered—across this world rang the notes of the hymn which Pan Andrew had just played exquisitely, the Heynal, or Hymn to the Holy Mother.

"It is wondrous sweet," said Joseph.

"It is so, my son," replied the father. Thereupon he told the boy of the morning, years before, when the square below them had been full of hostile Tartars; of the lad who had kept his oath, even with the last breath of life itself; and of the honor paid him from that day to this by the tower trumpeters who end the Heynal at the broken note.

And Joseph, listening with eyes shining and heart throbbing, realized more at that moment than ever before how dear to him was his native land and all the customs that had been bequeathed by brave men and women who had made it great forever among all nations; it seemed as if tears were forcing themselves to his eyes as he thought of the sacrifice of that young life so many years before, but a thrill of pride drove back the tears when he thought of the nobility of the deed, as he stood silently gazing out of the little tower window.

They re-entered the inner room.

"I have brought you here tonight," Pan Andrew explained when he had closed the door and hung the trumpet on the wall, "in order to instruct you in the duties of the trumpeter of this church. For there might come a time when I should be ill, or perhaps even wounded— who knows, since I have so many enemies? I have taken the oath that I will play this trumpet each hour, and that it is no vain oath you have learned from the story which I have just told you. The trumpet must be played, happen what will. Therefore"—he drew out a piece of parchment and sketched on it with a bit of charcoal a series of lines—"you are to learn by heart the notes which I sketch here."

"Here are the notes of the Heynal," he continued after he had worked silently some minutes upon his composition, "the tune goes like this." He hummed the melody and indicated on the parchment how each symbol represented a note.

"This," he said, "it is necessary to learn. Work upon it during the coming week, and at this time next week be able to write it out. Do not let it interfere with your work at the collegium but glance at it in spare time. Also, if you can, sing to yourself beneathyour breath the melody of the Heynal. When you have learned the melody, I will teach you to play it upon the trumpet. It is not a hard task, although perfection comes only after much effort. I will teach you single tongue and double tongue, and triple tongue, which is the queen of the trumpeter's music, just as grammar is king of the scholastic kingdom."

Joseph slipped the parchment inside his coat.

"And now," directed the father, "go down the stairs quickly and run with dispatch to our house. As you descend leave the lantern against the wall on the lowest tower level; be sure that you extinguish it. The mother is waiting and may be already lonely."

"Nay, I left her with Elzbietka."

"Bless the child. But, just the same, go with all speed, for city streets are dangerous at night. Keep close to the watchmen where possible, and if asked why you are out so late, reply that your father is trumpeter in the tower and that you are returning home with a message from him."

Joseph descended; he left the extinguished lantern at the place where the steps begin to mount the scaffolding and felt his way down the stone steps to the tower door. There he rapped, until the watchman let him out. Once in the street he was off like the wind, until he found himself in the Street of the Pigeons.

Much to his surprise the entrance door was opened, not by the old woman who saw to the care of the building, but by her son, who up to this time had kept himself well out of sight. As the light from the lantern fell upon his face, Joseph drew back in alarm; when his father had mentioned the fact that the old woman was living with her son, Joseph had imagined that the son was a youth, or perhapsa boy—he did not expect to see a man who had the face of one of middle age. Yet the term "man" was less applicable to the son than was the word "creature," for he was lank and thin and bowed over uncannily; long wisps of hair fell about his eyes; his fingers were bony and claw like; his cheeks were sunken, and his eyes peered out of hollow caverns as if they feared the light. As he moved ahead of Joseph, with the lantern in his hand, he clung to the wall as does a cat, shunning open spaces and skulking as if always needing a rear defense.

At the foot of the stairs he stopped.

Joseph was about to pass him and begin the ascent when the creature raised one of his hands and passed it over the boy's shoulder. Joseph heard the long nails scraping on his coat—in a horrible second it seemed as if he could feel them on his skin. The perspiration broke out on his forehead.

"What do you want?"

"A little—little coin," whispered the man.

Joseph handed him a piece of copper gladly.

"Good boy—good boy," the other mumbled, "bless thee, bless thee. And when you have much that jingles remember Stas. Stas I am, and here I sleep." He pointed at the door standing open on the lower floor, but Joseph's eyes did not follow him. His attention was taken suddenly from Stas by a burst of flame that leaped like a live thing from the tiny window of the loft of the alchemist on the fourth floor. It was just a little flare—a small flame that issued through the opened shutter, which the alchemist usually kept closed—it died down in a second or even less, but for that instant it lighted up the whole court and the surrounding buildings.

"Hey," said the man, pointing upward, "there they have magic that takes a soul away from a body.... See"—there was another dash, brighter than the first and longer continued—"there be devils that come to earth with the fire of hell upon them.... Their servant is the alchemist Kreutz, and they have one among us here on earth that is more like them than like us.... You know whom I mean?" He swung the lantern close to Joseph's face, the boy recoiling fearfully. "The student Tring! He it is that would deal with the devil and give him his soul. Have I not heard him at night as he lay awake in his room on the farther side of the court, mumbling and calling and singing? He it is who is the curse of this house....Well, I must sleep. A good night to you." And he went in through the open door.

VII. IN THE ALCHEMIST'S LOFT

Joseph found himself too sleepy when he was inside his tiny bedroom to give any further attention either to the flashes of light from the loft above or to the mysterious grumblings of Stas. And the beginning of his studies at the Collegium Minus on the following day, drove, for the time being, all matters of lesser importance from his mind. There was an evening a week or more later, however, when the incident recurred to him. He had accompanied his father, as was his custom, to the tower, and returning early, had paused for a moment on the landing outside his door before entering the house. The night was fine and he peered contentedly about over the starlit roofs, the red chimneys, and the black walls. Down below him Wolf started uneasily in his sleep, as if he were dreaming of evil things. From the little window of the room beside the door of his own dwelling there was thrown upon the darkness a faint glimmer from a lamp which signified that his mother was sitting up, perhaps with Elzbietka, who had said earlier in the day that she would come down that evening.

He fell to musing in the sweet calm of the night, as young people will do, and in his musing wondered mightily what might be the importance which his father had attached to the treasure which he had brought to Krakow. It might be a gem worth thousands and thousands of gold zloty—it might be merely a fashioned piece ofglass of value only to the tradesmen who worked in glass. But then, why had it made the impression that it had upon Jan Kanty, and why was the bold stranger so eager to gain possession of it? And why in such a peaceful world must names be changed and goings and comings veiled in a mantle of night? Why—

Flash! Into the night suddenly leaped the same brilliance that had startled him on that earlier evening when he had been alone in the court with Stas. Only, immediately following it now, here came a cry of someone in fright or pain.

The door at the landing above him was thrown open and a figure in white emerged. It began to descend the stairs hurriedly, and as it came near, Joseph saw that it was Elzbietka in her night clothes, over which she had thrown a white coverlid from her bed.

He spoke quickly in order that his presence might not alarm her.

"Elzbietka," he said, "it is I, Joseph. What has happened?"

"My uncle," she cried, "Joseph, I know not what they are doing."

"I thought you were with my mother," he exclaimed.

"I was, but I became sleepy, and she told me to go up and sleep. I did sleep, for some time, too. But then this loud talking and noise began. Joseph," she came close up to him, "Joseph, I am frightened. Something is going on upstairs that is not good. The student Tring is with my uncle always now. He came early in the evening, and they have been there together ever since. Uncle never used to go up there at night before—he stayed with me. Joseph, I fear that student Tring."

"I know what you feel," he said.

"I believe that he has some power over people that is not of thisearth," she continued. "You do not know how much my uncle has changed since he first knew him. And I am all alone."

"What did you hear tonight?" asked the boy.

"I was wakened by a loud tramping on the floor. Then my uncle said, 'No, that will kill.' Then the student laughed a terrible laugh. After that there was a long, long silence. I was almost asleep again when I heard another voice—it was like to no one that I had ever heard before. There was something about it that made me think it was my uncle speaking, but it was in such a tone that it made my blood run cold. And now there are those flashes of light. Joseph, if you would serve me, climb the stairway and look through the casement. Do not let them see you, and do not stay long. Come down as soon as you can and tell me that my uncle is alive and well."

"I will. But first you go in and stay with mother. You can sleep here tonight if you wish, and tomorrow I will ask my father what can be done."

He knocked at the door, but without waiting for his mother to come, ran up the second flight of stairs and reached out for the first board of the rude staircase. When he had found it he managed the ascent by clinging to the rail at the side, for the steps here were much steeper than those below; indeed, in the dark it seemed to him a dizzy bit of a climb, but he managed it nimbly and found when he reached the landing that he could just peep in through one corner of the opened window shutter. Had the shutter been closed, as it usually was, he could have seen nothing, for the glass, consisting of little round uneven blocks, was unglazed and set into a network of lead. Through the opening he peered, clinging to the railing of the stairsfor support, and keeping one foot close to the top step, in order to descend in haste at the first hint that the occupants of the room were aware of the presence of a third person.

What he saw at first glance startled him, for the loft was literally blazing with light coming from oils burning in four copper braziers which hung from the ceiling. Above these braziers, to protect the roof from the heat, were layers of metal, one separated from the other, so that an air current played between them and cooled them. A fifth brazier, not now alight, hung close to the window where Joseph was peering, and it was from this brazier that the dame had sprung that had lighted up the whole court—as a matter of fact, the light had come from the rapid combustion of a handful of powder which the alchemist had thrown on the brazier's charcoal.

The loft itself was higher than the boy had realized—there was but one large room in it, for on the farther side could be seen the shutters of the building's outer wall. In the middle of the room at the back was a closet—for Pan Kreutz's most valuable substances, Joseph decided, since it was fastened with chains as well as with a huge lock and key. The beams of the roof, sloping but slightly, were well above the height of a tall man and were not of bare wood, as is common in lofts and attics, but were plastered over with some thick white substance.

In the center of the room stood a tripod supporting an iron basin, and in it was burning some substance that gave a peculiar pungent odor.

The alchemist in his black robe and the student Tring in his leather jacket sat elbow to elbow before this basin. They were watching something that was burning there in flames of many colors.

"It takes away my strength," Joseph heard the alchemist tell Tring, "to experiment in the fashion which you have suggested. It has interested me, and I know that it has its fascination, but it is not, after all, in my sphere. I am an alchemist, one who seeks the truth above all things in the actions and reactions of material substances. I mix vinegar and sugar and soda, and there is immediately a bubbling and a change. Something new is created. I melt lead and silver and copper, and they form together some metal that is new."

"But are not these changes influenced also by the position of the stars in heaven?" asked Tring.

"Yes, and no. The sea, I admit, seems to follow the pull of the moon. Harvests depend upon seasons and seasons sometimes seem to be servants of the movements of the heavenly bodies. But as to other things I know not. Besides, I am not an astrologer. I am an alchemist. The powers of the sky may be found by those who search the skies."

"But is not the conduct and life of man governed by the stars?"

"That I leave to magicians and necromancers, as likewise I leave to them that hideous magic which makes compounds of cats' paws, and owls' eyes, and dead men's fingers."

"But," persisted the student, "you seek the elixir of life, do you not?"

"No," answered the alchemist, "although in regard to it I admit that I have much curiosity. If it is true that all things are subject to change, then one might change from old to young as well as from young to old if one could but find the laws to reverse the process of life. And as to this I do not doubt that a restorer of youth can be found. Yet I am not interested as are those who have lived vain livesand hope to do better if life may be relived."

"The Philosophers' Stone, what think you of that?" Joseph noticed a distinct change in the student's voice as he said this; his eyes shone with a greedy light, and his fingers seemed to curl perceptibly.

"Well," answered the alchemist, "that is indeed much sought. To the superstitious and ignorant the Philosophers' Stone means only some substance which by magical power can transform all things it touches into gold, like King Midas of ancient days. But to us who study and work, it is apparent that only a process and not a substance can bring this to pass."

"How—how?" demanded the student, leaning forward.

"Well, it is commonly known that each substance in the world, such as brass, or paper, or glass, has certain properties in itself. Did not Archimedes, father of all our learning, establish this truth by the proof that different substances thrown separately into water each displace a different amount of water? Gold is a substance, brass is a substance, both susceptible to change in the elementals, fire, water, air, and earth. Fire melts, water changes the color or disintegrates, air hardens, and earth darkens. To make brass of gold, or gold of brass is not impossible if one might know what would break down the dissimilarity between them."

"Then why do you not keep trying until you find the secret?"

The alchemist drew a long breath. "There are things that interest me more. Though I am an alchemist, I am much concerned with the spirit that is behind material things. I would learn if life itself is a matter of substance, if there is not the same difference between man and man that there is between metal and metal. I would learn thesecrets of the earth, the messages of the sky, and I would know as well the secret of the soul, and how one might seek to help and save the souls of men whose bodies are from birth misshapen. I would learn, if I might, the composition of the earth, the reasons for the spring and summer and such phenomena—I would learn what makes the stars to shine and the sea to be tempestuous. God has given me a mind that searches ever for the light, and I feel that I am doing His will when I seek the truths that lie about us on every hand."

Tring came close and spoke very low, though his voice carried to Joseph at the casement.

"You are a fool, you, Pan Kreutz," he said. "Here are you, the most gifted scholar and alchemist of our time, fretting away your hours in such pursuits, with a much greater object to be gained at your very elbow."

"You mean—"

"You know what I mean. You and I have begun to experiment in things that men know but little of."

"I know, and I am of two minds about it. There is something in what you persuade me into that I like not. But upon such matters you are indeed the teacher and I the student. This I do know, and that is that when I am in a trance such as you sent me into a short time ago I can see things and hear things and even know things that I am not familiar with in my everyday mind. But such experiments, though they enthrall the soul, are perhaps dangerous to men. They are tried in Nuremberg, I believe, and in other lonely places in the Black Forest. But here in Krakow we have ever been wary of them."

The alchemist was looking into the fire. Tring, sitting beside him, cast at him at these words such a malicious look and leerthat Joseph shuddered. There flashed into Joseph's mind the word "demon"—a veritable demon from the darkness Tring seemed, striving to exert some influence over his victim.

The look passed. "Pan Kreutz," began Tring again, "I know from my teachers in the old town of Nuremberg that man has in reality two brains. One of these brains is wise and powerful and dominant, and yet one knows nothing of it except when one is asleep in such a trance as I put you in but a short while ago. The other is the brain of daily life; by it we know when to eat, work, and rest. It is the lesser brain."

"Something of this you have proven to me," said the alchemist.

"Then use your higher brain," commanded Tring.

"To what end?" asked Kreutz.

"To the end that all men would reach. Gold!"

He said the word with an intensity that sent a cold thrill through Joseph.

"Gold matters not so much to me," answered the alchemist.

"It does—it does—it does," insisted Tring. "You do not know what you could do with it. With this secret, you and I could become the very kings of the earth. We could live in the finest palace in the world—we could have diamonds and rubies and emeralds—we could travel about the lands of Europe like the mightiest of merchant princes—armies would be at our disposal, and we could make every human being perform our will."

For a moment he forgot the alchemist as he reveled in this dream made out of fancy and desire, but as a glance at Kreutz's face found no response there, he went on more cunningly:

"Think what you could do as an alchemist! Is this attic a fittingplace for your experiments? Are these poor tools sufficient for the concoctions that you would devise and for the laws which you would prove? You could become the greatest alchemist in Poland— in the world! You could work in a room that would contain this poor attic a dozen times. In it would be every instrument that has ever been invented for the study of alchemy. No precious substance that comes out of the East, no priceless gem nor precious stone would be beyond the means that you would possess. Does this not tempt you?"

He had touched him this time. "It would tempt any poor scholar," Kreutz replied, in the voice of one who had seen a sudden vision. Then more keenly, "But do you think that I possess in myself, my greater self as you call it, this secret of changing base metals into gold?"

"I am sure of it"—Tring was almost dancing about his chair in eager enthusiasm—"if you will cease being a plodding scholar and a fool and set yourself night and day to conquer this problem of the universe. Gold—gold—gold—that is what every man wants. Success always means gold, and those who work all their lives professing none but unselfish motives are but deceiving others in order to make themselves reverenced—some of them perhaps are deceiving themselves. Why, with gold—think what you could do for your niece, think what you could do for the students of the university— you could make this school and, aye, the whole kingdom of Poland the greatest and most desired place in all the world."

Kreutz thought deeply for some minutes. It was quite evident even to Joseph, young and inexperienced as he was, that Tring had utterly poisoned the alchemist's mind. Indeed, now Kreutz, lookingat life through the philosophy of Tring, saw that his own life was the life of a dusty plodder; it was the life not only of a poor man but of a foolish man who might be better off if he wished, who now had the opportunity to do a great deal for those whom he loved, if he would but set himself to it. His thoughts had been on a plane too high for practicality. He had idealized mankind and he had tried to learn things which had seemed to him to be the very jewels of knowledge in the crown of wisdom—yes, that was what he had been, a dusty old plodder.

And with these thoughts he surrendered utterly to Tring. "You are right, I truly believe," he said with a sigh, "perhaps then we can possess this secret which will make us kings of the earth, as you say. With gold we can do these things, we can accomplish what we wish in the world, we can help the struggling, cure the sick, and do away with poverty entirely in this kingdom. Yes, it is, after all, a noble task—shall we repeat the experiment again tonight? Shall I enter into a trance again?"

"Nay," Tring had gained his end, "it is getting late and I would not repeat the experiment so shortly after the first trial, for fear perhaps that it would not be so successful as before. Tomorrow evening we shall try it, when we are both fresh again.... It was curious that tonight, when you were in the deepest part of the trance, you called out that that which every astrologer, alchemist, and magician has sought for centuries was within a few yards of the place where you sat. I had begun to think that we were upon the eve of a great discovery."

"Aye, it was then that something awoke me," said the alchemist.

"Yes, the worse for us all," said Tring sourly. "It was a cry thatbrought you to your senses, upon the eve of so great a revelation. It was the cry of your niece from the room below."

"Elzbietka," exclaimed the alchemist with concern. "And why did she cry?"

"You were not silent in your trance. You shouted that there were some demons near by ready to kill you—you almost screamed in your fear—and then you talked as if your tongue were a pendulum."

"And I did not answer the child?"

"No. You sank back in your chair again, asleep, and this time it was a natural sleep, for when I questioned you again, you said nothing."

The alchemist rubbed his eyes. "I am sleepy now, in faith." Then, wondering, "What could have been the revelation? I know of no prize that could be near by. On the ground floor is the old woman, and her half-wit son, whom I frighten with fire—then on the second floor, but the three poor refugees installed recently. Across the court, only you and two poor students. No, it can be nothing in the possession of any one of these. Well, as you say, this for tonight is enough—" And at these words Joseph scampered down the stairway.

VIII. PETER OF THE BUTTON FACE

Summer burned itself into fall. The Vistula, which had been growing ever lower and lower with the heat, was now but a narrow ribbon of water, and the banks along it were parched and dried and yellow. Leaves were changing from green to brown, and the birds were making ready to leave for southern lands as soon as the first suggestion of cold should appear. Across the meadows now the horses and wagons were marching daily, and the dry hay was filling barn and shelter in all the country about. The fruits of the autumn were already appearing in the market, the apples of the first bearing, the golden squashes, and the late cabbage. And over the city and country hung a sky of deep, exquisite blue, for in all the world there is no sky so blue as is the Krakow sky, and no sun is so gold as is the sun of early autumn.

When the Month of the Heather had passed by and the Month of Hemp Beating was at hand, Joseph had learned all the notes of the Heynal and could play the little hymn upon his father's trumpet. Once, even, he had played it in the tower; on that night his father had played it toward the west, south, and east, and then had allowed the boy to play it at the north window.

The girl, Elzbietka, a little quicker of ear than Joseph, had long since mastered the air and quickly memorized Joseph's notes, so that she could not only hum the music, but reproduce it in writing upon awall or piece of parchment.

One evening when Elzbietka was visiting Joseph's mother—and she came more and more frequently now, since the alchemist had began to carry on new experiments with Tring—Joseph exclaimed suddenly:

"Before long I shall play all four Heynals."

She let her chin rest upon one hand, as she did often when she thought and when she spoke seriously. "I shall listen," she said. "It comforts me more than ever now when I hear the hymn played in the nighttime—since there is seldom anyone in our rooms when I awake. Joseph," she spoke in a very low tone, "do you know I think that my uncle is possessed?"

He gave a great start. "Possessed—and by whom?"

"I don't know. But he isn't himself. It isn't that he is out of his wits—no, not that at all. He is just as intelligent and just as kind as he ever was, but he has become so interested in something that he is doing in the loft that he thinks but little of me or of his friends in the world. There is that student, Johann Tring—"

"Yes, I know," he answered quickly.

"He and my uncle are together in the loft every night. Sometimes they stay there until it is light. They say queer things, and sometimes my uncle cries out as if he were in pain. You heard them the night that I told you to go up the stair-case. It is always like that."

"I told Father what I heard that night," said Joseph, "and he only said that it was none of our affair, that your uncle is a man who has been very kind to us, and who knows what he is about. Also he forbade me ever to spy upon your uncle again. Father said that youruncle is a great scholar and that he is now probably working upon something that will win him fame."

"Aye—perhaps," she meditated, "but I loved him better as he was."

From that time on Elzbietka became more and more a part of Pan Andrew's family. In the afternoons she used to bring her sewing downstairs into the front room and sit there for hours working and chatting or humming little tunes under her breath. When Joseph returned from his studies in the afternoon the two were accustomed to walk out into the city and see its changing wonders, its new caravans, its pageants, its companies of knights and soldiers, its processions of guilds. Often they walked out through the gates into the country, where there was rich black earth, and behind them or alongside or ahead ran the great Tartar dog. The walks took them to the old Jewish city of the Kazimierz, across the fortified bridge on the west arm of the Vistula, to the old church on the Skalka where the holy Stanislas was murdered at his altar, to the high mound above the city where it was said that old King Krakus was buried; to these and to many other places had they wandered while the sun was bright and the air not too cool.

Once they went to visit the towers of the Church of Our Lady Mary in the late afternoon. The watchman let them in at the little gate at the base of the tower and they climbed up to the room where the day trumpeter was on duty. He was the man that Pan Andrew relieved at night, and he thought it a great honor to have a visit from such a little lady as Elzbietka, and he told her many of the legends which have come down from old days, when the church tower was being built.

Joseph picked up his father's trumpet from the table. "When I first play all the four Heynals you must listen and see if you hear a single note played wrong."

"I will listen."

"If I play a wrong note, I will give you my cap. If I play two, then I will give you Wolf." He smiled then, as a boyish thought came to him. "If I ever play the Heynal through to the end, without stopping at the broken note, then you may run to Jan Kanty and tell him to summon the watch, for then something will have happened to me."

"How do you mean?" She was, as ever, serious, though he was smiling.

"You know the story of this hymn, the Heynal?"

"Yes," she answered.

"How, when the Tartars burned the city, the trumpeter stayed on duty and played the hours as he had sworn?"

"Yes.... A brave story."

"Well"—Joseph liked to see the blue eyes widen—"one night the Tartars will attack the city, or perhaps the Knights of the Cross. I shall see them coming from afar, in the midst of fire and smoke, and I shall hear war cries and their horses' hoofs. And I shall be all alone in the tower that night, for neither my father nor any person will be here. And when I realize that it is an enemy, I must have a signal, since I myself may not leave the tower—a signal to someone in the town who will give the alarm. So I will play the Heynal, but I will not stop on the broken note. That note does not end the measure, you know. I will play on, two or three notes further."

"Excellent," she cried, and her cheeks were red with theexcitement of it. "If I hear you play the Heynal without stopping at the broken note, I will run straight to Jan Kanty."

"Now come look at the city," he broke off conversation on the subject. He was a little ashamed, for he had not expected Elzbietka to take his remarks quite so seriously. She had not taken the trumpet signal as the jest he intended, but had rejoiced at it, as do most young people when they have a secret with some important person. And, to her, Joseph was a person of very great importance, not only because of his prowess with the trumpet and his progress in the collegium but because, indeed, he possessed somehow more than ordinary seriousness for a boy of his age.

They peered through a little window. Off to the right ran the Street of St. Florian, with the gate and church beyond: new towers were being constructed that very year in the walls that ran about the city, and two of them near the Florian Gate were visible from the tower of the Church of Our Lady Mary. To each city guild was assigned one of these towers, to be kept in repair and to be manned in case of attack on the city. The joiners' and the tailors' guilds had watchtowers near this gate. Between these watchtowers and the church were many palaces with large enclosures in the center, open to the sun, where guards and soldiers were working or waiting or disporting themselves, breaking each other's heads with quarter-staves, or fencing, or shooting with arrows at pigeons tied to the tops of high poles.

Directly below them the market was still busy, although it was late afternoon, for the peasants were ready to sell at small profit what remained of their stock and go home; under the arches of the Cloth Hall the crowds were still passing from booth to booth, examiningthe laces and embroidery and fine silks that had come in from the east and south; beyond the Cloth Hall rose the tower of the Town House, or Ratusz, and in front of it two luckless wretches struggled in the pillory while a crowd of urchins pelted them with mud and decayed vegetables. To the left rose the peak of the Church of the Franciscans—they passed to the south window and there saw the twin towers of the old Church of St. Andrew, and far beyond it the great rock citadel, the Wawel, with its palace and cathedral glorious in the afternoon sun.

There were blue shadows already lengthening across the market when they descended from the tower and crossed the market square. Against the palaces that lined the open space there were more shadows, and moving like shadows within these shadows promenaded black-gowned students and masters. They were moving definitely in one direction, and when once caught up in the crowd, Joseph and Elzbietka followed, unresisting, for they knew that some excitement was afoot in the students' quarter.

The black figures grew constantly more and more numerous, until at length the two stopped and pushed right and left in an endeavor to reach a position of vantage in front of the dormitory in St. Ann's Street. The dormitory was set back from the street, and in front was an open court, grassed over, in the center of which was a stone statue of Kazimirthe Great, the founder of the university. Here, upon the pedestal of this statue, leaning back upon the throne which bore Kazimir, stood a man in the gown of a master of arts, speaking to the assembled students in the Latin language.

"I heard of him today," Joseph told Elzbietka. "He is a celebrated Italian scholar who comes here to read the writings of themaster poets and to recite some verses of his own. He talks of poets who bear such names as Dante and Petrarch, and he says that the day will come when a new learning will rule the world. He says that men have been in darkness too long, that the barbarism which fell upon the world after the downfall of Pome will be done away with only when men write in their native tongues and think for themselves."

"And can you really understand him when he speaks?"

"After a fashion. He speaks Latin, as do all our masters and priests and scholars. My father had teachers for me when I was eight years old, and since then I have worked much with the Latin tongue. At first it pleased me not at all, for there were rules and tables and grammar, but when I began to understand that Latin would admit me into the proudest society of the world, then I began to like it better. In the months that I have been here my teaching has all been in Latin, and I hope, myself, to be able to speak it fluently sometime. I can understand much, though not all."

"Why does not this Italian poet speak, then, in the university?"

"He might, perhaps—but to a certain extent it would stir up strife, since there are those among the masters who do not like the New Learning, as it is called. Our old teachings are all of the great Aristotle, and yet we have never read anything of him in the Greek language—everything that we study is in Latin. We have many treatises upon learning which the masters have used for centuries, and most of them do not desire to change their ways."

The Italian scholar at that moment began to read his own verses in the Latin tongue. He had scarcely finished, amid much acclaim, when a Polish scholar mounted the pedestal and began to read some of his verses written in the Polish language.

"Why do they not all do that?" asked Elzbietka. "One can understand them so much better. If I were a poet, I should not think of writing in an old language that no one speaks except a few scholars. I would write of Poland and its flowers; I would write of the trumpeter in the tower and the blue sky that one sees behind the castle on Wawel Hill. Truly, I like this New Learning as you call it."

Joseph smiled but knew not what to say.

"And," she continued, "why is not this learning as good for women as it is for men? Why is it that all writings of poets and scholars and men of learning should be read only by men? I would read such writings too."

It was said with such gravity and such an air of wisdom that at first Joseph was inclined to smile, but as he looked into her face and saw the seriousness there, he desisted.

"Truly," he said finally, "I know not why you should not read as do men, but I know of no woman who ever entered the university."

As they turned through a short lane from St. Anne's Street to the Street of the Pigeons they failed to notice a pair of men conversing quietly behind the buttress of a house on the farther side. Both were of short stature, and one was much bent—as he spoke he raised his long, lean fingers close to his mouth:

"Sh-h.... That is the boy."

The other started and turned quickly, but appeared puzzled. "When did you say he came?"

The bent-over man, who was no other than Stas, son of the woman who lived in the court, gave the date to a day.

"Then it must be he," exclaimed the other. "On the day that I saw him he was dressed like a country youth and his clothes weredusty from travel. Today he is arrayed in velvet like any prince and has besides the cap of a junior collegian. But his stature is the same. And you say that he lives above you?"

"Yes. Goes by the name of Kovalski."

"H'm—it was Charnetski when I knew him.... Now, you, look at me—do you see this piece of gold? That's true gold, red gold, an' will buy many a dainty or many a drink. That is to be yours, for your very own."

Stas almost shrieked for joy when the stranger put the piece of money in his hand.

"But, look you—no talking about this anywhere else. This is my business, mine and yours, and I tell you that when we are finished there will be more gold pieces for you just like that. Now show me the place where they live."

They followed along until Joseph and Elzbietka stood before the entrance to the court.

"That is the place," said Stas.

"Well and good. Now keep a close watch and let me know anything that is new. I will be at the Inn of the Golden Elephant every afternoon at the third hour, but do not tell anyone there that you are looking for me. Let your words be only for my ears. And remember, the lantern in the man's face tonight. There will be much gold for you. You understand?"

The man did. His very shoulders seemed to chuckle at the thought of it. He let himself into the court and went at once to his room.

In the meantime the other walked briskly to the inn and sat down at a table. His thoughts were dancing in his head, for by anextraordinary piece of luck he had succeeded in locating the family of Pan Andrew. Luck indeed it was, because never, if he had come upon him face to face in the street, would he have known Joseph at all. It was only because Stas had named him as the son of the man who went abroad only by night that he could see any resemblance to that boy who had sent his horse flying away through the mud on that morning so many weeks before. For this man was that same one who called himself Stefan Ostrovski.

They disappeared that day after the riot—he thought to himself as he sat in the inn—and were nowhere to be found. The earth might have opened and swallowed them whole. No other Charnetski in Krakow answered their description—I had well given them up for lost, and with them, a castle and coffers of gold in the Ukraine. For when Ivan, himself, promises, then there is profit to be had. I return to the Ukraine, but there is no word from them there. My men are even now riding from city to city in the vain hunt. Meanwhile I, answering some tiny voice of wisdom that speaks from somewhere into my ear, come back here.

He struck the table with his fist. "Men call me Bogdan Grozny-Bogdan the Terrible," he exclaimed. "But terror often has brains. This venture has begun in luck and must end well. And once I get what I seek from that white-faced Pole he shall rue the day of my humiliation at the Krakow Gate." And with the thought of that adventure, a look of hatred came into his eyes.

His attention was diverted for the moment by the sight of a beggar with a dirty bandage across his face working from table to table at the inn, begging for alms in a whining tone.

As the beggar came near, the man dropped a coin in the out-stretched hand and whispered, "You come late today."

"Pardon me, master, I thought I had a scent."

The beggar seemed to expect a blow, and assumed a defensive attitude, when the man smiled.

"No matter, the work is done," he whispered. "Mount your horse tonight and ride like the wind for Tarnov. There you will send out our brothers to bring in the men who are hunting. It may take three weeks—but hurry before the first fall of snow comes."

The beggar took the orders, ambled out of the inn quietly, just as he had come in, and proceeded in like fashion until he was well along the street which skirts the market on the west. Then, suddenly stepping behind a house buttress, he tore the bandage from his face and ran with all speed for the gate on the Mogilev Road, in order to get through unchallenged before

the night watch came on duty. He passed through, sauntered down the road until he came to a small peasant cottage with a stable in the rear; here he found the horse which he had ridden to Krakow, and with a single word to the owner of the house, who seemed to understand his movements fully, galloped off to the distant bridge where ran the Tarnov Road.

The man at the inn continued to ruminate. That stoop-shouldered misbegotten thing that calls himself Stas came to us like an angel from heaven. Often had I noticed him in here, talking and making free with all the beggars, and even at first look of him, I thought to myself that here was such a man as might serve a purpose for me sometime. So I have the landlord bring him a friendly glass, and talking as he drinks it, he drops a word about the new trumpeter who never goes forth in the daytime! That is the boy as sure as man canbe sure, despite his new trappings of velvet; and then the fact that there are three of them, and the date of their arrival. Tonight when the trumpeter leaves by the door, Stas will hold the lantern to his face, and I, hiding near by, will see—but there is scarce need of that, it is as well as proved. My men will be here in a week or two, and it will be but short work after that.

His face was working pale in his excitement—it was all white save the button mark which stood out on it like a clot of blood.

What would the honorable Pan Andrew have said that day—he chuckled—had he known that Bogdan Grozny was before him? For he, and every man in the Ukraine, knows Peter of the Button Face. That was a good name I gave him—Ostrovski! Ostrovski of the proud family at Chelm that once called me slave.

Peter of the Button Face was indeed a name feared everywhere in the Ukraine. It had been bestowed upon this man, whose real name was Bogdan, chiefly by the Poles, for among the Cossacks he was known as Grozny, or Terrible. A savage outcast, born of a Tartar mother and Cossack father, he had been involved in every dark plot on the border in the last ten years. Houses he had burned by the score, and men and women he had put to death cruelly. Under his command was a band of ruffians who would rise up suddenly in the Ukraine, overnight almost, and set out upon any adventure of fire and sword that he suggested.

He was not despised by great folk either—Polish or Muscovite-when there was unlawful work to be done; nobles often employed him for unscrupulous tasks that they dared not perform themselves; the Great Khan of the Tartars even had dispatched him on a mission among the Golden Horde; his name was a power on both sides of theboundary, for in Poland also he had confederates who served him.

And at the present time the great country of the Ukraine, which had come to Poland through the marriage of Jagiello of Lithuania with Jadviga of Poland about one hundred years previous—this huge land was full of plots and counterplots in the struggle for mastery between Muscovy and Poland. Ivan of Moscow had already begun to turn envious eyes upon this territory, which had been the heart of the old Byzantine Russia with Kiev as its capital, and was making plans to wrest it from Poland at the first opportunity. And in such fashion many a dweller such as Pan Andrew Charnetski found himself bereft of property and fields in a single night. For there were many such as Bogdan the Terrible, or as the Poles knew him, Peter of the Button Face, who were ready at a minute's notice to engage in some such fearful task with rewards of plunder and captives for their work.

However, little realizing what savage forces had been let loose against them, the family of Pan Andrew sat down to a quiet supper.

IX. BUTTON-FACE PETER ATTACKS

Cold weather came in late November—or Listopad, the month of Falling Leaves, as Polish folk call it—and found the poor people in the villages already fortified in their log huts with the thatched roofs. Sand had been heaped high about the walls of the houses, all crevices that led to the outer world were stopped up with mud or tree branch or stone, wood and charcoal were piled under table and bench, and from the ceiling hung dried vegetables and mushrooms and sausage. The geese and pigs still ran about outside the house but would be taken in with the first frost, to share the "black" or large compartment of the hut with the family. In the second or "white" compartment of the hut the whole family slept when the weather was not too frigid, but when the snow was up to the roof level, and the cold was so great that one could hear trees cracking in the night, all slept in the "black" room which had not even a chimney to vent the smoke that poured out steadily from an open fireplace.

In the city houses, wealthy men were beginning to build high tile stoves of Italian pattern, but for the most part, people depended for heat and comfort upon the open fireplace. When the first frost came boys ran hither and thither with flaming coals for starting the first fires; up in the tower of the Church of Our Lady Mary the watchmen kept eyes constantly wide open in order to detect as quickly as possible the patches of flame which sometimes broke outfrom the roofs of over-heated dwellings, and many a troublesome night was spent by the water master and his men quenching such fires.

A light snow was falling on the last Wednesday of the month, when Pan Andrew started for his nightly duties at the church. The world had been going well with him, he reflected, as he made his way through the dark and well-nigh deserted streets: his son was making marked progress in the collegium, his wife was happy and contented, he himself was earning enough to support them both comfortably, and he hoped that before long he would have a chance to present his offering to the king. For it had not been possible thus far to gain an audience; either the king had been away on business in Torun with soldiers and diplomats, or he was in Vilna, the home of the Jagiello dynasty, which now ruled Poland, or in Lvov, where the Ruthenian subjects lived.

In the short snatches of time when he had been in Krakow neither Pan Andrew nor Jan Kanty had been able to reach him, because so many had been waiting ahead of them—the ambassadors from the Czechs who came to offer him the crown of Bohemia, the delegation from Pome, the scholars from Italy, the deputation from the Teutonic Knights asking for a compact against the Hussites, and other men of title and power.

This delay was no great cause of concern to Pan Andrew, however, since an audience was eventually assured. Late in the summer Jan Kanty had sent a petition to the very throne itself, and the king had advised the gentle scholar by message that he would see him at the first opportunity. In the meanwhile the treasure seemed hidden in as safe quarters as Pan Andrew could ask for.

It was several hours after Pan Andrew had left his lodgings on the Street of the Pigeons that there came a violent ringing of the bell that summoned Stas. Stas unfastened the door and thrust his lantern directly into the face of the man who stood there, and for his pains was rewarded with a smart blow upon the chin which tumbled him into the soft snow which was now beginning to cover everything.

"Don't do that again as you value your life," the stranger muttered as he picked up the fallen lantern and straightened the limp Stas upon his feet. "You fool, don't you know that someone might have seen my face? If some watchman took me, he would as well take you; it is for your safety that no man knows anything of this meeting. Is everything ready?"

"Yes," responded Stas a bit ruefully.

"Then tell me, who is in the building?"

"Well—-there is the lodger on the top floor and his niece, and there is the boy and his mother."

"The students?"

"They have gone to a discussion at the Hungarian pension. Sometimes they do not return before daybreak."

"Good! Then we can work without fear. A dozen men will suffice, four to enter the rooms of Pan Andrew, four to quiet the tenants if need be, and four to stand at the gate. If the guard should come, we can silence him."

"Will you see the stairs?"

"Yes, they live—"

"Up one flight." They ascended the stairs, Stas in the lead. It seemed to the stranger that the staircase swayed a little beneath their feet.

"We must take care here," he muttered. "It seems as if a weight would bring this down."

Just then a dog began to bark in the court below.

"What is that?" demanded the man, turning on Stas. "You did not tell me of a dog."

"He is chained," replied the other. "Will you give me the gold now?"

"Here." The man thrust him a few coins. He took them greedily and felt them over in the darkness, for the stranger was holding under his coat the lantern that he had picked up from the ground.

"This is not all?" Stas' voice rose to a whine.

"Swine!" For a moment the man lost control of himself. "Here is the rest, then," and he swung his free hand to Stas' throat, and sank his fingers in the flesh. Stas fought but could not release himself from those fingers that dug like iron points—at length the man freed him.

"No more of that," he admonished. "The next time you will find yourself in paradise, or some other world. Listen, fool, once and for all—if all goes well here, I will give you double of that which you already have. But if you betray me, or make one foolish blunder, then you will receive, not gold, but a punishment that is worse than anything you dream of."

Stas beat a retreat down the stairs, the stranger behind him.

"Remember," was the final admonishment, "we will be here just after the second hour has sounded. Let us in, and your part in this is finished."

Now it so happened than Pan Kreutz, the alchemist, was working alone in the loft above his room that night. He had alreadyfinished one experiment, and was about to begin a more difficult one, when his attention was caught by the sudden barking of a dog in the court beneath.

What can that be? he thought. There is no moon to cause barking, nor does the dog bark at any of the dwellers in the court.

He quickly threw a covering over the lantern that lighted the loft, and opened the door so that he might look down.

His suspicions that all was not well in the court were confirmed in the next second, when he heard a whispered conversation somewhere below, while the stairs creaked as if two persons were ascending. Then all at once came an exclamation of pain in a voice that he recognized as Stas'.

More whispering, and the footsteps descended.

The next instant the alchemist, leaning forward to listen, heard the stranger's final instruction to Stas.

There is, then, some mischief afoot, he decided. Doorkeepers do not let honest visitors into any house at two o'clock in the morning.

He re-entered the attic room, and uncovered the lantern after making fast the door. For some time he puzzled about what he had heard. Who was the stranger, and what business did he have with Stas, the watchman? And what ought he to do about it? He was for a moment minded to notify the night watch.

I am perhaps magnifying things, he finally concluded. More than likely two o'clock on the morrow was meant. Besides, I myself could give any marauder here a very warm reception—he glanced about the loft. The thought seemed to please him, for he chuckled for the space of a moment, and then turned seriously to his work.

For an hour or more his experiment, which was difficult andexacting, held all his attention. But when it was finally finished and the results carefully noted, the thought of Stas and his mysterious visitor returned to him. In the stillness of the late hour the affair seemed to show a graver face.

He jumped up suddenly and set the fires leaping in two braziers. He melted a gum in one of them and heated some liquid in the other. At length at the end of fifteen minutes he covered the fires and took out the substances. With a small brush he smeared the mixture of the two over his long student gown that hung against the wall. Then he took the mask, which he used when making experiments with certain poisonous gases, and covered this with the same drug he had compounded in the braziers—the gum causing it to cling to the surface of the mask.

I have but to sprinkle this with aqua phosphorata, he said to himself, and the heavens will not be more brilliant than I.

He sat back in his chair to wait, and with closed eyes tried to reason it all out. What can be the meaning of this? he thought. The stranger with Stas stopped on the landing of Pan Andrew's lodging. What mystery can have attached itself to this family? Why should the name be changed? Who would seek revenge upon a man and a woman and a boy? Elzbietka has found a mother, and I good friends. They have no treasure with them, no money of any kind, for even on that first day Pan Andrew was obliged to sell his cart and horses for the means of living.

He was becoming drowsy, for he had worked much of late, and had had but little sleep, and he was on the point of succumbing to his weariness when he heard the watchman at the Church of Our Lady Mary strike twice upon the bell and then begin to play the Heynal.The fourth Heynal was scarcely finished when he heard a motion in the court below. It was Stas creeping along the wall in order to open the door. Throwing back his door noiselessly the alchemist lay flat on the floor and leaned out over the threshold. The door below creaked a little as it opened. Someone came in. The alchemist listened: One—two—three—more! By the lightning, there must be a dozen of them, if footsteps tell no lies. I did wrong not to notify the watch. If I shout now, he may come, but there are enough to silence both him and me. No, I have made my beer and I must drink it.

Next the stairs began to creak, and almost instantly the hoarse barking of a dog cut through the air.

"Silence that dog," he heard someone whisper from the steps. Footsteps were heard again in the court as if someone had gone back to combat the animal. At this same moment the door leading into the court was slammed shut, and there was a rattle of the chain that fastened it on the inside.

A precious jewel, that Stas, thought the alchemist. He shall pay for this tomorrow.

A cry of pain rang out suddenly from below. It was the cry not of a dog, but of a man. Ha, thought Pan Kreutz, Wolf finished that one.

There was a sound of a man running across the court. "I can't get near him without injury," he whispered loudly to the leader of the party. "He sank his teeth in my leg, and I am faint for pain."

"Three of you attack him at once," directed the leader.

There was scuffling again, and suddenly the night was made hideous with the mad howling and barking of Wolf and the shrieking of men in pain; at this moment Joseph, with a light in his hand,appeared at the door on the second story:

"Wolf—Wolf," he called.

He did not call again.

Whew, thought the alchemist, they silenced the boy. A gag, probably.

He was right. The leader of the attacking party had seized Joseph and thrown a cloth bag over his head.

"To the house," he shouted to the men below. "Four of you stand guard at the door. Four of you wait at the stairs and let no one descend, and the rest come with me."

As the light of the lantern which he had taken from the boy swung upon his face, the man watching above could see that it was marked with a great round scar like an immense button.

"Tartar or Cossack," he exclaimed, "for the plague which leaves such scars is an Eastern plague; these men have come from a long distance."

He was right. This was indeed the band of that ruffian whom the Poles called Peter of the Button Face and whose bad fame men knew in all the Ukraine and the lands to the east.

In the next second, almost, they were inside the house—Peter, and three men following. There came to the alchemist's ears the scream of a woman, followed by a crash as if she had been thrown upon the floor. Then came the sound of the breaking of furniture, of the tearing up of matting, of the destruction of everything within the house as if a quick, violent search was being made. The door was open and the alchemist could hear clearly all the sounds below.

"Look in the bed," the leader spoke.

Pan Andrew and his wife slept in a large bed in the front room.Swords were quickly at work ripping this to pieces. They cut open the pillows, they tore apart the blankets, and it was only after the bed was a complete ruin that the leader found what he had been seeking.

"There it is," he shouted; "that large package, done up in cloth."

With his sword he ripped away the layers of cloth that bound it—one by one they fell away upon the floor until the object he sought stood uncovered in his right hand. But just at that instant, as he was about to dart for the door, there came a shrill voice, shrieking, "My gold—my gold!"

Peter turned like a flash. "Blood of a dog—"

The lantern was held up. Its light disclosed the face of Stas, maddened with the fear that he should not receive the price of his treachery.

"Gold! I'll give you gold," shouted Peter, infuriated. "Someone take him and throw him down to the dog. Then he can take what gold we choose to throw him."

Two men seized him, but he fought madly and dashed into the room. There the third man headed him off and the two others fell upon him from behind; his slim body wriggled loose, however, and he fell across the table already over-turned by the intruders in their search for Pan Andrew's treasure and clung there with ferociousness to the upturned legs. He kicked, he bit, he struck out blindly—but they tore him loose just as Peter set the prize on the floor to take the man in hand himself.

The lantern rested on the floor behind him, and as the struggling men swung toward him, Stas, shot with a brilliant idea, worked a leg loose and kicked the lantern over. As it fell, the door swung open and the candle went out. Almost instantly, however, the ruffiansclosed their grip upon him and hustled him to the door.

Over the rail he would have gone without further ceremony had not there come the sudden screaming of a girl from the floor above.

"The plague upon them all," exclaimed Peter, dropping Stas. "Here everything is as smooth as water in a lake, then all of a sudden babies and fools raise the dead with their cries. Come, we have enough—let us get out of this at once."

He groped his way back to Pan Andrew's bed, and was feeling in the dark for the precious thing that was the object of his raid, when there came a crash like that of thunder from above, and through the open door appeared a terrible red light that seemed to come from the sky and enveloped everything for the moment in a garment of red.

X. THE EVIL ONE TAKES A HAND

Peter rushed to the door and stood, staring.

Balls of red fire were shooting out into the air from the opened casement of the room in the loft, flooding the place with light as they burst with terrific explosions. In the light Peter could see his men standing horror-struck, four below him at the bottom of the stairs, and four on guard at the door. Those who had been clinging to Stas on the landing had recoiled in fright before the fiery balls, and the half-wit had seized the opportunity to slink stealthily away through their legs, and make for the lower steps.

For a moment Peter stood motionless. In bodily things he was braver than the brave, but in the face of such magic as this he was a coward; yet though he trembled, he realized that he must play a man's part if he wished to keep the leadership of his band, and accordingly, spurring himself up to a pitch of bravado, he rushed up the stairs from the second floor to the third and stood there just as another bomb soared out into the air.

"Come back! Come back!" they were shouting from below.

"Come up! Come up!" he commanded. "What are you frightened of?"

"It is the Evil One himself!"

Peter shook his curved Cossack sword in the darkness. "Come up—come up, I tell you, you cowardly dogs—come up or I'llseparate your coward heads from your useless bodies. Come up, I say—come up!"

And so much was he feared that the three men on the second-floor landing crossed themselves in the manner of the Creek Church and went creeping up after him.

"We have the treasure," pleaded the nearest man in a trembling voice, "let us escape from here. This is nothing human. This is the work of the Evil One. Devils are abroad and a man is not sure of his soul."

"Devils," roared Peter, "bones and fiddlesticks! Come up here, you, and be men. This is no devil. This is some joker who values his head but lightly. If we do not silence him, he will alarm the whole city before we get back to the gate."

"Up that," he commanded a second later, shoving the first man against the staircase to the loft. "Up that, and tell us what you see."

The man mounted, trembling violently, for he was sure that the powers of darkness themselves were working against them.

"The door is open here," he whispered, "and no lights within." A man below him on the stairway passed the word along to Peter.

"Then up, every mother's son of you," ordered the leader. "There is a man there. Put a knife in his throat and descend quickly."

The rest pulled themselves up and entered the loft. After a few minutes of impatient waiting Peter climbed the steps himself and pushed himself across the dark threshold.

"What have you found?" he demanded impatiently.

"Nothing," the answer came faintly from one corner of the loft.

"If there is anyone here let him speak now," Peter bellowed. His voice drowned the quiet opening of the door of a closet in the backof the room. "If we find anyone, it will go hard—"

Like a bolt of lightning out of a clear sky the loft was suddenly illuminated with a glow of red fire as there leaped into existence out of the blackness of the night the very incarnation of the Evil One in his worst mood. Clad in fiery garments which smelled of fire and brimstone and which seemed to blaze and burn and give off a greenish smoke and dame, he moved slowly forward, waving in his right hand a scepter of flaming red which was crackling with heat as a green bough crackles when it burns, while from its end little balls of fire were dripping.

It was so sudden, so unexpected, this apparition in a pitch-black world of night, of a red, fiery, glowing devil, that Peter, stouthearted as he was, let out a sudden shriek, and trembled like a leaf.

But if he trembled, the others went mad with fear. "Out! Out!" they shrieked, crowding to the stairway.

Upon their heels came the fantastic demon waving his scepter right and left and favoring first one and then another with smart blows, as they fought to be first at the stairway. Two reached it at one time and went scrambling down, to be joined by the third a second later, who came tumbling down upon them just as they gained the third-floor landing.

Peter, however, stood his ground for a moment. Turning about at the head of the stairs he shouted, "Be you man or demon, I will see what you have in you," and rushed with his drawn sword upon the weird figure. That one simply stood aside as he rushed, and waved his hand in the direction of the man's face.

"Ahew-ahew!" the brigand screamed with pain, for some-thing choking and powdery was filling his eyes and throat. "Help—cowards—I am in the hands of a thousand devils. Help, I say!"

There was no sound outside save the noise of the men scrambling down the next stairway.

Peter stumbled blindly to the steps and fairly slid down them, fearful lest the phantom should follow and give him another dose. But the phantom, though following, did not repeat his attack; he came slowly down the stairs after the retreating party, hurling little bombs of colored fire into the air, which as they exploded flooded the court with lights of rainbow hues.

Below, the din was deafening. The dog had worked his head loose from the bag which had been thrown over it, and was barking at the top of his lungs. Men were shouting and crying out in terror, forgetful of caution and the necessity for silence. Joseph, who had been gagged and bound in the rear room of the family's dwelling, had gotten his feet loose from the ropes and was kicking with all his force against the wooden partition wall, Elzbietka was crying out for aid, and heads were beginning to emerge from open casements in all the adjoining buildings. Someone in the street outside was calling loudly for the watch, and Stas, having rescued himself from one predicament, was for no reason at all pulling at the rope of the bell that hung over the door, its clamor adding to the general uproar.

On the landing at the second floor the three retreating ruffians collided with the four men standing there and almost toppled them into the court. They had barely regained their balance when the lower supports of the stairs, which had been groaning already from the unaccustomed weight and traffic, suddenly collapsed and catapulted the whole company, amidst indescribable turmoil, into the court below. Peter, coming behind the three, managed tosave himself by leaping nimbly to the threshold of Pan Andrew's dwelling, but the flaming figure behind him remained momentarily on the stairs above the second floor where the supports and staircase held firm. Not for long did he remain there, however, for as Peter turned his back to disappear into the house, the pursuer leaped from the lower step of the remaining stairway and landed squarely upon Peter, hurling him with a crash to the floor well inside the front room of Pan Andrew's dwelling.

Below in the court there was a veritable pandemonium: the crashing apart of beam and beam where the staircase struck the ground, the shrieking of the frightened, the moaning of the injured— for two men had been pinned beneath the fallen staircase—the terror and distraction of the ruffians on guard below, whose one idea now was to escape through the outer door before the arrival of the watch.

While all this was transpiring in the court, the alchemist, who with his chemicals and powders had caused all the trouble, shook his heavy scepter, a club smeared with glowing resin, in the face of Peter, who lay prostrate beneath him, and demanded:

"Now—what do you seek here?"

But Peter had gotten some of his courage back, and besides the voice sounded more like that of a man than a devil. "I will not tell!"

"You will!"

"I will not."

"You will be turned over to the watch."

"I care not. They can learn nothing."

"First let us have another look at you."

He carefully drew a fireball from a fold of his gown, keeping his weight upon the man under him and holding one hand at histhroat. The ball he ignited by rubbing it against the floor, and when it was burning he tossed it upon the stone hearth. There was a flash of light and the room was suddenly as bright as even day could make it.

But, after all, he did not look at Peter! For there was something else in the room that claimed his attention at once. It was the large round object that Peter had sought in Pan Andrew's bed—there it lay upon the floor a short arm's length away, gleaming like a thousand prisms of finest glass.

"Oho," he exclaimed, "oho! So that's it. Well, Pan Robber, it seems that your expedition was no ordinary one. No common house looting, this.... Lie still there, or I'll sink these fingers into your windpipe," for Peter had tried to wriggle to one side while the alchemist's attention was taken with the new object.

"Who sent you here?" demanded the latter.

Peter was silent.

"But you must talk. Do you hear that—below?"

It was the night watch shouting, "Stand, in the name of the king."

Peter, whose courage was now revived, since he realized that it was a man and not a devil that he was dealing with, decided to try a little strategy.

"I will tell you all if you will hide me here."

"I give no promises. But tell me what you know."

"Then see that." He twisted one hand away from his captor as if to point toward the shining object on the door, which was now gleaming like a miniature sun in the last rays of the nearly burned-out fireball.

"I see it." The alchemist glanced at it; the instant's relaxation proved fatal, however, for with the moment, the under man's right hand came clear and tore the alchemist's grip from his throat. In the struggle that followed, the alchemist was no match for the lithe and wiry Cossack. They rolled back and forth across the floor, tight in each other's arms, they broke table legs, they brought down crockery from the shelves, they crashed into walls—and through all this the Cossack little by little overcame the advantage which the other had held in the beginning. First he twisted his legs in such fashion that he caught Pan Kreutz's body as if in a vise, a trick that he had learned in the old days in the Ukraine; then he snapped his hands free from the other's grip and wound his arms in under his shoulders. Tighter and tighter he drew arms and legs, until the alchemist's bones began to send out cracking noises; then, with a quick movement, he had reversed their positions and it was he who was on top and the alchemist underneath. Smash! He had bumped the man's head against the floor with all his force, a blow sufficient to stun a giant, and in an instant had tossed him against the wall.

There the alchemist lay.

Like a panther moving to attack, Peter seized the object, which he had come to procure, and leaped for the door.

He did not reach it unscathed. Pan Kreutz had also a last stratagem. It was fortunate for him that when the Cossack bumped his head against the floor, it was his mask that had borne the brunt of the blow—otherwise it is doubtful if he could ever have risen. But when the Cossack tossed him aside he lay there feigning unconsciousness, and as the other turned, he reached with a swiftness as quick as Peter's into a pocket of his gown, where hehad concealed a small package of explosive powder which might be ignited only by concussion. A wonder it was indeed that the powder had not exploded while they were wrestling on the floor.

This Pan Kreutz poised in his right hand as Peter made for the door. In another second the man would be gone—the alchemist caught his balance and hurled the package with all his strength.

It was a fair shot! It caught the Cossack with full force square on the back of the head and burst with a loud report.

Those below, now already turning their attention to the noise and the confusion on the second floor, heard the sharp explosion and saw the court flooded with light. In the midst of the glare there came a shriek that seemed to stir every corner of the courtyard, and almost immediately a man with hair flaming and garments streaked with fire sprang from the threshold of Pan Andrew's lodging to the edge of the stairway that had not collapsed, and darted to the floor above. He stopped there only for one fleeting glance below. The court, blazing with torches and alive with tumult, was full of figures—students, watchmen, soldiers—so that escape that way was impossible. He leaped to the loft stairway and mounted it. Clutching at the roof, which was not far above his head, he swung the low door back until it lay alongside the house and then climbed over it to the roofing. Along this he rushed like a meteor, his blazing hair streaming behind him in a trail of sparks—he leaped to an adjoining roof, and then to another, until he came to a place where the roofs sloped down to a wall, and there he was seen last.

A hue and cry was set up, but the man had escaped. Some said that he ran along the top of the wall and leaped into a monastery garden beyond—others that he only pretended to descend and hadcrept back among the housetops. At any rate, he was not discovered.

When temporary stairs were finally put in place the watchmen released Joseph and his mother from the small room in their own quarters where they had lain bound, and brought Elzbietka down to them. Pan Kreutz, who had retired to his loft, where he shed his torn gown and his mask, was bleeding and weak from his struggle and lost no time in getting into his bed. It was thought by all that the robbers had carried away nothing, but when Pan Andrew returned in the morning the house was searched thoroughly, only to find that the treasure was missing. Spectators swore that Peter could not have carried anything with him when he made his perilous escape over the roofs, and a few said that they had noticed that his hands were empty.

However, hunt high or low as they did, the treasure was gone, and Pan Andrew, in spite of the views of the spectators, was fully convinced that the robber had stolen it.

Those of Peter's band who had been injured in the fall of the stairs or had been unable to escape from the court were taken to jail and sentenced to various punishments. Several were put away into dungeons, where they could do no more harm, two were banished "for a period of ninety-nine years," and the rest were delivered to justice in other towns, where they had committed previous crimes. But the most vigorous questioning could get no information from them, and it was concluded that they knew little of the designs of the leader upon Pan Andrew.

As for Stas, his mother would have naught of him after this act of treachery. She lost little time in turning him out of her house, and never would she receive him back again. It was heard some timelater that he had become a waiter in the Inn of the Golden Elephant, but after the robbery of a guest there one night, he disappeared and was never heard of in Krakow again.

Pan Kreutz, although somewhat unnerved by his share in the encounter, met Pan Andrew in his lodging the next morning and described as fully as he could the man who had been leader in the events of the preceding night. He had scarcely finished when Pan Andrew sprang to his feet and struck the back of his chair with his fist.

"It is as I thought," he exclaimed fiercely, "the man who has assailed me twice before. And now I know for a certainty that it is that half Mongol, half Cossack that calls himself Bogdan and is known as the Terrible throughout the Cossack lands. I have heard of his evil deeds many times, as has every dweller in the Ukraine. And it would be like him indeed to lead this villainy against me. He is a very devil, a man without pity, though I will say a man of the boldest breed that God ever benefited with the gift of breath. We, the Poles of the Ukraine, knew him as Peter of the Button Face, because of the scar which you have seen upon his right cheek, and by that scar I would doubtless have recognized him on the morning when he attacked me outside the Krakow Gate, had I not believed that he carried on his lawless deeds always nearer the border."

Thus saying, he went sorrowfully to his work of repairing the damage done by the Cossack band.

XI. THE ATTACK ON THE CHURCH

Down in the Ukraine that winter, when men went about from habitation to habitation on the little horses that had noses so pointed that they could poke them through the snow and eat the dry grass of the steppe beneath, it was known that a great change had come over a certain Bogdan, called the Terrible along the Dnieper and Volga, and Peter of the Button Face among the Polish colonists. It was not that he had lost so much hair that certain ones called him behind his back Bogdan of the Singed Locks, that made him sad and contemplative instead of boisterous and ready as he had once been— it was the effect of some failure that brought on despondency and kept him a recluse for several months. When he did return at length to men's sight and began to appear in the taverns, his hair had grown to its accustomed length, and a huge scar that fire had made was nearly healed over. It was hinted, too, that he had made a journey clear up to the land of the Muscovites and had had conference with Ivan, called the Great, but this he did not speak about, and men dared not question him.

Spring came with the month of March in the year 1462, with peace over all the Dnieper lands, save where here and there tribes were on the march, or the Tartars were threatening raids. With spring, set out Bogdan the Terrible, and with him traveled as fine a crowd of cutthroats and cattle stealers as ever the Ukraine knew.They rode to Rovno, the town of the Level Plain, and then struck out for Chelm on the border just beyond the River Bug. They established headquarters in the Lublin Woods for a time, for the purpose of pillaging, and then hearing that soldiers had been sent after them, they vanished into the swamplands to the north and were not heard of again in those parts.

It seems that Peter had opposed this pillaging from the first, because he had other work in hand, but they were tribesmen and wild, fond of robbery and theft and eager for gain.

At Tarnov, having them well in hand again, he organized them into a caravan of Armenian rug merchants and marched them—carts, horses, and merchants—to Krakow, the great market of the eastern part of Europe. In Krakow they camped with their wares in the square on the East Side of the Cloth Hall.

Now the saddest man in Krakow at this time was Pan Andrew Charnetski—sad because he had lost, through no fault of his own, a treasure which he had intended to present to the king of Poland, and evidently a treasure of great worth since certain men seemed to envy him its possession. Jan Kanty sought to comfort him, and his wife and son and Elzbietka did much to divert his thoughts from the seriousness of the loss, but on the long nights when he was alone in the tower, moods of depression would often engulf him.

Joseph, knowing this, took to visiting him in the night vigils when it was possible, before holy days and vacations when there was no collegium on the following morning; often he would come with his father at the tenth hour of the night and remain until morning. Sometimes he would take the duties of the watchman while his father slept and sound the Heynals at each hour and inspect the cityregularly from each of the tower windows in order to sound the alarm whenever a red tongue of flame leaped into the sky. Joseph had progressed each day in playing the trumpet and could now sound the Heynal as well as his father.

He was in the tower with Pan Andrew on this same night that Peter and his caravan of merchants were encamped in their carts in the market place below the church. The moon was at its full and the shadows of the church towers fell far across the street and market. Down in front of the church doors a watchman with lantern and halberd paced to and fro calling out, as was his custom, the hours as they were sounded from the tower.

He had already called out the first hour when Peter of the Button Face, watching from a cart across the square, decided to make his first move.

"Michael," he called in a loud whisper, "Michael." And at that, a man in a suit of leather with hat to match and thick sandals slid out of the next cart. He had already divested himself of the round turban and blankets that he wore as an Armenian merchant, and his body seemed to move in a constant succession of quivering and glidings—in fact, lie had always been known in the Ukraine as the Snake—and he stood for a moment by his chief's wagon to receive a whispered command in one ear.

Then, true to his name, he wriggled beneath a dozen carts and past the flank of an outhouse near the church to take refuge behind a tree that grew at this center of the Rynek. Doubled up here, he waited until the watchman should pass in front of the church. He had not long to wait.

Out from the shadows at the base of the church emergedsuddenly a mall carrying a lantern that threw a star-shaped light about it. This man tested the door to the stairs leading to the trumpeter's tower, found it securely locked, yawned, and struck the paving stones several times ill front of the door with his long halberd, as if he were weary of doing nothing. The Snake's eyes sized up this man as his opponent. He was a man perhaps past middle age, clad in a garment of leather over which was a very light chain armor poorly woven; this fell like a skirt with pointed edges just below the knees. Above the waist the links of armor were a hit heavier, extending over the shoulders and hack into long sleeves clear to the wrist, and up past the neck to a kind of head-covering like a cowl, over which he wore a pointed helmet of rough metal. Outside the armor he wore a very short leather vest caught with a belt from which hung a short sword, and across the shoulders just below the neck another belt with a buckle at the left, where the halberd could be secured and balanced.

He passed from the front of the church to the south side, looked about carefully to see if there were any signs of life in the street or square, and finding none, turned away from the church and entered the churchyard at the south, where the moonlight fell brightly upon the old gravestones. Squatting down behind one of these and crossing himself as if in excuse to the people buried there for disturbing their slumbers, he laid his halberd on the ground at his right side and the lantern at the left. Then, reaching into a wallet which he wore at his girdle, he took out a crust of bread and a huge portion of meat. These he began to eat with no suspicion of any interruption.

In this conduct he was justified, for he had been doing this samething over and over again for many years; there had been no serious duties about the church save perhaps on a holy day when youth on mischief bound would play some trick upon the watchman, and them he could easily dispatch about their business. Thieves seldom troubled churches in this period, and the cemetery itself was guard enough against marauders in a period full of superstition. Up above him the trumpeter kept a much stricter vigil, and all about the town, the watch tried house doors and questioned late passers-by.

"Oh-ho-hum!" he yawned. Such a quiet thing was life!

But—flattened against the church wall behind him was one whose intention might have disturbed those weary thoughts had the watchman been able to discern it. The Snake had sized up this situation with rapidity and had taken advantage of the moment that the watchman turned his back upon the square to dart into the projecting shadow of a buttress. Edging along the wall, he moved cautiously until he was but a few yards from the tombstone by which the watchman sat.

Plof! The Snake had pounced like a hawk on a mouse.

There was not even a scuffle, so prepared was the intruder and so taken by surprise was the victim. Down went the watchman on his back by the side of the grave, and in a second the deft Michael had bound his scarf tightly about the man's mouth, so that he could not utter a sound. It was the work of a moment as well, to secure the hands and feet with short bits of rope that he carried in his jacket— he was at first minded to cut the man's throat with his own sword, but he feared lest he might make one last dying cry and upset all their plans.

Inside the victim's leather vest he found a huge brass key. Thishe cut loose from the short chain, which held it, and thrust it into his own belt.

Then, making sure that the bonds were secure, he leaped back into the shadow of the church and stole back to the wagon of his chief as deftly as he had come.

"I have bound and gagged the watchman behind yon gravestone," he reported, "and here is the key to the tower door."

A whispered command traveled along the line of carts. Then there was a general doffing of blankets and turbans, and the band of Peter, in leather jackets and hats, high hose and tall soft boots, stood ready behind their carts to follow the leader into his excellently planned enterprise.

It was but a short distance from the carts to the tower, and Peter led the way, keeping close to the ground in the shadow cast by the tower. They stood at length, about twenty of them, within the shelter of the angle which the tower made with the church.

"Keep close behind me," said the leader, "when we mount the steps, and watch lest there be loose boards in the stairs beneath your feet. The boy is here this night in the tower with his father. Mount carefully, but rush and secure both father and son when I give you word."

Here he fitted the key, which Michael had stolen from the watchman, to the lock and swung the small iron door on its hinges. He had to stoop as he went in.

"Quiet," he whispered, "follow closely."

In a very few minutes they were all inside. The last man, following directions, closed the iron door, so that if a curious passer-by should inspect it, he would find it shut as it was usually.

"The task is easy," whispered Peter when they had climbed the narrow steps that led to the stairs built in the tower scaffolding, "we have now but to bag our rabbit. But you must see to it that he is not a noisy rabbit. If he once gets his hand on a bell rope, he will awaken the whole town with his ringing. He must be secured quickly."

They went up and up, mounting quietly the stairs that wound about the heavy scaffolding, and treading ever carefully so that not a single board should squeak. At last the leader stopped.

"The light is just ahead," he whispered.

Through the opened door of the tower room came suddenly the voice of Joseph, "You can sleep for the rest of the night, Father," he said. "I will sound the Heynal at every hour; the hourglass is plain to read, and I shall make no error."

It was lucky to hit upon a night when they were together, thought Peter. We can bind the old one and make the young one show us the way to the prize.

Joseph had just spread a manuscript before him on the table in the tower room and had moved a taper close to it to begin reading, when he heard a sudden noise just outside the door. Turning about sharply, he was just in time to see the door thrown violently open, and then three men rushed toward him before he could even assume a defensive attitude; he was absolutely powerless. One man held his arms as closely gripped as in a vise while the two others leaped upon Pan Andrew as he rose, dazed with astonishment, from the little bed.

A fourth man stood in the doorway. His hands were at his hips and he laughed merrily. "Ho—ho—my merry singing birds," he said. "We meet again high up above the noisy world, where none can come to disturb us." Then his brews darkened and he asked, "Doyou know why I am here?"

Joseph shuddered. This man was the same that had met his father on the first day that he had seen Krakow—this was the man that had incited the crowd in the Rynek to stone his people—this was the voice that he had heard while he lay bound hand and foot in the small room of his lodgings. But at the same time he wondered what had brought the man back to the city. He had already obtained the prize, Joseph thought, after the risk and danger of the first trial. Was it, perhaps, that he wished to avenge himself upon his father for the incident of the cart?

Joseph made a motion as if to cross himself at thought of this, for here they were high up in the air above the city, and nothing would be easier than to hurl a man from the summit into the graveyard below, and none would know of it until morning came and they found the lifeless victim.

Pan Andrew, however, looked at the intruder steadily. "No," he said, very deliberately, "I do not know why you are here. But I do know you now, Peter of the Button Face, sometimes called Bogdan—it is strange that I did not recognize you that morning when you threatened me."

Peter took notice in no way of Pan Andrew's latter statement. He heard only the negative answer. Apparently he had not expected it.

"You do not? You lie! ... Do you think that I do not know everything?" He pushed his way in and held the candle close to the prisoner's face. "I say to you that I have come all this way to get what I want; I have the means for doing it, too, and I have men in this company that would rather see a dog like you dead than alive.Now come—if you value your skin. Where have you hidden the Great Tarnov Crystal?"

Joseph leaped with a thrill. This, then, was the prize that they had brought from the Ukraine—a crystal, the "Great Tarnov Crystal," whose loss the father had not ceased to mourn. But, after all, was a crystal something that men valued so highly? If it were a diamond or a precious stone, there might be some reason for so much covetousness, but a mere crystal—why, he himself knew caves in the Ukraine where one might knock rock crystals from the walls. But perhaps this had a certain significance.

"You know as well as I," returned Pan Andrew, "that it disappeared on that same night that you attacked my lodgings. If you have it not, I know not where it is to be found."

"It disappeared!" Peter was at first shocked, then incredulous. "You lie!" he shrieked, "you lie! You have it still. I will find a way.... Come here!" he called to Michael the Snake, "take this boy to the house where he lives, and keep always your knife at his throat. I will stay with the old one here, and if you do not return in a quarter of an hour, we will put this Pole out of all trouble in this world.... No," he continued, as if changing his mind, "I will go with the brat myself. While we look the house over, you keep your sword close to the old fox's throat. If the boy leads me the wrong way, I'll slit his throat, likewise if he tries to betray me. But if we do not return with the crystal in a reasonable time, do as I have told you."

That Pan Andrew would gladly give up the crystal to save not only his own life but that of the boy, the Cossack had believed firmly. Therefore his denial of the possession of the crystal was unlooked for and baffling. However, he dismissed the matter fromhis mind promptly. Undoubtedly, Pan Andrew had lied to him, and unless something unforeseen happened, it would be but a matter of a few minutes' time before the crystal was in his own hands. It was true that Joseph might not know the exact hiding place of the crystal; what he did know was that the men in the tower would kill his father if he did not return at once with the prize, and he and the mother would make a quick search of the house in order to find it and redeem the father. It did occur to Peter that perhaps Pan Andrew had deposited it elsewhere, but if the house did not give up its prize, then they would return and try to torture the information out of the father.

"Stay," he said suddenly, just as Joseph's captor delivered the boy into his hands, "the hourglass there on the table shows that the sand has fallen to the second hour. It is time that the trumpet was sounded from this place otherwise someone may suspect that something is wrong and come up here to see.... You, boy—you trumpet sometimes, I know. Surprises you, does it? Peter has eyes and ears everywhere. So, before we set out to get this precious stone, take down that trumpet from the wall.... No, leave it there a moment, and come here."

He led him to the bell rope outside and stood over him.

"Ring twice upon the bell; then get your trumpet and play your Heynal from the four windows."

He watched the boy carefully, with his knife gleaming in his hands, as Joseph tugged twice at the cord that moved the hammer against the bell.

"Do as you always do, and play no tricks."

As Joseph went back to the little room and took up the trumpet,he was thinking of another young trumpeter who, standing in the old tower over this same spot, had fallen pierced by an arrow while performing his duty. And it seemed curious that he too was called upon to show his mettle in much the same way. In his heart much of the first tumult of fear had died out. There had come to him that gift of everlasting staunchness which had been one of the most characteristic qualities of the Polish people. It was perhaps the inspiration which the thought of that other trumpeter had brought, for immediately afterward and at the minute that he had thrust the trumpet through the tower opening on the west, his mind flew back to his conversation one day with Elzbietka. He had spoken in jest that day about the Heynal, but she had taken it as a childish secret— bless her!—he was sure that she would remember.

This hope increased instantly. He knew that Elzbietka was awake at the second hour; she had known that it would be at that hour that he would take his father's place, and if the Heynal was played straight through and two or three notes were added at the end where usually the music broke off on the broken note, she would know that something was wrong. What would she do? Her uncle, lost in his experiments, would only laugh at her fancy, as he would call it. Would she dare in the night to go to Jan Kanty? If she did, it was possible that Kanty could summon the watch quickly enough to save his father's life, for he felt in his heart that Peter meant to kill Pan Andrew after the crystal was found.

It all depended on this. Did Peter know the story of the Tartar invasion and the broken note at the end of the Heynal? God must be trusted that he did not. This prayer was on Joseph's lips as Peter said, "Now for your music."

Up went the trumpet.

Then it seemed to Joseph that he had once done this very thing before. The whole world changed beneath him. The great stone city had become wood, and it was everywhere in flames. Men of short stature and ugly faces were riding about furiously on little horses. Close at hand a man had descended from his horse and had drawn a bow from his shoulders and an iron-tipped arrow from a quiver. The bow bent, the arrow was notched.

He played.

Peter nodded. The Heynal was not new to him, and he knew that the boy was playing as usual—that is, he knew up to a certain point. Joseph hesitated at the place where the music ordinarily breaks off— this time he added three notes of his own, which definitely finished the Heynal. It took courage to play those notes, for he knew not but that at any moment he might feel the Cossack's dagger in his throat. At length, he let the trumpet fall and looked about.

The blood surged into his head with a rush. The Cossack was nodding approval! He did not know, then!

He went to the windows at south, east, and north successively and played as he had already played.

"Now hurry for your lodgings!"

Peter gripped the boy's arm and pushed him ahead all the way down the stairs, after giving final orders to the men who guarded Pan Andrew. They found no one in the square below and slunk along in the shadows toward the university district. The Cossack was exulting again that his plans were working, and as he went along he looked about him for a quiet corner where he could finish Joseph with his dagger once he had the crystal in his hands and was on the way backto the tower. Then they would settle with the father and there would be no one left to give information concerning them. A company of Armenian merchants would leave the city unhindered in the course of the following day.

XIV. A GREAT FIRE RAGES

Since earliest times Krakow was divided into four sections—the Castle Quarter, the Potters' Quarter, the Butchers' Quarter, and the Slavkov. At the head of each of these districts was a quartermaster, who was responsible for everything that went on in his district, the fighting of fires being one of his chief concerns. Therefore the watchman from one of the streets that lay in the districts threatened by the fire went pounding at the gate of the quartermaster's house, shouting "Fire" at the top of his lungs in order to send the servants flying to the master. In a short time the quartermaster was up and dressed and had sent summons to the water master, who had charge of the town reservoir and aqueducts.

The bell meanwhile began to sound clamorously from the tower of the Church of Our Lady Mary, for the watchman there had caught sight of the flames. Cries of "Fire" were now being echoed from all sections of the city, and in the red glare which was beginning—to illumine all the grim Gothic buildings and churches, a very tumult of confusion was arising. The water master had already set his machinery in motion, and drummers were pounding away at their drums in all the city streets in order to awaken the merchants and their apprentices, upon whom fell the burden of fighting the flames. All the town guilds were assembling, companies of servants from the palaces were filling buckets of water and taking positions on theroofs of their own houses, and all citizens were busily getting down from the wall, hooks and axes and pails such as the law required them to keep for such emergencies.

A fire of any size in Krakow was a serious thing in those days, for there were hundreds upon hundreds of wooden and part-wooden houses clustered together in the thickly populated streets. In the section about the old university the majority of dwellings were very ancient, dry, and cobwebbed everywhere, and a single spark upon their roofs was enough to turn them in exceedingly rapid fashion into belching furnaces of flame and smoke. As the fire raced through these streets, the inhabitants poured out in panic-stricken confusion; each building was literally teeming with life, and the whole scene, viewed from above, would have resembled a huge ant hill suddenly destroyed or burned out by a careful gardener.

Women and children came out rushing and shrieking. Black-robed students dashed through the streets with manuscripts and parchments in their hands; others came carrying glass tubes or astrolabes or metal dividers; frantic domestics ran here and there with no definite refuge in view save only to escape the heat and terror of the ever-spreading flames. The streets were rapidly filling with furniture, clothing, beds, and personal possessions of every variety, hurled out of casements by desperate owners—and some of this material in the streets had already caught fire from the sparks which were descending like rain in a spring thunderstorm, making the lot of the fugitives even more unendurable. Inside some of the courts those who had preserved presence of mind were combating the fire with much vigor; tubs of water and pails were being pressed into action, and burning walls were already being hauled down.

The water master had marshaled a line of water carts which extended from the burning buildings to the aqueduct; these water carts were usually drawn by horses, and some of them were on this night, but there had been difficulty in getting enough horses quickly, and men and boys were harnessed into the shafts. At the aqueduct, men were busy filling the carts with water; as each cart was filled it moved on some little distance to the fire, and there being emptied, swung about into another street and returned to the aqueduct for another filling. The nearest section of the aqueduct was about an eighth of a mile from the point where the fire started.

Forces of men armed with hooks and axes were sent out by the water master to surround the district where the flames were reaching, for the rapid spread of the fire had made it apparent at an early stage that very little could be saved in the university area. These men were under orders to demolish any building that seemed to offer a chance for a further spread of the blaze, whether the fire had already reached it or not. One detachment formed a line in front of the Church of the Franciscans, another on St. Ann's Street, and another on Bracka. All these detachments were forced to retreat, however, as the fire ate its way out of the district where it had started. The Rynek was the scene of a turbulent mob which had struggled from the burning section in the Street of the Pigeons, and every open space was quickly filled with rescued goods. Two families had even taken possession of the plat-form where the town pillory stood, and children were being put to sleep there by mothers thankful to find a place of rest.

Amid all this uproar, an elderly woman, a boy, a girl, and a dog were fighting their way through the Street of the Pigeons amidst the debris of furniture and personal belongings that had been thrownfrom windows. They had all been sleeping when the fire broke out, and not having been roused until the flames were all about them, had been able to rescue nothing but themselves and the clothes which they wore. The boy was Joseph, the girl, Elzbietka, and the woman the wife of Pan Andrew. Wolf, cut loose by Joseph, was the most terror-stricken of the group, but he followed after them, submissive and obedient, not knowing exactly what he was expected to do.

Each of them was busy with separate thoughts as they fought their way through the disorder. Joseph was ever figuring the quickest route out of the burning district, and this was no easy task, since the fire was playing so many tricks. It was not marching ahead in a straight wall of flame, but was whirling about, leaping here and there, skipping this house and fastening upon that, advancing, retreating, spreading to the flanks, all with terrific speed and unexpected vivacity. Sometimes the roofs just above the heads of the fugitives would shoot up in flames—passing these with great peril, they would find that the fire was now behind them and rejoice at the breath of air that fell upon them; then, suddenly, without warning the roof of a building just ahead would belch forth smoke and flame as if the fire demon were working invisibly, and this new peril must be passed.

At length they reached the place where the Street of the Pigeons is cut by a cross lane, known today as Wislna Street, but this lane was already full of smoking beams and fallen timbers; escape that way was impossible. There was nothing to do but to push on through the Street of the Pigeons where it curves to meet Bracka.

Elzbietka was wondering most of all about her uncle; there had been no answer to their hurried calls when they left the doomedhouse, and besides, the loft was glowing in red and purple flames of such intensity that no person alive could have been there at that time. Joseph's mother was thinking of the father, wondering if he had left his post at the church to come to his family's aid, and wondering, too, if they could reach him at the tower before he began to suffer too much from anxiety concerning them.

The houses were a little higher in this portion of the street, and there was therefore more cool air, in the lower reaches. The fire was still whirling along here, but was not taking hold quite so fast as it had done down below, and consequently the fugitives made better progress. The only difficulty was the ever-increasing crowd that now swept in from three directions, making it hard for the three to keep together. Finally, they locked arms and literally fought their way through the crowd. All about them the scenes were heartrending, men and women fleeing with but few possessions from the only homes they had ever known, children lost in the mad scramble who set up shrill cries and tried to keep their feet as the crowd pushed ahead. Sick persons were brought into that raging torrent of humanity, carried on the shoulders of their relatives or perhaps stretched upon cots. Here was one old man who sat astride a young fellow's neck like Anchises on the back of Aeneas, fleeing from the burning city of Ilium.

At length they stood where the fire had not reached, much more fortunate in that than many other people that night. Joseph waited only until they caught their breath, though he, too, felt like throwing himself down upon the ground and resting, and then started forward again through Bracka in the direction of the Rynek. In his heart he hoped that when he had settled Elzbietka and his mother in thetower where his father was on duty, he might come back with the apprentices and help fight the fire, for there is that in a youth which draws him into such fighting. As they went along Bracka he heard the sound of horses' hoofs from the direction of the Wawel.

"Wait," he said, drawing the women back on a footpath, "here come soldiers from the castle to preserve order."

He spoke truly, for the next moment a great troop of cavalry wearing mail armor and carrying spears rode into Bracka Street from below and began to deploy in lines that marked the district immediately threatened by fire. A few minutes later, foot soldiers and artisans began to appear, and joining with the watch, pulled down buildings at the edge of the fire. Siege machinery was also drawn up into Bracka, and the buildings just outside the reach of the fire began to crumble under its pounding.

This will prevent the spread of the flames, thought Joseph.

They went ahead again toward the church, but while they were still in the Rynek they saw a company of soldiers dragging forward a prisoner whom they had taken in the burning district.

"A thief," said the boy.

"Bless us," exclaimed the mother. "It is not possible that men could be so cruel as to steal from poor folk driven mad with terror."

As the company came near and the torches fell upon the face of the prisoner, Joseph let out a cry of amazement.

"Why, Mother, that is Peter of the Button Face, the leader of the men that attacked our house. That is the man who met us on the first day we were in Krakow. He it was who tried to make us prisoners in the church tower.... See how he struggles—but they are holding him tight for all that. And Mother, it is not the city watch that has takenhim. It is the king's own guard. Do you not see the royal crown on their helmets, do you not notice the richness of their clothing? I wonder what it can be about."

Joseph spoke truly. Peter had at last fallen into the hands of guardians of the law, and this time it was the king's own men that held him. It was evident, too, from the way they held him that they thought they had a prize. They did not stop at the Town House, where offenders against municipal law were kept, but marched straight along Castle Street in the direction of the royal castle on Wawel Hill.

At the church they found Pan Andrew in a very sweat of anxiety and fear lest something of harm had befallen them. He caressed them all one after another and then said to Joseph earnestly:

"I want you to remain here and sound the Heynals for the rest of the night. There is much work to be done in the quarter where the fire is, and every man's hand is needed to stay the flames.... I see that Pan Kreutz is not with you. He stayed, too, I presume, to work with the rest of the men?"

"Indeed, Father, I know not. We called many times, but his loft was a mass of flames like to a roaring furnace when we were driven down the stairs."

"I must see, then, if I can find aught of him. He has been on a previous occasion our very great benefactor, and it would but suit us ill not to seek at least his body in the ruins. Should he not have perished, as I pray God he has not, then we can offer him shelter here until such time as he can find a roof again."

But when Joseph told him of the capture of Peter, he looked very serious and said that if such people were in the city, then he had better not leave his wife and the young people. On second thought,however, it seemed right for him to go, for the city was now lighted by flames and it would be easy to summon aid if they were attacked.

And so he, with thousands of other valiant men, fought the fire in Krakow that night. They formed in a ring about the conflagration and tore down all the buildings across which it might run. The Collegium Minus was the last building to catch on the side toward the city wall, and then the fighters tore down the houses near the old Jew Gate and stopped the fire there. The flames swept around the other buildings of the university, destroyed one or two, though not all, and were finally halted on the second street above St. Ann's. Sweeping in the other direction, the fire had early in its progress destroyed the monastery and adjoining houses of the Church of the Franciscans, and had crossed over to Castle Street, where it burned flat a whole line of buildings.

On these and the other edges of the district a wide belt of destruction was created by the fighters. This belt the tradesmen, running to and fro with water wagons filled constantly at the aqueduct, wet down and soaked until it was almost a water wall. So furiously had they worked that the main progress of the fire was checked in seven or eight hours, and although certain buildings and ruins smoked and even blazed for several days afterward, yet the great danger passed when this well-soaked belt of destruction was completed.

When Pan Andrew returned to the tower in the full blaze of the morning sun, nearly one third of the city of Krakow lay in ruins. Fortunately, it was not the better portion of the city, and many of the old wooden-built hovels had been there since before the days of Kazimir the Great; that monarch had successfully converted about one half the city of Krakow from wood to stone more than onehundred years before; had he not done so, it is probable that the fire of 1462 might have utterly consumed it.

Elzbietka and Joseph's mother were asleep on the trumpeter's bed, clasped in each other's arms. Joseph sat outside the compartment with the hourglass before him on a beam, gazing out over the smoking ruins of the university quarter.

"Is the city saved?" was the first question he asked his father.

"It is not now in danger," answered Pan Andrew. "But there are many homeless souls in the city this day."

"Did you see the alchemist?"

"I did not. He has disappeared as if he had flown away on the clouds of smoke that covered the city."

"Poor Elzbietka," exclaimed Joseph.

The girl inside the compartment moaned slightly as her name was spoken, although she was deep in a heavy slumber.

"I wonder if he was caught in the loft?" mused Pan Andrew. "It was in the very center of the burned district."

The answer to his question came with sudden unexpectedness. There was a sound of footsteps on the stairs and Jan Kanty's head appeared from below. The scholar was leading another man by the arm, a man who had been in the fire—his charred clothes and blackened face showed it; around his shoulders and falling to his waist was all that remained of what had once been a black robe. He kept his hands beneath this robe.

"Pan Andrew," whispered Jan Kanty softly, "I have found in the street—Pan Kreutz." And, checking the other's startled exclamation, he explained, "He is not in his right senses. Something has affected his brain. But he has here something of interest to us all."

Pan Andrew turned toward Kreutz—he never would have recognized him had not Jan Kanty identified him; Joseph felt his eyes glued with strange eagerness upon the eerie blackened figure and the mysterious folded hands beneath the robe; it had been a scholar's robe once.

"Ha, ha, ha!" laughed the alchemist suddenly, "up to heaven goes everything in fire, and yet no gold is found anywhere. Johann Tring!" he looked about anxiously. "Where is Johann Tring? He answers me not. He is lost in the flames, the flames that came so red and purple when niter mixed with charcoal. Oho, Johann Tring! Come, Johann Tring, and see what I have carried this whole long night for you."

Throwing back the black robe, he held up the object that he had been concealing there, and at the same moment the sun, streaming in through the little window on the east side, fell full upon that object; fell upon it and made it sparkle like the myriad of dew diamonds shining upon a morning lawn newmowed; sparkled like the thousand chandeliers in the king's great hall in the palace on the Wawel Hill; sparkled like the rubies and emeralds that gleam in the queen's crown; sparkled like the wondrous thing that it was, all touched by the red rays of the morning sun—the Great Tarnov Crystal!

"Now whence has that come?" shouted Pan Andrew so loudly that the sleepers in the next room awoke. "Where, by all that is good and holy in the world, have you found the gem which has been in my family for years and years, which all my ancestors and I have sworn to guard forever and to surrender to no person except to the king of Poland? How has it come into your hands after it was stolen from me, and my heart was nearly broken? Did you get it perhapsfrom that ruffian who has been captured by the king's guards? Did you find it perhaps in the ruins of the town? Did you perchance—" The truth suddenly flashed upon him and he was speechless.

"It is an accursed thing," cried out the alchemist suddenly, reeling in Jan Kanty's arms as if he were gone faint. "There is blood upon it, and fire! It has lured princes and kings to their destruction! It has made men's brains mad with lust for want of it! It has caused good men to steal, and evil men to kill. I will have none of it. I will have none of it, I say." He was growing almost boisterous, yet there was something in this attack of madness that had much of reason and determination in it. "I will have no more of it," he repeated, "and no more of Johann Tring."

At that he fell fainting to the floor.

Jan Kanty raised him, and Elzbietka, who had run out from the trumpeter's room, rushed to him and kissed and fondled his blackened hands.

Pan Andrew picked up the Great Tarnov Crystal and held it at arm's length with a smile.

"Now may peace come upon us all," he said, "for I may fulfill the oath that my family has taken and deliver this to the king. While the secret of its hiding place remained with me, I might keep the crystal as long as I chose, but now that the secret is out, there is but one place where it may be guarded safely, and that is in the palace of the king. Pan Kreutz is right. This jewel has already done too much harm in the world."

"Then you may rid yourself of it at once," broke in Jan Kanty. "The king returned to Krakow two days ago, and we may find him at the castle this very morning."

XV. KING KAZIMIR JAGIELLO

Of all the wonders that the capital city of Poland possessed, Joseph knew of none that stirred his imagination more than did this royal castle of the kings upon the Wawel. Impregnable through many sieges its great rock base had stood, brick and stone heaped high above it in a great mass of towers, turrets, and walls. At its very heart, high above the winding Vistula and the town, stood a strangely built round tower, enclosed and protected by the palace wings, where men in prehistoric times worshiped the old nature gods of the Slavs; a place of rest and seclusion where on rare occasions, when townsfolk might visit the castle, Joseph had stood thinking of things that had been in the old days.

He knew well the legend of Krakus, the hero of the Dark Ages who slew a dragon that had once made this hill his habitation. There was a cave, so Joseph heard, that ran from the fortress underground beneath the river, a secret exit in time of siege; here had been the dragon's lair, until the hero overcame him, and from that day men made the Wawel a home from which might be seen climbing into the air spires and belfries. All this Joseph had seen; he had fed his fancies upon every object that graced the bleak, majestic rock, and yet there remained one glory that had never yet met his eyes. That glory was Poland's king.

But this morning, after the fire, when the little company set outfrom the Church of Our Lady Mary toward the Wawel Hill, Joseph felt his heart leaping strangely in his breast at the thought of the adventure that was to be theirs. To see the king, to have audience before him—it made the blood sing in his ears and tingle in his fingertips.

They took the alchemist with them, on Jan Kanty's advice, although he still seemed like a man in a dream.

"I found him wandering through the fire-swept streets early this morning," said the scholar. "He had been running hither and thither all night long in the most dangerous parts of the city, and how he has escaped death from falling timbers and burning coals is more than I know.... The man has something on his mind, something that troubles him hugely, and with it all, he seems to be acting like one in a spell."

"Do you think it well to bring him with us?" asked Pan Andrew, who had doubted from the beginning that there would be any benefit from the man's presence.

"Yes—I have a curious notion," answered the scholar, "that he may be able to help us. We have much to explain to the king, and the man's presence will make our story more credible. And who knows, perhaps the alchemist himself may get help—he needs some light thrown into that brain of his, and since he is harmless, it will do no damage to take him."

Pan Kreutz's hands and face had been washed and dried, and most of the fire grime had left him; the scholar's robe was useless, however, and Pan Andrew hung a kontusz, or long coat, about his shoulders.

Joseph was there with the three men; Wolf had been left behind,sleeping upon the floor of the high tower room. Joseph's mother and Elzbietka were under the protection of the day watchman who relieved Pan Andrew at dawn. It was necessary for Pan Andrew and Jan Kanty to assist the alchemist in walking at times, when his feet would shuffle curiously, like those of a man walking in his sleep, but he plodded along bravely, not yet realizing quite clearly what was happening about him, yet confident that the two men near him were his friends and were leading him to some good place.

From Castle Street they turned at length up the long slope leading to the castle on the Wawel. Behind them lay street after street of desolation, of smoking ruins, of masses of wood still flaming; amidst these ruins men were still working valorously, tearing down charred beams and hurling in tons and tons of water from the water wagons, which were now all drawn by horses. One side of Castle Street had suffered badly, the houses on the Street of the Pigeons were entirely destroyed, St. Ann's Street had but few buildings left, while much devastation had been done along the Street of the Bakers, the Street of the Goldsmiths, and the Street of the Jews and Broad Street.

Jan Kanty's company was challenged twice by guards on the way to the palace, but when the soldiers recognized the good father, they were at once passed along without question. It was another proof to Joseph of the esteem in which the man was held; in himself, however, there was not the least indication of pride and ostentation, he was as simple as a child in most matters affecting worldly things, and yet his name was as magic, even in the court of the king.

At length they all stood in the little passageway on the Wawel through which one passes to the palace, and here the guard, withspear raised in salute to the scholar, bade the company wait until he went to see if an audience might be had.

The soldier came back quickly. "The king," he said gravely, "will grant any request that may be made by Father Jan Kanty; he only begs that the company wait a few minutes, until a present audience is finished."

They waited perhaps fifteen minutes, until an important-looking functionary in a blue robe came to announce that King Kazimir Jagiello would receive Jan Kanty and his friends.

Out into a wide court they went, following the courtier in blue, up a marble staircase to the left, and along a balcony. Then suddenly a door was flung back and they were in the presence of the king.

To Joseph, remembering it afterward, it all seemed like a dream, it was all so quiet and without ceremony. King Kazimir had chosen to receive them in a small antechamber in which he often met certain persons who were to be received without the usual ceremony of presentation, and Jan Kanty was one of the privileged ones that he met in such fashion.

Joseph and his father dropped upon one knee in front of the king. He was sitting in a high-backed chair without a canopy, which bore at its highest peak a royal crown; this crown was just above the monarch's head, so that at first it seemed as if it were actually upon his head and he were crowned. He wore a huge purple robe which fell clear to the tops of his soft leather sandals; it had a great collar embroidered with silks of many colors and in many patterns; a heavy gold chain held the folds of the collar together, and beneath the collar folds, could be seen a rich vest embroidered with gold. The sleeves of the robe were immense and hung down far below hisknees as he sat there; the robe itself was fringed with heavy fur. His head covering was a simple cap of the same color as the robe, flat, soft, and turned up a trifle at each side.

The king himself seemed the picture of comfort and informality; not so his guards. On each side of him stood a guard in plate armor, with stiff metal pieces over the arms, stomach, thighs, and legs. At the waist they wore short, straight swords, ready for action at a second's notice. These two men were as motionless as statues. About the room stood knights in different kinds of armor, some in light chain with long skirt like coats, some in mail jackets that resembled checkerboards in pattern and extended only from shoulder to thigh, some in heavy armor and metal shoes armed with spurs.

In front of the king were two pages carrying scepters. They, too, stood motionless as he spoke.

"What is this?" he asked as Jan Kanty came forward to kiss his hand, which ceremony the king did not allow. "Have we here some poor city dwellers driven forth by last night's fire?"

"Yea," answered Jan Kanty, "that is true, though we come not on business of that sort. We are here upon some matter that may be of deeper interest than one would suppose. These are Pan Andrew and his son Joseph, by family name Charnetski, dwellers of the Ukraine driven forth by violence and come here to have audience with your Majesty."

"So," said the king with quick interest. "Stand, if you please, and tell me the circumstances of your trouble, for it greatly interests me at this present time. I have much news from the Ukraine, and not so pleasant, either. How came you by your misfortunes?"

"If your Majesty please," began Pan Andrew, rising and takingout the crystal from beneath his coat, "I wish to deliver to your Highness the Great Tarnov Crystal."

The sunlight touched it as he held it up, and the room and its splendid company were suddenly agleam with wavy flecks of light, red and orange and blue and yellow; there was a dazzling brilliance to it that struck each eye with almost the force of lightning. The king literally sprang forward to take the wondrous thing from Pan Andrew's hands.

"What a marvel! What a thing of beauty!" he exclaimed, while a very murmur of astonishment ran through the circle of his attendants. "Where in the world is to be found any jewel one-half so miraculous as this?"

"I know not," answered Pan Andrew, "but it has been in the keeping of my family for many years."

"Then why do you deliver it up to me?" demanded the king. "It is worth a quarter at least of all the treasures in this palace."

"That I will explain. My family has held it in trust these two hundred years and more, and we have sworn to guard it until the secret of its hiding place became known, and then, since there would be great danger following such a discovery, to deliver it into the hands of the king."

"Then its hiding place has been discovered? But tell me first the reason for concealing such a wondrous stone."

"That, your Majesty, is a long story, which if your Majesty so desires I will deliver shortly in writing, but I may say briefly that when Tarnov fell before the Tartars these many years ago, the citizens entrusted this crystal to a member of my family. He took oath to guard it zealously, with his life if need be, lest it fall into thehands of people who might abuse its powers, for its beauty hides strange properties which are allied to magic and sorcery and the black arts, and it has been at times a curse, a thing of mystery and a source of evil. When Tarnov was rebuilt, new dwellers came there and the crystal remained in our family."

"How did the secret become known?"

"I had a servant, a Tartar. He was with me for many years. It was my custom to conceal the crystal in the rind of a pumpkin, and many a time this man must have seen me scraping out the inside of a pumpkin and rubbing the shell with oils and gum in order to preserve it. Because he was a simple fellow, I took no pains at any time to conceal my task. But though lacking in wit, it seems that the man was not lacking in curiosity. And his curiosity, I now believe, led him to spy upon me, and eventually he discovered the use to which I put the preserved pumpkin rind. He left me about a year ago, and it was only a few months later that my house was attacked. I am sure that he sold his information to some Tartar chieftain."

"Could he suspect the value of the crystal?"

"That I do not know. I do know, however, that legends concerning this crystal are everywhere to be found among the Tartars and Cossacks. When they are children they are told tales of it, and all of them grow up in the hope that some day they may find it."

"Thou thing of beauty," said the king, gazing at the crystal, "could thou but speak and tell all that men have done to possess thee. Thou cruel, marvelous thing."

Pan Andrew fell upon his knees before the king. "Take this crystal and guard it, your Majesty," he exclaimed with great feeling,the tears already streaming down his face. "It has already done enough harm in the world. In my own family it has been nothing but a burden, a source of endless anxiety and suffering. My father's fathers, years and years ago, even dug a passageway in the earth, through which one might escape with it secretly in case of an attack, and so cleverly was this passage concealed that for years no one but the master of the family has known of its existence.

"In spite of the beauty of this jewel, I hate it from the very bottom of my heart, and I hope that I may never look upon it again. For every ray of light that it reflects, thousands of men have fought and died for its possession; for every color that lurks within its depths, miseries and sufferings have swept over whole nations. I have guarded it faithfully but no more shall I guard it. I am fulfilled of my oath."

The king looked into the crystal fixedly, and then suddenly shuddered, as if he saw something fearful there.

"I shall be before many years an old man," went on Pan Andrew, in a pleading tone. "My home in the Ukraine exists no more. My house is burned, my fields are laid waste, and all because I had this jewel in my possession and men envied me."

He then went on to tell the story of the escape from the Ukraine, the pursuit, the attempted robbery of his house, the attack on the tower, and the persistency and repeated appearances of Peter of the Button Face, whom he had heard of in the Ukraine as Bogdan the Terrible.

"I do not know," he said, "who it might be that sent this man to dog my steps, but my son, Joseph, has told me that your guards have taken this same Peter a prisoner in the streets, and that he is acaptive of your men. Let me confront him here, and perhaps I may learn who it was that drove me from the Ukraine."

While he was speaking, the king gradually took his thoughts from off the crystal, and when he mentioned the name Peter, the king grew restless with excitement.

"I have the man," he exclaimed, "and he shall be brought here. My spies in the Ukraine reported recently that a great treachery was afoot and that this man Peter, or Bogdan, was in Poland for the purpose of consummating it. His description was given to my guards, and a reward was offered. Last night he was seen in the district where the fire was raging, and my guards brought him in. I shall have him here directly."

Two spearmen brought him in; as he walked, the chains which hung from his arms and legs clanked on the door. He did not deign at first to glance at Pan Andrew or any of his party, but simply looked at the king and folded his arms defiantly and with spirit. Whereat the two guards forced him to his knees.

His air of indifference disappeared, however, when his eyes fell upon the Tarnov Crystal, which the king had set down upon the floor before him. He glanced left and right and favored the trumpeter and the alchemist with a look of bitter hatred.

"You are accused of treason against the Commonwealth of Poland," said the king immediately. "Have you any plea to make?"

"Who accuses me?"

"The governors of the Ukraine," answered the king. "And moreover you are charged with other crimes, among them that of persecuting this citizen here before me—you have destroyed his home and fields and attacked him while he was on duty in the churchtower. The penalty for any one of these is death."

Peter did not lose his self-assurance for a moment. He realized more quickly than another might that his plea of innocence would soon be broken down. He fell back then quickly upon another means of obtaining his end.

"I would buy my freedom," he asserted.

"What have you that is worth while to me?" asked the king.

"Much. You are threatened in the Ukraine."

The king thought for some minutes. It rather irked him to give this man his life, since he had already done such damage, hut on the other hand he might be able to obtain some really valuable information. The whole Ukraine was in some kind of uproar, and even his most trusted spies had not been able to get to the bottom of it. The usual method of obtaining information from prisoners in those days was torture, and in the field of battle it was employed widely, but often in cases of such desperate men as Peter torture led them to confess wildly but seldom with truth. The Cossack was ordinarily a man of his word, and Peter had enough Cossack blood in him to make him pass for a Cossack in the Ukraine and in the East.

"It pleases me to be merciful today," replied the king. "There has been too much suffering at my very gates to make me wish for more. Your death would in no way pay for your crimes, and it is possible that your information might be of service to the commonwealth. I could wrest this information from you by torture, but I prefer an easier way.... Now, mark," he cautioned the Cossack, "I know certain facts concerning what you have to tell, I have information from my own men in the Ukraine, and if you utter somuch as one word of a falsehood to me, I will have you taken out and hanged by the neck from the tower gate. Do you understand?"

"I understand," answered Peter, turning just a trifle pale at the threat. He was a bold man, he was a desperate man—otherwise he would not have ventured back into Krakow after having been defeated there twice—and he had no fear of death in any form, so long as he was free and able to fight. But now his knees smote together at the thought of hanging, and he resolved that he would keep close to the truth. After all, the whole affair was finished for him. The crystal was in the hands of the king, and he was not likely to part with it easily.

"One thing," he said in a low tone, "one thing, your Majesty, I beg, and that is that you will let none talk of what I say. For if it were known that I had spoken the truth, my life would not be worth—that"—he snapped his fingers. "I have your promise, your Majesty."

"You have."

"Then hear what I have to say. I am Bogdan, known in the Ukraine as the Terrible. Two years ago in March I was summoned to Moscow by one in authority, who said that a powerful lord had something to say to me. Now, having an open mind always for new activities, I went, although our people have but little love for Muscovites. And there I was taken to one Ivan."

The king interrupted. "You mean—"

"I mean Ivan himself, chief power among the Muscovites, son of that blind one. He has the ambition to unite all lands thereabouts under himself—as emperor, men say."

The king bit his lips and his eyes flashed. "This they havetold me," he exclaimed in an angry voice. "I only wanted the confirmation of it that you have given me. Ivan—Ivan—that one who makes friendly proffers to one's face and strikes in treachery when the back is turned." He strode up and down the room for a moment and then turned to the captive again. His tone was as calm as it had been in the beginning. "Proceed," he ordered.

"In this he has partially succeeded, but his ambitions run higher, and he dreams of establishing his power over the people outside the borders, the Ruthenians and Lithuanians. Knowing them to be willingly under Polish domain, however, even the city of Kiev, which fell beneath Tartar rule, he wishes instead to strike a blow at the Poles in the Ukraine. Someone advised that he loose the Tartars against the Poles, and an ambassador was even sent to find out what would induce the khan to send his warriors to fight the Poles. The answer that he made was a curious one."

"And that was—" asked the king.

"This was his answer. He would lead his Tartars against the Poles in the Ukraine on one condition, and that was that Ivan should deliver into his hands the Great Tarnov Crystal."

At this the whole company started, chief among them Pan Andrew, for none of them had suspected that such great importance was even now attached to the stone.

"How did he know of the crystal?" asked the king.

"Everyone in the East knows of the Great Tarnov Crystal," answered Bogdan. "Every worker of magic, every astrologer, every chief, every prince, is desirous of possessing this treasure. For it is said that, in addition to being a jewel of great value, it has this quality also, that one may look into it and there read of the future—one may also find there secrets of great worth, one may see the faces of men long since in their graves. There are many legends and stories of it too, and since the days when it disappeared from Tarnov, when the Tartars conquered western lands, there has been search after search to find it."

The king thought for a few seconds. "Then the khan of Tartars knew that he was asking Ivan for an impossibility when he demanded the crystal? Does that mean that he meant to refuse to go against the Poles?"

"Please—your Majesty—it was no such thing," Bogdan stated emphatically. "A short time ago a servant who had left the services of this man here," he pointed to Pan Andrew, "went to the land of the Tartars and there spread the report about that the crystal was to be had for the taking, that it was hidden in a country house in the Ukraine. You may be sure that this reached the ears of the khan, whose passion for curious jewels is almost a madness, and when I, going from Ivan to Tartary, learned this, then Ivan promised the khan that he would get him the crystal if it could be gotten."

"You were the go-between?"

Bogdan bowed.

"And Ivan sent you to get it from Pan Andrew?"

Bogdan bowed, though not quite so low.

Fire leaped into the king's eyes. "Dog that you are," he said, "less than beast in all things that Christians believe, for this you must destroy a man's house and ruin his fields, yes, and threaten his life, too, if it would serve your purpose.... God knows, my kingly duties lie heavily upon me.... All that I seek in this, my commonwealth, is peace, peace with my neighbors and happiness for my people.And yet Poland is ever insulted to the point where nothing but war is possible. It is not enough that enemies on the north and west threaten, there must be plots against our happiness on the south and east. Oh, Poland, Poland, when will the day come that thy sons and daughters may enjoy the tranquillity that God has designed for all people? ...As to you," he turned again to Bogdan, "what further have you to say?"

"Only that I have failed," answered Bogdan miserably. "And only that I know that I shall go free, for there was never yet Jagiello who did not keep his word. Though had it not been for this creature here"—he pointed to the alchemist, who from the rear of the room had been watching the scene through half-shut eyes—"I should have had the crystal long ago."

The king did not reply. "Take him away," he said to a guard.

A captain in armor came forward. "Deliver this Bogdan at sunrise to the guards of the Florian Gate. Tell them to see that he has safe-conduct through to the border, but that his chains are not to be struck off until he reaches the frontier. After that, let happen what will, but if he so much as sets foot again upon Polish soil, he shall be hanged to the nearest tree."

When they had departed, he said to Pan Andrew:

"In this, my right and duty of kingship in the Common-wealth of Poland, I commend you most heartily as a man who has been of great service to his country. It is a most extraordinary and gracious thing that a family such as yours should be so faithful to its word through so many years and be willing to suffer so much for an oath once given. Therefore to you go my whole thanks."

He took the gold chain from his throat. It was a thing ofwondrous beauty, of heavy solid links cut out of the purest metal.

"Wear this," he said placing it with his own hands over Pan Andrew's shoulders. "This chain shall ever be to you the token of your faithfulness. I shall see to it that the state makes return to you for the property which you have lost, for in so losing it you have conferred a favor upon us all. Had the crystal been taken by these thieves and delivered to the khan of the Tartars it is probably true that by now the Ukraine had begun to be overrun by Tartars and the armies of Ivan. In due time I shall see to it that a more formal and proper reward is given you."

Here Jan Kanty made a sign that the interview was finished, and the whole company fell upon their knees before the king.

He, too, stooped, but only to pick up the crystal, which had lain upon the floor before him during the entire interview. It seemed to Joseph, glancing up at that moment, that the instant the king's eyes were fixed upon the stone he became suddenly oblivious to everything else that was before him, and stood as one in a dream or trance, gazing into the depths of the fearsomely beautiful thing.

XVI. THE LAST OF THE GREAT TARNOV CRYSTAL

Joseph and his father were still kneeling when there came unexpectedly a certain happening that changed the whole complexion of the day. It came from the alchemist.

He had been listening attentively through all the talk; he had followed back and forth the give-and-take of conversation, the balancing of argument, the gestures, the decisions, even though his eyes had seemed but half open. Just at this final moment he sprang up from his place, behind the others, like a dog leaping for a bone and snatched the Tarnov Crystal out of the hands of the king.

Gripping it, he rushed, like one gone wholly mad, straight for the door, brushing aside a guard who fell back in astonishment.

"Stop him," cried Jan Kanty, "he will do something desperate."

They might better have tried to stop the wind. He was through the door and out on the balcony and down the steps to the court below, where the guards, though astonished, had yet no pretext for seizing him, since he was an honored guest, one of the party of Jan Kanty. Through the little entrance to the court he went at top speed, just as the king, the scepter bearers, and the guards, followed by Pan Andrew and Joseph, with Jan Kanty behind, raced along the balcony and shouted to the guards below. These at once set out in pursuit, shouting in turn to guards at the farther gates. But the alchemist wastraveling like a hurricane; and passing the men at arms at the very entrance to the castle, he was off down the slope to the meadows below, where he swung to the left and bore toward the spot where the Vistula curves about the base of the Wawel.

Pan Andrew and Joseph continued in pursuit with the guards, but the king, with Jan Kanty, seeing the alchemist's direction, hurried to the extreme end of the fortifications, where one looks down directly to the river. At the very water's-edge the alchemist turned and beckoned to his pursuers to stop, threatening by his motions to throw himself into the current, which at that time of the year was swollen and swift. They paused, helpless, waiting until he chose to speak.

"Listen," he cried, gazing first at the pursuing party that stood not far distant from him on the shore and then directly upward, where Jan Kanty and the king were leaning over the wall.

A curious figure he presented as he stood there for a moment in silence, his garments sadly disordered, his hair twitched hither and thither by the wind, his features working from emotion—the globe of amazing beauty in his hands.

"Listen!" His voice now rose shrill and screaming. "It was I that stole the crystal from Pan Andrew. The first sight of it drove honesty from my head, as it has driven honesty from the heads of many who have seen it. I saw there all the magicians and astrologers of all ages have devoutly wished for. I saw there the means of working out a great name for myself, of becoming famous, of becoming envied over all the world. I was tempted and I fell, but I shall see to it that no more trouble comes from this accursed stone."

He paused, overcome by the effort of so much speaking, butin a second a flood of wild laughter burst from him. "There was the student Tring," he shouted, "yes, Tring—who used to be my student. Because I looked so much into the crystal my mind grew weak, and he knew and I knew. It was he who said that if we but possessed the secret of turning brass into gold, then we should have power without stint, and it was he who first directed me to read in the glass what formula I might find therein for such magic. What did I find there?... Only the reflections of my own crazed brain. And at last between us we have done nothing but cause want and misery and suffering all over Krakow. It is because of our madness that half the city is now but a heap of ashes, that men and women and children are homeless and in poverty."

With these words his voice shrank to a wail, and he stood, a pitiful figure, his shoulders drooping, and his face turned toward the ground.

"Cease, man! We are thy friends," shouted the scholar.

"Nay. Such as I have no friends. But"—his shoulders suddenly straightened—"with such jewels as this, that cause strife between man and man, and war between nation and nation—here—now—I make an end!"

Then, raising himself to such a height that for a moment he appeared to be a giant, he swung about and hurled the crystal into the air with all his force.

The sun struck it there as it seemed for a moment to hang between earth and sky like a glittering bubble or a shining planet. Then it fell, fell, fell—until it dropped with a splash into the black, hurried waters of the Vistula River, so that the circles for a moment beat back the waves of the rushing torrent—then all was as before.

Deep silence fell upon the onlookers. There was in the man's act something solemn, something unearthly, something supernatural— his emotion was so great, and the crystal had been such a beauteous thing; and when Jan Kanty said, "Let us pray," the whole company fell upon their knees. When he had finished a simple prayer, they went forward and took up the alchemist where he had fallen, for he had dropped down as if he had been suddenly overcome by a sickness. They carried him back to the tower of the Church of Our Lady Mary, where his niece and Pan Andrew's wife watched over him.

Meanwhile the king called the scholar into conference, and after much parley, and much weighing of pros and cone, it was decided that no attempt should be made to rescue the crystal from the bed of the river. There had been in its history too much of suffering and misfortune to make it a thing at all desirable to possess, in spite of the purity of its beauty.

And should its hiding place become known—should a foreign power again seek to obtain it, what chance had such a power with the king's army and the fortified city of the Wawel forever ready in its defense? Surely never had treasure a safer resting place.

And so, to this day, it has never been disturbed, though in later centuries many men have sought for it, and it rests somewhere in the Vistula River, near the Wawel, where the alchemist Kreutz threw it in the year 1462.

Pan Andrew received from the state enough recompense to rebuild his house in the Ukraine, and he repaired there that same year, taking with him Elzbietka and the alchemist, who was broken in health for a long time as the result of his experiences. When hecame to his senses, a few days after he had thrown the crystal into the river, he had returned to his right mind fully, though he had no remembrance of the dark scenes in which he had played a part. The student Tring must have left for his home in Germany directly after the fire, for he was never seen again in Krakow. In later years he gained some fame in his own native village by the practice of magic, in which it was said that he often called upon the devil himself for assistance.

Joseph continued his studies in the university until he reached his twenty-second year, and then he returned to the Ukraine to manage his father's estates. He was shortly afterward married to Elzbietka, the friend of his boyhood days....

And now, since we have come to the happy end of all things in this tale, may we close with the thought that every Pole carries in his mind—with the words that are foremost in the Polish National Hymn:

May God Save Poland.

EPILOGUE: THE BROKEN NOTE

It is the year 1926. The Vistula River now no longer turns at the Wawel Hill and plunges straight through the Krakow plain, dividing the city of Kazimierz from the city of Krakow, but instead swings far to the left and surrounds the whole plain, now the new city. The castles and towers and cathedral of the Wawel still rise proudly on the hill, as in former days; St. Andrew's, which has defied fire, siege, and war for eight centuries, raises its head—two towers—above Grodzka Street; the old Cloth Hall, beautified during the Renaissance, still stands in the middle of the central Rynek. And although the glory of former days is departed from the city and kings no longer sit in the castle on the hill, there has come with the years the growth of a new glory, the glory of culture as seen in the university of fourteenth-century origin, in the schools of fine arts and music and handicraft and trade. From all Poland come students to study and to live in this venerable city, which is Gothic in every corner and every gable save where here and there a bit of Romanesque wall or arch has survived the Tartar, or the Cossack, or the Swede.

But the chief glory of the city is the Church of Our Lady Mary. It no longer stands apart, a monument visible from afar as of old—other palaces and buildings have shut it in, and one sees its towers only, until one is close upon it. Then the sudden magnificenceleaps upon the visitor. A splendid silence lurking in its high roof descends suddenly, like the thousands of pigeons that thunder down for particles of bread. Beneath one's feet is the old city cemetery; there on the walls are the tablets and shrines; there at the south doorway are the iron collars that once clasped the throats of petty criminals as they stood supplicating the prayers and pennies of the faithful. Inside, the church is a veritable miracle of beauty. Above its exquisite wood carvings and choir rises a vaulted roof of sky blue, studded with stars. Images of stone look down from breaks in the Gothic fluting—tablets, banners, altars, shrines—all strike alike upon the sight in amazing beauty.

But listen: is the organ playing? Whence come those notes that float down from above like God's own music from heaven? They come from the towers, for the hour is striking on the bell, and a trumpeter is playing at one of the open tower windows. And that tune? It is the Heynal, the same tune played by a young man so many centuries ago, when the Tartars burned the city—and listen, the trumpeter breaks off his song in the middle of a note.... Four times he sounds the Heynal, once at each of the four windows, west, south, east, north. And many a man or woman or child on hearing that song thinks of the days when the young life was given to country and God and duty.... Poland has been through many fires since that time—she has had centuries of war, a century of extinction. But in all that time the Heynal has sounded with each passing hour and men have sworn each year to keep the custom unto the very end of time. Hark, it is sounding now.

May it bring in an epoch of peace to all men!

END OF BOOK

第一章　玛妮雅唱歌

怎么不行？如何不行？到底为什么不行？为什么不让玛妮雅读书？她最终还是把问题埋在了心里。她不愿意去问自己温柔美丽的母亲；她只会撑着自己倔强的小脑袋，百思不得其解，一缕金发后那双明亮的灰蓝色眼睛透出锐利的目光。

总是这样！她自顾自地说：“我就不能读书吗？”一摸书，就肯定有人会说，“玛妮雅乖孩子，快去花园里玩玩吧”。或者“你可是一整天都没玩布娃娃了呢”。又或者“快用那些漂亮的新积木搭幢房子吧”。玛妮雅对他们这些小把戏早已了如指掌。她要是读书那就是淘气——但这只针对她一人而言，要换作是布朗尼娅那就完全不同了；然而事实上，布朗尼娅根本看不懂书，只有玛妮雅才能读懂。不过，她但凡从布朗尼娅手里抢来本书，那就是大错特错，尽管她并没有任何恶意，这可真让人摸不着头脑。有时候她们待在叔叔的果园里无事可做，布朗尼娅就会叫她一起玩字母卡片，于是两个人就躺在草地上，摆弄着卡片将字母拼成单词。从叔叔家回来后的某一天，爸爸问起了功课，对布朗尼娅说：“来看看你最近读书有没有长进。”布朗尼娅摊开书，开始拼单词，但却读得结结巴巴、磕磕绊绊。玛妮雅一把夺过书来放声朗读。“玛妮雅！”妈妈厉声喊道，又急又气，而爸爸则是一脸严肃，布朗尼娅也气鼓鼓的。玛妮雅别无选择，只能啜泣道：“对不起……玛妮雅不是故意的。”

自从那天起，家里就彻底不让玛妮雅读书了，她站在妈妈的房间门前不知所措。布朗尼娅与约瑟夫和海拉一起玩堡垒对峙的游戏，于是整个早上玛妮雅都要不停地穿过长长的走廊给布朗尼娅运送“军备物资”。堡垒是用新积木块堆成的，这运送的“物资”中自然也包括积木块了，不一会儿玛妮雅就又热又累，游戏也就暂告一段落。休息时，玛妮雅看到了姐姐便跑去花园里。“若莎！若莎！”她边跑边叫道，然后两个人手牵着手一同走。若莎已经十二岁了，在他们四个小屁孩儿的眼里那就是大人了，四个孩子中约瑟夫、海拉、布朗尼娅已经年满八岁，而玛妮雅当时只有五岁，不过她四岁便开始读书识字了。正是因此才不让她读书，斯克沃多夫斯基夫妇不想让他们天资聪颖的小女儿过早承受压力，但夫妻俩却没想着要给玛妮雅解释这个原因。

花园又大又平整，四周围墙环绕，草坪被踩得有些破败，但周围树木茂盛。花园里大部分地方都能让孩子们玩得尽兴，唯独出入花园时他们却要特别当心，因为要经过“怪人”叔叔家的窗户，这个花园坐落在男子中学里，斯克沃多夫斯基一家和怪人叔叔都住在学校里。即便是若莎，在经过怪人叔叔家的窗口时都是小心翼翼，放低声音悄悄告诉小妹妹要保持安静。

尽管只有五岁，但玛妮雅懂得的事情可不少。她知道奥格尔是个怪人，因为有一群人将她的祖国一分为三并且出卖给外人，就像巨人与两个同类瓜分战利品一样，而奥格尔就是这群人中的一员。玛妮雅是波兰人，奥格尔是俄国人，是一所学校的校长，玛妮雅的爸爸就是那所学校的数学和物理老师。奥格尔要求学校里所有的波兰人，不分男女，举手投足都必须表现得和俄国人一样。玛妮雅知道和这样的人在一起必须时刻保持警惕、小心翼翼，不要被抓住把柄。

玛妮雅知道的还不止这些：尽管她生活在城市里，但她清楚地知道乡下是个景色秀丽、充满欢乐的地方。在乡下，人来人往、热闹非凡，有自己的叔叔婶婶、堂兄弟姐妹；在乡下，可以在溪流里划船涉水，可以捏泥巴然后在太阳光下烤干做成“美味的泥巴蛋糕”。乡下还有一株古老的椴树，他们七个堂兄弟姐妹可以坐在上面，尽情地嚼着从清爽绿叶下摘下的醋栗果。玛妮雅一来，他们便将她举上弯弯曲曲的树枝上乘凉，给她摘果子吃。七月里玛妮雅简直就是个玩疯了的小农夫。

她还很了解自己的妈妈。她知道妈妈爱她远胜一切。妈妈温柔美丽、歌声动人，玛妮雅对此深信不疑。每晚睡前，妈妈都会抚摸玛妮雅的秀发和额头，虽然不是亲吻脸庞，但玛妮雅很喜欢这种特殊的亲密方式。晚上，全家人都会围跪在圆桌旁祷告“保佑妈妈快点好起来”，玛妮雅却从未想过这样做是因为妈妈生病了，也没联想到这就是妈妈不能亲吻她的原因。

玛妮雅出生于1867年11月7日，取名玛丽雅，不过大家都唤她玛妮雅或玛妮莎，或者更亲昵地称呼她一个特别的小名安丘佩秋，因为波兰人特别喜欢昵称。若莎有时候会坐在花园里给玛妮雅讲个关于安丘佩秋的长长的故事，若莎讲故事讲得比别人都好，还会经常编一些有趣的小短剧，自编自演给弟弟妹妹看，她一个人扮演所有角色。若莎演得惟妙惟肖，看得玛妮雅时而哈哈大笑，时而胆战心惊，都搞不清自己到底生活在哪个国家，周围的邻居是什么样的人，故事里的人物又是谁。

回到家，她们看见爸爸已经下了课，正坐在书房里，书房是家里面积最大且欢乐最多的地方。两个人轻手轻脚地走进书房，看见妈妈正坐在那里给玛妮雅缝鞋，剪刀咔嚓咔嚓作响，裁过硬硬的皮革。蜡线刺啦刺啦在皮革层间穿梭、拉紧，小锤头叮当叮当地敲在按扣上。斯克沃多夫斯卡夫人白皙纤瘦的双手灵巧敏捷，即便是做这样费劲儿的活儿也游刃有余——不过她也必须这样，因为五个孩子一年就能穿坏好多双皮鞋。

爸爸整晚都在谈论奥格尔，平常也经常会提起他。奥格尔对这个家庭影响很深，而且以后还会更深。奥格尔最近严厉地批评了一个波兰男孩，就因为他犯了一个俄语语法错误，但俄语可是世界上最难学的语言之一。斯克沃多夫斯基先生又没忍住，替学生解围道：“奥格尔先生，尽管您是土生土长的俄国人，但您也会犯语法错误呀。”奥格尔没有立刻反驳。他皱着眉，瞪着眼，但最终还是忍住了怒火，准备留着以后一起算账。

玛妮雅在爸爸的书房里踱来踱去，挺着自己笔直的小鼻子，沉浸在自己的想法里，小心翼翼地摆弄着喜欢的小玩意儿，怕吵到哥哥姐姐，他们都在爸爸那张平整的大书桌上做作业呢。玛妮雅对挂在墙上的那幅精美的主教画像丝毫提不起兴趣；据说这幅画出自名家之手，但并不对玛妮雅的胃口。她喜欢桌子上那座钟表，能一直聚精会神地盯着表面，听着响亮的嘀嗒声。她的手指在色彩明丽的西西里桌子那光滑的大理石板上有节奏地划来划去；她也喜欢这张桌子，但不喜欢它上面的诸如蓝色塞勒夫杯子之类的东西。她格外留心地从一旁走过，以免碰到这个易碎的物件。而其他的宝贝就没有这么娇气；它们更结实也更神秘，有又长又难懂的可爱名字——这挂在墙上的气压计，爸爸每天都会在孩子们的注视下认真检查；玻璃橱柜里还摆着精致的天平、矿物质和金箔验电器。“那些……？”玛妮雅有天问道。

“那些是什么？”爸爸用一本正经却又略加调侃的语气打断了玛妮雅，“那些是物理仪器。”

爸爸并没有想到！玛妮雅自己也从没想过，日后她与物理仪器之间会结下怎样的不解之缘，但她当时确实喜欢上了这个发音独特的名词，边跑边唱道：

“物——理——仪——器，物——理——仪——器……”

第二章　玛妮雅学习

玛妮雅上的学校可真是个怪地方，她在那里学些不寻常的事。比如，如何打破禁条，做不允许做的事；如何快速掩饰自己不守纪律的小动作；如何假装在做自己并没做的事；如何蒙骗政府巡查员。因为玛妮雅比一般小孩都聪明，所以她很快就比别人做得都好。但学校里最奇怪的就是，无论班主任还是女校长都觉得玛妮雅是个温顺乖巧的好孩子，而不是个问题学生。

一天，班里二十五名学生都在如饥似渴地听着历史课——历史课比英语课生动多了，因为这是一堂禁课。班里的二十五名学生和老师都知道这是违反纪律的。

孩子们端坐在教室，年龄大多十二岁左右。玛妮雅只有十岁，坐在第三排靠近窗户的位置，透过高高的窗户她能看到外面白雪皑皑的草地。班里所有孩子都身穿海军蓝的校服、系着钢扣、翻着白领子，头发编成整齐的辫子别在耳后，挺着笔直的腰杆。她们全都竖着耳朵，左耳朵费力地听着历史课上的每一个字，右耳朵警惕地准备捕捉随时可能响起的门铃叮当声——她们全部都参与了违禁活动！老师和学生们随时都可能被抓住！

玛妮雅正在回答问题——老师很喜欢叫她回答问题，因为她历史成绩总是名列前茅，在算术、文学、德语和法语课上也是数一数二。这会儿，她正在复述她学到的关于波兰国王斯坦尼斯拉斯·奥古斯特的相关内容。

她说：“1764年，奥古斯特当选为波兰国王。他是一位睿智聪颖、文化造诣极高的国王，与诗人和艺术家为友。他深知波兰弱小的原因，努力让国家走向富强，但遗憾的是他缺乏勇气……”即便是玛妮雅这样的小姑娘也知道国王必须勇敢有魄力，因而她的语气满是惋惜，这是一个早谙世事的十岁孩子发出的沉重叹惜。当——当——丁，丁。所有人立马吓得一个激灵。大家快速行动，并且绝对安静。女教师杜佩莎收起波兰课本，所有的学生也都摞好他们的练习册和波兰历史书。五名值日生用围裙收好所有人的书，一个箭步冲到住校生的宿舍里放好。其余人拿出针线包，在棉布上缝着精美的纽扣，就好像从未做过其他事。

俄国巡查员走进来，旁边跟着女校长，她因为没能挡住巡查员快速的脚步而面色沉郁，并且有些惊慌失措，担心那两声长两声短的警铃没能给孩子们足够的时间来掩饰违禁行为。但事实上，孩子们并没露出任何马脚，好似一直在专心做针线活，别的什么也没有，唯一可疑的一点就是那五名值日生小姑娘热得两颊红扑扑的，气喘吁吁。不过男巡查员根本察觉不到这一点。

巡查员霍恩贝格先生一屁股重重地坐在椅子上。他脑袋胖乎乎的，且剃了光头，但长得还算顺眼。他身上的制服也为他平添了几分帅气，他身穿黄色裤子，合身的蓝色皮夹克上扣着锃亮的银色金属扣。在一片寂静中，他透过金丝边眼镜眼神凌厉地扫视着每一名学生，并且快速瞥了一眼杜佩莎老师摊开在桌上的书。

“学生们做手工的时候你还大声读书吗？”他审问道，“是什么书？”

“《克雷洛夫的寓言》。我们今天刚开始学。”

霍恩贝格先生熟知这本俄语书，并且打心眼里认可。他随意打开一张课桌，发现里面净无一物。孩子们停下手中的活儿，礼貌性地等着巡查员训话。而他却一点儿也看不出孩子们那一张张平静的笑脸背后隐藏的恐惧和机灵，以及庄重严肃的眼神背后透露出的愤恨。

“女士，请点一名学生起立。”

杜佩莎如释重负，她肯定会挑一名绝不会惹出麻烦的学生。然而，这名学生也在默默祈祷千万不要被点到，“老天爷，求求你，千万别是我……”她却没听到上天说，“玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡，全世界都在等着你学会去做那些令人不悦的事。”她确实听到杜佩莎老师叫到了玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡！

她站起来，脸上红一阵、白一阵，羞愧感如鲠在喉。

“背诵主祷文。”霍恩贝格命令道。

玛妮雅听从吩咐，按照这个俄国巡查员的命令，用俄语而不是按照自己的民族习惯采用拉丁语，开始背诵。

“说出继叶卡捷琳娜二世之后，伟大俄国沙皇的名字。”

“叶卡捷琳娜二世，保罗一世，亚历山大一世，尼古拉一世，亚历山大二世。”玛妮雅用标准的俄语背诵道，就好像自己是土生土长的圣彼得堡人。

“还有沙皇家族成员的名字和头衔。”

“皇后陛下，皇太子亚历山大殿下，大公殿下……”

“很好！谁统治我们？”

玛妮雅犹豫了。

“谁统治我们？”巡查员重复道，有些恼怒。

“俄国沙皇陛下亚历山大二世。”玛妮雅吞吞吐吐道，脸色苍白。

讯问结束，巡查员走了，对他所见所闻甚是满意，感觉对自己的部门领导得十分成功。但玛妮雅却因此崩溃大哭，痛苦得仿若心碎。

放学了，走在外面的大街上，孩子们兴奋地向前来接她们的妈妈和保姆阿姨们讲述一天发生的事情；但一定都是低声耳语，因为他们清楚地知道，任何一个路人、闲逛的人都可能是间谍，甚至会将一个孩童说的话向政府报告。

海拉和玛妮雅一边一个牵着露西娅阿姨的手。“巡查员考问玛妮雅了，”海拉悄悄说道，“她对答如流，但事后又哭得像个孩子。不管怎样，巡查员什么刺儿也没挑到。”

玛妮雅绝口不提。她厌恶这一切——厌恶自己的恐惧，厌恶自己属于一个被奴役的国家，厌恶自己不得不撒谎，一直在撒谎。她紧抓着阿姨的胳膊，记起了自己厌恶的一切，首先是想尽办法让爸爸不能再教书的奥格尔。这件事迫使他们不得不接受学生借宿在自己家里。学生们调皮、令人讨厌，常常让家里人觉得不自在。但比起没有若莎陪伴，没有若莎给她讲故事，听她倾诉衷肠，这点不愉快根本不算什么。若莎不幸被家里借宿的一个学生传染上了伤寒症，永远离开了人世。

阳光和煦，三个人穿过白雪覆盖的公园向华沙老城走去。老城里街道狭窄，两边建筑物高斜的屋顶上环绕着一圈白雪。不时地探出奇形怪状的小雕塑，是圣女的脸庞或奇特的石兽。

突然，头顶上方传来古老教堂的钟声，在这冷冻结霜的空气中显得清脆而洪亮。这附近有很多类似的教堂，露西娅阿姨引着孩子们穿过其中一座黑漆漆的大门，多年前他们常来这里做礼拜。没有了若莎，玛妮雅现在怎么走进去？但她还是进去了，因为她现在心里比任何时候都感到冰冷和害怕，也想祈求上帝能让母亲身体渐好。“让妈妈好起来吧，”她祈祷道，“就让我替母亲去死吧，求求你，上帝。”

在冬季凛冽的寒风中，露西娅阿姨提出：她们要去维斯瓦河，从运输船上买些苹果。忘掉了忧伤，孩子们蹦蹦跳跳地走下长长的石阶，朝河边走去。伟大的维斯瓦河翻滚着沉郁的黄色巨流，绕过低平的沙洲，长长的、空荡荡的驳船缓缓地停靠在一起，有时因为撞到浮槽和岸边的洗衣房而发出沉重的砰砰声。只有在两只长长的、载满苹果的驳船边才显露出这冬季里的一丝生气，它们从河上游的远方而来，为华沙城的孩子们带来了红润明媚的欢乐。船主惬意地裹着羊皮袄，来回摆弄着货物，抱起货物上盖着的稻草，向客人们展示：尽管驳船在维斯瓦河上一行数日，但船上的苹果还是红彤彤有光泽，丝毫没有被霜冻坏。

先是海拉，而后是玛妮雅，她们脱掉了暖手筒，放下书包，兴奋地挑拣起苹果，整齐地码在大柳条筐里，将好不容易找到的坏苹果扔进河里，比比谁投得远。

露西娅阿姨找了个男孩将篮子提回家，并从船上把两个孩子赶下岸，那会儿她们俩还在大口大口地啃着红润的苹果。

她们五点钟才到家，用过家里的可口晚餐后就坐在大桌子旁开始写作业。很快在这些愤怒的小孩子中间便爆发出了喧杂的读书声，他们声音很大，这在波兰以外的国家肯定是种不礼貌的行为。孩子们要用俄语学习。而用俄语学数学对波兰孩子们来说更是难上加难。学法语和德语语法也是用俄语，有不认识的单词就查俄语字典。当然他们可以用波兰语描述难点，但第二天一上学就要用俄语，而且还要用俄语复习几何课。他们要用外语写作，并且直接用俄语来学习法文。学习真是件困难的事。

但玛妮雅可是个小小魔术师。她好像有魔力似的，不用刻意去学，就能知道很多事；俄语诗只要读两遍，就能毫无差错地完全掌握，小幸运星！她也是个好心肠的幸运儿，有时提前做完作业，她就会帮别人解决难题。当然这只是偶尔。如果有机会，她就会两肘支在桌上，中间放上一本书，双手捂着耳朵不去听海拉的背诵，只是专心阅读。玛妮雅读书的时候全神贯注，什么都无法打搅；她什么也听不见。全家人有时可能特意开玩笑，敲打着罐子，制造出像在动物园里一样的声响，而玛妮雅如果是在看书就什么都听不见。这就是聚精会神，上天赐予她的美妙礼物。

有一次玛妮雅看书时，其他人在她周围用椅子搭起了一个架子，左右各放一把椅子，后面一把，上面一把，头顶上方又搭了三把。她不仅听不到搭椅子的声音，连椅子或者搭建者的影子也看不到，更听不到别人兴奋的窃窃私语或捂嘴发出的咯咯笑声。玛妮雅看完书抬起头，“椅子大厦”轰然倒塌，躲在一旁的人群立即爆发出洪亮的笑声。这让玛妮雅有些不悦。她揉了揉青肿的肩膀，走进另一间房，顺便瞥了一眼哥哥姐姐们，说道：“真幼稚！”

晚上睡觉前，斯克沃多夫斯基家的女孩们在餐厅里打地铺，卧室让给了付费借宿的学生。睡到半夜，皮毯经常滑落，把人冻得瑟瑟发抖。而且他们早晨天不亮就要起床，把餐厅腾出来，再为学生们准备早餐。

但这些对于玛妮雅来说都不重要。她妈妈病得越来越重，就连她也看得出来。她经常向上帝祷告，但上帝好像并没有听到这个十岁小女孩的声音。春天，将近五月份时，玛妮雅还不满十一岁，妈妈就去世了，并在临终前对女儿说道：“妈妈爱你。”

玛妮雅自此学会了很多；认识到面对生活，不仅仅是一个国家的君王需要勇气，整个国家、成年人和孩子们都需要充满勇气。她对这一切也有了自己独到的看法。生活对她来说既残忍又不公平，更是无法完全理解的。她固执、愤怒，且绝不顺服。

第三章　反叛

十四岁的玛妮雅出落得还没有姐姐们漂亮。布朗尼娅已经日渐成熟，穿着拖地长裙，金黄的头发在脑后束成发髻。她接任了母亲在家的角色，照看家务和寄宿学生。海拉已经十六岁，出落成了一个美人，白皙高挑、光彩照人。约瑟夫也长得高大帅气，他已经上了大学，在学习医药专业。

女孩们也憧憬着自己有朝一日能上大学，但在俄国统治下的波兰，女人是不能上大学的。如果她们想在中学的基础上再有所深造，便只能从书本中获得，或者去其他国家学习。

此时，玛妮雅对自己还比较满意。她上到了高中，就像小松鼠捡到了坚果一样快乐；但她有点儿担心布朗尼娅。上不了大学，布朗尼娅该怎么办？玛妮雅能不能想个办法把布朗尼娅送到某个国家，在那里女孩能学习她们想了解到的一切？她下定决心，要努力工作赚钱供养姐姐。然而，赚钱最快的方法就是顺利毕业！一天早晨，玛妮雅如果不快点吃完早饭，上学就会迟到，她切好午餐吃的三明治，最后正准备切做三明治用的羊肉时，朗斯特一个箭步跑来抢肉吃，这打断了玛妮雅的思绪，但她救出了——是的，她从朗斯特嘴里救出了羊肉。朗斯特是一条赤毛猎犬，是全家人的宠儿。它十分漂亮，淘气地做尽了一切不该做的事。它的耳朵、尾巴和四肢上长着金毛，本应做一条温顺的猎狗，但却丝毫未被驯化。玛妮雅还有兄弟姐妹们都十分宠溺它，经常亲吻它，把它宠得像条哈巴狗。它在椅子上呼呼大睡，尾巴一扫打碎了花瓶；偷吃别人的午餐；对来客张牙舞爪、惹人心烦，悄无声息地叼走客人的帽子和手套——等再找回来时，那帽子和手套几乎都戴不成了。

玛妮雅终于安全地包好午餐，把书包往背后一背，叫朗斯特乖乖待在家后，便连忙往学校跑去。

经过扎莫伊斯基伯爵住过的蓝色宫殿时，玛妮雅停下脚步，在一座守护着古老石头庭院的大青铜狮子前驻足，用手将狮子嘴上挂着的重铜环推到鼻子上。

“玛妮莎，先别走，”窗边传来一个声音，“卡西娅马上就来。”玛妮雅经常来接卡西娅一起上学，那是伯爵图书管理员的女儿；如果卡西娅来晚了，她就会把青铜环推上去，然后先走。这样卡西娅就能知道她是不是先走了。

“今天下午来喝茶，”卡西娅的妈妈说道，“还有你们最喜欢的冰可可。”

“你一定要来喝茶哦，”卡西娅说道，“哦！我们是不是要迟到了？快走吧！”

于是，两个人沿着狭窄的街道一路狂奔，穿过公园，但都没能像路人一样观察到彼此之间的差别。卡西娅穿着精致得体，一看就是父母特别宠爱的小公主，而相比之下玛妮雅穿得就有些寒酸了。

上学的路很长，她们有足够的时间闲聊，也有足够的时间玩点儿小游戏。在多雨的日子里，两个人穿着胶鞋踩过水洼最深处，拖出一道长长的水印；天气晴朗的时候，她们就玩“绿色”游戏。

“咱们去商店买个新练习本吧，”玛妮雅说道，“我之前见到一些特别漂亮的练习本，绿色封皮的那种……”

但卡西娅并未上当。还没等玛妮雅把话说完，她一听到“绿色”这两个字就从兜里摸出早就准备好的一块绿色天鹅绒递给玛妮雅。卡西娅成功避开了惩罚，不过游戏没有继续下去。玛妮雅好像并不想玩游戏。她讲起了上次的历史课，课堂上老师一反常态地告诉学生波兰只是俄国的一个省，波兰语也只是一种方言。

“不过老师看上去有些不自在，”玛妮雅评论道，“你难道没注意到老师根本就不敢直视咱们，而且面色有些苍白吗？”

“没错！”卡西娅说道，“他几乎都脸色发绿了。”不消一瞬间，她就看见玛妮雅在她眼皮子底下捻动着嫩绿的栗子叶。

“我们都走过纪念碑了！”玛妮雅惊慌地叫道，“哎哟，天啊！我们得赶快往回走！”她们回过头时刚好就在萨克斯广场，看见四只石狮子上立着一根高柱子。柱子上面写着“献给忠君爱主的波兰人”。沙皇让人立起柱子，警示那些背叛国家的波兰人，他们为支持压迫者而奋斗至死。每次经过纪念碑，忠心爱国的波兰人都会向石碑吐唾沫，这已经成为他们的职责。玛妮雅和卡西娅每次都会尽心履职，哪怕是走路折返或是上学迟到。

“你今晚要来看跳舞吗？”玛妮雅问道。卡西娅当然会去。每周都会有几家人来斯克沃多夫斯基家里聚会跳舞；不过只有长大成人的女孩们才能跳舞。卡西娅和玛妮雅只能静静地坐在一旁看。然而，她们光是看也能学会一些技巧，研究舞步，探讨移动姿势，熟悉曲调；等大人们跳完舞，她俩就开始自己练习。

她们穿过学校里的拱门走进庭院，边走边热切地聊着“长大成人”的趣事。女孩们从四面八方拥进庭院。她们一个挨着一个走到空地上，走进三层楼的建筑里；人群中充满了欢声笑语和兴高采烈的寒暄问候。但其中有一个女孩，独自一人行色匆匆，尽量避免惹人注意。玛妮雅和卡西娅迎面走向她，发现她双眼红肿，而且衣衫不整，好像匆忙穿上来不及收拾一样。

“库妮卡是怎么了？”她们互相问道，其中一人用胳膊搂住了她。

“库妮卡，你怎么啦？”

库妮卡几乎说不出话，她苍白的脸上满是痛苦。“我哥哥出事了，”她断断续续地说道，“他被秘密逮捕了……已经整整三天了，我们没有他任何消息……他们……他们明天黎明时分就要把他绞死。”

这些话听完只会让人觉得大脑一片空白。两个人将库妮卡从人群中搀到一边；俯下身来，试图仔细理解她说的话，努力安慰她。但对于哥哥明天就要被绞死的人来说，任何安慰都无济于事！玛妮雅和卡西娅认识那个年轻活泼的男孩。他是她们的朋友。他什么也没做错。可他怎么就要死了呢？

“快回去上课，同学们！也聊够了吧！”耳边传来德国督学迈尔小姐那恶狠狠的声音，三人不得不掩藏起痛苦，回去上课。

这已经不再是玛妮雅孩童时期上学的那所私立学校了，如今变成了俄国政府统治下的公立学校。在这所学校里，除了学生，一切都是俄国的。波兰学生只能上这所学校，他们别无选择，因为只有这样才能获得一纸文凭、找到工作。他们还在上学，所以能比大人们更加反叛，并且可以更加自由地表达思想。玛妮雅和卡西娅喜欢编俏皮话来打趣她们的俄国老师、德国校长，尤其是迈尔小姐，并以此为乐。迈尔小姐讨厌玛妮雅，而玛妮雅对她的厌恶更是有过之而无不及。

小个子、黑皮肤的迈尔小姐，为了不让人发觉，总是穿着软底鞋到处走，以便更好地监视女孩们。

“没必要再和那个叫斯克沃多夫斯卡的女孩废什么话，”她说，“跟她讲话就是用青豆砸墙，丝毫不起作用！”

“看看你那愚蠢可笑、任性妄为、曲曲拳拳的头发，玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡！你多长时间梳一次头？过来，我给你梳梳，最起码让你看上去像个大方得体的女学生。”“那才像德国版的玛格丽特呢！”玛妮雅在心里嘀咕道，但她嘴上什么也没说。于是，迈尔小姐拿着那把不知梳过多少人头发的梳子，蛮横生硬地梳着玛妮雅的头。不过无论她怎么用力，那些鬈发就像和她作对一般——那一头光亮精致且固执任性的鬈发仍旧原模原样地勾勒着玛妮雅那张叛逆的小圆脸。

“别用那样的眼神盯着我！”迈尔小姐吼道，“你没有权力低头轻视我！”

“我也无能为力。”玛妮雅如实说道，她比迈尔小姐高出整整一个头。有些话能够一语双关，这无疑让玛妮雅一阵窃喜。

不过，学校里的某些老师还是受人爱戴的，他们中有一些是波兰人。而在一些俄国老师身上，学生们也惊讶地发现存在着对波兰的同情之心。于是他们开始慢慢理解，即使在俄国，也存在反叛之人。一位俄国老师竟然将一本革命诗集作为奖励赠予学生。这一无声举动迅速成为校园里热议的话题，学生们也充满好奇与敬仰地打量起这位老师。波兰人与俄国人可以和平共处。是的，没错！学校里的学生本不就是有俄国人、波兰人、德国人、犹太人吗？在学校他们丝毫感觉不到种族的区分。而在校外，各国人彼此之间保持距离，以防间谍。

尽管这样，玛妮雅还是热爱自己的学校；带着一丝羞愧，她坦白了这一切。“卡西娅，你知道吗？”她有次放假写信时写道，“我喜欢学校。你会因此嘲笑我吗？我喜欢学校，甚至非常喜欢。我虽然没有极度渴望上学，肯定没有！但我也不会因为一个又一个的学期而苦恼，更不会因为还要上很多年学而感到害怕。”

但就在那一天，当迈尔小姐将学生们从庭院里叫回来时，玛妮雅却根本无心上学。在这个阳光明媚的早晨，她满脑子本来想的都是音乐、跳舞和玩乐。但忽然之间，世界天翻地覆。课堂上晦涩的内容全都左耳朵进右耳朵出，她什么也看不到，眼前只浮现出自己认识的那个热血少年……以及带有绞刑架的寒冷黎明。

当晚，斯克沃多夫斯基一家根本无心跳舞。玛妮雅、布朗尼娅、海拉、卡西娅和她姐姐乌拉都陪着库妮卡通宵坐到天明，守望着漫漫长夜，心念着那个即将失去生命的男孩。守夜是天主教的习俗，让人保持清醒以便思考。六个孩子包括库妮卡在内围坐在一起。我们旁观者根本无法体会她们当时的所思所感。这与亲人的自然死亡截然不同，即便是孩童也能领会自然死亡；但这种——只能坐等时间的静静流逝，等待昭显人类残酷冷漠的时刻步步逼近，等待人类用不义的行为污染黎明——的确令人毛骨悚然。这场守夜一定是沉默寂静的，因为无言可诉、无事可为，唯有思绪万千，唯有六颗年轻反叛的心所拥有的反抗思想。她们时不时竭尽所能地安慰库妮卡，也因为同情而心如刀绞。她们试图劝慰库妮卡喝些热水；轻柔地搂着她或帮她擦干泪水。忽然间，她们觉察到有烛火之外的亮光射进房间。天际绯红。红色的黎明已经到来。六人将充满恐惧的面庞深深埋藏在臂弯中，跪卧在地上，为那个逝去的男孩祈祷。

第四章　整整一年的假期

玛妮雅十六岁了。授予金质奖章的日子悄然来临，玛妮雅是家中第三个拿到金质奖章的孩子。颁奖的日子在六月份，正当炎炎酷暑。玛妮雅同其他获奖人一样，身穿黑裙，腰带上别着一束蔷薇花。周围熙熙攘攘的人们向她握手道贺。这一切的结束也就意味着玛妮雅永远告别了高中生活，她挽着自豪的父亲，手指紧紧地握着父亲的胳膊。

父亲亲口许诺要给她放整整一年的假。这的确是一份大礼，整整一年的毕业假！玛妮雅不知道为什么自己可以放这么久的假，但父亲认为玛妮雅一直以来十分勤奋，而且比同龄的其他女孩都早毕业，她可以尽情享受自己的努力成果，悠闲等待同龄人追赶上她的进度。于是玛妮雅一下子从一个勤奋上进的小姑娘变成了“小懒虫”，开始尽情享受这其中的乐趣。

“亲爱的小伙伴，”她在给卡西娅的信中写道，“我已然不知这世上竟然还有代数和几何这样的东西。我早把它们一股脑儿抛在脑后了。我甚至连手工也不做了。我什么都不做。我早上十点钟起床，有时六点，什么也不学，有空就看看故事书。我现在是笨蛋中的大笨蛋，我嘲笑自己的空虚无聊、无所事事。我们一群人在树林里闲逛，或是打打羽毛球，有时还玩躲猫猫或找头领等益智类游戏，在这方面我简直就是个傻瓜。这儿到处都是野生草莓，一个铜板就能买一堆，足够一顿饭吃的——能装满满一大盘，摞得高高的还止不住往下滚。哎呀呀！哎呀呀！这一大盘都快吃完了，我的胃好像无底洞，我都被自己的贪吃给吓到了。荡秋千……荡得高高的，直冲蓝天。然后下河游泳，举着火把捉虾。顺便告诉你，我们遇见了一个演员。他给我们唱歌、朗诵，还给我们摘好多好多的醋栗。作为回报，我们就用深红色的野生罂粟花、蓝色矢车菊和粉白色的鲜花给他编了一个花环，在他动身去华沙前送给了他。伙伴们说看见他戴上了花环，等火车进站时又把花环装进了行李箱，一路带去了华沙。”

玛妮雅要在乡下度过她整整一年的假期。她热爱乡下的一点一滴。她将亲眼见证四季更迭，发现波兰这片土地角角落落的自然之美。她的叔叔赛维尔住在斯沃拉平原。在这里，她能望见平坦的大地绵延伸向远方，一望无际到天边地平线，绿油油的大地上遍布着一片片土黄色的耕地。叔叔家的马圈里养了许多匹马，于是玛妮雅也学会了骑马。她丝毫不必为骑马的装束而费心。从堂姐妹那里借来的衣服太大，她就用皮带把衣服扎起来，束出一片片衣褶，整装待发。左手拉着缰绳，拽着大马的鬃毛，左脚踩着马镫，右手扶着马鞍，她想像叔叔和堂姐妹那样一跃上马。但想骑到马背上可不是一件容易的事儿！无论她怎么又蹦又跳，就是上不去，那匹温顺的老马站在那里纹丝不动，她还是上不去。

“动作还行！”叔叔说道，“使劲往上爬！”而堂姐妹们也不会对她置之不管。她们教她上马时后背要向着马头的方向，教她可以巧借小土堆上马，最后给她讲跳上马的不同方法，这样即便是最高的马，她也能顺利坐到马鞍上。在绵延不断的田野上骑马远行带给玛妮雅最大的快乐。很快，即便是马儿一路小跑，她也能从马鞍上站起身来；即便快马疾驰，她也能稳坐如山。她骑着马到访了许多新村庄，遇见不同的乡里人，也领略到了越来越多的波兰平原风情。

其实还有更大的惊喜在等着她：玛妮雅后来又去了另一位叔叔家小住，那位叔叔的名字对英国人来说简直无法发音，他叫兹齐斯瓦夫，住在喀尔巴阡山区。这是玛妮雅第一次见到白雪皑皑的高山，它们闪烁着耀眼的白光，深色的松林带像一条条黑色的河流，将白雪衬得愈白……玛妮雅渴望近距离接触雪山；穿过树林走到白雪覆盖的山边。她长途跋涉，沿着蜿蜒的山路一路向上爬。有时候道路戛然而止，悬崖峭壁横在面前，她也就只能沿路折返。有时候，道路的尽头坐落着一间小木屋，玛妮雅和她的堂姐妹们就敲开木屋的门，想要看看屋主人的手艺活儿；所有在这片地区生活的山里人都是木匠，随便一件简单的家具就是一件艺术作品。山上的农民喜欢向人们展示自己的手艺，当孩子们对桌椅板凳、布谷鸟钟及挂在墙上的彩色木碗大加赞叹时，山民们就在橱柜里掏掏拣拣，拿出木刻的小人、酒杯、玩具，甚至还有木刻版画。

一次，玛妮雅闲逛时在山里发现了一个小湖，一汪湖水静静地躺在山间，瓦蓝瓦蓝的，就像长了一大片水蔓菁，山里人也叫它“蓝海之眼”。这汪湖水落在白雪皑皑的山峰之间，显得格外明媚动人。玛妮雅想，这儿风景秀丽，定是整个国家的瑰宝。

家里的生活也超乎寻常地令人感到轻松愉悦。叔叔爱热闹，美丽的婶婶和三个堂姐妹亦是如此，他们整日欢笑，玛妮雅也不觉加入其中。家里的宾客络绎不绝。叔叔婶婶有时候外出打猎，带回山野猎物款待客人。如果没出去打猎，便宰掉一只家禽，反正院子里养着上百只踱来踱去的家禽。女孩们就疾跑到厨房，匆忙地烤制些蛋糕。盛宴一切准备就绪。对于宴会穿的衣服，她们翻箱倒柜找出漂亮的裙子并缝制好，准备猜字谜的时候穿；如果是冬天，就准备好玩“库利格”时能穿的衣服，“库利格”可是严冬里的庆祝活动。

玛妮雅第一次参加“库利格”的经历总是让她记忆犹新。夜空漆黑，但却被北边的白雪映亮。玛妮雅和三个堂姐妹裹着厚厚的毛毯，穿着打扮就像克拉科夫的农民，分坐在两架雪橇上。她们的骑士是穿着朴实的乡下男孩，举着熊熊燃烧的火把照亮黑夜。穿行在漆黑的树林里，他们瞥见周围还有其他火光也在移动。寒冷的夜晚突然间响起了音乐声，原来是乐手来了，随行的还有四个犹太人。在接下来的两天两夜里，他们拉着小提琴，弹奏出扣人心弦的华美乐章。他们演奏华尔兹和玛祖卡舞曲，整个世界都跟着副歌一起欢唱，奏响夜晚的美妙乐章，叽叽喳喳好不热闹。

伴随着犹太人的乐曲，其他雪橇也穿过黑暗加入队伍中，三架、五架、十架，雪橇数不断增多。尽管有些令人汗毛竖起的艰险弯道和草坡，但那些乐手一个音也没错，用音乐引领着队伍在朦胧的星空下一路前行。

系着响铃的雪橇在途中遇到的第一间农舍前停下来，人们卸下挽具，欢笑着，高喊着，大声敲着农舍的屋门，叫醒农舍主人，不过屋主人也只是在假睡。乐手一下子就被举到了桌子上，房间被火把照得通亮，舞会正式开始。

热腾腾的晚餐端上了桌，随即一个手势，整个房子突然空无一人——不见了木桶，不见了欢闹的人群，不见了马匹，不见了雪橇，一切都不见了。一个更庞大的队伍，加上了农舍里的所有雪橇，穿过树林又赶往下一个农场。

几匹健马拉的雪橇在试图超车时，偏离了熟路，没法再返回原路，撞翻在了雪堆里。大部队停下来，火把在风中燃烧，众人围成半个圈，七手八脚地拍掉翻车人身上的雪，扶正他们的雪橇。疾驰的雪橇又响起了叮叮当当的铃声，打破了夜晚的沉寂。不过乐手去哪儿了呢？没有人知道。领头的雪橇滑得越来越快，希望能追赶上乐手；但很快就意识到他们走的并不是同一条路，也就不再继续追赶。队伍停下来，想起了刚才走过的岔路口。没办法只能折回去，去另一条路上看看能不能找到犹太乐手。大家都有点儿担心，找不到乐手可怎么去其他农场跳舞呢？突然这时，有人听到了响铃声中夹杂的那些欢快旋律，队伍终于完整了，而每到一处农场，队伍都会加长，越来越长。

日升……日落……太阳又一次升起。乐手几乎没有时间吃饭和睡觉。第二晚，庞大的雪橇队带着气喘吁吁的马儿和丁零当啷的响铃，在最大的农场门前停了下来，舞会正式开始。

矮小的乐手演奏着响亮的乐曲。宾客们各就各位，准备跳那著名的交谊舞。领舞的男孩帅气优雅，穿着刺绣的白色礼服，向前一步牵住舞姿最优美的舞伴，那便是玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡。她穿着山林仙女般的梦幻裙子，披着天鹅绒外衣，连着蓬松的亚麻袖，头戴如星星般闪亮的王冠，缀着飘逸鲜艳的彩带。

他们彻夜起舞，清晨八点钟还在跳玛祖卡舞。玛妮雅说她从没有过这样放松愉悦的感觉，婶婶说如果她真的这么喜欢库利格活动，将来结婚时可以采用这种方式来庆祝。

假期带来的欢乐还远未结束。斯克沃多夫斯卡夫人以前的学生，现在已成为弗勒里伯爵夫人，她邀请海拉和玛妮雅同她小住几日。伯爵夫人的公馆坐落在两条河流之间的狭长地带。在玛妮雅住的房间里，刚好能看到河水交汇时的壮丽景象，这段日子也让她学会了划船。她在给家里的信中写道：“只有我们想不到的，没有我们不能玩的。我们每晚睡得安稳，有时候白天也能适当休息。我们跳舞，几乎玩疯了。现在看来只有疯人院能容得下我们啦！”

她们除了睡觉、跳舞，还换着花样来骑马、采蘑菇、讲笑话。一次，玛妮雅写了个便条给伯爵夫人的弟弟，让他去镇上一趟。这个年轻人没起半点疑心，便赶赴镇上。往返小镇路途遥远。等回到家时天已经黑了，走进自己的房间，他才发现原来小伙伴们将他的被褥、桌椅、行李箱、衣服都挂在了屋子的横梁上。他的物品被挂得到处都是，多到在房间里走路随时都会打到脸。

有一天，有尊贵的客人登门拜访，家里准备了丰盛的午宴，孩子们却并未获邀参加。他们在中午前便把那午餐都吃掉了，并在空桌子上放了一个稻草人装扮成一位心满意足、饱餐过的伯爵先生。这些恶作剧的小坏蛋们呢？跑哪儿去了？早都消失得无影无踪啦！

在伯爵先生和夫人的结婚纪念日上，这群淘气的小家伙们送给他们一顶用蔬菜做的巨形王冠。正当夫妻二人乐呵呵地坐在装饰华丽的宝座上时，小家伙们呈上了这个重达一百磅的王冠。最小的孩子背诵了一首诗，这首诗是玛妮雅为了庆典专门作的，结尾如下：

在这受人祝福的美好日子
一顿美味代表我们的心意！
愿每位少女都能觅得如意郎君
如二位一般伉俪情深
共同携手步入神圣殿堂
请赐予我们，赐予我们这欢乐时光

伯爵先生和夫人用尽心思举办了一场舞会。玛妮雅和海拉想要尽情享受那个美好的夜晚。破洞的舞裙尽显二人的穷困。她们数了数钱，又翻来覆去仔细检查舞裙。扯掉褪色的薄纱，发现里衬还能继续穿。两个人决定买点蓝色的塔拉丹薄纱，两边再系上绸带，那就是件新裙子啦。干瘪的钱包和熟练的针线活儿能化腐朽为神奇，其他的地方就用鲜花来装点，剩下的钱能买两双新鞋子。买好了东西，缝好了裙子，也从花园里采好了鲜花，一切准备就绪，望着镜中的俏丽佳人，仿佛在说：“你们是最美的。”

玛妮雅穿着新鞋跳了一整晚，直到跳烂了鞋子，第二天早上便把鞋子扔掉，迎接新的一天。

第五章　人物

玛妮雅回到了华沙。她一双灰色的大眼睛带着笑意审视着这个截然不同的世界，厚实的上嘴唇常常因为欢乐的微笑而颤动，不过脸上仍然挂着严肃的神情。同世界上大多数父亲一样，斯克沃多夫斯基先生也会想方设法让孩子们明白要靠自己的双手养活自己。他不再接受学生寄宿，一家人又重新回到了自己的小房子生活。尽管父亲还在努力赚钱维持房租、女佣和日常开销，但生活已经举步维艰，他们还要考虑到父亲将来只能靠微薄的教师退休金度日。这一点一直困扰着父亲。像世界上大多数父亲一样，他也想赚足够多的钱让家人生活富足。晚上坐在油灯旁，父亲也会深深地叹息。四双明媚的眼睛，或是长春花般浅蓝或是灰亮，都会抬起头来看着父亲，揣测他的想法；四个孩子异口同声抗议道：“爸爸别担心，我们年轻力壮，难道还养活不了自己吗？” 尽管斯克沃多夫斯基先生对孩子们的热忱感到欣慰，但他心里也不免犯嘀咕，自己这辈子没什么建树，不知道孩子们是否能成功。他天资聪慧，勤奋努力，但从生活中得到的物质回报却极少。孩子们会像他一样吗？这个身材矮小、体态臃肿、谢了顶的男人穿着他精心整理却依然破旧的黑外衣坐在灯下。这位父亲的一切都是一丝不苟、整洁利落的：他的字，他的思想，他的言语，甚至是他的行为。他也用同样细腻无微不至的爱抚养孩子们长大。带孩子们出门短游，父亲会提前制定好出行路线，带孩子们领略自然的美景，发现常人不易觉察的美好，大多数人未能发现美是因为无人提及。如果看到著名的古老建筑，父亲会讲述它的历史背景。在玛妮雅的眼中，父亲是完美的。她从未质疑过父亲那一丝不苟、精益求精的态度。她觉得父亲无所不知。事实上，父亲确实学识渊博。他用自己挣来的辛苦钱买了内容丰富的书籍，实时了解物理和化学界的新发现。他精通希腊语、拉丁文和五门当代语言，自己却觉得不足为奇。每周六晚上，父亲都会自己写诗并声情并茂地朗诵给孩子们听，让他们逐步接触到博大的文学世界。有时想给孩子们读些外国名著，比如《大卫·科波菲尔》，他会用波兰语朗读，尽管手中握着的是英文版本。

“家里没什么新变化，”玛妮雅在给朋友的信中写道，“植被真是生长得愈发茂盛！杜鹃开花了，朗斯特睡在毯子上！我把裙子染了，家里的女佣古茜娅正在竭力洗干净它。她已经把布朗尼娅的弄好了，很成功。我既没时间又没钱。有人介绍我们去给一位女士上课；但当布朗尼娅告诉她一小时一先令时，她夺门而出，好像房子着了火。”

然而，不管挣得多不多，玛妮雅都要做家教。那个年代，女孩能做的工作真是少之又少。但她此前从未想过，“我能招多少学生？能挣多少钱？”如果这样想，那就不是玛妮雅了！她有自己的梦想——不像女孩憧憬结婚，不像男孩渴望驾驶。她的梦想是波兰。她，玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡，必须拯救波兰。仅凭十六岁的青春年华，凭着父亲、学校和书本灌输到她脑袋里的那点东西，如何才能做到呢？玛妮雅知道还有人也怀揣着拯救波兰的梦想，谋划着炸死沙皇。还有人梦想着上帝能回应他们对波兰的祈祷。尽管玛妮雅为帮助一位革命党人而把护照借给了他，她却从没想过上述这些方法。她觉得最务实的方法就是最好的：做好眼前事；向俄国政府竭尽全力愚化的波兰人民传授知识；不断教学、教学、再教学，直到让华沙成为伟大思想的核心摇篮，直到让波兰强大到能引领欧洲。

英法两国目前正在盛行一股新思潮。一位年长玛妮雅十岁的朋友得到了风声，创办了一个秘密社团，名为“双翼学社”，专门研究新思想。玛妮雅、布朗尼娅和海拉都加入了社团。小团体每次在不同的成员家里聚集学习，不是学什么“旁门左道”或稀奇古怪的东西，就是学习解剖、生物和自然历史。然而，突然的敲门声和壁板里老鼠的响动，都会让大家打个激灵。如果警察逮住了他们，那谁都逃不过坐牢的命运。成员们既要学习也要授课。玛妮雅收集了大量图书，建起了一个小小图书馆。她把这些书借给穷人，不过她要提前教会这些人认字和阅读，这样他们才能看懂书。

有些波兰商店愿意让自己的女工下了班后聚在一起，跟着玛妮雅看书学习，开动脑筋，成长为更有作为的波兰公民。压根不用担心有人会将秘密泄露出去。小玛妮雅虽然内心欣喜，但表面上表现得很矜持，面对这群年长且粗犷的女工，她要求她们一句粗话都不能讲，一支烟都不能抽。玛妮雅觉得自己的鬈发太引人注目便索性剪了去，却没意识到剪了头发的自己更显得稚气未脱。她一天到晚忙个不停，什么都想尝试：演讲、参会、画画、写诗、读六七个国家的文学作品——毕竟，要紧紧追随伟大作家的先进思想。

但她思索最多的还是怎样处理布朗尼娅的问题。姐姐一天天长大，至少玛妮雅是这样认为的，如果她不上心根本没人会关注布朗尼娅的前途。每天早上，不论是晴空万里还是刮风下雨，玛妮雅都要去做家教。有钱人让她站在寒风凛凛的走廊里等候，对他们来说玛妮雅不过是名穷家教。“斯克沃多夫斯卡小姐，真不好意思，我女儿今早要晚点上课；不过你还是要上够课时，对吧？”到了月底，课时费又经常忘了给。“真抱歉，我丈夫会两个月一起结给你。”但是玛妮雅当时真的很需要钱。她迫切需要这笔钱来买生活必需品。

布朗尼娅当时面无血色，神情沮丧。玛妮雅不得不先将自己的梦想搁置一旁，暂时放弃自己上大学追求知识的迫切愿望。她必须先为布朗尼娅谋划好出路。

“布朗尼娅，我一直在心里盘算这件事，”某日，玛妮雅说道，“我也和爸爸谈过了。我已经找到了解决办法。”

“解决什么的办法？”

玛妮雅既谨慎又委婉地问道：“布朗尼娅，你现在攒的钱够你在巴黎生活多久？”

“够旅费和一年的生活费，不过学医要五年呢。”布朗尼娅立即回答道。

“好吧，做家教一小时才一先令，根本实现不了咱俩的梦想。”

“那？”

“这样，如果咱俩分头为自己攒钱，谁都成功不了。不过要是按我的计划来，你今年秋天就能坐上前往巴黎的火车。”

“玛妮雅！你不是痴人说梦吧！”

“当然不是。开始你先花自己的钱，然后我会给你寄钱。爸爸也会寄钱给你。同时，我也会给自己攒点钱。等以后你成了医生，就该轮到我去上学，到那时你再帮助我。”

布朗尼娅的眼泪在眼眶里打转，她知道这个提议对玛妮雅意味着什么，不过她也觉得这个“如意算盘”并不好实现。“你怎么能又养活自己，又接济我，并同时给自己存钱呢？”布朗尼娅问道。

“嗨！我一直也在想办法。我想找一个寄宿家教的差事，这样生活就不太用自己花钱了！这个想法是不是很完美？”

“不行，”布朗尼娅说，“我觉得没理由让我先上学。你比我聪明。如果你先上学，很快就能成功，之后我再去。”

“这怎么行？我的傻姐姐，布朗尼娅！你不是已经二十岁，而我才十七岁吗？你已经等待了太久，而我还有时间。年长的先去。等你在诊所谋得了差事，我就能跟着沾光啦！而且我已经下定决心了，就这样决定吧！”

于是九月份，就在她十八岁生日前的一个月，玛妮雅坐在了家庭女教师咨询机构的接待室里，按照自己想象中女教师的样子搭配了穿着。她新长长的头发服帖地顺在褪了色的帽子下面；她的裙子平整朴素；她心平气和、安静如常。

她紧张地走向坐在办公桌后的女士，手里紧紧地握着自己的毕业证和推荐信。那位女士仔仔细细地看着推荐信，突然抬起头看着玛妮雅，甚至是盯着玛妮雅。“你真的会德语、俄语、法语、波兰语和英语吗？”她疑惑地问道。

“是的，”玛妮雅回答道，“虽然英语没有其他语言讲得好，但是授课也能达到考试水平。我高中获得了金质奖章。”

“哦。那你期望的薪水是多少？”

“寄宿家教，一年四十镑。”

“如果有合适的职位，我会联系你的。”带着这个听上去没什么希望的承诺，玛妮雅离开了咨询机构。

不过没多久，玛妮雅就成了一名家庭女教师。那家人的姓名保密，因为他们可不想回忆起命运之神的捉弄。这家人为年仅十八岁的玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡开了一扇小门，玛妮雅后来告诉我们，如果当时穿过这扇门便可以隐隐预见日后悲惨的生活，她肯定不会进去。生活注定要让玛妮雅成为一位将天赋发挥到极致的英才，而不是郁郁寡欢、遭人白眼的小奴隶。这户B姓人家家境富裕，他们时刻提醒家庭教师自己的身份地位，对玛妮雅讲话更是冷若冰霜，唯恐暴露出自己内心的想法。他们在众人面前广施财富，却克扣了玛妮雅六个月的工资，又不让她在晚上读书，以免浪费灯油。他们人前讲话浓情蜜意，而一转脸背过身去便诽谤中伤，玛妮雅说这家人可是把朋友们也批驳得一无是处、体无完肤。

“我从他们身上学到，”玛妮雅写道，“现实世界中还真有书本里说的那种人，不与利欲熏心的人为伍才是明智之举。”也许就是在十八岁的年纪懂得的道理，让玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡在日后面对任何财富的诱惑都能保持初心、不为所动！

然而，玛妮雅的计划并没有奏效。住在镇上的B姓人家里，她发现自己每天都会产生一点儿花费。时不时能见到父亲，能与双翼学社的朋友们保持联系都很让人高兴，但一旦决定执行计划就必须坚持下去，无论付出什么代价。玛妮雅觉得自己必须彻底离开家，在偏远的乡下找份工作，这样就几乎不会有什么其他花费了。只有这样，已经远在巴黎的布朗尼娅才能达成自己的心愿。

玛妮雅苦苦寻找的职位终于出现了。远在乡下，而且薪水更高一点——一年五十镑。当然，那个时代的五十镑可比现在值钱多了。然而，玛妮雅还是怀着沮丧的心情给了父亲自己的新地址，不过对父亲来说新地址听上去并没有那么偏远和奇怪。

玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡

Z先生——

斯图集村

近普扎斯内什市

一月份，玛妮雅动身前往乡下，一月份的波兰已是一连积了好几个月的雪。当火车缓缓驶出车站，玛妮雅再也看不到向自己挥手的父亲了。这也是她人生中第一次独自一人，第一次感到迷茫害怕。遥远村庄里的那些陌生面孔很可能会像上一任雇主那样冰冷严酷，村庄偏僻更是让人逃脱不得。而父亲一天天变老，很可能会生病要人照顾。她留下父亲远赴乡下，这样做对吗？夜色渐浓，白雪覆盖的平原在夜幕下绵延至远方，但在玛妮雅的泪水中一切早已变得模糊。

坐了三个小时的火车后，玛妮雅还要再搭乘雪橇。她浑身裹着暖融融的毛毯，在漫天白雪的冬夜里一路前行，四周寂静，唯有雪橇铃叮当作响。

雪橇足足跑了四个小时。玛妮雅饥寒交迫，想着马儿到底什么时候才能把她送到。随后她看到了一小片光亮、一扇打开的门，全家人都出来迎接她——高大的屋主人、女主人，还有抓着妈妈衣裙有些害羞的孩子们，眼神里充满了好奇。女主人用热情友好的话语欢迎玛妮雅的到来，给她端来热腾腾的茶水，亲自将她领到准备好的房间，周到地留下玛妮雅一人暖和暖和身子，收拾一下随身带来的旧行李箱。

玛妮雅身处偏远乡下。她环视四周，满意地打量着房间雪白的墙壁、简洁的装饰和壁橱里的热炉子。

第二天早晨，她拉开窗帘，本以为会看见白茫茫的田野和白雪覆盖的森林，但眼前看到的却是工厂冒着黑烟的烟囱。她向后退了几步并再度放眼望去——有好多烟囱，看不见一棵树、一丛灌木、一个树篱。原来她来到了甜菜生产区。目光所及之处全是开垦好的准备种植甜菜的耕地。整个乡村都在种植甜菜。农民们开垦、播种、丰收。那些工厂也都是甜菜精炼厂。村里部分屋舍就是炼厂的工人们在工厂围墙边搭建的。玛妮雅住的这家男主人是炼厂厂长。村边的河流里也都漂着甜菜根。

玛妮雅看到工厂有些失望。对于周围大户人家的年轻男女亦是如此。人们谈论的话题无非就是家长里短、穿衣打扮，谁家要办舞会以及上场舞会持续了多久。有次Z先生和太太跳完舞回到家都中午一点了，这让玛妮雅甚是吃惊，她可能早都忘了自己上次跳舞到清晨八点的欢乐愉悦。“赐我一支讽刺漫画家的神笔，”她说道，“可以让我把这里的某些人好好描绘描绘。女孩都是大笨蛋，连怎么开口说话都不会，唯有我的学生布兰卡，这家的大女儿，聪明理性、热爱生活，就像一颗闪闪发光的珍珠。”除了布兰卡，斯图集村另一个有趣的人便是她三岁的弟弟斯塔斯了。他可是这所大平房的活力之源。他迈着小步子啪嗒啪嗒地到处跑，走下长长的楼梯，跑到外面的玻璃阳台上，阳台上面的藤蔓叶子掉光了，略显破败。而他咿咿呀呀的话语更是逗乐了玛妮雅。一次保姆告诉他上帝无处不在。“斯塔斯不喜欢那样，”他回答道，“我担心他会抓到我！他会咬我吗？”

而十岁的安迪亚是玛妮雅的问题学生，喜欢乱跑乱动，家里一来客人她就跑得不见了踪影。玛妮雅一天本该给她上四个小时的课，但她不断逃课，好不容易被抓回来还要再从头上起，使得授课并没有什么大的进展。安迪亚还喜欢赖床，玛妮雅每天必须拽着她的胳膊把她拖下床，每次这个过程都让玛妮雅气不打一处来。某天早上，玛妮雅花了两个小时才渐渐平息怒火、恢复平静。 玛妮雅一天最快乐的时光便是和布兰卡一起读书的三小时，以及业余能写信回家的休闲时光。“复活节的时候，我就回到华沙啦，”她写道，“每每想起这件事，我的心就明朗起来，控制着自己不再像野人一般大喊大叫。”

走在泥泞的村庄小道，玛妮雅看见了村里脏兮兮的男孩女孩。乱蓬蓬的头发下，他们明亮的眼睛上下打量着她。“这不也是波兰人吗？”她自顾自地说道，“我发誓要教书育人，难道不该为这些孩子做些什么吗？” 这些穿着破烂的孩子要么一无所知，要么只知道俄国字母表。玛妮雅想，给这些孩子秘密开设一间波兰学校将是件值得做的事情。

布兰卡听到这个想法后为之一振。“别高兴得太早，”玛妮雅说，“如果我们被抓住了，等待我们的那可是西伯利亚，你知道的。”两个人都知道西伯利亚的寓意——流亡在万里冰川的恶劣平原。但布兰卡甘愿冒此风险。两个人征得了Z先生的同意——正式开课了。

幸运的是，有一条户外楼梯直通玛妮雅的房间。十到十八个脏兮兮的小孩子爬着楼梯来上课。玛妮雅借来一些桌椅板凳，又花了原本就弥足珍贵的不多的积蓄给孩子们买了练习本和钢笔。欢乐也随即而来。笨拙的小手们握着不熟悉的钢笔，在雪白的纸上歪歪扭扭地画着字母。慢慢地，这些小顽童们就意识到原来自己听到的话语都可以在白纸上用黑字表达出来。孩子们的父母并不识字，因而为此颇感骄傲，纷纷走上木楼梯，在教室后面兴奋地看着孩子们的“伟大举动”。但其实孩子们学写字并不那么轻松容易。他们表情纠结、眉头紧皱、嘟嘟囔囔，就好像写字跟把甜菜根搬上山一样艰难。玛妮雅和布兰卡围着孩子们转，帮助他们写字。这些学生们脏兮兮的，经常走神，并不十分聪明，但大多时候，他们明亮的大眼睛里闪现着对上课的兴奋和对知识的渴求。

第六章　不幸中的万幸

夏天来临，其他人都放暑假了，但家庭教师一年到头都要坚守岗位。男孩们放假回家、女孩们在酷暑寒冬要起床的时候，玛妮雅的作用就显得格外突出。玛妮雅厌倦了这一切。生活没有一丝变化。明天不过是昨天的复制粘贴——早上从八点工作到十一点半，下午从两点到七点半，中午十一点半到两点是午餐及散步时间。晚上，如果安迪亚表现好就给她读书；表现不好的话，玛妮雅就做些针线活儿，顺便和她聊聊天。晚上九点才终于迎来了属于自己的自由时间，可以读书学习。不过就算这时，她也经常被打断，去做一些家庭教师要做的杂七杂八的小事。比如，安迪亚的教父让她陪着下棋；打牌三缺一，才不会管家庭教师到底喜不喜欢玩牌。玛妮雅对知识越来越如饥似渴，因为学习的机会越来越少。她的书已经陈旧过时，也没有人能听她倾诉自己的痛苦。她不知道自己该怎么办。她羡慕世界各地那些能自由上学的女孩，面临这个年龄该有的选择，接触大师们的先进思想，在实验室里学习和工作。维也纳、柏林、伦敦、圣彼得堡，尤其是巴黎，简直就是玛妮雅心中的神圣殿堂！不，不能是维也纳、柏林或圣彼得堡，它们可是波兰压迫者们的首都。但伦敦和巴黎可以！她极度向往巴黎，自由包容的巴黎不会压迫任何人，反而张开怀抱欢迎流亡的异乡人，拥抱那些渴求知识的人们。玛妮雅感到了深深的绝望。独自一人努力拼搏太过辛苦。存钱的速度极度缓慢， 布朗尼娅用钱的日子还长。父亲以后年老体衰了还需要她来照顾。玛妮雅还能去上大学吗？

玛妮雅已经出落得明媚动人。一头光滑迷人的秀发，宽阔高挺的额头，显露出无比的坚毅；精心勾勒的眉毛下嵌着一双灰色的大眼睛，灵动而深邃；随性的嘴巴带着一丝浅浅的笑意，让人不由得多看几眼。她肌如桃花，优雅迷人，手腕脚腕长得十分秀气；而她的睿智聪慧更为她增加了一层神秘感，让人充满好奇，想要一探究竟。

家中的长子卡西米尔放暑假回到家，很高兴结识了玛妮雅。他第一次遇见玛妮雅，是在花园里看见她在修剪枯萎的玫瑰。他从妹妹的来信中已经听说了关于玛妮雅的事，不过他并不相信，家庭女教师难道不是乏味无聊的代言人吗？

“但是……以祖国波兰的名义发誓！” 他自语道，“这一位截然不同！”

“老师，您今早给扶贫学校放假啦？”

“没有！” 玛妮雅说，她的脸上一如既往闪现着兴奋，“他们要忙其他事，五点以后才能来上课。”

玛妮雅想这是布兰卡深爱的哥哥，眼前这位高大英俊、举止迷人的年轻学生讲话温柔友好，对她的学生甚是关心，虽然一直坚持将她创建的学校称作“扶贫学校”。

当天晚上九点钟，玛妮雅并没有像往常一样去读那些沉重的书本。能和一位大学生切身聊聊他所学的专业会让人受益良多。明日再也不是昨日的复制品了。暑期打乱了之前工作的时间安排。卡西米尔坚持要划船野餐，而玛妮雅正是划船的好手。她骑马英姿飒爽，而马圈里大有可供挑选的骏马。三人从四十多匹马中挑出自己心仪的，整日在一望无际的平原上肆意驰骋。有时，一家人也驾着马车出去野餐，卡西米尔注意到玛妮雅纤细的手腕能自如地控制另一驾马车的缰绳。卡西米尔的左手拇指扭伤了，于是车夫就只能赶着第一驾马车，载着母亲和孩子们。

卡西米尔见过无数的“呆头鹅”，没人能有玛妮雅这样的谈吐和神秘感。秋季开学，卡西米尔重回华沙，他又开始盼望冬季圣诞节能够回家。

“最好永远都是冬季。”他说。听到玛妮雅大感吃惊的回答“不好！为什么呢？”他笑了。“我们不是要崇尚美好的事物吗？还有什么比一位脚踝优美、滑冰优雅的女孩更令人愉悦的呢？还有跳舞！你舞跳得那么好，难道你不喜欢跳舞，不喜欢在冬季的星空下滑着雪橇到处穿行吗？”

是的，玛妮雅再次回归了舞会，但她还是喜欢夏季——喜欢暑期。

“暑期？我在这儿的时候？”

卡西米尔一直在猜测她的答案。他说自己立马就要去征得父亲的同意。人们通常不会娶家庭女教师，但玛妮雅与众不同，简直完全不同。家里的每个人都喜欢她：父亲邀她一同散步；母亲把她介绍给自己的朋友；他的妹妹们更是喜欢玛妮雅。家人经常邀请玛妮雅的父亲、兄弟姐妹来家里做客；玛妮雅过生日时，全家人给她送礼物、送鲜花。他们肯定满怀期待，等着玛妮雅成为自家的儿媳。

但关于这一点，卡西米尔其实大错特错。当他告知父母自己要娶玛妮雅为妻时，父亲勃然大怒，母亲几乎晕厥。他们对自己的长子寄予厚望，期待他把整个乡下最富足高贵的女孩娶回家，怎么会同意让他去娶一个一无所有的家庭女教师，去娶一个在别人家打工谋生的女人？

“卡西米尔，你疯了吧！正常人谁会娶家庭女教师！”

“谁会娶家庭女教师呀！多好笑！”整片大地都在低沉回荡着这句话。地球绕着太阳高速运转，带来春夏秋冬的四季更迭。正是如此，才有了日后的玛丽·居里，而非玛妮雅·卡西米尔·Z夫人。

但当时并不能预见未来的玛妮雅心情十分抑郁。卡西米尔的家人对她开始变得冷漠，但她还不能辞掉工作一走了之，因为她每年还要给布朗尼娅寄二十镑。她唯一能做的就是下决心再也不会爱上任何人。生活又开始重复，日复一日。她教课，批评安迪亚，叫醒朱力克（因为不管什么书都能把朱力克送入梦乡），给扶贫学校上课，读化学书，下棋，跳舞，散步。只有一件事偶尔能给她带来点欢乐：当道路的边际模糊，有时完全消失在白雪下，雪橇连人一起翻到了白雪覆盖的沟壑里。这种情况下，人们会哈哈大笑，依稀能恢复一些往日的友善和快乐。

那段时间，玛妮雅给家里写的信更长了，但经常因为没钱买邮票而无法寄出。“好久都没收到布朗尼娅的来信了，”她抱怨道，“不过可能她也没邮票吧。”基于自身的忧伤，她也更能理解父亲、哥哥和海拉面临的困境。她写信给父亲，“别担心我们，您已尽到了一位父亲应尽的责任，您不是还教会了我们善良的品行吗？我们肯定能挣钱养活自己的。” 她在给哥哥的信中写道：“约瑟夫，借上一百卢布，好好待在华沙。别把自己埋没在乡下，也别因为我给你提建议而恼怒。还记得我们约定要有什么就说什么。大家都觉得在乡下行医就是坐井观天，不会有什么大的发展。缺少药店、医院和书籍的支持，医生就会变得束手无策，无论你怀揣多么崇高的治病救人的理想。亲爱的哥哥，如果这件事发生在你身上，我一定会悲痛万分，因为我现在对自己已经完全失去信心，唯把希望寄托在你和布朗尼娅身上。你不能埋没了我们家族世代相传的天赋。这些天赋必须在我们某个人的身上体现出来。我越对自己失望，便越对你充满希望。” 玛妮雅对海拉也充满爱怜，那会儿海拉被爱人抛弃，也由此对男人充满了愤恨。“说真的，”她写道，“人要学会认清他人！如果不想娶贫穷的女孩，就让他们见鬼去吧。没人强迫他们这样做，为什么还要与穷女孩相爱，然后又让她们伤心落泪？”

这是玛妮雅人生的低谷期。她担心自己受学生影响，脑子会变得愚笨僵化，很多教师都有这样的担忧。她的远大梦想看起来愚蠢可笑。“我现在唯一的愿望，”她写道，“就是有一个属于自己的小角落，能让我和父亲安身。要是能获得独立并有属于自己的家，我宁愿折寿。如果能离开Z一家，虽然不太可能，我就在华沙的某间寄宿学校里谋一份差事，再私下带点课挣些外快。这就是我唯一希望的事。生活不值得这样操心忧愁。”确实，这是她人生的低谷期。但一本名为《尼曼河河畔》的小说有幸提醒到她，真正的玛妮雅身上不该有这样消极的想法。“我的梦想都到哪儿去了？”她给布朗尼娅写信，“我想为人们做点事情，突破重重困难教会了十几个村里的男孩女孩读书写字。这是为了提醒他们自己是谁，自己能为世界做些什么！人们根本无法想象这种境况。生活是艰难的。我变得如此狭隘平庸。突然有这样一本书让我为之一振，我也为此痛苦不已。”与此同时，她给堂姐妹写信：“我处于黑色幽默之中，每日面对的就是凛冽的西风，夹杂着雨水、洪水和泥土。连霜都没有，我的滑冰鞋忧伤地挂在衣橱里。你们可能不清楚，在我们这个小地方，霜就像加利西亚的保守党和自由党人之间的辩论那样重要！不要认为你的故事会让我感到无趣。相反，能听到大地上其他地方还有人在活动甚至思考，都让人为之振奋！我只能用暴力手段粗暴地感知生活！随即我摇醒自己，逃脱出梦魇重新做回自己，我告诉自己：‘不要被其他人或其他事击垮。’但对新环境、新变化和新活动的渴望有力地督促着我，让我想做一些极度随性的事来结束这漫长且一成不变的生活。幸运的是，我有许多工作要做，因而这种念头并没有对我产生太多的影响。”

第七章　变化

玛妮雅渴望变化，而且即将迎来变化。她将远行。听说华沙有位学生，不过目前正远在比利时度假，玛妮雅要去比利时与她会合。玛妮雅突然开始怀疑自己是不是能欣然接受这么大的生活变化。她要独自一人远行，换乘五趟火车。她肯定会走丢的；或者小偷会趁她睡觉的时候，在半夜偷偷潜进她的车厢。但这些情况一次也没发生。她安全到达目的地，见到自己的新雇主，来到一个崭新的世界——一个到处充斥着财富并且也能让她享受其中的世界。学生的妈妈长得美丽迷人。这是玛妮雅人生中第一次见到沃斯牌的漂亮裙子；她能亲手触摸到柔软的皮草，欣赏到闪耀的首饰；她身边交往到的朋友，他们的肖像就挂在墙上，而且往往是出自著名画家之手。她在财富营造出的美好事物间游走，欣赏着魅力四射的舞会派对，倾听音乐，享受快乐，而且这些富人平易近人。F夫人很喜欢玛妮雅，走到哪儿都带着她，并在朋友们面前称她为“精致可爱的斯克沃多夫斯卡小姐”。

我们无法得知玛妮雅本人对这一切的真实想法，因为她很快会遇到一件更令人兴奋的事。大厅的桌子上放着一封信，上面盖着巴黎的邮戳，写着斯克沃多夫斯卡小姐亲启，是布朗尼娅的笔迹——这是布朗尼娅在课间休息时急急忙忙用方格练习纸写的信。好消息！布朗尼娅要结婚了！她在信中说一旦在巴黎有了属于自己的家，就邀请玛妮雅过去同住！巴黎！……大学……她所有的梦都要实现了吗？

事情远没那么简单。此前，玛妮雅就知道布朗尼娅和一个在巴黎求学的波兰学生订婚了，男孩聪明帅气、性格开朗。他的名字和玛妮雅唯一的爱人一样，也叫卡西米尔，卡西米尔·杜鲁斯基。他不得已逃离波兰，因为涉嫌一起谋反案。在巴黎，他还是生活在俄国沙皇派来的警察的监视之下，巴黎宪兵队的名录上也记录着各种各样对他不利的信息。但尽管这样，他仍是一名年轻有为的医生，并且即将与布朗尼娅完婚。因此，布朗尼娅再也没机会回到华沙照顾父亲。照顾父亲的重任就落到了玛妮雅的肩上，因为海拉对照顾人也不在行。

只看布朗尼娅的描述，未来是多么美好，多么愉快，多么理想！但玛妮雅在回信中写道：“我一直以来就是个傻瓜，十足的大傻瓜，以后还会这样傻下去，或者用句当下流行的话语，我从未被命运眷顾过！” 因而不幸的事也许会接二连三垂青于她。她继续写道：“我渴望巴黎就像人类渴望救赎，但对巴黎的希望很久以前就破灭了，而当现在前往巴黎的机会再次降临时，我变得不知所措。我不能跟爸爸说这件事，我觉得他一心想着我们明年要在一起生活，我也想给他的晚年带来一些快乐。另一方面，每当想起白白浪费掉的才华，我的心都要碎了，才华就该物尽其用，充分发挥。”玛妮雅正是因为觉得才华要充分发挥，才在同一封信中催促布朗尼娅收起自己的骄傲，用尽一切逢迎的技巧，祈求一位富人朋友帮助约瑟夫发挥他的才能。玛妮雅写道不单单是约瑟夫自己能得到帮助，整个世界都会因他的才华而受益。玛妮雅终其一生都秉持一种观点：世界上最崇高的工作就是帮助极具天赋的人将他们的才华发挥得淋漓尽致。她在结尾写道：“我心情阴郁，我觉得自己不该跟你讲这些事，影响到你的幸福。”

于是，玛妮雅回到家，和爸爸在一间属于自家的小房子里共同生活了至少一年。对某些人来说这可能略显枯燥，但玛妮雅很聪明，她能在家中发现一些更加合理的讨论。她也重返了双翼学社这个秘密社团，进行学习交流。

但命运总深藏一些意料之外的事情。五月，走在克拉科夫幽静的绿荫大道上，闻着绿草如茵的66号庭院中那株紫色丁香花的香气，没有人能想到这儿会发生什么意想不到或震惊世界的大事。庭院里的丁香花旁，有一幢窗户狭小的小平房。门上写着几个大字：工农业博物馆。难道这里会收藏古老的犁头或史前的铲子？才不是！俄国人还是保留了博物馆。一直以来，博物馆都是沉寂、无人问津的地方。但任何有学问的人都可以在博物馆里教书。玛妮雅的表哥是这间博物馆的馆长，也在此秘密教授科学。他还有一间实验室，可以让学生们亲自动手做实验。

玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡生平第一次走进实验室！而这将对日后的世界产生巨大的影响。她不能经常去实验室，只在晚上和周末才有空。实验室里也没有老师指导。她独自一人尝试按照书本上的描述进行实验。实验结果有时无法预期，有时一点小小的成功会让她燃起希望，而有时一次意外失败又令她深感绝望，但不变的是她勇于探索、不断尝试探究未知奥妙的精神。

深夜回到家，玛妮雅缩进被子里，有些事紧紧萦绕着她，在她的脑海里挥之不去，在黑暗中向她喃喃诉说。她无法入睡，就好像身体里还藏着一个人在与自己对话，揣摩着自己的想法，并告诉自己该起床做些什么。工作自己找上门来，必须坚持做完。博物馆里的试管还有曲颈瓶和父亲之前收藏的物理仪器同属一类，玛妮雅甚是喜欢。玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡找到了自我——精巧的双手必须永远摆弄试管和火苗、元素和金属，聪明的大脑会从手里的工作中得出结论，还能洞察未来。

不过她该怎么办呢？双手和大脑都鼓励她继续前行！而亲情却提醒她要留下来陪伴父亲和兄弟姐妹，留下来陪伴爱人卡西米尔·Z先生，他还在努力争取赢得父母对两个人婚姻的许可。放假了，两个人终于能够碰面。他们一起上山，他滔滔不绝地讲述自己的痛苦处境，征求她的建议。

“如果你自己都想不出办法，”玛妮雅终于失去了耐心，吼道，“那也别来问我。”她至少最终还能明白自己真实的想法。她匆匆忙忙地给布朗尼娅写信，“给我个明确的答复。我不会给你添麻烦的。我睡在哪儿都行。但我祈求你真实地回答我。”

布朗尼娅做了诚挚的回答。如果电报不那么贵，她肯定就发电报了。玛妮雅如果没有那么多事情要安排，她肯定就搭最近的一班火车了。她把自己所有的积蓄摊在桌子上，和父亲一起清点。父亲也倾其所有，拿出了自己的积蓄。他们眼前摆在桌上的圆卢布，让去巴黎成为可能，但也仅仅只是可能。

就连一路都只坐三等车厢，玛妮雅也负担不起。在波兰和法国，三等车厢就是最便宜的，但德国还有四等车厢。四等车厢就像大型的行李车。中间光秃秃的，没有隔间，贴着四面车厢壁各放一个长条凳，细心的人自己会带小板凳坐在车厢中间。玛妮雅就可以这样做。她要带很多行李，以便在巴黎节省开支，但她能用行李车托运的最大物件便是床垫、毯子、床单和桌布。她唯一要买的就是一个廉价结实的大木箱，她在上面骄傲地写上了玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡的首字母“M.S.”。她在木箱里放了结实耐穿的衣服、鞋子和两顶帽子，随后又放了旅途中要随身带的东西：坐火车三天的吃食、板凳、书、一包焦糖和一条毯子。

玛妮雅动身前往巴黎。二十四岁的她，眼睛里闪烁着期待和愉悦的光芒。期待已久的旅程正式开始了。

第八章　“我抓来太阳，随手又将它丢在一边……”

“我抓来太阳，随手又将它丢在一边……”玛妮雅看到这句话笑出了声。自己在哪儿？在巴黎的中心。一切有趣和自由的事情都有可能在这儿发生，而她伟大的老师保尔·阿佩尔也遵从自己的内心，想教什么就教什么，想怎么教就怎么教。如果他讲授真理，那么就会有大批的学生拥入课堂。

玛妮雅很早就来上课，在巴黎大学圆形剧场式的教室里挑了一个前排位置坐下，将笔记本和笔盒整齐地摆在面前的课桌上。周围充斥着人群走进教室的喧闹声，但玛妮雅什么都听不到；她完全沉浸在自己的思考当中。教授走进来，教室瞬间安静了下来，在座的学生都是心潮澎湃的数学家，他们期待学术上的美妙碰撞。

阿佩尔教授晃着他方方正正的脑袋，身穿一袭深黑色长袍，显得严肃庄重，他清楚地解释着为何行星会有规律地按照自身位置移动，而地球也要遵循规律运行。他玩转着数字和星星，带领着学生在广阔的宇宙间勇敢探索，大胆探知宇宙最深处的奥秘。他讲课简直就是行云流水、挥洒自如，刚好印证了那句话，“我抓来太阳，随手又将它丢在一边……”

玛妮雅很高兴。怎么会有人觉得科学枯燥乏味？宇宙间亘古不变的规律多么精妙，而人类大脑能够理解这些规律又多么神奇。科学难道不比童话故事更奇幻，比探险书更扣人心弦吗？此刻能听到学界泰斗口中的那句话，就算吃再多年的苦也值：“我抓来太阳，随手又将它丢在一边……”

不过玛妮雅在巴黎还有许许多多其他的收获！当她跳下火车来到烟雾弥漫、喧闹嘈杂的北站，她挺起胸膛贪婪地呼吸着外面的空气，丝毫没注意到烟雾。这是她第一次呼吸到一个自由国度的空气。车站外的一切都是那么不可思议。贫民区的孩子们率性地用自己的语言调侃着彼此；对于一个只能讲俄语的波兰孩子来说根本无法想象！书店可以自主卖书，世界各地的书籍随便挑，太不可思议了！

玛妮雅跳上生平所乘的第一辆公交车，爬到顶层的廉价座位上，更令人振奋的是脚下这条路，它将把玛妮雅·斯克沃多夫斯卡送到一所向女性敞开大门的大学！而且还是一所知名大学！巴黎大学举世闻名。甚至那个德国人马丁·路德都曾说过，巴黎拥有全世界最著名的学府。学校正在重新修建，随处可见装修工人，到处都是烟尘和噪音。随着装修进度的改变，上课地点也不停变更。但这些对玛妮雅没有丝毫影响。她终于能学自己渴望已久的知识了。

玛妮雅开始用法语书写自己的教名——玛丽。不过姓氏无法法语化。年轻的同学们觉得玛丽的姓氏发音太艰难，这也是她受到孤立的部分原因。在长长的走廊里，他们也会不时地回望这个穿着朴素、秀发飘逸、眼睛明亮的外来人。“她是谁呀？”一名同学问道。“就是那个名字古怪的外国人，”旁边的同学回答道，“听说她物理成绩总是数一数二，但不怎么爱说话。”

玛丽必须奋发学习。她不知和同学比起来自己还是多么的无知。她的法语也不像自己想象的那样交流无碍。课堂上也有整句整句听不懂的时候。她发现自己的数学和物理还有很大的进步空间。她决心要努力学习以弥补自己的缺陷。

刚开始寄居在布朗尼娅和卡西米尔家里的那段日子还算顺心。布朗尼娅简直就是居家达人，把一切打理得整齐舒适。她在巴黎郊外租了一间公寓，房租比市里便宜得多，借了些钱把房子装修了一番。她可不是那种会担心还不上借款的人。她还要在家里添置一些精致的家当，如绣着精美花边的窗帘、体面洋气的家具、钢琴，还有插着娇嫩鲜花的花瓶。在不大的厨房里，布朗尼娅能烹饪出精美的菜肴，烘烤出香浓的蛋糕，用从波兰运来的茶叶沏出沁香的茶水，因为她一直觉得总有些东西是巴黎无法出产的。

她们所住的街区在中世纪是专门为屠夫修盖的，于是杜鲁斯基医生的病人也大多是屠夫。他们在小书房里接诊，这间书房是专门腾出来给杜鲁斯基瞧病用的，每天都有固定的时间段。其他时间，布朗尼娅就在这间小书房里给屠夫们怀孕的妻子做检查。到了晚上，两位医生都将工作搁在一旁，并怂恿着初来巴黎的妹妹一同去参加各种娱乐活动。如果手里有点闲钱，他们就会买最便宜的票去剧院看戏；如果没钱了，就在家弹琴或者召集同样背井离乡的波兰朋友们开个茶话会，油灯旁充斥着交谈、欢笑和调侃，茶桌上摆着布朗尼娅烘焙的蛋糕。玛丽通常会早早地从聚会中抽出身来，回到房间继续学习，因为她总觉得自己根本没时间闲玩。

“快出来吧，书虫小姐！”一天晚上，卡西米尔在门外喊道，“是波兰在呼唤你，这次你一定得去。快拿上帽子和大衣，快点！我可是拿到了音乐会的门票哦。”

“可是……”

“可是什么可是！就是我们之前说过的那个年轻的波兰人，没什么人买他的票。我们得去给他撑撑场。我还叫了自愿前往的人，我们可得去给他鼓掌捧场，让他觉得自己成功了。你不知道他钢琴弹得有多美！”

卡西米尔的眼睛乌黑闪亮，玛丽根本无法拒绝自己面前这位快活巧言的姐夫。她急忙跑下楼，穿好衣服，冲上旧马车。她坐在一半座位都空着的音乐厅里，看着那个瘦瘦高高、面庞英俊、一头红发的年轻人走上舞台，打开琴盖。她认真地听着……他手指弹出美妙的音符，仿佛是李斯特、舒曼、肖邦再世。玛丽被深深地感动了。钢琴家穿着破旧的大衣，冲着空荡荡的观众席弹琴，但在玛丽看来他可不是什么无名小卒，而是国王，是几乎神一样的存在。

杜鲁斯基邀请他到家中做客。他带着自己美丽的未婚妻欣然前往，他未婚妻和玛丽的妈妈碰巧还是旧相识。斯克沃多夫斯卡夫人过去曾提到过这个女孩，说她美丽动人，简直不敢带出门。有时，这个红头发的年轻人会走到杜鲁斯基的钢琴前，在他的演奏下，这件寻常物件立刻变得神圣庄重，响彻着天籁之音。这个演奏者是帕德雷夫斯基，将来某一天会成为世界名人，他起初只是一位钢琴家，随后成为自由波兰的总理。

但那时离帕德雷夫斯基成为总理的日子还很遥远。1891年，玛丽旅居巴黎，周围是一群流亡法国的波兰人，他们建立起了一小片波兰区。他们年轻，他们活跃，他们贫穷。每逢节假日，这些人共同聚会，一切尽可能仿照波兰习俗。吃波兰蛋糕，玩波兰游戏，用波兰语打印活动项目，并用波兰的风景图来装饰：茫茫雪原上的村庄，志向高远的男孩在专心读书，圣诞老人在往烟囱里投递科学书籍，老鼠在啃空钱包。他们演话剧时，玛丽根本没时间去仔细了解人物；但在情景剧里，她有次要演绎“冲破枷锁的波兰”。穿着古代人穿的束腰外衣，裙边摇曳着波兰国旗的颜色，秀发勾勒着她斯拉夫民族的面庞，年轻人都觉得她就是波兰之光。

但即使是在自由的巴黎，公开表达对波兰的爱国之情也是件危险的事。斯克沃多夫斯基先生苦口婆心地劝说玛丽不要再参加波兰的欢庆活动，因为这些活动很可能会见报。“你要知道，”他在信中写道，“有些人专门在巴黎记录那些参加波兰活动的人的名字，这可能会给你招来麻烦，影响你以后在波兰找工作。远离聚光灯才是明智之举。”

玛丽其实不太需要父亲的提醒。她想全身心地投入工作中去，一个人住，远离钢琴，远离姐夫每晚喋喋不休的高谈阔论，远离朋友们的登门拜访。她还想住到学校附近，节省通勤时间和费用。

于是在杜鲁斯基夫妇的陪伴下，玛丽略带忧伤地离开了姐姐家的舒适和友善，开始找工作的地方，也开始了自己的孤独之旅。

她即将过上自己梦想中的生活，完全沉浸在学习中的生活。为了能过上这样的生活，她一周只有一镑，甚至更少的生活费。此外，还要负担房租、食物、衣服、稿纸、书籍和大学学费。能负担得起吗？这是个需要认真计算的数学问题，好在玛丽很擅长数学，但仍需要精打细算。“啊！”她想，“我可以少吃点！” 她没时间练厨艺。朋友们更经常打趣说她连汤里面该放什么都不知道。她是不知道，也根本没时间去了解。她无法想象要浪费研读物理的时间去准备一顿晚餐。于是她每天就吃些面包黄油、樱桃和茶水，偶尔吃个鸡蛋或一块巧克力。

她租的房子很便宜——一周四先令六便士。不过就是间屋顶的阁楼，有面斜窗能透点亮光，没暖气，没煤气，也没自来水。屋子里唯一的家具就是一张可折叠的架子床和从波兰带来的床垫，一个炉子，一张松木桌，一把厨房椅，一个盥洗盆，一盏昏暗的油灯，一个能到一楼提水用的水桶，一盏做饭用的酒精灯，两个盘子，一副刀叉，一个汤匙，一个茶杯，一口平底锅，一把茶壶和三个茶杯。如果有来客，她的大木箱子上还能坐两个人。

一年需要用两袋木炭，玛丽在大街上买到木炭，然后一桶一桶地提上六楼，尽其所能地为自己提供温暖。但对于光亮，她一点办法都没有。夜幕一降临，她就去圣杰纳维夫图书馆读书，胳膊肘支在长桌上，双手撑着头，直到晚上十点闭馆。回到家，她就点上油灯，学习到深夜两点才上床睡觉。

食物、住所、取暖和照明的问题都解决了。至于衣服，玛丽能缝会补，她打算通过勤缝补、勤清洗让衣服干净整洁，这样就不用再添置新衣服。租屋的水池里就能洗衣服，不过是费点肥皂。

这就是她给自己规划的简朴生活，任何事情都不能打扰她学习。但女孩的身体总有反映自己的问题的方法。看完书后她经常会觉得晕眩，对此她也很诧异。有时还没躺到床上就在半路晕倒了。恢复意识后，她自觉生病了；但即便如此，她也不太在意，简单地认为自己很快就会好转。

玛丽做医生的姐夫说她看上去像生病了，她推托说自己只是太忙了，并把话题转移到外甥身上。她特别宠爱布朗尼娅刚出生的孩子，并把注意力集中在小家伙身上。

不过有一天，玛丽当众晕倒了，有个姑娘请来了姐夫卡西米尔。他赶到时，玛丽已经苏醒过来，但卡西米尔还是坚持给她做了检查。他一言未发，起身巡视房间里的一切。他问食橱在哪？但玛丽家根本就没这东西。屋子里没有一丝食物的痕迹，只有一包茶能证明玛丽喝过东西。

“你今天吃的什么？”医生问道。

“今天？……我不知道……我中午吃了……”

“吃的什么？”

“樱桃……还有，其他各种东西……”

最后，玛丽不得不坦白从昨天到现在，她只吃了一小捆萝卜和半磅樱桃。她工作到凌晨三点，只睡了四个小时。

医生勃然大怒，看着眼前的这个小傻瓜就气不打一处来，而她一双灰色的大眼睛还闪耀着愉悦的光芒，显得无辜又可怜，更气的是自己竟没发现妻妹在某些方面是这样执拗，容易犯傻。

他板起脸，要求玛丽收拾好一周的生活用品跟他走。他怒火难消，一路上一言不发。回到家，布朗尼娅出去买回牛排，他们要求玛丽就着香醇的肉汁和清脆的土豆片将牛排全部吃掉。不到一周，她就又变回了刚从华沙来时的那个健康女孩。

由于玛丽还有考试要准备，暂时获许回到阁楼，但前提是她必须好好吃饭。不过第二天，她就又开始有了上顿没下顿的凑合生活。

工作！……工作！…… 玛丽感觉自己的大脑在快速成长，双手也变得越来越灵巧。很快，利普曼教授就因为一份独自完成的研究实验而对她颇为赏识，玛丽也赢得了能够展示自己才华和创造力的机会。每天六点，玛丽就穿着粗糙的实验服，站在巴黎大学神圣的物理实验室的橡木桌旁，仔细观察着眼前精密的仪器，注视着某些沸腾着的化学物质。她周围还站着一些同学，大部分都是男性，实验室里一片沉静，因为大家眼前着手在做的事可比闲聊有意思得多。

不过实验结束后，男同学们望向玛丽，有时站在门边同她说上几句话，一个接一个地凑到她身边跟她交个朋友。她也没之前那么冷淡了。有时候男孩们想和她结伴而行的愿望表达得太过强烈，她的好朋友迪都斯卡小姐就不得不用遮阳伞把这些男孩轰走。玛丽根本没时间交朋友。怀着坚定的意志，以追求卓越的狂热和难以想象的执着，她全身心地投入到工作中去。

1893年，她顺利拿到物理学学位，1894年拿到了数学学位，物理学成绩名列榜首，数学成绩屈居第二。同时，她还在努力提高法语水平，想尽办法去掉波兰口音；她想把法语讲得像法国人一样好，只是发 “r”音的时候带一点卷舌，虽然她不是有意为之，但这反而增加了她的独特魅力。

她还会抽空去欣赏巴黎的春景和鲜花。她从未忘却自己是个波兰乡民，属于田间地头。她在乡下过周末，谈论的话题是盛开的丁香花和果树之花，以及充满花香的空气。

当炙热的七月来临时，她又迎来了另一场考试。玛丽很紧张。她和其他三十名学生坐在空气凝重的教室里，她盯着试卷，卷子上的字符在眼前闪烁跳跃。她定了定神，继续答题。玛丽和其他人一起，怀着沉重忐忑的心情等待出成绩的那一天。真到了那天，她溜进半圆形大教室的一角，紧张地等待着宣布结果，在满满一教室的学生和家长中，她显得毫不起眼，确信自己考砸了。

主考官拿着名单走进教室，谈话的嘈杂声和熙熙攘攘的人群瞬间安静了。玛丽根本还没准备好，就听到主考官念出了第一名的名字：

玛丽·斯克沃多夫斯卡。

随后放暑假，玛丽满怀喜悦带着考试结果回到波兰的家中。她还有其他东西一同带回去——给家人的礼物！这次，她可以花光自己的积蓄，是的，花光所有，花光每一分钱。她可以给父亲、给约瑟夫、给海拉买礼物，还要给自己两千公里的旅程准备食物。每个在外的波兰人都要身无一文、满载礼物地回到家乡，这是项不可打破的习俗。

在漫长的暑假里，遍布波兰的亲戚热情地款待了玛丽。不过一直萦绕她心头的问题是：秋天该怎么办？去哪里，怎么赚钱才能支付起自己另一学年一周一镑的生活费？迪都斯卡小姐再次打着她的遮阳伞出现了。没人知道这次她会用遮阳伞赶走谁，但她成功说服了华沙的专家给玛丽授予一项奖学金，理由是玛丽将为这座城市带来荣誉。好消息是，玛丽可以获得六十英镑的亚历山德洛维奇奖学金。这可是一年的学费。她精打细算，尽可能节省。在她能自己挣钱后，她竭力攒钱还上了奖学金，这样其他穷学生就能体味到和她一样的快乐。数年后，奖学金管理处的秘书在收到寄回的钱时大为震惊，之前从未有学生想过要返还奖学金。

她重新开始工作，但这次的工作可不是什么苦差事，而是她毕生所爱、全身心投入的事业。这是她最钟爱的人生环节，她艰难的求学生涯，在贫穷与孤独中奋发向上，带着年轻人的活力与冲劲，做回最真实的自己。她被称为“永远的模范生”——老牌大学古老传说中的那群人：年轻、穷困、渴求知识，相信天降大任于己，并不惜一切代价达成目标。

在旧油灯下辛勤工作的玛丽，深知自己身处一群伟大的科学家之中，人类的辛勤工作者。她没什么生活来源，但却活得十分快乐积极，心无旁骛，简单幸福。寻求真理是她的日常乐趣，这种乐趣偶尔会被一双穿破了的旧鞋破坏。买一双新鞋会花掉她好几周的生活费；她也要为此忍受更多的饥寒交迫。一天晚上，她冻得实在受不了，就把箱子里的衣服都拿出来，盖在床上。但她还是冻得瑟瑟发抖，不过家里除了一把椅子已经没什么能搭在身上了。于是玛丽小心地拖来椅子搭在被子上，一整晚都一动不动，担心用来取暖的旧椅子随时会掉。

水壶里的水放到清晨早就冰凉，但她仍然热爱那时的穷苦生活，甚至写了首纪念的小诗：

求学生活举步维艰
周围青年享乐安逸
享受多么容易，享乐多么常见
独自一人，日复一日
内心坚定，充满欢乐
时光飞逝，逐渐远离
知识与艺术的原野
生活不易
内心常叹阁楼时光
安静工作的场景再次浮现
满满都是人生回忆

第九章　玛丽的爱情故事

玛丽身处困境。这不是第一次，也不会是最后一次。她有项很有趣的科研项目要做，但却没有科研场所。全国工业促进协会请她就不同类型钢铁的磁性进行论文研究。这正是她钟爱的工作。在利普曼教授的实验室里，已经成功进行了大部分实验，但实验室根本没地方放所有需要用的大型仪器。她要分析矿物质和金属样本，她不知道哪儿能租到一楼的实验室。她将自己的困难告诉了一位科学界的波兰朋友柯瓦斯基先生，他碰巧和妻子来巴黎做演讲，顺便度蜜月。

柯瓦斯基认真地望着玛丽。他觉得这件事很重要，不过他一个在巴黎的客居人又能给出什么建议呢。

片刻思索后，他突然喊道：“我有主意了！我还真认识一个在勒蒙大街物理化学学院工作的人，他还算有些能力。他也许能借到实验室，就算借不到也能给点建议。明晚吃完饭来我家喝茶吧。我也会邀请那个年轻人来家中做客。他名声在外，你可能听过他的名字，皮埃尔·居里。”

当玛丽走进柯瓦斯基夫妇寄宿的独栋公寓时，望见了一个个子高高的年轻人正站在阳台窗户的凹处。他看上去十分年轻，这可在玛丽的意料之外，她想自己要见的这位业内名人怎么也该上了年纪。这个年轻人看似普通，却令人印象深刻；看似休闲随意，但举止优雅，这种气质在宽松合体的穿着下愈发突显。两个人互相介绍认识时，他的眼神真挚而纯净，让他看上去十分真诚、简单、年轻。玛丽欣赏他严肃却略带稚气的微笑，他们立刻谈论起了科学，这不就是将两个人牵线到一起的关键因素吗？

皮埃尔的父亲是名医生，他虽然年轻却不同于常人。皮埃尔没上过公立学校，有专门的私人教师。他在家中长大，承欢父母膝下，与哥哥相处融洽。他深受家庭影响而热爱科学，经常陷入沉思，并在日记中写下自己的思考。“女人，”他很年轻的时候就写道，“比男人更加热爱生活：有才华的女人弥足珍贵。当我们专注于某项伟大工作而无法兼顾日常生活时，我们就要和女人们周旋。母亲想要儿子的关爱，尽管这种爱会让儿子变成傻瓜。而陷入爱河的女人甚至会为昙花一现的爱情牺牲掉世界上最伟大的才华。”

这样理解女人的方式虽然有些偏激，但皮埃尔却有自己的理由。他的观察有时确实符合现实，再加上初恋令他饱受痛苦，他决心尘封这段往事并决定终身不婚。但当他与玛丽在阳台上谈论科学的时候，他再次相信命中注定，那时他已三十五岁。在法国国内，他并不知名，甚至被忽视，不过法国经常让伟人们饱尝令人心碎的忽视感，但却并不会削减这些人的伟大。

在法国之外，他已经名扬四海。他和哥哥发现的微量电测量方法已为其他国家的科学家广泛使用，让大家心存感激。他独自发现的晶体对称结构原理，成为现代科学的基础。一种新的天平和一项新的物理规律都以他的名字命名。他和开尔文爵士一样享有盛誉，但他的薪水却仅仅等同于高级技工，一周仅有三镑。

不过，他的一贫如洗也部分归结于自身原因。曾经也有一份收入颇丰的工作摆在他面前，但他的回答是：“不了，谢谢，这类工作简直就是对我精神的最大折磨。”他也被提名政府荣誉奖，但却请求除名，下决心永不接受这些虚名矫饰。

这位坚定决绝的科学狂热者站在玛丽面前侃侃而谈，他修长纤细的手搭在桌上，一双安静清澈的眼睛望向玛丽，透露出一股深邃、平和、超然物外的神情。也许皮埃尔突然记起了他过去所说的名言——“有才华的女人弥足珍贵”。

起初，因为是四人见面，他们之间的谈话较为笼统。随后，皮埃尔和玛丽就谈到了科学。她来此的目的不就是一心为了科学吗？满怀尊重，她认真请教了眼前这个年纪不大却已小有名气的年轻人，仔细倾听了他的建议。后来，皮埃尔一反常态地谈到了自己，讲到了自己的梦想，说到了他在研究并且寻找结晶学的规律，虽然谜团重重但却让人着迷。皮埃尔的脑海中突然闪过一个念头：自己竟然会和一位女性谈起挚爱的工作，各种学科术语和复杂的公式。眼前的这位女性不仅年轻迷人，还对科学充满热忱与浓厚的兴趣，他发现她善于理解，谈论细节问题时很有自己的真知灼见……多么愉快的交谈！他再次望向玛丽，看着她的一头秀发，看着她因化学酸性试剂和家务而变得粗糙的双手，欣赏着她的优雅，欣赏着她撇去浮华与娇柔的一切——多么迷人，拨乱人心弦。这就是那个在波兰工作多年一心想来巴黎的女孩，现在实现了梦想，独自一人、身无分文地在阁楼上勤奋努力。

“你会一直住在巴黎吗？”他问道。

“不，当然不会，” 玛丽回答道，“如果暑假前我顺利通过考试，我就会回到华沙。秋季可能会再回来，但我不知道自己是否能负担得起学费。我可能最后就在波兰的某所学校里面教书了，努力发挥自己的才能。波兰人绝不会背弃自己的祖国。”

两人间的谈话随即又转移到了波兰正在承受的苦难，提到了它的压迫者。皮埃尔，这个先前一心扑在科研上的人听到这样一段人类追求自由的艰难故事，不免感到既吃惊又悲伤。也许是他想到了如果科学家不能一门心思做科研，那会给真理和知识的追寻带来多么惨重的损失。也许是他想到自己要与波兰竞争，为把这个罕见的天才留在巴黎科学界而努力。无论如何，他都不会与玛丽失去联系。他去物理协会听讲就是为了见到玛丽，她经常去那里听新发现。他送给玛丽一本自己限量版的新书。工作时间，他也会时不时到利普曼教授的实验室去看望穿着亚麻衣在仪器设备间忙碌的玛丽。

皮埃尔随后要了玛丽的地址，并来到帝皇大道11号拜访玛丽。他可能因为科学家路易斯·巴斯德曾在这条大街上住过而对此熟知。爬上六层楼，走进小阁楼，这个出身于医生家庭的男子被眼前穷困潦倒的景象深深触动了。不过这与玛丽十分相配！她穿着磨得开了线的毛裙，穿过空荡荡的房间来见皮埃尔，显得分外可爱；身形纤细，朴实无华，热情而又坚毅，她在一无所有的房间中显得愈发光彩照人。

皮埃尔的所有痛楚都烟消云散，就像阳光穿透浓雾。两个人交谈甚欢，皮埃尔于是带着不一样的心情继续投入工作；本来觉得不重要的事情现在也显得尤为重要，愈发明晰。他的新理论被一位著名博士的论文验证，他也在生活中发现了一位不仅没有扼杀反而唤醒男性才华的女士。他现在越发坚信自己的崇高理想，因为他爱上了玛丽。

不过她的心意到底如何呢？皮埃尔还要仔细观察。他带玛丽去了美丽的法国乡间，两个人都热爱乡村生活；他们一起采摘雏菊并带回家，为小阁楼营造了一种简洁优雅的氛围。皮埃尔带玛丽回到了巴黎郊外位于索城的家，见到了自己的母亲和性格开朗的老父亲。玛丽仿佛置身于自己另外一个家，一个和华沙的家极其相似的地方，周围是平易近人、相亲相爱的一家人。他们爱好看书，热爱自然，最重要的是热爱科学。大家谈论起美丽的波兰，讲到玛丽在绵延草原上的漫长穿行，聊到了即将在瑞士群山中度假的欢乐。

“但十月份的时候你会回来的吧？”皮埃尔焦急地问道，他突然紧张起来，“如果你抛弃了科学，那可是大罪过。”

玛丽才不会上当。她知道皮埃尔的意思是若抛弃了他那才是罪过。

然而，波兰仍占据着她的心。她抬起头，略带羞涩地望向皮埃尔说：“我觉得你说得对。我应该还会回来。”

皮埃尔很快就鼓起勇气向玛丽表达了自己的心意，并向她求婚。但玛丽拒绝了。她不可能嫁给一个法国人，从而背弃自己的祖国波兰。他们围绕这一问题展开了很多讨论，皮埃尔知道科学站在自己这边，他坚信没有人有义务为了国家而放弃科学，科学属于整个世界，不能为了一国之利而做出牺牲。

于是，玛丽再次回国度假，除了继续维持朋友关系外，她不能向皮埃尔做出其他任何承诺。皮埃尔给玛丽写了一封又一封长长的劝说信。他想去瑞士待几天看望玛丽，但玛丽要和父亲一起度假，他觉得自己的出现可能会破坏玛丽的美好假期。他写信表达自己的全部思绪和犹豫，并不断渗透自己的想法，认为一个人要终身为之奋斗的梦想就应该是科学。他写道：

在政治领域，你可能永远不知道自己在做什么；也许本意是爱国但实际造成了破坏。想拯救人类，却不知该从何入手。但科学是纯粹的。任何发现，无论多么渺小，一旦出现就会一直存在。一旦发现了真理，它便不会消失，也不会出错。

相信我

爱你的

皮埃尔·居里

玛丽喜欢给他写信表达自己对自由的追求。

“谈论！”他回答道，“我们都是奴隶，感情的奴隶，偏见的奴隶，谋生的奴隶，是机器上的轮子。我们必须向周围环境做出让步。如果让步太多，我们会一无所有；如果让步太少，我们又会被摧毁。”

十月份，玛丽回到了巴黎，固执的不止她一人。皮埃尔说的对周围事物的让步到底是什么？皮埃尔开始思考自己是不是该做出妥协。很快他便将想法付诸实践！他主动提出可以放弃巴黎，奔赴波兰。他愿意暂时放弃科学，教法语谋生，然后再找机会回到科研工作中。

玛丽向布朗尼娅吐露了自己的纠结，并询问她关于皮埃尔要放弃自己国家这个提议的意见。就她自己而言，她觉得一个人根本没权力去要求别人做出如此大的牺牲。但皮埃尔的这个提议确实令她备受感动。皮埃尔也向杜鲁斯基一家征求意见。他们完全站在皮埃尔一边。

布朗尼娅陪着玛丽拜访了皮埃尔的父母，并从他母亲口中得知皮埃尔是个十分优秀且孝顺的儿子，布朗尼娅相信妹妹与他携手定会幸福快乐。

玛丽又纠结了十个多月，然后这两个曾经的不婚者放弃了自己的信条，牵手走向幸福。

玛丽的哥哥从波兰寄了一封热情洋溢、充满理解的信，口吻就好像波兰祖国母亲在告诉她的女儿，嫁给皮埃尔·居里这位法国科学家比回到华沙做一名女教师要有意义得多。事实上，后来发生的事也都表明玛丽的决定是正确的。

于是玛丽可以放心快乐地筹备自己的婚礼了，这是一场不同寻常的婚礼！

1895年7月26日，万里晴空，玛丽·斯克沃多夫斯卡心情亦如阳光般灿烂。她美丽的脸庞上闪烁着幸福的光芒，一头秀发也显得愈发有光泽，穿上了她崭新的海蓝色裙子和卡西米尔·杜鲁斯基的母亲送给她的蓝色条纹衬衫。她并不想穿婚纱；她很高兴自己能有一条新裙子，因为她目前只有一条裙子，而且自己每天都在穿；她喜欢实用的、日后做实验还能穿的衣服。

玛丽梳妆打扮好，皮埃尔接上她一同坐车去火车站，搭火车前往索城，奔赴他们的婚礼。沿着圣米歇尔大道向下，马蹄嘚嘚响，经过巴黎大学时两人相视一笑，眼神中充满爱意——不就是爱将两个人连在了一起吗？

在索城，客人只有布朗尼娅和卡西米尔，斯克沃多夫斯基先生和海拉，他们从华沙远道而来。两个人买不起金戒指，也没钱筹备婚礼早宴。婚礼礼物中，最重要的就是一位堂兄送的两辆崭新的自行车，两个人计划骑着自行车去度蜜月。

婚礼过后，双方的父亲见过两位新人，随后玛丽的父亲对皮埃尔的父亲说：“你可以将玛丽当成女儿来疼爱，她从出生那刻起就没让我伤心失望过。”

第十章　居里夫人

皮埃尔和玛丽开始了一场不同寻常的蜜月之旅。他们没买票也没订房间，打算随心所欲地骑着自行车到处走。两个人在自行车上绑了几件衣服，由于夏天潮热，他们还带了两件长长的防水橡皮雨衣。自行车的轮胎在湿润的道路上静静滚动；所有的法国乡间小道都郁郁葱葱，明亮斑驳的阳光在粗壮的树干上留下点点光影；头顶上方浓密的绿叶在路上留下蛇皮般的阴影，摇曳着上次降雨时的雨滴，洒落在行人身上。

两个人单独在一起的旅程多么美妙！他们不去想何时结束，也不知旅程中还有多少惊喜，也不知道路的尽头在哪里，更不去忧愁今晚要寄宿何处。

皮埃尔一直喜欢在寂静的森林里漫步。他喜欢树林凉爽湿润的感觉，来到岩石遍布的山坡时，他也喜欢丛生的迷迭香、小叶薄荷和野蔷薇。无论漫步在白天黑夜，还是清晨黄昏；不管是十一点或三点，还是七点或十点吃饭，对他来说都无所谓。而现在，一切变得更加美好，因为玛丽陪伴着他，也绝不催促和打扰。

两个人一点都不铺张浪费，所以也不住酒店。晚上到了村庄，找到一间简陋的小旅馆，里面有一个大大的酒吧，摆着几张桌子、很多把椅子。店家给他们铺上一张洁白的桌布，端上稠稠的热汤。吃过晚饭，两个人爬上吱吱作响的木楼梯，穿过杂乱的走廊，来到一间烛光微弱、昏暗不清的房间。法国的乡间旅馆一般都是这样，晚餐丰盛，床褥整洁舒适，而且花费不高。

第二天吃过面包卷，喝过咖啡，他们骑着自行车穿过另一条树荫密布、两旁树木丛生的小路。两个人满怀期待，沿着绿荫小道，经过长长的骑行来到了神秘的树林深处；将车停放在路边的村舍里；一定要检查好指南针，因为在法国广阔的森林里很容易迷失方向；口袋里揣满苹果，双脚踩着柔软的苔藓，陷在泥泞的土里。多有意思！他们早把方向、时间抛在脑后，没人知道他们什么时候会返回。

皮埃尔走在前面，随心所欲地大步向前。玛丽跟在后面，步伐较慢，但步调一致。玛丽没戴帽子，在当时的社会，女性散步一般都会戴帽子。这不是她有意要制造的潮流。她本应着拖地的长裙，因为裙摆上沾着的小泥块弄脏了鞋子，于是便将裙子高高挽起，露出了优美的脚踝。她的鞋子虽厚实但灵巧，皮带上的口袋里装着小刀、钱和手表。尽管皮埃尔在前面走得很快，就像要去赶火车，但他说的话玛丽听得一清二楚。虽然他在同玛丽说话，但他没回过头，他可能是对着树木在高谈自己的晶体研究。没什么比晶体研究的话题，或者专业来说是结晶学研究，更高深难懂但令人受益匪浅。玛丽欢快地倾听着，她的回答、评论和建议的精彩程度丝毫不亚于皮埃尔，两个人简直就是英雄所见略同。

玛丽开始感到疲倦，忽然就走到了森林深处一处开阔的空地，空地上有一湾芦苇丛生的湖泊。玛丽躺在岸边享受阳光浴，皮埃尔像孩子般前去打猎，看看湖泊里有什么好玩儿的：蜻蜓、蝾螈和火蜥蜴。湖水深处还漂浮着睡莲；湖水近处，盛开着黄色的鸢尾花。他想采点花打扮玛丽，但苦于没船。远处一棵树倒在湖面上——可能有点滑，不过面对爱人，滑点又算什么？皮埃尔运气很好，他很快就采回鲜花，用沾着水滴的莲花和鸢尾花编了一个花环戴在新婚妻子的头上。

突然，他四肢匍匐静悄悄地趴在近水处，好似看到了猎物。玛丽并没在意，在烈日炎炎的八月，能静静地坐着，什么都不做，别提多舒服了。突然她尖叫一声，恐惧地望着自己的手掌。一只凉冰冰、湿漉漉的青蛙正蹲在那里。

“你不喜欢青蛙吗？”皮埃尔吃惊地问道。他很喜欢青蛙。

“不讨厌，但不能在我手里呀。”

“好可惜！它们这么可爱。快看，它长得多帅气。”

不过他还是把帅气的青蛙先生送回了湖中，不让它破坏了两个人的欢乐休憩。

两个人继续边走边聊，玛丽一直戴着那顶别致的花环，直到重新回到公路上，骑上自行车。

八月中旬，他们已经骑车沿着林间道路环游了巴黎，随后来到了巴黎以北的尚蒂伊，一座掩映在丛林里的小镇，如今各家的马厩里都圈养着赛马。玛丽和皮埃尔要在森林里的一座名为拉比什或称为雌鹿的农场和家人碰面。在那里，他们顺利见到了布朗尼娅、卡西米尔和小依莲，大家也叫她露，另外还有祖母杜鲁斯卡、斯克沃多夫斯基先生和海拉。

森林深处的农场有自己独特的美。四周静悄悄的，只能听到几声狗吠，树干折断的嘎吱声，远处伐木工锯木的吱吱声，受惊了的野鸡扇动翅膀的簇簇声，还有野兔在草丛中穿梭的窸窣声。在人们足迹可达或目光可至的地方，到处都闪耀着五月的明媚，整个大地都覆盖了一层山谷百合泛黄飘落的叶子。

他们在农场里畅谈，经常还带着只有三岁的露。小孩长得漂亮可爱，天真而充满童趣。有时他们会同斯克沃多夫斯基先生探讨神圣的科学，分享抚养孩子的心得。有时他们还会同皮埃尔的父母聊一聊医学和政治，老人家专门从索城赶来度假。法国是片言论自由的土地，玛丽经常听到她的法国公公同朋友们大谈政治，情绪激昂，言论自由得让她吃惊。政治就是他们的生活；他们密切关注国家治理，在自由的法国随性地表达自己的想法，这也让谈话充满乐趣。但皮埃尔不同。他不喜欢政治，因为愤怒会让人失去理智。不过当政治出现不公或残忍的一面，他也会表达自己的立场——站在受压迫、被迫害的人的一边。

蜜月结束，皮埃尔和玛丽在巴黎找了一间公寓开始了自己的小生活，不过他们的家居生活可不同寻常！没有来客，于是家里就只放了两把椅子。如果有不请自来的客人不辞辛劳爬上四层楼，也只能看到这对小夫妻在埋头工作，环顾四周想找个地方落脚，都不用别人开口，自己就会发现根本无处可坐。不过最难做的还是要以委婉的方式拒绝来客。皮埃尔夫妇根本没有时间享受娱乐。任何时候，玛丽都要一人分饰两角：妻子的工作，相信天下大多的贤妻都深有体会；科学家的事业，相信大部分科学家都感触颇深。

玛丽决心将家布置得很简单，越不费时打理越好。没有毯子需要掸，没有扶手椅或沙发需要刷，墙上什么也没挂不需要掸灰，也没什么摆设需要擦亮。一张桌子、两把椅子、书架，木质坚实，打理不费事。房间布置简单，花瓶中插着一束鲜花，为室内增添了些许芬芳，而书籍、油灯和一摞关于物理的文件显示出这是一间学者的卧房。两个相爱的人，同时崇尚自然和求知，心无旁骛。不过他们还要养家糊口。这无疑占用了科研时间，令人遗憾，不过玛丽这次无法再忽视生活的现实。

为了好好打理家务，她首先买了一本黑色封皮、印着记账本三个金字的笔记本。她深知准确无误的精打细算是幸福家庭的重要基础，对一个每年只有240镑生活费的家庭来说更显得尤为重要。

她的厨艺也容不得些许差错，否则皮埃尔就会出现消化问题。此外，玛丽还要找些小窍门，这样晚餐就能简单易做，她可以把更多的时间花在科学实验上。现实残酷、不容改变，但聪明的大脑可以反其道而行。第一点就是延长工作时间。她一大早就起床去菜市场，回到家再整理床铺、扫地、准备晚餐。哎，又是做饭！结婚前，布朗尼娅和杜鲁斯卡夫人都给她培训过厨艺，不过人从课堂上总学不到什么东西，犯错其实是最好的老师。好在皮埃尔并不知道他吃的是什么，无论饭做得好坏他都吃得一样开心，但玛丽不能忍受她的法国婆婆——一个来自著名美食国度的女人——认为波兰女孩根本不懂厨艺。于是，玛丽一遍遍地研究菜谱，像研究科学一样认真；在食谱的空白处记笔记，并详细记录每一次的失败与成功。不过还有一些是菜谱上学不到的东西。煮牛肉是要用热水还是凉水？怎样把一根根粘在一起的通心粉分离开来？这些都需要科学实验一一解答。一点一点，玛丽的厨艺愈加精湛，她研究的菜肴可以在她外出时留在炉火上慢炖；她精确地研究出了不同菜肴熬炖的时间和相应的火苗高度，设置好燃炉，她便可以离开家去实验室工作八小时。谁说科学知识对厨艺毫无帮助！

晚上在和皮埃尔回家的路上，玛丽就买好了蔬菜或水果。回到家吃过晚饭，收拾完家务，记好账单，她拿出学位学习的书籍，一直学到深夜两点。从早六点到深夜两点，这真是漫长的一天。不过她还能抽出点时间给哥哥写信：“我们一切安好——身体健康，生活愉快。家里慢慢布置得和我理想中的一样，但我一直坚持简约风格，不用费时费力维护，因为我真是没什么帮手。小时工每天来一小时帮忙做些清洗工作，解决家务活儿中最麻烦的部分。”

夫妻二人没有任何娱乐活动。他们经常去索城看望皮埃尔的父母，同时也带着自己的工作，家里专门腾出两间房让他们专心搞科研。夫妻俩几乎没怎么去过剧院，别的活动那就更不用说了。两个人甚至都没钱去参加海拉在华沙举办的婚礼。他们一年到头都全心工作，只在复活节放几天假，就这样持续到八月份，而玛丽又迎来了期末大考。

她又一次稳居榜首。皮埃尔骄傲地搂着她的脖子一同回家。一回到家，就给自行车打好气，将背包塞满，骑车前往奥弗涅山脉。

玛丽记录下了那个美妙的假期：“阳光明媚的假期，多么美好的回忆。经过一段漫长艰难的爬行，我们穿过了奥布拉森嫩绿的草原，尽情呼吸高原上的新鲜空气。另一段鲜活的回忆就是在特吕耶尔峡谷欣赏黄昏的美景，爬上峡谷好似人在画中游，从溪流下方的船上远远传来了吟唱的曲调。我们计算错了路程，无法在黎明前返回旅店。随后遇到了一队马车，马匹因为我们的自行车受到了惊吓，迫使我们不得不横穿农田。回到大路上时，整个高原沐浴在朦胧的月光中，夜晚被赶进棚的牛一只只从暗处缓缓踱出来，目光温和的大眼睛望向我们。”

假期结束又回到工作当中，生活继续用它的艰辛不易磨砺着玛丽·居里，就像曾经调教玛丽·斯克沃多夫斯卡那样，唯有辛苦付出才能收获世间最美好的事物。

玛丽像渴求科学一样渴望孩子，更愿意与皮埃尔分享一切。但这次她发现自己根本无法做完所有事。她不能再一站就是八小时地来研究钢的磁性，她不能和皮埃尔骑着自行车在布列塔尼的蓝色海湾畅玩。她惊讶地发现自己竟然要向某些事情做出妥协。玛丽的父亲特意从波兰赶来看望她，好让她早点儿休假。皮埃尔用简单的波兰语给她写信，虽然他觉得波兰语很难，但还是为自己的进步感到骄傲。

“我的宝贝，亲爱的小甜心，我人生的挚爱。今天收到你的来信，我很开心。没什么特别的，除了我还是一如既往地想你；我的心早已飞去与你同在。”玛丽用尽可能简单的语言回信说道：“天气很好。阳光明媚。温度较高。没有你在身边，我很忧伤。快回来吧。我从早坐到晚等你回来，但却不见你的踪影。我很好。我尽力工作，但庞加莱的书比我想象的要难。我必须和你谈谈，我们要一起探讨一下难点。”

艾琳的到来增添了玛丽的欢乐以及工作量。这是她的小公主，要喂她吃饭，给她洗澡、穿衣服，如果不是医生强烈要求，她肯定不会让保姆帮忙。

如今，玛丽的时间被四件事情占据：实验室、丈夫、家和女儿。她想工作时，艾琳就咬紧牙，哭得撕心裂肺；或者艾琳得了感冒，磕到了头。两位伟大的科学家，已经为人父母，整夜照看着这个蓝眼睛的小家伙。有时，即便艾琳一切安好，玛丽在实验室忙于科学研究，也会突然心里一惊，留下手旁的报告，冲到花园里看看保姆有没有照顾好孩子。没事！保姆推着婴儿车，艾琳稳稳地坐在车里。保姆不在的时候，艾琳有外公这个忠诚的护卫，玛丽把孩子交给父亲就十分放心，可以转身去忙实验室里的事儿。

但没人注意到艾琳的妈妈越来越瘦了。不过玛丽很幸运，消瘦的身材让她愈发美丽，有一种高贵轻盈的美。她简直像纸片人，弱不禁风，不过额头仍然高挺，眼神还是柔和而深邃。

第十二章　黑暗中的一丝光亮

于是，这个神秘的放射性未知物有了名字，却没人见过它的面目，甚至包括为它取名为镭的皮埃尔和玛丽。它不像其他珍贵且真切的物质，可以触摸，可以看见，能放在瓶中，甚至能称重。称重这一问题很重要。重量——“原子量”——对科学家来说就是元素存在的最好证明。皮埃尔和玛丽心里很清楚，连他们自己都不知道原子量的物质，从科学家的角度来审视则相当于根本不存在。不能这样，皮埃尔和玛丽一定要找到镭，并进行称重。只有这样做才能让科学家们相信它的存在。

“它存在于沥青铀矿中，”居里夫妇想道，“微乎其微，肉眼难见；但如果能从足够多的沥青铀矿中提炼出所有的镭，也许这个体量肉眼就可见了。”

但如何才能得到足够多的沥青铀矿，比如上百吨？得到了又该放在哪里呢？即便有地方存放，又该怎样开展工作呢？

两位科学家准备一步一步来。首先要找到沥青铀矿。他们知道在哪能找到大量铀矿，因为波希米亚人用沥青铀矿来制作精美的玻璃品；但价格昂贵，居里夫妇甚至连谈论它的资本都没有。当然波希米亚人并不是用沥青铀矿本身来制作玻璃，他们从中提炼出铀来生产玻璃，将大量的废渣堆弃在圣约阿希姆斯塔尔的丛林里。“镭和钋，”居里夫妇说，“不在铀里，那就肯定在废渣里。也许我们能劝服生产商将废渣廉价卖给我们。”

“卖？”生产商和善地说，“如果你们自己付运费的话，就直接送给你们。”即便是运费也已经很高昂了，但居里夫妇倾其所有，将运费送到了波希米亚。

问题解决了。废渣很快就会送到，装了整整几节火车车厢。不过到底能放在哪儿呢？

皮埃尔和玛丽来到了科学的殿堂——巴黎大学。在那一幢幢教学楼里，肯定有废弃的房间能让他们存放价值丰富，被寄予厚望的废渣吧。但事实上根本没有！他们不得已又来到了物理学院，即便在这儿也没寻找到任何满意的地方。唯一能提供的地方就是实验室院落里另一侧的棚屋。真的只是棚屋！玻璃屋顶已经破碎，雨天会漏雨，而他们的实验却一定要保持周围环境的干燥。没有铺地板，只有用焦油刷的粗糙地面；没有家具，除了一两张旧餐桌、一面黑板、旧炉子和锈迹斑斑的铁皮烟囱。夏天，这两位辛勤工作的科学家将会像要被煮熟了一样，因为屋顶是全玻璃的。冬天，外面天寒地冻，他们在屋里会被冻得瑟瑟发抖，因为炉子没有任何热度；雨天，他们又会被雨水浇个透。这都不算什么，由于房间没法装排烟器，不能排出有毒气体，于是他们的大部分工作都要在户外进行。就像那句古老的格言：“乞丐没有选择权。”居里夫妇还是决定在棚屋里开展实验。

在那个伟大的早晨，负重的黑色马匹伴着响铃，驮着煤箱，停在了物理学院的门外。这对盼望已久的夫妇连帽子都顾不得戴，穿着实验服就冲了出来，欢呼雀跃地迎接自己的货物。运送到的可不单单是煤。

其实，运到的货物不是煤，是一袋袋的褐色废渣。玛丽等不及将麻袋搬进实验室，就激动地在大街上，在马儿庄重的目光中，解开了捆绑在麻袋上的细绳。这可是沥青铀矿呀！她的沥青铀矿！或者说是沥青铀矿中那重要的一部分。她心中、眼中还有轻轻跃动的指尖上，无不透露出强烈的好奇。终于，她能将双手伸入这堆棕黄色的废渣中，其中还混杂着波希米亚松树林的松针。镭，这种放射性极强的神秘物质真的存在其中吗？玛丽定要一探究竟，即便她要提炼小山堆般的废渣。

首批几吨的废渣运进了棚屋中，开始实验研究，持续进行了整整四年，这是玛丽人生中最美好也最艰难的日子。

她用一口巨大的铁锅来提炼废渣，并用和自己身高差不多的铁棒不断搅拌。她一整天都沉浸在自己的工作中，为了不影响工作进度甚至吃喝都在棚屋里。几乎每天都能看到这样的玛丽：她的头发在风中飘扬，脏兮兮的实验服上溅满了污点和酸液，不断搅拌着暂无一丝希望的废渣。她选择了最费劲儿的户外体力劳动，而皮埃尔则坐在棚屋里的桌旁进行着精密的实验，研究镭的属性。有时候，玛丽能一次性提炼四十磅以上的废渣，在棚屋里摆满了盛着沉淀物和液体的器皿。她经常搬重物，将一个器皿中的沉淀物倒入另一个当中，不断搅拌着那口沸腾着的大铁锅。

结束了一整天繁重的工作之后，玛丽回到家还要照看孩子。她给艾琳洗完澡，把她抱上床，希望能哄她快快入睡，这样就能回到书房和皮埃尔一起进行研究。但艾琳可不这样想。只要玛丽一转过身，背后就会传出一句哀怜的“妈妈”……于是玛丽就要回到艾琳的床边坐下，直到她入睡。皮埃尔对此有些不满，他也想要玛丽多花些时间在实验研究上。不过当艾琳熟睡之后，这对夫妻就又能坐在一起，研究至深夜。

第二天又是一天的工作。镭元素到底在哪？他们永远都看不到了吗？日子一天天变长成月，月数超过十二成年，第二年又悄悄流逝到了第三年，第三年又交替为第四年。他们就像在梦中工作，心中唯念一件事，嘴上只谈一件事。“真找到了镭，它会是什么样的呢？”一天，玛丽和皮埃尔抽空在院中散步时忽然说到。

“我希望它颜色美丽。”皮埃尔回答道。

1900年，法国化学家安德鲁·德比尔纳前来帮助他们共同研究，但在找到镭或钋之前，先发现了一个“兄弟”元素，命名为锕。

时光飞逝，马车运来了更多吨沥青铀矿的废渣。每天带着极强的耐心，玛丽从中提炼出镭纯度越来越高的物质。不过仍不见镭的踪影，它仍然掩藏着自己，保持着自己的神秘性。

玛丽仍然维持着极大的耐心，但困难重重。她和皮埃尔的钱不够生活，两个人也没有足够的时间工作。皮埃尔还要花大量的时间教学来赚取那维持生计的二百四十镑，这也占用了他研究镭元素的时间，而且收入还远不能维持他们的日常开销和艾琳的养护费用。于是皮埃尔决定在大学里谋个职位，这样他的工作能更加高端，收入也会更加可观。也许他还能拥有一间真正意义上的实验室，电力足够进行实验，白天不用上那么多课，晚上也不用批改那么多无聊的作业。

但不幸的是，职位并不总是给那些科研能力强的人，而是经常落到了院长朋友或那些懂得如何夸耀自己的人的囊中。好不容易等来了能申请职位的机会，皮埃尔又被告知要按照习俗前去拜访每一位任命委员会的成员。他讨厌这种行为。他羞涩地按响门铃，请求面见委员会成员，走进成员家中坐下。但当成员进来时，皮埃尔由于过于窘迫，便开始用溢美之词对自己的竞争对手大加赞赏。于是到了职位任命公布的那一天，他的竞争对手自然顺利受聘。

但总要做点事情谋生。皮埃尔在法国工业大学——法国最著名的两所高校之一——谋得了一份教师的工作。职位虽有些低微，但一年能额外增加一百镑的收入。

与此同时，日内瓦大学也给了他一份心仪的工作，大学讲师的头衔、理想的实验室，且配备有他要求的所有仪器。他接受了这一职位，和玛丽来到了日内瓦。但到了之后，他们更明白自己无法割舍下巴黎，更是不能抛下镭元素，它就像是两个人的孩子。不论巴黎如何对待他们，他们唯有在巴黎才能进行镭元素的研究。于是带着满满的歉意，皮埃尔还是拒绝了日内瓦大学的心仪工作，回到了巴黎，再次陷入贫穷，但也重新投身到了镭元素的研究工作当中。

不过令人开心的是，皮埃尔在物理化学自然科学院找到了一份工作，玛丽也开始在塞夫勒培训学校给女孩们上初级教师培训课。这些女孩能有玛丽·居里当老师，别提多幸运了。但遗憾的是，世界没有意识到，成千上万的人都能在塞夫勒教学，而玛丽从事的镭研究工作却仅有她本人才能完成。玛丽用心备课，获得了不少赞誉，这是学生们上过的最原创也最动听的课程。但一周几次的交通往返，备课和批改作业，也浪费了她不少宝贵的时间。这就像是让荷兰著名画家伦勃朗去画门柱一样。皮埃尔和玛丽已经筋疲力尽。他们还能见到镭吗？

玛丽也早都将她要在婚后善待身体的誓言抛在脑后。“你们俩都不好好吃饭，”医生在给皮埃尔的信中写道，“我不止一次看到居里夫人就着一杯茶，只啃了两根细细的香肠。再强健的体魄也不能天天挨饿呀……我知道你的理由，‘她那是不饿，她是个成年人，知道什么对自己有益。’其实才不是。她就像个孩子。我必须站在朋友的角度告诉你们，要多花些时间享受食物……不要边看书边吃东西，或探讨物理……”

不过，无论是皮埃尔还是玛丽都没将医生的叮嘱放在心上。他们要在勒蒙街的这间棚屋里将镭元素公之于世，没有什么比这更重要。

某段时间，皮埃尔建议应该把时间投入镭元素属性的研究上，暂时搁置寻找这种物质，但玛丽并不同意。

她其实越来越接近了。她不再提炼粗糙的废渣。她已经提炼出了一种能放在室内的物质，且蕴含着几十吨废渣中的所有镭元素。要想进一步研究，还需要精密的仪器，并在一间无灰尘也无湿气、既不冷也不热的科学实验室中展开，不要有任何因素影响到实验的准确性。但玛丽根本没有这样一间实验室，灰尘、酷暑、严寒和风不断破坏她的实验结果，迫使她浪费时间和精力进行重复实验。她的忍耐力真是惊人。

1902年，距离玛丽宣布可能存在镭元素的时间，已经过去了三年零九个月。她最终还是战胜了这个放射性元素。她在残渣中找到了遗珠，她看见了镭。她提炼出了整整一分克的镭。它有重量，原子量为226。化学家们纷纷向此致敬。

晚上，玛丽和皮埃尔坐在家中，艾琳已经熟睡。这个四岁的小魔王终于妥协，同意闭上眼睛，让妈妈回到爸爸身边去给她缝制新裙子，艾琳所有的衣服都是玛丽亲手做的。玛丽突然放下手中的活儿，说：“我们再回去看看！”

皮埃尔无须多问。他们才与镭元素分别两小时，但就迫不及待地想要再见到它。他们对它仿若对待新生儿般眷恋。他们告诉父亲要出去一趟，便手挽着手穿过熙熙攘攘的街道，经过破旧的街区工厂，回到了勒蒙街，走进了那间棚屋。

“别开灯，”玛丽说，“你还记得曾说过期望镭能有一个漂亮的颜色吗？”

在黑暗的棚屋中，镭元素不仅显现了自身的颜色，更重要的是它还能发光！

“看呀！快看！”玛丽低声说，她走到椅子前，坐下仔细观察。

黑暗的房间中闪烁着星点亮光，仿若蓝白色的月光在水面上跳跃，星星点点的亮光在黑暗中闪烁。在桌面的架子上，这些奇妙神秘的光亮不停跳动。终于，镭元素在小容器中现身，用黑暗中的一丝光亮证明了自己的存在。

第十三章　不申请专利销售

整个世界都为之亢奋！一种全新的事物进入了人们的日常生活，改变了他们对许多事物的认知。不仅科学家们在谈论镭，孩子们在放学回家的路上也在谈论，女性，在因男性包揽了所有伟大发现而沉默了几个世纪后，终于可以大肆欢庆，因为有位女科学家发现了全新的未知事物。不过一开始，根本没人能料想到镭的真正价值。

英国、丹麦、德国和奥地利的著名学者纷纷开始给居里夫妇写信，想要了解这一项新发现的具体信息。世界各地的科学家也都开始着手研究镭，发现了该元素的更多属性，找到了更多的同类元素。两位英国的科学家威廉·拉姆赛和弗雷德里克·索迪发现这种新元素自身能释放出一种微量的未知气体，将之命名为氦。换言之，镭能变成氦。这一发现令人震惊。科学家习惯于嘲笑那些鼓吹自己能点铁成金的中世纪炼金术士。炼金术士那冒着青烟的神秘炼炉勾勒出了一幅白日做梦的图景，而科学家认为物质本身就由其化学成分和原子量决定。但如今他们面临的事实是镭元素本身产生了氦，于是他们开始思索，其他新物质中又会蕴藏着哪些元素。现在看来，该轮到炼金术士的在天之灵来嘲笑化学家们了。

不论何时，点铁成金的这种技能都无法与镭元素具有的特别能力相提并论。它看上去就像普通的食盐，但其放射性却是铀的两百万倍。除了金属铅，它的射线能穿透任何坚硬的金属。但它也有自身的缺陷——该元素如此活跃，即便是放在玻璃试管中，一天也会自我损耗四分之一。其本身可产热，一小时内就能融化一块与自身同等质量的冰。如果将其与冷气隔绝，则其自身温度会高于外界。如果将其放置在玻璃器皿中，则能使玻璃变成淡紫色甚至是紫色。如果用纸张或脱脂棉包裹它，它能让两者腐化。即便夜间不点蜡烛，该元素发出的光亮也能让人阅读。

最神奇的一点是，镭元素的光并不自有。它能将光传送给周围事物，即便这样的慷慨奉送并不总受人欢迎。

这也为人类的未来生活带来裨益，因为它的光可以让真钻发光，让赝品暴露无遗。钻石的买家可以用镭元素来测定物品的真伪。

玛丽发现镭元素对所有的实验都会产生干扰。只要被放在镭元素试管旁边，任何物质都会产生放射性。镭元素将光传播给空气、灰尘、玛丽的衣服、实验仪器，甚至是笔记本。即便是在镭元素消损后，这些周围的事物仍带着它的光亮。

科学家喜欢看到自己的想法被颠覆，所以早些年刚发现镭元素的时候，一定曾令科学家们兴奋不已。因为不仅镭元素本身能创造出新元素，而且新元素本身又会产生新物质，如此类推。母元素的物质发生转变，产生新的放射性元素，而这些新元素又具有不同的属性。但镭带给科学家们的震惊还远不止于此。他们发现在特定的时长内，每一种放射性元素都能自我损耗将近一半，而这段时长是固定不变的，这段时间很长，长得足以让人们觉得无须担心会失去这些放射性元素。铀元素要想全部耗尽需要几十亿年。镭元素仅需一千六百年，而它的子元素仅需四天，子元素的子元素仅需要几秒钟而已。

镭元素静静地躺在那里，当你望向它的时候，它还在不断地产生新的子元素。镭元素本身和新元素都在不断消耗，或者相互碰撞。

突然间，这种新元素又表现出了一种新属性，好似之前表现出的特性都不足为奇一样。皮埃尔仍在苦苦研究时，被镭元素灼伤了。他手上的皮肤发红，但并没有疼痛感。随后颜色越来越红，第二十天的时候，伤口就像普通灼伤一样开始结痂，然后出现溃疡。到第四十二天时，皮肤表面的溃疡痊愈。

玛丽一开始并没料到会被镭元素灼伤，但却突然发现自己也被灼伤了，尽管镭元素装在玻璃试管里，且存放在锡盒里。

随后是他们的朋友贝可勒尔，他将盛着镭元素的玻璃试管放在自己的夹克口袋里，在回家的路上也被严重灼伤。

“这个可恶的孩子，”他向玛丽抱怨道，“它灼伤我做什么？我多么珍视它，但现在可对它充满怨气。”而现在，玛丽对这个一直视为掌上明珠的新元素也颇有怨言，因为她手指尖被伤得很重，都脱皮了。

然而很快，人们就能正确认识镭元素的灼伤性了，因为伤口愈合得很好。医生对这一现象颇感兴趣。他们用镭射线去除坏死的皮肤，伤口愈合后，疾病也就消除了。全世界都燃起了希望。也许镭射线可被用来治愈癌症。

这至少证明了镭元素的价值。人们都等待着它的销售。玛丽从八吨沥青铀矿中提炼出了一克镭。这些镭价值三万法郎，但不外售。玛丽将其视若珍宝，打算在她有生之年精心保管，并把它留在了实验室，作为勤奋与成功的珍贵象征。

某个周末的早晨，皮埃尔和玛丽坐在凯勒曼大道的家中，邮差送来了一封贴着美国邮票的信给皮埃尔。他仔细看完信，折好放在书桌上。

“我们得谈谈，”他说，“谈谈镭元素。要批量生产了。他们从布法罗寄了封信来，询问有关镭元素的信息。”

“嗯？”玛丽有些不耐烦。

“嗯，不过我们还有选择权……我们可以将自己的研究成果及提炼方法公布于天下……”

“当然。”玛丽微笑道。

“或者，”皮埃尔继续说道，丝毫没在意自己被打断，“我们也可将自己视为这项成果的主人，镭元素的发明者。这样的话，在公布从沥青铀矿中提炼镭元素的方法以前，我们就要申请专利，之后便能从世界各地镭元素的生产中获利。”

皮埃尔的话清楚地表明，只要接受专利申请，便有一笔巨额财富等待着他们。

镭的生产专利能给他们带来足够的财富，建造一座宏伟的实验室，购买镭元素来进行研究。如果有钱了，还能做好多好多的事！

玛丽沉思了一会儿，随即说道：“这不可能。这样有违科学精神。”

皮埃尔完全同意，但他让玛丽仔细考虑，一旦做出决定就不能反悔。他提醒玛丽也要考虑两个人都梦寐以求的实验室，考虑考虑女儿的未来。她真的确信自己不想成为富人吗？

玛丽熟知科学家的惯有约定，像法国化学家巴斯德这样的伟人都会遵守的约定，她说：“物理学家经常发表研究成果，我们的发现能谋利只是机缘巧合。镭元素能治病救人，我觉得不能从中谋取私利。”

皮埃尔也同意，靠镭元素的知识赚钱有违科学精神。他当晚就写了回信，将镭元素的所有研究信息毫无保留地告诉了美国人。

于是，皮埃尔和玛丽放弃了成为百万富翁的良机，但丝毫不后悔。他们不会对镭元素申请专利并借机谋利。是科学精神将镭元素带到他们面前，并呈现给世人。不论当今社会如何世风日下，他们仍然崇尚这种将知识无私奉献给全人类的科学精神。在财富与贫穷面前选择了后者之后，玛丽和皮埃尔又骑上了自行车，像往常的假日一样，到夏季的树林里为家中采集野花。

第十四章　黑暗

玛丽和皮埃尔声名鹊起。法国为两个人颁奖。英国向他们发出邀请。他们从法国带了一件礼物送给英国朋友开尔文，那就是装在玻璃瓶中的微量镭元素，开尔文带着孩子般灿烂的笑容骄傲地向自己科学界的朋友们展示。皮埃尔将在皇家学院就镭元素作演讲，玛丽也将成为第一位获准在此神圣庄严的科学殿堂参加会议的女性。此次演讲盛况空前，在座的全都是英国知识渊博的著名学者，皮埃尔向他们展示了镭元素的神奇力量。皇家学院为之振奋，整个伦敦都渴望一睹镭元素“父母”的风采。他们专门为两个人举办了宴会，权贵们打扮得珠光宝气，他们带着惊讶的神情望向玛丽——这位伟大的女性科学家，只穿了一条朴素的黑裙子就来赴宴，没戴任何首饰，她那被酸液腐蚀的双手也没戴任何戒指；但这丝毫没有影响她的高贵，她身材高挑，面庞光彩照人，额头光洁高挺，拥有一双炯炯有神的大眼睛。玛丽自己很喜欢周围的繁华盛景，但她却有点惊讶地发现，平常对于宴会漠不关心的皮埃尔，显然也已经沉浸在了这种眼花缭乱之中。

“珠宝很美艳吧？”玛丽问他，“我从没想过世间还有如此美丽的东西。”

皮埃尔大笑。“你知道，”他说，“吃晚宴的时候我没事儿干，脑子里就在想，这些珠宝加起来能建多少设备齐全的实验室啊！”

天啊！居里夫妇的确“与众不同”。他们了解发光物质，但却搞不懂珠光宝气的石头。皇家学会授予玛丽戴维奖章，夫妻二人甚至不知道该拿这金质奖章作何用。皮埃尔把它给艾琳当摔不碎、咬不坏的玩具，艾琳非常喜欢。

他们也不知道该如何对待名誉、人群、掌声和记者。这些只会徒增玛丽的痛苦。

1903年12月10日，玛丽与亨利·贝可勒尔分别被授予诺贝尔科学奖。她是科学界第一位获此殊荣的女性，但并没引起她多大的兴奋。她反而更享受荣誉带来的实际影响：科学家们对她工作的认可，获得经费的欣慰；但闪光灯和曝光、名誉、陌生人寄来的庆祝信、要签名的请求、摄影师和记者们邀约采访的请求等，这些事情她并不喜欢。“我恨不得把自己藏起来，借此得到片刻安宁。”她写道。

玛丽喜欢能支配金钱的感觉，而她支配金钱的方式也完全体现出她的真挚善良与个人魅力。她把一部分钱存进银行，这样获得的收入就能雇个帮手在实验室里帮忙，皮埃尔也能辞去在物理学院的教师职位，潜心科研。此外，她还给杜鲁斯基夫妇在波兰创办的养老院捐赠了一笔钱。给皮埃尔的哥哥和自己的姐姐们买了礼物；对科学协会进行捐赠；资助了一些波兰学生、实验室的男孩们以及一个急需帮助的塞尔夫女孩。玛丽随后又记起了自己年迈的法国老师，老师目前客居波兰，平生的夙愿就是能再回到她深爱的法国看看。玛丽给老师写了封信，并寄去了车旅费，邀请她前来法国和自己同住。那位年迈的老妇人面对这意料之外的幸福喜极而泣。最后，玛丽还给自己准备了一份礼物——给位于凯勒曼大道的家装了现代化的洗浴室，给起居室更换了新壁纸。

但遗憾的是！平庸的大众！不是集资建设实验室，让居里夫妇做更多镭方面的研究，他们的过分关注让玛丽在大街上要躲躲藏藏才能顺利回家，浪费了她大量的时间。报纸上刊登居里夫妇生活的小细节，侵犯到了夫妻二人的隐私，即使连艾琳这个小孩子对保姆说的话，连屋顶上花猫的颜色都被一一曝光在众人面前。玛丽抗议道：“他们严重影响了我们的工作。我们的生活也被荣誉和光环破坏了！”她说的没错。玛丽寡言忙碌，却几乎被缺乏理性的大众逼疯了。一次，居里夫妇去参加法国总统的晚宴，一位女士走向玛丽，请求她将自己引荐给希腊国王。“我觉得没这必要。”玛丽语气平和，但目光坚定。那位女士其实就是卢贝总统的夫人，玛丽的回答让她很惊讶。“当然……我当然会尊重您的意见。”她面色绯红，吞吞吐吐地说道。能面见国王对许多人来说是莫大的殊荣，但玛丽不同寻常。她年轻，并对这一切深感厌倦。她渴望休假，能自由放松地生活，做一位寻常的母亲，一位普通的妻子。她希望艾琳的咳嗽能快点好起来，希望皮埃尔的病痛快点消去。从上一次她在波兰跳过舞后，这二十年间她的生活中只有工作，但她也没像现在这样渴望无所事事，渴望忘掉自己是著名的居里夫人。她只想再成为那个简单的玛丽，尽情吃草莓、睡觉、享受生活。

但皮埃尔此时根本停不下来。他手边有大量的工作要做。他无法理解玛丽想放假的心情——这种愿望太小女孩化了，太不符合科学精神。皮埃尔告诉玛丽，他们必须要为科学献身，玛丽顺从了。她一直都顺着皮埃尔的心意。但她真的筋疲力尽了，累到连自己肚中的孩子伊芙都不想要。“可怜的小家伙，”她说，“要生活在这纷乱的世界里。” 事实上，她的那些仰慕者和追随者，严重影响到了她对于生活的勇气和幸福感，这是无比残忍的。

然而，伊芙的出生也为她带来了乐趣，玛丽喜欢孩子，她还能顺理成章地享受伊芙出生带来的产假——伊芙长着黑色的头发和蓝色的眼睛，与艾琳金黄色的头发和淡褐色的眼睛完全不同。伊芙不愿躺在摇篮里，奋力挣扎着抗议，玛丽不忍心让她在摇篮里哭泣，心软地将她抱起，一直哄到她入睡为止。

在伊芙出生前，巴黎大学给玛丽授予了一项特权，即可在皮埃尔的实验室里工作。她其实一直就在实验室里工作，但学校不知怎的突然醒悟，给了她这项任命——任命她为“物理学科的组建者”，一年有九十六法郎的薪水。众所周知，居里夫妇一直都是并肩作战，学校目前也认可了这一点。他们的时间、思想和工作都自然平分，就好像是一个人。

1905年6月，皮埃尔和玛丽来到了风景秀丽的斯德哥尔摩，皮埃尔受邀以二人共同的名义发表演讲，这也和诺贝尔奖相关。他对瑞典大加赞赏，用尽溢美之词，这个国家遍布着湖泊、峡湾，周围仅有一点陆地，两个人享受着不被打扰的静谧，享受着这个国家毫无压力的礼遇。

玛丽有时会和陌生人交朋友。有位名为洛伊·富勒的美国芭蕾舞演员，她用奇幻的灯光让舞蹈显得更加美轮美奂。她写信问玛丽，如何能利用镭元素照亮自己的蝴蝶袖。皮埃尔和玛丽虽然觉得这想法很奇怪，但还是回信委婉地解释了镭射线的性能。洛伊回信道，她唯一能表达感谢之情的方式，就是来居里夫妇家现场跳一段芭蕾舞。居里夫妇接受了这不同寻常的感谢方式。一天，一个打扮奇特、拥有孩童般蓝眼睛的女孩出现在他们家门口，身后还跟着一队电气师。电气师鼓捣了一整天。晚上，居里夫妇家的餐厅点缀着各式各样的彩灯，装扮如同仙境，洛伊跳着舞，交替出现火苗、鲜花、飞鸟和巫术。

这位小小的艺术家成了居里夫妇的好朋友，并将两个人引荐给了自己伟大的雕刻家朋友罗丹。坐在罗丹的工作室里，在铸件和大理石中，这几个来自科学、雕刻和舞蹈领域的人彻夜交谈，相谈甚欢。

时间到了1906年的4月。在法国的骄阳下，紫罗兰盛开，芳香四溢，紫色和白色的花朵相映，装点着谢夫勒斯山谷里的灌木。玛丽和皮埃尔带着艾琳和伊芙在此度假。晚上，一家人去农场里打奶；伊芙这个小魔头，在学步车里蹒跚走路，逗得大家哈哈大笑。早晨，皮埃尔和玛丽骑着自行车，穿过树林采摘鲜花，再看一看蜜月时发现的林间湖泊。湖水已干涸，水仙花也不见了，唯有四周环绕着的黄色芦苇，像一顶色彩鲜亮的皇冠。玛丽和皮埃尔漫步回家，从河岸边采回了紫罗兰和蓝色的长春花。

第二天中午，他们沐浴在阳光里，艾琳举着绿网捕蝴蝶，发出兴奋的尖叫声和欢笑声。

“生活待你不薄，玛丽。”皮埃尔低声说道。

晚饭过后，皮埃尔就搭乘火车返回巴黎工作，随身携带着他们在湖边采摘的黄色芦苇。第二天，玛丽也带着孩子们重返巴黎，4月亦如它的节气，变得潮湿阴冷。

1906年4月19日，玛丽和孩子们已经返还家中——这是潮湿的一天，街道上泥泞湿滑，天空阴暗，布满乌云。皮埃尔在城里还有几项工作要做，玛丽则要回家整理家务，在镇上还有些事要处理。她忙碌且快乐地走来走去。六点钟她到家，很高兴能再次回到舒适的家中，渴望见到皮埃尔，与他像往常一样一同进行科研到深夜。

她打开客厅的门。看见三名男士站起身来，带着深深的敬意，仿佛将玛丽视为女王。在他们的神情中玛丽读到了沉痛的忧伤。她之前的老师保罗·阿佩尔告诉玛丽，皮埃尔在街上滑倒了，被运货马车的轮子碾到了头。

“皮埃尔死了吗？……死了吗？真的死了吗？”她问道。

伊芙长大后，撰写了母亲的生平事迹，她告诉我们，从知道皮埃尔去世的那一刻起，一种孤独与无助就深深萦绕在玛丽心头，从那个悲伤的四月起，她就一个人被孤独地留在了人世间。

第十五章　无论发生什么

玛丽天生具有非凡的勇气。终其一生，她都不断鼓足勇气努力生活，内心越来越强大，甚至坚不可摧。再者，她曾深爱过一个伟大人物，皮埃尔留给她一句话，令她终身铭记，即便周围的世界轰然崩塌。“无论发生什么，”某次两个人谈到死亡时，他曾说过，“无论发生什么，即使徒留一副空皮囊，失去了精气神，人也要努力工作。”政府要给玛丽颁发抚恤金，但被她拒绝了，她说自己还年轻，能自食其力，养活自己和孩子。

她找到了一种自我安慰的方式，但这只会更让人心疼。她每天写日记，仿佛在与皮埃尔对话：

他们让我替代你的职位，我的皮埃尔，你所有的讲座和实验室的职位。我接受了。我不知道自己这样做对不对。你经常对我说，希望我能在巴黎大学授课。我很希望能继续你未完的事业。从一方面看，这是维持生活最容易的方式，而从另一面看，我就像个傻瓜。

1906年5月7日：

我的皮埃尔，我止不住想你。我的脑子里全是你，我已失去理性。我不能想象没有你的日子。你是我生活的伴侣，我无法想象不能再对你微笑的日子。树木发新芽，花园景色优美。今早，我带着孩子们欣赏花园美景。你不知道她们现在有多可爱，如果你在，肯定会带我去看盛开的长春花和水仙……

5月14日：

我想告诉你，他们已经提名我为巴黎大学物理学院院长，也就是你先前的职位，有些人愚蠢到因此而祝贺我。

玛丽并没有因为对傻瓜强烈的愤怒而感到心烦意乱。之前没有女性能在这一领域担任学科带头人，但在法国还没有人能接替皮埃尔的工作，因此这个重担自然就落在了玛丽肩上。也只有她一人有此天赋。她决定要好好备课才能对得起皮埃尔的盛名，于是将孩子送到乡下，整个夏天都待在巴黎，继续皮埃尔的研究课题、研究成果。

她需要换一间房子，决定定居在皮埃尔长眠的索城。孩子们的爷爷有点担心，如果玛丽搬去更小的房子，会不会就不想和他生活在一起。不过这种问题他怎么能问出口？玛丽也担心他会不会因为儿子去世，而不愿单独和儿媳妇住在一起。老人最终还是打破了尴尬的局面，“皮埃尔已经不在了，玛丽，你没有理由再和老人家生活在一起。我可以和大儿子他们一起生活。这由你决定。”

“不，您来决定，”玛丽低声说道，“如果您走了，会让我伤心难过。但您有权力选择自己喜欢的生活方式。”

“玛丽，我当然更偏向于跟着你们一同生活啦。”

玛丽要走出去面对外界的那一天还是来了，全世界都对她的忧伤痛苦充满了柔情与尊重，她也要习惯自己是位名人寡妇的身份。她清楚各大报纸都在要求巴黎大学改变规定，能让自己在半圆形的大讲堂里授课，这样成千上万名学生就能听到这位科学界的第一夫人在巴黎大学的授课。玛丽应该很欣慰，因为巴黎大学是世界上最保守的地方之一，并不容易改变校方规定。她听说沸腾的人群渴望来听讲座，正在热烈讨论她讲课的内容、她会如何评论自己的丈夫，因为每一任新的学科带头人都要对上一任大加赞赏，这是学校不成文的惯例。依照惯例，还要感谢教育部部长，感谢学校。就职演讲那天，人们就像群鸟守候猎物，殷切期待着玛丽的演讲会感人至深，甚至预期或许会看到她情绪失控。讲堂并不大，人们蜂拥而至，推挤着那些真正来上课的学生，甚至都将学生挤出了座位。

在雷鸣般的掌声中，玛丽快步走进教室。很快一片安静，她站在皮埃尔生前站的位置上，开始讲授高等物理：“回顾过去十年物理学界发生的变化，我们惊讶于自己对电和物质认知的变化……”

听众很惊讶,惊讶的是出乎意料的结果，而非电的变化。他们本期待来看一场表演，却发现眼前的这位女士完全没有任何表演的痕迹，真实虔诚，一心只考虑工作，而非自己。他们深受触动，泪水涌上眼眶。玛丽讲起了电结构、原子裂变和放射性物质的新理论。在课堂最后，她简单总结知识，简洁快速地离开了教室，如同来时一样。

如果说她之前的工作艰难，那现在则变得愈发困难。她要摸索出教育孩子的方法。同时，要兼顾实验室的科学研究和巴黎大学的授课。她还有家要照看，有花园要打理。她有一件特别的事情要做。她想方设法建了一座以皮埃尔命名的实验室——这一直是他梦寐以求的事。

在索城的新家里，伊芙和艾琳与蓝眼睛的祖父快乐度日。他教艾琳植物学、自然历史和诗歌，帮她在花园里开垦了一小块空地，种上色彩明亮的鲜花，而伊芙则在一旁的草丛里玩乌龟或者追赶小黑猫和小花猫玩儿。

玛丽早上总是匆匆忙忙，踩着她快捷的商务步伐，追赶前往巴黎的火车，到晚上华灯初上时方才回家。孩子们一天也见不上妈妈几面，但孩子们一天的学习计划都由玛丽制订。她们早上起来要先学习一小时。艾琳喜欢数学，而伊芙热爱音乐。随后不论天气如何，她们都要外出散步，然后去喜欢的体育馆。之后，她们再做些烹饪，或是搭搭模型、做些手工，或是园艺。周末或节假日，她们就会跟着母亲去骑车或游泳。玛丽要孩子们变得坚强和无所畏惧。玛丽让她们锻炼得无惧黑暗或灾难，不害怕攀爬，不害怕骑行或动物，不畏惧一切。要勇敢坚毅也要浪漫热情。玛丽教孩子们波兰语，但她不想让孩子们也饱受和自己相似的折磨，感觉自己被两个国家牵引，尤其一方还是一个被压迫的国家。孩子们的教育中只有一项未曾涉及——与陌生人打交道、在舞会上突出自己的艺术。两个孩子在这方面没经过任何练习。

玛丽不希望孩子们过于疲劳，但法国学校上学时间长，有时上六小时课还要再做三小时的作业。玛丽和大学朋友经常讨论这一问题，他们决定让孩子们休学，在家自己教。这真是伟大的想法。这些幸运的小孩一天只用上一节课，但老师却是巴黎最伟大的科学家们。第一天早上，他们赶到巴黎大学实验室，由让·佩兰教授化学。“巴黎大学还没被逼急，”报纸上写道，“但我们拭目以待。”第二天去乡下由保罗·朗之万教授数学；第三天去找玛格洛这位雕塑家学习雕刻塑形；再一天是现代语言文学教授授课；周四下午来物理学院找玛丽·居里学物理。这些幸运儿呀！

在这神圣的殿堂里，从没上过如此简单的课程。他们将漆黑的自行车轴承滚珠落在倾斜的白板上，亲眼观察自由落体的曲线。有时，玛丽还会问他们一些简单的问题，比如：“要维持盘子里液体的温度，该怎么做？”

“用羊毛裹着。”一名学生说。

“与外界隔绝。”另一名建议道。

“我，”玛丽微笑道，“肯定会先盖上盖子。”

然而不幸的是，父母都要忙于赚钱养家，根本没时间给孩子一直上课。愉快的课程结束了，伊芙和艾琳还是回到了学校，不过这所学校的上学时间没有大多学校那么长。孩子们后来回忆，小时候上的这些课让她们勤奋而热爱工作，对金钱处之泰然，独立自主，认为自己能克服任何困难。

在实验室取得的诸多成功中，玛丽有一个最伟大的成就。那时她已经提炼出了镭盐。随后，她又和安德鲁·德比恩成功制成了镭金属。但只成功了一次。无论他俩还是其他人之后再也没制成过。

1911年，玛丽被授予诺贝尔化学奖。在此之前，还没有人能荣获两项诺贝尔奖。

那么大家肯定会猜想，整个世界都将像对待科学家一样崇敬她，像对待悲伤的女人那样怜悯她。但不幸的是，有些人在听到别人成功或目睹他人的美丽时，会大加忌妒，这是一种奇怪的病态心理。玛丽兼具成功与美丽，于是有人开始给她写匿名信，编造她的坏话，指责她的错误，这连她自己都没想过。她的朋友们试图保护她，但想战胜躲在暗处的敌人并不容易。他们觉得最好的保护，就是科学协会公开授予殊荣，让她成为其中一员。这是她当之无愧的，但此前还从未有过女性成员入会。编造谎言的人又变换把戏，想方设法阻碍选举。他们甚至将一张错误的选举条塞进玛丽一位盲人朋友的手中，造谣她的朋友都开始反对她。科学协会最终还是以一票之差无情地将她拒之门外。

玛丽对谣言很是气愤。一段时间，她都要假借姐姐的名字来躲避反对者。她如白昼一样光明磊落，而她的攻击者却躲在暗处，这让她觉得恶心。这件事几乎摧毁了她的勇气，也让她陷入了痛苦和疾病的深渊。医生说手术可以治愈疼痛，但她说手术时间要推后，直到她参加完下一届物理学会议。她仍然果敢坚毅。

之后她在生病期间，还做了一项伟大的决定。她早已筋疲力尽，更不愿思考太多，但波兰决定在华沙修建一所大型放射物质实验室，邀请她任实验室主任。她多想接受！多么诱人的邀请！人们告诉玛丽波兰需要她，她的祖国现在处于颓废低迷期，需要一些事物让它重振精神。

但其实很多年前，玛丽就已经做出决定，尽管她十分热爱祖国波兰，但她更深爱着皮埃尔·居里。她仍然深爱着他，而皮埃尔和波兰仍旧在往两个不同的方向拉扯着她。如果玛丽选择了波兰，就意味着要放弃建设皮埃尔梦想中的实验室。如果玛丽不待在法国，皮埃尔的梦想就不会成真。她只能忍痛拒绝了波兰。

但波兰仍坚持让玛丽远程指导新实验室的修建，并出席剪彩仪式。在此次访问波兰期间，还发生了许多激动人心的事情。第一，她在波兰发表了科学方面的主题演讲，这是她人生中第一次用母语进行科学演讲。第二，她出席了一场在博物馆举办的盛大庆祝仪式，她曾在那儿进行了自己的第一场物理实验。第三，在波兰妇女为她举办的欢迎会上，她遇到了自己第一间学校的老校长。玛丽匆忙穿过人群走向那位老妇人，亲吻她的双颊。老校长看到自己以前的学生成了举世闻名的女科学家，该有多开心！

玛丽得到了一次休假的机会。她准备背着自己的小背包在瑞士闲逛，教会艾琳和伊芙爬山，教她们欣赏峡谷美景。

同行的还有一位朋友，他和玛丽大谈特谈物理学，孩子们不得不盯着他，以防他掉进峡谷中。但她们好奇地听着他口中谈论的那些奇特的事，整个过程中充满了欢笑，根本没人会去注意峡谷。

“夫人您看啊，”他说道，“我想知道的是：如果电梯掉入真空状态，那么里面的乘客间会发生什么？” 这问题对伊芙和艾琳来说，听上去并不难，而且很有趣。她们不知道自己听到的其实是高深的“相对论”，而这位看似粗心大意的朋友不是别人，正是伟大的物理学家爱因斯坦本人。

当时，玛丽的情绪渐渐好转，因为皮埃尔·居里大街上的皮埃尔镭研究所的围墙已经开始修建。巴斯德研究所的罗博士曾在两年前提议，要筹钱给居里夫人修建实验室。这件事让巴黎大学突然意识到，巴斯德研究所很可能会从他们手中将居里夫人抢走。为防止这样的损失，双方达成一致，共同建设新实验室。

玛丽心中充满欢乐。她参与制订计划，同建筑师探讨所有房间和窗户的形状，坚持设计大窗户，保证良好的采光。她同时坚持打理花园，在实验室开建前，自己种了树和玫瑰，希望在实验室建成时能添些光彩。

1914年7月，她终于看到了门前石柱上刻着的字：居里大街镭研究所。

玛丽告诉我们，她想起了巴斯德曾说过的话：

“如果你在意那些造福于人类的成就……如果你因祖国曾参与这些伟大发现而骄傲，我恳求你待在那被我们称为实验室的神圣地方潜心工作，不忘初心。祈求实验室的数量不断增多，这样能创造出更多奇迹。它们是未来的神殿，是财富与福祉的圣堂。就是在这里，人类渐渐变得愈发伟大、强壮、优秀。在实验室里，人类研究造物者的精美作品，也是世界进步与和平的象征。而人类自身的作品，通常野蛮粗暴，具有毁灭性。”

1914年7月，玛丽见证了皮埃尔实验室的竣工，回忆起了巴斯德的这段话。实验室虽建好了，但玛丽还要再等四年。在整整四年的战争之后，她才能看到镭研究所的正常运营，看到皮埃尔的梦想成真。

第十六章　战争

1914年8月1日

亲爱的艾琳，亲爱的伊芙，

情况变得越来越糟糕：我们随时都可能要准备撤离——我不知道自己是否需要撤离。保持冷静，勇敢镇定。如果没有战争，我周一就能到；如果战争爆发，我就只能先待在这儿，再尽快去接你们。艾琳，我们俩一定要发挥自己的作用。

8月2日

开始撤离了，德国人还没宣战就进驻了法国。可能有很长一段时间都无法通信了。

巴黎一切平和，除了对上前线打仗的男人们的不舍与忧伤。

8月6日

勇敢的小比利时没有对德国不战而退。所有的法国人民都充满希望，这场战争尽管艰辛，最终一定能取得胜利。

波兰已经被德国占领。打完仗，我的祖国还能留下什么？我已经收不到家中的任何消息了。

玛丽给远在布列塔尼度假的孩子们写信说道。

玛丽一个人在巴黎极其孤独。她的同事们都前去参加战事，除了一名因为有心脏病而不能参战的机械工。玛丽病了，身体虚弱。但她还没想到这场战争会给自己的研究工作带来什么样的灾难。玛丽也没随大流，像其他女人一样前去当护士。一如既往，她脑子转得飞快：思考她的工作能为战争做些什么。前线和后方的医院几乎都没有X射线设备，没有这项新设备，医生怎么才能检查病人的枪伤以及伤口深处的碎片？X射线和玛丽本没什么交集，她只是对此比较感兴趣，上过几节课。这并不重要。眼前着急的是，要快速建立起X射线站。她只用了几小时，就把巴黎可用的X射线设备列出一张清单，并分发到了各大医院。玛丽找了所有可能会用X射线的科学家，将任务分配下去。这就是巴黎能提供的。

但前方大量的伤员被运送回来，成千上万的伤员被救护车从前线送回战地医院，他们该怎么办？玛丽丝毫不敢犹豫。时间就是一切。她向法国女子联盟筹集资金，制造了第一辆“放射车”。这是由普通汽车改装的，利用汽车上的发动机给X射线设备供电。在贫穷、破烂但风景秀美的马恩河乡下，X射线流动车在不同的医院之间来回奔波，让战场上的伤员能得到快速的救治、安全的手术，如果没有X射线流动车，那么很多人将不能治愈。

但在马恩河战役之前，德国的战线仅离巴黎几公里远。他们能冲破防线吗？他们会占领巴黎吗？玛丽应该怎么办？她的孩子还在布列塔尼。她要去和孩子们团聚吗？医疗队撤离巴黎时她该跟着走吗？不。她要待在巴黎，无论发生什么。因为，她写道：“如果我守护着皮埃尔·居里实验室的新楼，德国人应该就不敢摧毁它；如果没人在这儿守卫，德国人肯定会将这里夷为平地。”坚强不屈的玛丽最痛恨当逃兵。害怕只会助长敌人的威风。无论如何，她都不会让敌人得逞，进入无人看管的皮埃尔·居里研究所！但是，就算玛丽不离开巴黎，她那珍贵的镭元素也必须运走，而且只能由她自己护送镭元素安全撤离。

她穿上黑色的长袍，收拾好行装，提着小巧但极重的铅箱，搭火车前往法国波尔多地区。车厢内十分拥挤，玛丽蜷缩在木椅上，脚边搁着存放镭的箱子，注视着窗外九月初骄阳炙烤的田野，道路上川流不息的汽车以及在其中穿梭前行的小货车。

在波尔多的西海岸边，玛丽站在月台上，脚边放着小铅箱，一小时又一小时地焦急等待着，这箱子对一个女人来说太重了，但却弥足珍贵。月台上没有搬运工，没有出租车，也没有休息室。她苦笑着，猜想自己是不是一整晚都要站在这里。但最后，一位同行的旅客向她伸出援手，帮她找到休息的床位，镭元素被送到了银行保管。

第二天清晨，玛丽返回巴黎。晚上，她还只是一名毫不起眼的旅客，夹杂在逃往安全地带的人群中，而早上她就又回到了众人的视线范围内，大家都想看看“那女人又重新回来了”这样不同寻常的新闻！这位重返巴黎的伟大女性很高兴能有机会告诉众人，巴黎并不危险，巴黎不会陷落，这里的居民不会生活在水深火热之中。而实际上，这位重返巴黎的伟大女性早已饥肠辘辘。她从前一天晚上起就再也没吃过东西。她所搭乘的运兵列车一路上不是在田野间停顿休整，就是在朝着巴黎缓缓爬行。她很感激身边一位友善的士兵，他从背包中掏出一片面包分给她充饥。当她抵达陷入战争危险的美丽巴黎时，也迎来了激动人心的消息：敌军被挡在了马恩河外。

没做片刻休整，玛丽就急匆匆地赶往国家救助协会总部，想要贡献一份力量。

“休息吧，夫人！”协会主席阿佩尔说道，“躺下好好休息一番。”她顺从地点点头，不过又开始讨论未来的工作了。“她苍白的脸上一双大眼睛炯炯有神，”阿佩尔说，“就像一团燃烧的火焰。”

随后，她改装了更多的“小居里”射线车。玛丽的两个孩子远在布列塔尼，但对法国的士兵而言，她也是X射线车的母亲。从前线受伤的战士回到后方，第一时间就能见到这样的救助车。玛丽在实验室中一辆一辆改装好射线车，从极不情愿的官员那里搜集所需的一切物资。这位曾经害羞腼腆的女性，现在却为了她的救护车而据理力争，成为一个不容忽视的人。她从某人那里拿到“通行证”，从另一个人那里获得“通行口谕”，又从其他人那里拿到护照——富人捐的钱，好心人送的汽车——“我会还的，”她说，“如果这些东西战争结束后还能用，我肯定会还的。”

玛丽给自己找了一辆雷诺车，比普通轿车要大，像货车一般。随后就开始在外奔波。

巴黎家中的电话响了。一大群伤员需要X射线车的治疗。玛丽将车刷成灰色，上面划着大大的红十字臂章。车上塞满伤员后，玛丽穿上黑大衣，胳膊上别着红十字，戴着她柔软但有些褪色的圆帽子，背着泛黄褪色的旧背包,爬上副驾驶的座位。这辆破旧的老爷车全速前进，无论白天黑夜,刮风下雨，玛丽都跟随射线车深入战争前线，去到那些战事吃紧的地方——亚眠、伊普雷、凡尔登。

哨兵将他们拦下盘问，随后放行。雷诺车停到医院门口。居里夫人找到房间，将仪器搬进去。她迅速将仪器摆好，其他人则摆好电缆，将仪器与车载发电机连好。司机启动了汽车，玛丽调好电流。玛丽将一切准备就绪，戴上手套和眼镜，准备好铅笔和导线。把灯关上，拉上窗帘，如果没有窗帘就用床单遮住窗户。同时，将旁边的房间准备好，用作洗片暗室。

只用了半小时，一切就准备妥当，医生也就位了。随后大批伤员被担架抬进手术室。一个接一个，一个接一个。玛丽调试好仪器，这样，医生就可以准确检查伤员的骨头形状或器官上的阴影。

身边的助手会根据医生的口述记录下金属的位置，为之后的手术做准备。有时医生边观察边做手术，用镊子深入病人的伤口，从骨头碎片中挑出碎弹片。

时间一点点流逝，有时手术一做就是好几天。只要有伤员，玛丽就要待在旁边的暗室里。在离开医院前，玛丽计划在医院建立一个永久的X射线站。玛丽竭尽全力建成射线站，仅用了短短几天就带回来新的仪器和一名放射线学者，根本没人知道她是从哪儿找到的。

就这样，玛丽独自一人在各大医院建立起了两百个X射线站，二十辆射线车治好了一百多万伤员。这对一位女性来说，简直就是壮举。

但我们也不能把玛丽想得无所不能，她开车时旁边总是坐着一位老司机，负责安全。有时她必须自己开车，握着那充满魔力的换挡杆。如果路面平坦，没有太多沟沟坎坎，玛丽就很开心，但这些道路上经常有各种各样的断面。在战争年代那天寒地冻的日子里，玛丽那纤细且被镭元素灼伤的手指还要冒着冰霜去换轮胎。有时她在清洗不太熟悉的汽缸时，也会像面对科学实验时那样皱着眉头。有时她还要做搬运工的工作，当男人都赶赴前线参战时，她要搬重物。

一次，她被惹怒了！司机突然一个急转弯，把车翻到了沟里，玛丽被压在了一大批松垮垮的箱子下面。她其实并不在意自己的身体。但担心会摔坏精密的仪器，所以她还是勃然大怒。年轻的司机小伙绕着车子一圈圈地寻找她，焦急地喊叫着：“夫人，你死了吗？夫人呀，你是死了吗？”玛丽听到时还是笑出了声。

有时玛丽会忘了要吃早饭或晚饭。她经常随处安睡——有床就睡床上，没床就睡在星空下。她可以坦然接受这一切，因为她从小就尝尽生活的苦楚，现在更是战争勇士。

但救助士兵的工作只是玛丽工作的一部分。一有时间，她就会整理好旧实验室里的仪器，送到皮埃尔·居里研究所的新实验室里。她将实验器械摆放好，渐渐整理出了一个科学的新天地。她前往波尔多地区取回了镭元素，每周她都会收集镭元素的“释放物”，装到试管里，送往医院。

随着X射线被应用得越来越广，放射学学者的缺口也越来越大。玛丽在新的镭元素研究所里给他们上课培训。有些学生天生愚笨，反应慢，但玛丽极具耐心且善解人意，她帮助学生，鼓励学生，直到学生们自己能胜任这份工作。整个教学过程中，玛丽都有女儿艾琳做助教，她那时已经十七岁了。艾琳当时还在巴黎大学学习放射学，但母亲却从未觉得孩子年龄小就不能在战地医院工作。

两年的时间，她们共培养了一百五十名放射科护士。

不过这一切还不够，玛丽又去了比利时医院。有时到了陌生的医院，那些打扮入时的护士们会将眼前这位穿着朴素甚至有些破旧的女士误认为清洁工，对待她缺乏礼数。不过玛丽并不在意，她只会因为与她在霍赫斯塔德并肩工作的某位护士或某位沉默寡言的士兵的努力而感到温暖与欣慰：伊丽莎白女王与比利时国王艾伯特。她自己已经摒弃了所有冷漠的言行，温和谦让，平易近人，为伤员带来鼓励和信心。她要不断地去向因不了解实情而担惊受怕的村民解释，那些看起来奇怪的仪器根本不会伤害到他们，就像普通的照相机一样。这时的玛丽重新找回了快乐。

她从不提及自己，也没听她说过自己是否疲惫，是否害怕炮弹落在周围。她每天做着自己分内的工作，就好像这是世间最天经地义的事。

但她渴望和平，渴望一切暴戾残忍都能终结！1918年11月11日，对她及整个世界来说是最欢欣鼓舞的一天，停战的炮声响彻天地，也让身在实验室的她激动不已。她和助手克莱因立刻冲出实验室，想买国旗装扮研究所，参与到举国欢庆的浪潮中。但巴黎市内根本没有国旗！他们只好把三种颜色的长布缝在一起。玛丽开着旧雷诺车，加入了街上狂欢的人群，丝毫没注意到车顶和挡泥板也站上了十位不速之客。

谁能猜到这之后还会有哪些好事发生？

对玛丽来说，不仅是法国从战争的恐惧中解脱了出来，她的祖国波兰亦是如此。波兰最终也得到了解放，重获独立。她给哥哥的信中写道：

“我们，‘在奴役下出生，在枷锁中长大’，终于见证了国家的复兴。”

第十七章　归家

玛丽再一次回到塞纳河畔自己的老式宽敞公寓中。塞纳河将法国的腹地分割成两个小岛：一个是轮船形状的西岱岛，法国的老城，坐落着庄严美丽、享有盛名的建筑；另一个是圣路易斯岛，同样古老但略显空旷。玛丽就住在圣路易斯岛的贝休恩码头。两个世纪前，贝休恩大街上住的都是公爵和贵族绅士。玛丽的公寓多有走廊和台阶，房间开阔宽敞，地势较高。她这辈子就没学会过如何享受财富，如何享乐。硕大的房间里，就只有几件桃木家具孤零零地立在光洁的地板上！她和艾琳都没注意到房间空阔、寒冷刺骨，只有伊芙愿意花钱将房间装扮得温馨优雅。但家中有一间房装扮得舒适惬意，即玛丽的书房，房间中摆放着书架，挂着皮埃尔的肖像，摆着鲜花。不过所有的房间都很亮堂，窗户高耸，没装窗帘，望向窗外就能见到如画般的景色：阳光下的塞纳河波光粼粼，游船来来往往，载重的驳船色彩鲜艳，远处的巴黎圣母院依稀可见。

玛丽当时就是看上了这座小岛的清幽安静，但事实上，她的家中经常是人声鼎沸。伊芙经常弹奏钢琴，猫在楼梯上玩耍，发出嘎吱嘎吱的声音，门铃和电话的丁零声常常打破沉静，耳边还经常传来河上的汽笛声。

每天清晨八点钟，玛丽矫健急促的步伐都提醒着艾琳和伊芙，忙碌的一天又要开始了。接下来的十六年里每天都是如此。八点四十五分，外面传来的三声喇叭声提醒玛丽，接她的小汽车已经在门外等候了。她迅速拿上帽子和大衣，急急忙忙跑下楼，让司机等待的时间可不能超过三分钟。她起初是让研究所的一位男士给她开车，等找到固定司机时，那个可怜的男人因为自己不能再给居里夫人开车而难过地抽泣。他们途经图尔内勒大桥，穿过拥挤的码头，到达拉丁区。据记载，这里最早是年轻学生享受诗情画意、安贫乐道的地方，而如今这里聚集着各大研究所。

玛丽站在皮埃尔·居里大街的镭研究所门前。大厅里挤满了人。每天早上，大厅都挤着一群人，玛丽将他们戏称为苏维埃委员会。各大院系的学生们在玛丽开始工作前就在此等候，以免占用她的研究时间。他们要么来问问题，要么来给老师看自己的研究成果，有些人甚至希望玛丽昨晚已经想好了新问题让他们解答。她也经常不负所望。“哦，某某先生，你的解决方案行不通，我给你提一点建议……”玛丽解答一个又一个难题，人群不断增加，每个人都带着难题而来。玛丽其实并不在意问题有多难。只是这些学生用断断续续的法语和英语问问题，这增加了解答的难度。研究所简直就是一座巴别塔，汇集着东西方各类语言。玛丽曾讲过她的一名中国学生与她用英语交流的故事：学生彬彬有礼，即便知道老师讲的不对，他也不会直接点出，而是诱导着老师用她聪明的大脑去发现自己心中的疑惑。玛丽说，她会在东方学生的面前因为自己的言行举止而感到羞愧，“他们真的比我们更注重礼节。”

一旦开始在大厅解答疑惑，就几乎是没完没了的，不过玛丽要学着适应。大厅里没有椅子，他们就坐在台阶上。想想她蹲坐在台阶上，身边围站着高大的学生，就觉得很有画面感。她是实验室主任，她读过所有用五种语言发表的关于镭研究的书籍，她仍在研发新技术，她好似具有超能力，她的学生对她的教学指导深信不疑。她胆大又心细。

学生一个个都回去做实验了。有时，有一两个学生会带着玛丽去看自己的实验成果；有时，玛丽终于有些时间，可以回到自己的实验室中进行研究。

中午她回家吃饭，也要在餐桌上和艾琳探讨物理学。伊芙有时跟不上谈话内容。妈妈和姐姐有时在说BB 原始状态和BB方形状态，在法语中BB的发音等同于“婴儿”的发音，伊芙心里还犯嘀咕：原始态的婴儿和方形婴儿都是什么呀。

1926年，艾琳嫁给了一位名叫约里奥的年轻有为的科学家，就剩伊芙陪在玛丽身边。

“亲爱的，讲讲你身边发生的事吧，”玛丽说，“大家都在做什么？” 伊芙就给她讲自己了解到的一切，玛丽对一切都感兴趣，尤其是那些简单幼稚的事。她喜欢听伊芙说自己开快车的事，或者艾琳的孩子每天都说什么话，以及人们对新法西斯主义支持者的看法。

“哦！”玛丽应答道。如果听到有人赞扬独裁者，她就会说，“我从小就生活在压迫下。你们没有。你们不知道能生活在自由的国度里是件多么幸福的事。”如果有人赞成政府处决反叛者，玛丽就会说，“把拉瓦锡这样的科学家送上断头台，我永远都想不通。”

午饭过后，汽车又来接她，有时会送她去花卉市场买点花园里的花或野花，玛丽不喜欢温室里种植的娇媚花朵。有时候她还要去卢森堡花园会见一位重要客人，她的外孙女依莲。她会坐下来同小家伙玩沙子，直到该去参加下午医学协会的会议。玛丽是参会的唯一一位女性，就坐在罗博士身旁，罗博士是巴斯德最忠实的学生。

参加完会议后，玛丽回到实验室，平时都会继续工作到晚餐时间，如果需要偶尔会到深夜两点。

有时研究所的静谧也会被诸如茶话会这样的活动扰乱，比如为了庆祝某个学生顺利拿到博士学位。实验室的器皿变成了茶杯，玻璃棒变成了搅拌勺，庆祝活动经常以玛丽的致辞结束，通常都是对新晋博士的赞美之词。其中最令人欣慰的两场就是艾琳及其丈夫弗雷德里克·约里奥获得博士学位的庆祝会。1934年，艾琳和约里奥获得了一项重大发现，成果堪比人工放射性物质的发现。他们用镭射线轰照铝元素和其他物质，将其变成具有放射性的新物质，这也成了能提炼镭的新来源。科学家看到了希望，也许有一天能制造出镭元素的替代物。多么美好的事物，在研究所院子另一侧的建筑里，人们正利用镭元素治疗癌症，这种方法也被称作居里治疗法。镭元素不可或缺，也弥足珍贵。

随后涌来了大量来信。想想名人收到的那些信件！幸运的是，有秘书为她拆信——有不假思索直接要签名的，当然不会收到回信，有直接问愚蠢问题的，有广告商的，也有乞丐的。一摞信件中只有一两封真正需要回复。

终于，玛丽要开始授课了。她并不喜欢讲课。每个周一、周三，她从早晨一直忙到下午五点，因为要一直站在小教室里给三十名学生上课。

那些年她面临着失明的危险。医生告诉她，她需要在几乎失明的状态中忍受将近两至三年，之后再接受手术治疗。医生们可能并没有想到这对她来说意味着什么。她想要继续科研事业，也不喜欢接受别人的同情和怜悯。无论发生什么，她都不想让别人知道自己眼睛的状况。伊芙用卡瑞夫人的名义去眼镜店给玛丽配眼镜。如果有学生的论文需要批改，她就聪明地用提问的方式来了解学生到底写了什么。她想尽一切聪明的办法来掩饰自己的不幸遭遇，那些隐隐猜到的人也假装自己什么都不知道。真是贴心！在接受了四次手术后，她开始训练眼睛，逐步恢复视力。视力虽然大不如前，但玛丽并不会为此丧失信心；她的眼睛再次恢复如常。

回到玛丽的日常生活吧。她和伊芙吃完晚饭后，伊芙要外出，这时疲惫的玛丽躺在沙发上，看着女儿换装。“鞋跟真糟糕，伊芙！我就不能理解为什么女人愿意踩着高跷走路。”

“还有现在流行的露背装都是什么呀？露在前面还能理解，可是露后背……当然裙子还是很漂亮的。转个圈，让我看看你有多漂亮。”玛丽惊讶地注视着女儿：“我对你化妆并不反对，我也知道你经常化妆。古埃及的女人真是发明了些糟糕的东西。我只能说一句：我觉得真难看。眉毛画得不好看，嘴唇也涂抹得不像话。”

“不过妈妈，我确实看起来更漂亮了。”

“漂亮了？听着，为了不看你那张化了妆的小脸，我只能明天一大早在你没化妆前就去床边亲吻你。”

伊芙离开后，玛丽躺在摇椅上，读一会儿诗，或看几页喜欢的小说，但都不会超过一小时。这层楼就是她的小天地——她有足够的空间在身边铺开各种物理文献，工作到深夜两点。

伊芙回到家，看见母亲沉浸在自己的工作中，就连她进家门也没发现。她专心致志地计算着物理问题，用波兰语喃喃自语，声音只有在课堂上的一半大。

第十八章　出国

1920年5月。天气炎热。巴黎的栗子花开了，玛丽一如既往在努力工作。但有件事即将打断她的工作，而这件事太出乎意料，她一点思想准备都没有。

玛丽从没见过报社记者，更别说女记者。她不喜欢接受采访，她讨厌曝光。面对要采访她的陌生人，玛丽总是有礼但坚决地说：“居里夫人不想……”

但生活在美国的爱尔兰人有时能找到某种令人无法抗拒的方式发出邀请，有位名为麦隆内的女士给玛丽写了封信：“我的博士父亲经常说，人类取得的小小成就不容夸大。但夫人，这二十年来您在我心中的形象一直很伟大，我只想与您见个面，哪怕只有几分钟。”这其实说的是：“小猫能有荣幸面见女王吗？” 玛丽一反常态，回复道：“好的。”

于是五月的某个清晨，麦隆内女士就坐在了研究所小小的会客厅里。她后来描述道：

“房间门开了，我看见一位瘦削苍白的女士走了进来，脸上尽显悲伤。她当时穿着一条黑棉裙。她耐心而和善的面庞上闪现出学识渊博的人特有的超然物外。我突然觉得自己打扰到了她的生活，我甚至比居里夫人本人还要羞涩。我做职业记者已有二十多年了，但在那一刻，面对这位毫无防备之心的女士，我什么都问不出。”

玛丽后来谈到了美国和镭元素，这也舒缓了女记者紧张的情绪。玛丽告诉她自己知道美国有五十克镭元素，她也清楚地知道每座城市拥有的镭元素量。“那法国有多少克呢？” 麦隆内女士问道。

“我的实验室里也只有一克多一点。”

“您只有一克镭元素？”

“我？我一克都没有。这克镭元素属于实验室。”

随后，麦隆内女士谈到了专利问题。她猜想，玛丽肯定能从那些使用自己的镭元素提炼方法的人身上赚取大笔财富。

“镭不能成为任何人谋求财富的手段，” 玛丽说，“它是一种元素，属于全人类。”

麦隆内女士当时肯定觉得凭玛丽为人类做出的贡献，整个世界都应回报她。她突然问道：“如果您能问全世界要一件需要的东西，您会选择什么？”

玛丽犹豫了片刻，回答说：“我需要一克镭，以便继续进行自己的实验研究。但我买不起。镭元素对我来说太昂贵了。”

麦隆内女士当即认为美国应该赠予玛丽·居里一克镭元素。她回到家，试图游说十位富有的女性每人捐赠三千法郎，但最后只说服了三位。她之后又去游说劳苦大众。美国所有的女性都应该联合起来，让玛丽获得这份礼物。不到一年，她就给玛丽写信说：“我们筹集到了钱。你很快就能得到那克镭元素。”

整个美国都为这项活动而激动不已。很快所有的女性都得知了居里夫人镭元素基金的存在，大家都想见见居里夫人。然而玛丽不喜欢在人前讲话。她其实不想去，但又觉得对不起这份弥足珍贵的礼物。不过她一开始还是找了很多理由。比如，她不能和女儿们分开。这丝毫不影响美国人民的热情好客，她的女儿们也获得了邀请，而且将由总统本人将镭元素赠予玛丽。

于是，玛丽、艾琳和伊芙把所有的衣服塞进大箱子，应邀搭乘奥林匹克号邮轮，坐在高级客舱里前往美国。法国也在歌剧院举办了盛大的欢送会，著名演员莎拉·贝恩哈特和吉瑞斯都参与了演出。唯有大西洋显得不太友好，海面黑沉，让玛丽开始怀念家乡阳光普照的蓝色海湾。

奥林匹克号靠岸时，与玛丽她们同行的麦隆内女士陪同着玛丽走出客舱，迎接美国式的欢迎仪式，唯有亲身经历过的人才懂得这热情好客背后的真情实意。人群等待了整整五个小时，来迎接被他们称作“人类恩人”的伟大女性。时值夏季，蓝天白云下，高耸着亮丽的摩天大楼。码头上充斥着各色国旗，波兰的、法国的、美国的。学生们，年轻女孩们，和三百位在美国的波兰女性代表捧着红色白色的玫瑰迎接她们。玛丽就像小学生一样端坐在甲板的轮椅上，麦隆内女士拿着她的帽子和手包，把她推到相机镜头前。“头向右偏些，居里夫人。”“再往这边来点……”

美国热情欢迎。美国人要让世界都明白，科学家是最伟大的人。他们被玛丽对纯粹科学的虔诚追求、对金钱的清心寡欲以及服务人类的坚定信条深深触动。

他们无法为玛丽再授予任何殊荣，这并不重要。美国各地的人都想一睹她的芳容，却忽视了国家幅员辽阔而造成的交通时间。他们为玛丽举办了盛大的欢迎宴，宾客多达五百人，尽情欢乐，忘却时间。他们授予玛丽大量的荣誉头衔，但却忘记玛丽在自己的国家早就拒绝了这类嘉奖。他们邀请玛丽参加大学的仪式，惊讶地发现她竟然没有长袍和帽子。他们给玛丽送来了精心培育的鲜花，却忘记了她最喜欢自然生长的花朵。爱就是这样，玛丽尽管被折腾得筋疲力尽，但她能理解。唯一无法包容的，就是他们为她量身定做的各式各样的学院长袍。希望玛丽穿上丝织长袍本身就不现实，丝绸会弄疼她早已被镭元素灼伤的手指。

玛丽首先参观了女子大学。无论她走到哪里，穿着白色校服的女孩们都挤满了道路，或快跑穿过操场来追赶玛丽乘坐的马车。白色的人群中还有人挥舞着彩色的旗帜。在纽约，大学女生们排着长长的队伍，为玛丽献上法国百合和美国玫瑰。另一队是各国大使及重要人物，他们将玛丽称作“纽约的自由女神”，另一位获此殊荣的波兰人是音乐家帕德雷夫斯基。很多年前，在他还是一名穷困潦倒的钢琴家时，玛丽曾为他拍手喝彩。

随后是盛大的赠予仪式：赠送镭元素。

华盛顿白宫亲自筹备这一仪式。美国总统和各界政要都在等待会见玛丽，但独不见镭元素。它太珍贵也太危险了，不能放在桌上或是总统手里。它被安全地存放在工厂里，总统手里拿的不过是个替代品。赠予仪式期间，东边房间桌子上摆的不过是镭元素的仿制品。

四点钟，两扇门同时打开，人群缓缓进入，玛丽挽着哈定总统的手臂走进会场。

总统发表欢迎词，他表示玛丽不仅仅是位伟大的科学家，更是一位尽心尽职的妻子和母亲。她不仅像男性一样完成了自己的日常工作，还额外履行了女性职责。

致辞结束后，总统颁给玛丽一张证书，并将镭元素箱子的金钥匙挂在玛丽的脖子上。在蓝色的会场上，玛丽安静地坐着，宾客排着队同艾琳和伊芙一一握手，因为玛丽已经太累了。

玛丽终于得到了一克镭元素！而过程一点也不容易。在赠予仪式的前一晚，麦隆内女士将证书交给玛丽，她却一直坚持不管多晚都要请律师来公证这克镭元素是属于实验室的。当麦隆内女士建议一周后再进行公证时，玛丽严肃地说道：“也许今晚我就会离世！” 从那晚起，镭元素正式归实验室所有，玛丽只是有权用之进行实验。

还有很多参观活动。美国因让客人筋疲力尽而深感愧疚，试尽一切方法让玛丽消除疲劳。有时他们特意安排玛丽在目的地前一站下车，等早就守候在车站的兴奋人群发现这一点时，他们又纷纷开着车去追赶这位客人。有时，玛丽不得已在火车的另一边下车，跳到铁轨上，穿过轨道，但其实没什么作用。有时艾琳和伊芙也想代替母亲出现，但当教授们同年仅十六岁的伊芙谈论起“伟大发现”和“毕生工作”时，人群根本无法满足。

但当芝加哥的波兰人为玛丽举办欢迎盛会时，玛丽还是如期赴约了。对他们来说，玛丽就是远方祖国的象征，她的成就是属于波兰的。男男女女的面庞都被喜悦的泪水打湿，纷纷跪在玛丽脚边亲吻她的双脚和裙边。

六月底，玛丽搭乘奥林匹克号重返巴黎，镭元素被锁在邮轮精密的保险箱里。在玛丽的信中，丝毫未提及镭元素，更多描述的是她内心的愉悦，她终于能为法国和波兰赢得美国的一丝友善。

在美国受到的热情礼遇让玛丽认识到她对世界来说有多重要。她意识到单单是自己的名字、自己的出现就能帮助她在意和热爱的事物。于是她开始更多地到各地参观拜访，出席庆祝仪式和会议。她已经名扬四海。她去过南美洲、西班牙、英国和捷克斯洛伐克。即便在她没到访过的中国，在一座孔子庙里，居里夫人的肖像也和佛像、天朝皇帝的头像摆在一起。

每次旅途中，玛丽都能看到新奇事儿。她喜欢看到鱼儿跳出水面，在空中划过一道弧线，在赤道附近人根本看不到自己的影子，这也让她兴奋不已，她喜欢在陌生地方遇见的各色野花。

但除了能看到自己喜爱的事物之外，每一次出访玛丽也都在为自己热爱追寻的事业而努力奋斗。同任何热爱世界、服务人类的人一样，玛丽痛恨战争。她愿意在战争中履行士兵的义务，为国家而战。但在和平年代，她更愿意努力避免更多战争的发生。她不愿意浪费科研时间参加各种协会活动，但唯有一个例外：她被国际联盟行政院提名为协会成员，成员们都立志于促进不同国家间的相互协作。这个协会也被称作“国际智力合作委员会”。玛丽不想只在协会中动动嘴皮子，她想确切做些实事。有成员致力于让所有国家的科研人员都使用相同的科研术语，制作关于世界上所有科学书籍和科学发现的完整清单，这样学生们就知道科学界已经取得了哪些成就。

此外，玛丽希望能建立一种机制，帮助各国具有科学天赋但却穷困潦倒的科学家们发挥自己的才能。她认为对天才放任不理是世界上最可怕的资源浪费。她竭尽所能创造一个自由、和平和科学发展越来越迅速的世界。既然巴黎的镭研究所已经正常运作了，玛丽还想在华沙也建立一个镭元素研究所。她的姐姐布朗尼娅就在波兰，能帮助她实施这一想法。很快，波兰举国上下就贴满了公告；所有的邮局都开始出售印有玛丽头像的邮票；明信片上都印有“为玛丽·斯克沃多夫斯卡·居里研究所的建设添砖加瓦吧”这样的邀请，上面还有玛丽的笔迹：“我真切地希望能在华沙建立镭元素研究所。”

1925年，玛丽回到了华沙，参加研究所奠基仪式。波兰共和国总统垒下了第一块砖，玛丽垒下了第二块。他笑着问玛丽是否还记得自己穷困潦倒时玛丽送给他的睡枕。她回答道：“当然，不过您忘还了。”她也清楚地记得当年那个著名的演员在舞台上给她的问候，那个人就是科塔宾斯基先生，玛丽曾给他送了顶用野花编制的花环。

但镭研究所要是没了镭元素就显得有些可笑。麦隆内女士又成功说服美国给玛丽送了一克镭元素，玛丽也因此再次赴美。但这一次是以波兰的名义感谢美国。她待在白宫，看见到处都是象的雕塑，有大象、小象、小小象、白象，觉得很有意思。作为临别礼物，玛丽获赠两头象，一头象牙制的小象和一头几乎看不见的小象。大象是执政党的徽标。带着两个象雕和镭元素，玛丽回到华沙，看到研究所已经正常运转，开始医治病人。

同当年小女孩时一样，玛丽沿着维斯瓦河散步，并写下：

“河流蜿蜒，河面宽阔，河水缓缓，近处是灰色，远处如天空般碧蓝。美丽的沙滩在太阳下金光闪闪，勾勒出河流蜿蜒的轮廓。在河岸边，明亮的光线显示出水深的地方。我只想在这波光粼粼的河岸边漫步……有首歌唱的是：‘波兰的河水魅力无边，一旦爱上便永远爱上。’对我来说这千真万确。这条伟大的河流有一种不能言说的魅力。”

第十九章　度假

布列塔尼有个地方，粉色的花岗岩峭壁绵延伸向蔚蓝清澈的大海，海面平静，周围数千座小岛将大西洋的滚滚波浪隔挡在外。岩石深处有个地方叫拉尔库埃，坐落着渔民们的房屋，不算是村庄，顶多就是个小村落，布列塔尼的卖鱼妇们都戴着宽帽檐的白色亚麻帽，躲避海风的吹拂。

玛丽的度假山庄就坐落在荒野高处，风中一条清晰的小路直通屋门，远看就像一座灯塔，虽然是座破旧的村舍，但视野开阔，风景优美。在拉尔库埃，没有人认识玛丽。村长是个有些驼背、个子不高的老人，眼镜后是一双笑眯眯的眼睛，他住的房子就是一座又长又低的村舍，从上到下都用藤蔓覆盖，周围种着红色的吊钟花，让游客赏心悦目。房屋坐落在果园里，叫作塔什维翰，在布列塔尼这个名字的意思是“小果园”。大门经常敞开，除了东风肆意的季节，这位“老国王”的宾客们——玛丽、艾琳、伊芙、弗雷德里克·约里奥、孩子们、科学家和作家们——事实上，“国王”受所有人的爱戴，宾客们在他身边待了一整天，但没想过“国王”本人就是当今世界上知识最渊博的历史学家之一，虽不及查尔斯·瑟诺博斯那样知名。他发现了拉尔库埃，每年夏天，巴黎最博学、最聪明的学者都会来此度假。

每天清晨，玛丽都会戴着褪了色的亚麻帽子，穿着旧短裙、凉鞋以及拉尔库埃人穿的黑色双排扣夹克衫，像渔民和卖鱼妇一样，沿着陡峭的山路从原野上走下来，走到塔什维翰花团锦簇的花园里。

“早上好，居里夫人。”瑟诺博斯说道。

“早上好！”十五个左右躺在青草鲜花间的人异口同声说道，他们穿着如同吉卜赛人。

玛丽将帆布包放在地上，坐在包旁。拉尔库埃像其他地方一样，也有严重的社会分化，但和大部分村庄也不太一样。在拉尔库埃，底层民众被称作菲利斯人。对拉尔库埃来说，他们是外来人、陌生人。再上一级可能你听过，是“大象”。对拉尔库埃来说，他们是朋友，但也是不幸的“旱鸭子”，他们在海上没有在陆地上感觉那么舒服。他们值得同情，同时也值得帮助。再之上，是本地受人尊敬的水手们，而远在他们之上的贵族们就是“鳄鱼”，他们了解海洋的一切，他们不仅会游泳，还能“爬水”，在最急的浪潮中都能扬帆划桨。玛丽从未做过菲利斯，也不可能成为鳄鱼一族。她起初是大象，正努力成为水手。

瑟诺博斯让水手们从船舰上拖下来两艘帆船、六艘划桨船，停在码头上，还有小艇和游船，用船桨将它们划到岩石栈台。

瑟诺博斯喊道：“快上船！快上船！我要划船了，居里夫人来划桨，佩林和波莱尔划小艇，弗朗西斯掌舵。”

船员都是教授。白绿相间的小船在原地转圈，因为有人划得太使劲儿。舵手命令船员们注意：“船桨没跟上节奏。” 玛丽脸色绯红，认真调整着自己划桨的节奏。海水在太阳下微波浮荡，水手们唱道：

三个男孩划船上岛
船上充满了欢声笑语
小岛也在等着三个男孩
……

唱完第三首歌，也要换桨了，因为身强力壮的船员要带他们穿过浪花前往罗斯福莱斯，紫罗兰色的小岛，拉尔库埃人都在这里游泳。男孩就在海岸上换衣服，旁边是棕色的海鸥，女士们则到岩石后面用绿草搭建的更衣室里换泳衣。

玛丽第一个跳到了清澈的海水中。她虽然不会爬水，但很擅长游泳。在水中她仿佛又年轻了，白头发都藏在泳帽下，也没人能注意到她的皱纹。她身材修长优雅，姿势敏捷，并对自己的技艺颇为骄傲。“我可比波莱尔游得要好。”她对艾琳喊道。艾琳可不会阿谀奉承，她只会实话实说：“是的妈妈，你游得太好啦。无与伦比。”

游完泳，玛丽晒着日光浴，吃了一片面包。“太惬意了，”她低声说道，“多美好呀。” 即便是玛丽·居里也无须多言拉尔库埃的美。没什么必要。拉尔库埃是世界上最美的地方，这众人皆知。

中午，伴着船员们的歌声，他们回到家中。玛丽光着脚，光着腿，手中提着凉鞋，抓着短裙，踩着黑泥慢慢踱到岸边，成群的白海鸥在岸边休憩。

一群人在家中用过午饭，随后下午两点钟大部分人回到塔什维翰花园里，准备搭乘汽艇野玫瑰号。这些汽艇和船只都属于瑟诺博斯。他拥有一切，但他更喜欢和朋友们分享一切。玛丽不会玩帆船，她觉得坐汽艇也是个漫长的过程。于是，她坐在自己如灯塔般的家中批改科学论文，或者拿着铁锹、铲子和修枝剪在花园里修修剪剪。荆棘划破了她的皮肤，岩石让她扭伤了脚腕，有时又会被锤子砸到手指，但她对这些小事并不在意。下午六点钟，她重新回到沙滩上晒太阳，来到塔什维翰花园陪伴年迈的老妇人，等待野玫瑰号的归程。在落日的余晖下，帆船在晚饭前刚好回到了岸边，快乐的船员们走进塔什维翰花园，女孩们头上都别着瑟诺博斯每天送给她们的粉色康乃馨。

吃过晚饭，大家都走到了塔什维翰花园敞开的大门旁。有时，还会玩一些简单的猜词或者猜字谜游戏。有时也会踢球。有时又会拉响手风琴，演奏旧式舞蹈的乐曲，所有人——无论是科学家还是村民，无论是主人还是仆人——大家共同舞蹈。

有时夜晚月光明朗，玛丽和艾琳、伊芙就会手挽手沿着海边蜿蜒的小路散步。突然吹来的海风中夹杂着浪花拍打礁石的声音，也让玛丽想到她的放射性元素镭，它难道不就如同大海一般，神秘而危险？拉尔库埃距离潘波很近。拉尔库埃人一整天都在波光粼粼的海边玩耍，但潘波人是冰岛渔民，最了解海洋的神秘与危险。

每年度假，玛丽都会来到波光粼粼的海边。工作时，她专心研究镭元素。她沉浸在镭元素的射线中，这灼伤了她的皮肤，因为她让别人穿上厚重的铅服，而自己却脱掉了。这也对她的血液产生了不好的影响。即便是法国最著名的医生都束手无策。

1934年7月4日，夏季的一天，玛丽在桑塞罗摩疗养院去世，死于一种不知名的疾病，后来医生们猜想，这定与她长期接触她的伟大发现——镭元素——有关。

Author's Foreword

THE life of Madame Curie has been written by her daughter with a charm and beauty never surpassed. It is therefore with the deepest humility that I have ventured to make out of that lovely book a shorter tale for young people.

People ought not to wait till they are over sixteen to make the acquaintance of the greatest and most delightful human beings and to hear of the world's greatest deeds. Yet complete biographies are necessarily lengthy and are often written in words familiar only to those of much experience and many years.

I hope therefore that The Radium Woman and Robert Gibbings's beautiful woodcuts may help the younger members of a family to share the keen delight that their elders are taking in the life of Madame Curie and that it will promptthem to vow: “We will not let ourselves be deprived of a word or a hint concerning that wonderful woman. We will also read Eve Curie's Madame Curie.”

ELEANOR DOORLY.

Warwick. March, 1939.

Chapter I　Manya Singing

WHY not? Why not? Why not? Why shouldn't Manya be allowed to read? She didn't ask the question. She would not think of asking her gentle, beautiful mother why not; she only puzzled her own little stubborn head where a pair of bright, grey-blue eyes looked penetratingly out from under a shock of yellow hair.

It was always like that! She had only to say: “Mayn't I read?” or to put out a hand towards a book and someone would be sure to say: “Manya dear, run into the garden” or “You haven't been to see your doll all day” or “Build me a house with those lovely new blocks.” Manya knew all their wiles. Reading was naughty—naughty for her, but not for Bronia; and yet she could read and Bronia couldn't. It was very puzzling and apparently all the fault of the day when she had snatched a book from Bronia. She hadn't meant anything wrong. Bronia had asked her to play with the cardboard letters when they had nothing to do in their uncle's orchard except lie on the grass and move the bits of cardboard into words. Then one day, after they came home, their father had said to Bronia: “Let's see how the reading has got on.” Bronia had stood with the open book, spelling the words and stumbling over them. So Manya had seized it from her and read! “Manya!” her mother had exclaimed, surprised and shocked and her father had looked solemn while Bronia had sulked. There had been nothing for Manya to do but to cry and sob out: “Beg pardon... Manya didn't mean it.”

Since that day no reading had been allowed, so Manya stood hesitating at her mother's door wondering what she should do. All morning she had been carrying ammunition for Bronia across the long dormitory floor in the great war against Joseph's and Hela's fort. The fort was built of the new blocks and the ammunition consisted of blocks also and she had grown too hot and tired, so that game had been stopped as far as she was concerned. There was nothing for it but to find her elder sister and go into the garden. “Zosia!… Zosia!” she called through the house and the two went off hand in hand. Zosia was twelve and almost grown up in the eyes of the other four, who were Joseph, Hela, Bronia, aged eight, and Manya. Manya was four when she learned to read and five on the day we are talking about, which explains why she was not allowed to read. Monsieur and Madame Sklodovski did not want their clever little girl pressed. But it had not occurred to them to tell her the reason.

The garden was big, level and walled in, with a rather worn grass patch and lots of trees. In much of it they could play to their hearts' content, but they had to be careful what they did on their way out and in, because they had to pass the windows of an Ogre. The garden belonged to the boys' High School, and in the school both the Sklodovskis and the Ogre lived. Even Zosia was nervous when she had to pass those windows and lowered her voice to a whisper, telling her little sister to be quite silent while they tip-toed past.

Although she was only five, Manya already knew quite a number of things. She knew that the Ogre was an ogre because he belonged to the people who had cut her own country into three parts and shared them out, like a giant dividing his spoil with two other giants. She was a Polish child and the ogre was the Russian Director of the school in which her father taught Mathematics and Physics. He was there to see that all the Polish men, women and children pretended properly to be Russian and Manya knew that with such people you had to be on your guard, careful and quiet so as not to be caught.

There was another thing that Manya knew very well: the country was a lovely place, though she lived in the town. In the country there were crowds and crowds and uncles and aunts and cousins; there was a stream to paddle in and mud to make mud pies and plenty of sun to cook the delectable cakes. There was the old lime tree that seven cousins sat in, eating gooseberries from cool cabbage leaves. When she appeared they would hoist her up to their crooked perch and make a collection for her from each of the seven cabbage leaves. In July, Manya was a wild little peasant.

Then there was her mother. Manya knew that she loved her more than anything else in the world. She was very beautiful, so it was not surprising that Manya thought so, or that she loved her beautiful singing. She loved, too, her mother's odd little way of stroking her hair and her forehead when she went to bed, instead of kissing her and when, in the evening all the family knelt around the table and prayed “Pray God make our mother better,” Manya never supposed it was because her mother was ill or that that had anything to do with not being kissed.

Manya had been born on November the 7th, 1867, and named Marya, but she was more often called Manya or Manyusia—or oftenest of all, a strange pet name, Anciupecio, for in Poland they love nicknames. Zosia had spent the time in the garden telling her a long story about Anciupecio, because Zosia told stories better than anybody else and often made up gay little plays which she acted for her brother and sisters, taking all the parts herself. So real were those plays that Manya used to laugh and shudder by turns and not be quite sure in which country she lived or who were the people next door or who the people in the story.

When they reached the house, they found that their father had. just finished school and was sitting in his study, the largest, happiest room in the house. The two entered very quietly. There sat their mother making a pair of shoes for Manya. Creak, creak went the scissors, cutting through the hard leather. Snap, snap crackled the waxed thread as it tightened and grew taut between the layers, and clack, clack tapped the hammer on the nails. Madame Sklodovski's thin white hands were nimble and cunning even at such hard work as that—and they needed to be, because five children wear out a mighty deal of shoe leather in a year.

That evening their father was talking about the Ogre. He often talked about him. The Ogre meant much to the family and was going to mean more. He had recently punished a Polish boy savagely for making a grammatical mistake in Russian, which is one of the hardest of foreign languages, and Monsieur Sklodovski had not been able to resist the temptation of saying: “But you too, sir, though you are a Russian by birth, sometimes make a grammatical mistake in that language.” The Ogre did not at once retort. He glowered and scowled, but he saved up his revenge for another year.

Manya wandered round her father's room, straight little nose in the air, dreamily thinking her own thoughts, touching her pet ornaments, keeping carefully from disturbing her brother and sisters, who were doing their homework around their father's big, flat-topped desk. Manya was not at all interested in the splendid picture of a bishop which hung on the wall; it was said to be by a famous painter, but that was not the kind of thing she liked. She loved the clock on the desk and stayed a long time peering into its face and listening to its loud tick, tock. Then she ran her fingers daintily along the smooth marble top of the many-coloured Sicilian table; she liked that too, but not the whatnot with its blue Sèvres cup. She drew herself carefully away from that as the thing was breakable and something terrible might happen if she touched it. Not so the next treasures; they were more friendly and more mysterious with lovely, long, incomprehensible names—the barometer hanging on the wall which her father examined and tapped so seriously every day under the children's watchful eyes; the glass cupboard containing glass tubes and delicate balances and minerals and a goldleaf electroscope. “What... ?” Manya began one day.

“What are those?” interrupted her father in a solemn, teasing voice, “Those are physical apparatus.”

Little did he think…! Little did Manya think what was going to happen to her and physical apparatus, but she liked the odd sounding words and ran off chanting:

Phýs-ˇ-cˇal áp-pˇar-á-tús.

Phýs-ˇ-cˇal áp-pˇar-á-tús.

Chapter II　Manya Learning

MANYA'S school was an odd place and she learned odd things: how, for instance, to do what one is forbidden to do; how to hide one's disobedience quickly; how to seem to be doing what one isn't; how to diddle government inspectors; and because Manya was cleverer than most children, she was soon doing all these things better than the others. But the queerest thing of all in that school was that her form mistress and the headmistress found her a great help and not, as you might have thought, a great nuisance.

One day her class of twenty-five were having a delicious history lesson—a much more delicious history lesson than English children have ever had because it was a forbidden lesson. All the twenty-five and their mistress knew it was forbidden.

There they sat, the twelve year olds. Manya, aged only ten, was in the third row, near the high window looking out on to the snowy lawn. All the twenty-five were in navy blue with steel buttons and white collars, their hair tightly plaited and tied behind their ears with a neat tight bow. Their ears were all stretched, left ear listening hard for every word of history, right ear quick to catch the first tinkle of a certain door bell—conspirators all! Mistress and pupils were waiting, working, waiting to be caught!

Manya was in the middle of answering a question… Her mistress liked her to answer as she was always top in history, top too in arithmetic, literature, German and French. On this occasion she was telling what she had learned of the Polish king, Stanislas Auguste.

“He was elected King of Poland,” said she, “in 1764. He was a clever, highly educated king, a friend of poets and artists. He understood the causes of Poland's weakness and tried to make her strong, but alas, he had no courage...” Even Manya knew that a king should have courage and her voice was full of fierce regret, the fierce regret of a ten year old, who understood quite a lot. Tang—, tang—, ting, ting. Everybody shivered once. Everybody moved quickly, absolutely silently. Tupcia, as they called their mistress, piled her Polish books, every child piled her exercise books and her Polish history. The five whose duty it was, gathered all the books into their aprons and carried them with all speed to the boarders' bedrooms. The rest got out their needlework and were making exquisite buttonholes in cotton squares as if they had never done anything else.

The Russian inspector came in, accompanied by the unhappy headmistress, who had not been able to prevent his walking fast, and was in a panic lest the warning bell, with its two long rings and two short, had not given the children time to hide their disobedience. But there was no sign of anything but needlework, except that perhaps five little girls looked rather hot and breathless. But a man would not notice that.

Monsieur Hornberg, the inspector, sat down heavily. He was a fine looking man in spite of his fat and his shaved head. His uniform helped him with its yellow trousers and blue jacket fastened with well-polished silver buttons. In silence, he looked piercingly at the children through his gold-rimmed glasses and glanced swiftly at the book Tupcia had laid open on the desk with a bored air.

“You were reading aloud while they worked?” he questioned. “What is the book?”

“Krylov's Fairy Tales. We have just begun it to-day.”

M. Hornberg knew that Russian book well and sincerely approved of it. He opened one of the desks and found it tidily empty. The button-holing had stopped and the children were politely waiting for his words of wisdom. It was not he who would have the eyes to see in their motionless faces the fear, the cleverness, the hatred that was there behind their solemn eyes.

“Mademoiselle, call up one of those young people, please.”

Tupcia was relieved; she couId choose one who would not make a hash of things. The one, however, was praying not to be called up. “Don't let it be me, God, please God…” She did not hear God say: “Marya Sklodovska, the world is waiting for you to learn to do disagreeable things greatly.” She did hear Tupcia call Marya Sklodovska!

She got up, turned hot, turned cold; shame clutched at her young throat.

“Say the Lord's Prayer,” ordered Hornberg.

Manya obeyed, saying it in Russian as the foreign ruler bade, not in Latin, according to the custom of her own religion.

“Mention the Czars of Holy Russia since Catherine II.”

“Catherine II, Paul I, Alexander I, Nicolas I, Alexander II,” recited Manya in perfect Russian as if she had been born in St. Petersburg.

“And the names and titles of the Czar's family.”

“Her Majesty, the Empress, His Imperial Highness, the Czarevitch Alexander, His Imperial Highness, the Grand Duke...”

“Good! Who governs us?”

Manya hesitated.

“Who governs us?” repeated the inspector, irritated.

“His Majesty, Alexander II, Czar of all the Russias,” stammered Manya, turning pale.

The inspection was over and the inspector gone, very well satisfied with what he had seen and heard and feeling that he was making a real success of his department. But Manya broke down and cried as if her heart would break.

At the end of school, outside in the street, the excited children had a tale to tell their aunts and mothers and nurses who had come to fetch them; but in whispers they told it, for they knew only too well that any passer-by, any lounger, might be a spy, who would repeat to the government what even a child said.

Hela and Manya took their Aunt Lucia by each arm. “The inspector questioned Manya,” whispered Hela. “She answered like a brick, but cried like a baby afterwards. Anyway, the inspector hadn't any fault to find with anybody.”

Manya held her tongue. She hated it all—hated being afraid, hated being made to feel that she belonged to an enslaved nation, hated having to lie, to lie all the time. As she clung to her aunt's arm, she remembered all the things she hated: the Ogre who had managed to turn her father out of his professorship. That had made them so that they were obliged to have students lodging in their house, which was horrid and often made them uncomfortable and unhappy. But that happiness was as nothing in comparison with not having Zosia any more, Zosia to tell her tales, Zosia to listen to all she had to say. Zosia had caught typhus from one of the students and had gone away for ever.

Across the sunny, snowy park the three made their way to the old town of Warsaw with its narrow streets and high, sloping-roofed houses ringed with snow. From unexpected comers, odd little sculptures looked out, Virgins' faces or strange stone animals.

Suddenly, the old church bells clanged out above their heads, clear and noisy in the frosty air. There were quite a crowd of churches just there and Aunt Lucia drew the children in through the dark door of one where they used to go to mass years before. How could Manya go in now, without Zosia? But she went in, because there was a colder fear than any other in her heart now and she wanted to persuade God to let her mother get better. “Let mother get better,” she prayed. “Let me die instead of mother, please, God.”

Out in the crisp winter air again Aunt Lucia had a treat to propose: they were to go down to the Vistula to buy the household apples from the market boats. Forgetting their sorrows, the children ran down the long steps that led to the river. The great Vistula rolled its yellowish, sombre vastness around low sandy islands, great empty barges slowly heaved against one another, sometimes thudding with a low sound into the floating baths and wash-houses at the bank. Only around the two long apple barges was there life in that winter season, for they had come from far up the river to bring red, rosy joy to children in Warsaw. The master, cosy in his sheepskin coat, swaying as he moved about the craft, lifted the straw here and there to show the purchasers how red and polished and free from frost his merchandise was in spite of its many days' journeying down the Vistula.

Hela first, then Manya threw down muff and satchel and began excitedly choosing their own apples, piling them in the great wicker basket that was to carry them home, throwing any bad ones they had the luck to find far far out into the river, seeing who could throw the furthest.

Then Aunt Lucia engaged a boy to carry home the basket and marched her charges off the boat, each munching the reddest of all the apples.

At home at five o'clock, there was a meal of something more substantial than apples and then homework round the big desk. Soon a loud murmur rose from those aggravating people who do lessons aloud, a trying custom in other lands besides Poland. Those children had to learn their lessons in Russian. Mathematics in Russian for Polish children were even harder than usual. French and German grammar was all in Russian and words they did not know had to be looked up in Russian dictionaries. They might, of course, explain their difficulties to themselves in Polish, but when the next morning came they had to say the lesson in Russian and to go through a geometrical problem in a foreign language. They had to write their essays in a tongue not their own and to read French directly into Russian. Learning was a hard matter.

But Manya was a witch. She knew things by magic without learning them; she had to read her Russian verses only twice to know them without a mistake, lucky scrap! But she was also a kind-hearted scrap, for when her homework was done under time, she would help other people through their maze of difficulty. Not always, though. If she got a chance, she would put a book between her elbows on the table, her hands over her ears to keep out Hela's recitation, and… read! When Manya read, there was no waking her from her absorption; she heard nothing. A whole household might plan to tease and make a noise like all the zoos let loose with tin cans to play with and yet Manya wouldn't hear till her book was done. That was concentration and it was a joyful gift to have seized from the lucky-bag of life.

Once the others built a scaffolding of chairs round her as she read, a chair on each side, a chair behind and on top, three more chairs and so on over her head. She didn't hear or see a shadow of a chair or builder. She didn't hear delighted whispering or stifled laughter. When she had finished, she raised her head and down came the whole edifice amid shouts of laughter from the others. That didn't please Manya. She rubbed a bruised shoulder and went into another room, flashing at her elders as she passed just: “That's silly!”

When bedtime came, the Sklodovski girls slept on skins in the dining-room because the bedrooms had to be given to the students who paid. In the night the skins used to slip off and leave them cold. In the morning they had to get up in the dark because the dining-room had to be ready for the students' breakfast.

But such things as that were of no importance to Manya. Her mother was growing more and more ill, even she could see that. She prayed to God always, but He seemed not to listen to ten year old Manya. And in the spring, in May, before she was eleven, her mother slipped away, whispering to her little girl: “I love you.”

Manya was learning very much; was learning that life asks for courage from nations and men and children, not only from kings. She had thoughts of her own about it all. It seemed to her unjust and cruel and not at all to be understood. She was headstrong and angry and not at all submissive.

Chapter III　Rebels

MANYA at fourteen was not yet as pretty as her sisters. Bronia was quite grown up with long sweeping skirts and her golden hair done up into a bun at the back. She had taken her mother's place and looked after the housekeeping and the lodgers. Hela was sixteen and a beauty, fair and tall and graceful. Joseph was also fair and tall and handsome. He was at the university studying medicine.

The girls would have liked to think of themselves as going to the university also, but in Russian Poland no woman was allowed to go to any university. If they wanted to learn more than they learned at school, they had to get their learning from books for themselves or in another country.

For the moment, Manya was content for herself. She had gone on to the High School and was as happy as a squirrel with all the nuts it needed; but she was worried about Bronia. What would Bronia do without a university? Couldn't she, Manya, invent a scheme to get Bronia to some country where girls could learn what they wanted to know? She made up her mind to work and earn money to keep her elder sister. Well, the high road to earning was to get through school successfully! Manya, that particular morning, would be late for school unless she finished breakfast quickly, cut up the sandwiches for school lunch, saved, yes saved, the meat from Lancet who had interrupted her thoughts by a quick grab at the last of the mutton which was waiting to be cut up for those sandwiches. Lancet was the red setter, the adored of the household. He was very beautiful and did everything he shouldn't. He had golden feathers on ears and tail and feet and should have been a most obedient shooting dog, but he had had no education. Manya, her brother and sisters spoilt him all day, kissed him, even made a lap dog of him. He slept in the chairs, brushed vases down with his tail, ate other people's lunch, upset visitors with his uproarious welcome, took their hats and gloves for them with the politest air—gloves and hats that looked sadly the worse for wear when they were returned to their owners.

At last lunch having been safely wrapped up, her satchel slung on her back and Lancet persuaded to stay at home, Manya ran off to school.

At the blue palace where Count Zamoyski lived, she stopped, hesitated before the great bronze lion guarding one of its old stone courtyards and put her hand on the heavy ring in its mouth to turn it over its nose.

“Don't run away, Manyusia,” called a voice from a window; “Kazia'll be there in a minute.” Manya always picked up Kazia, who was the daughter of the Count's librarian, on her way to school; but if her friend were late, she turned the bronze ring up and went on. Then Kazia could be in no doubt whether she had passed.

“Come to tea this afternoon,” called Kazia's mother; “there'll be your favourite iced chocolate.”

“Of course you're coming to tea,” said Kazla. “Oh! Aren't we late? Come on!”

So the two hurried along the narrow street and through the park, neither of them conscious of the difference everyone else could see in them. Kazia was so well dressed, so obviously the petted daughter of two devoted parents, while Manya was a little left to herself, a little shabby.

It was a long way to school and they had plenty of time for chatter, time too to play certain games. In the wet weather they made a point of trailing their goloshes through the deepest parts of the puddles; in the dry, they played the “green” game.

“Do come to the shops and buy a new exercise book,” said Manya. I have seen some awfully jolly ones with green covers that will…”

But Kazia wasn't caught. At the word green and before Manya could finish her sentence she handed her a piece of green velvet she was keeping ready for the purpose in her pocket. She escaped a forfeit and for the moment nothing more followed. Manya seemed to have given up the game. She began talking about their last history lesson in which the professor had gone out of his way to tell them that Poland was a mere province of Russia and the Polish language a Patois.

“Still he seemed uncomfortable,” she remarked. “Did you see that he dared not look at us and turned quite pale?”

“Yes!” said Kazia; “he was almost green.” And immediately, she saw Manya twiddling a young green chestnut leaf under her nose.

“We've passed the monument!” a cry of horror from Manya. “Oh, well! We've got to go back”; and back they went right to Saxe Square where there was a lofty column supported by four lions. On it was written “To the Poles faithful to their Monarch.” The Czars had erected the monument to those Poles who, traitors to their own country, had died fighting on the side of the oppressor. It had become the duty of all Poles who were faithful to Poland to spit at the monument every time they passed it and Manya and Kazia would not leave that duty undone even if it meant retracing their steps or being late for school.

“Are you coming to watch the dancing tonight?” asked Manya. Naturally Kazia was going. Every week a few families met to dance at the Sklodovskis; but only the girls who were “out” were allowed to dance. Kazia and Manya were obliged to sit still and watch. Nevertheless they were getting hints of how to do it, studying the steps, discussing the movements, learning the tunes; and when the grown-up dancing was over, they practised by themselves.

They were eagerly discussing the joys of coming out as they walked under the school archway into the courtyard. Girls from every direction were trooping into the great bare, three-storied building; there were laughter and chatter and gaiety and many greetings. But one girl was hurrying in alone as if she wished to escape notice. As the two caught her up, they saw that her eyes were swollen and red and her clothes were untidy as if she had scrambled into them anyhow.

“What's the matter with Kunicka?” they asked one another and one of them slipped an arm round the girl.

“What's the matter, Kunicka?”

Kunicka could scarcely answer, her pale face was drawn with pain. “It's my brother,” she stammered. “He's been caught in a plot… For three days we hadn't had any news of him…They're... they're going to hang him at dawn to-morrow.”

The words seemed to have no meaning. The two drew Kunicka out of the crowd; bending over her, they tried to understand, tried to comfort her. But there was no comfort for someone whose brother was going to be hanged to-morrow! Manya and Kazia knew the young, gay brother. He was their friend. He had done nothing wrong. How could he be going to die?

“Make haste, children! Enough talking!” It was the hated voice of the German superintendent, Miss Mayer, and the three were obliged to bury their grief and go into school.

It was no longer the private school to which Manya had gone as a little girl, but the government High School, run by the Russian government. In it, everything except the pupils were Russian. The Polish children were obliged to attend it, because only by so doing could they get a certificate of any sort which would enable them to get work. They attended, but they were rebels and freer to express their opinions than their elders. Manya and Kazia took delight in inventing witticisms against their Russian professors, their German master and especially against Miss Mayer who detested Manya only a little less than Manya detested her.

Little and dark Miss Mayer used to go about in soft slippers not to be heard and the better to spy on the girls.

“It's no more use speaking to that Sklodovska girl,” she said, “than throwing green peas at a wall!”

“Look at your ridiculous, frizzy, disorderly head, Marya Sklodovska! How often have you been told to confine your curls? Come here and let me brush them down and make you look like a decent school girl.” “Like a German Gretchen!” thought Manya, but she said nothing. So with the brush that brushed everybody's hair, she set on Manya's head with good hard blows. But however hard she brushed, the curls were rebels still—those light, capricious, exquisite curls that framed Manya's round, rebellious face.

“I won't have you look at me like that!” Miss Mayer would shout. “You have no right to look down on me!”

“I can't help it,” said Manya truthfully, for she was a head taller than Miss Mayer. No doubt she was glad that words sometimes have two meanings.

But the girls liked some of their teachers, for some were Polish. In some of the Russians also, to their dumb surprise, they found Polish sympathies. They began to understand that even in Russia there were rebels. One Russian master had gone so far as to give as a prize a book of revolutionary poems. That silent act became the talk of the school and the pupils watched him with wondering, admiring eyes. Poles could live with Russians. Oh, yes! Were not the pupils in that city school Russians, Poles, Germans, Jews? And were they not all happy together? In school they found no difference in the races. Outside school each nation kept apart, for all feared spies.

In spite of everything Manya loved her school; a little shamefacedly she confessed it. “Do you know, Kazia,” she wrote one holiday, “I like the school. Are you going to laugh at me? I like it. I even like it very much. I am not longing for it. No! But I am not sad at the thought of term and two years more of it is no horrible thought.”

But on that particular day, when Miss Mayer called the girls in from the courtyard, Manya had no thought for school. In the sunny morning, she had been dreaming of music and dance and jesting. Suddenly the world had changed. While the dim words of unheard lessons floated around her ears, she could see nothing but the young eager boy whom she knew… and a cold, pictured dawn with a gallows.

There was no thought of dancing at the Sklodovskis that night. Manya, Bronia and Hela, Kazia and Ula, her sister, all went to sit up the night through with Kunicka, keeping watch in the long night, thinking of the boy who had to die. That keeping watch is a Catholic custom, it is just staying awake to think. The six children sat with Kunicka. We who are happier cannot imagine what they thought or felt. It is so different when someone we love dies naturally, even children understand that; but this other—to sit and wait while the minutes pass and the hour of man's exceeding cruelty comes nearer to stain the dawn with wrong—that was horror indeed. They must have watched in silence, for there was nothing to say, nothing to do, only plenty to think, rebel thoughts for the hearts of six young rebels. From time to time, they did what they could for Kunicka, their own hearts breaking with sympathy. They tried to get her to drink something warm; gently they put their arms around her or tried to dry her tears. Then suddenly they realised that the new light was no longer candlelight. There was a red line in the sky. The red dawn had come. The six buried their terrified faces in their hands and threw themselves on their knees to pray for the young rebel who was dead.

Chapter IV　A Whole Year's Holiday

MANYA was sixteen. Gold medal day had come and Manya's gold medal was the third in the family. It was June and very hot. Manya, like all the prize winners, was dressed in black with a bunch of tea roses in her belt. The crowd pressed around her congratulating her and shaking hands. When it was all over, she left the High School for good, her fingers pressed tight on her proud father's arm.

He had promised her a whole year's holiday. That was a gift indeed, a year's holiday! Manya hadn't an idea why she should have it, but her father thought that as she had been working very hard and as she had done her work in less time than other girls, it was only fair that she should take that delightful way of waiting for her age-fellows to catch her up. So Manya the industrious became a lazybones and entered into the full fun of the thing.

“My dear little Devil,” she wrote to Kazia, “I don't believe algebra and geometry exist. Anyway I have completely forgotten them. I don't even do my embroidery. I don't do anything. I get up at ten, or sometimes at six—in the morning, be it spoken—I read nothing or only tales. I am the stupidest of the stupid and I laugh all alone at my complete inanity. A crowd of us wander through the woods or play battledore and shuttlecock, at which I am a booby, or puss-in-the-corner or follow-my-leader or any such intellectual game. Wild strawberries are everywhere and for a penny-farthing we can buy enough for a meal—that's a soup-plate full, piled high and overflowing. Alas! Alas! they are almost over and my appetite is limitless so that I am quite scared at my greed. We swing… we swing right up into the sky. We bathe, we catch shrimps by torchlight. By-the-bye, we have met an actor. He sang to us and recited to us and gathered us so many gooseberries that in return we plaited him a crown of wild poppies and white pinks and blue cornflowers and threw it at him as he left for Warsaw. They say he put it on and then, when the train came in, packed it in his suitcase and took it all the way to the city.”

Manya was to spend her year in the country, She loved every bit of it. She was to watch all the seasons go round and to discover at every turn fresh beauties in the land of Poland. Her uncle, Xavier, lived on the plains of Zwola. There she looked over level land to the furthest, furthest horizon of which one could dream, green land streaked with the brown colours of ploughed earth. Her uncle had many horses in stable and there she learned to ride. What she wore didn't matter to her. She borrowed trousers from her cousin which were too big for her, turned them up, belted them into gathers and was ready. Left hand on reins and holding the big horse's mane, left foot in the stirrup and right hand on the saddle, she stood for the first adventure as she had seen her uncle and cousins stand. But what a long way it was up! She would never get there however much she hopped or however still the good old horse stood.

“Good to try!” said her uncle, “scramble!” But her cousins did not leave her untaught. They showed her how to stand with her back to the horse's head before she sprang, how to help herself with a convenient mound and, finally, how to get just the right spring that could land her into the saddle of the tallest horse. It became her delight to go long expeditions on horseback over the spreading fields. Soon she could rise in the saddle at the trot or sit tight at the gallop. She explored new villages and met strange country folk and knew more and more of the Polish plain.

But an even greater pleasure was in store for her: she went to stay with another uncle, whose name is quite unpronounceable to English ears, Uncle Zdzislaw, who lived among the Carpathian Mountains. For the first time she saw snowy heights, dazzling in their whiteness and dark pine forests like rivers of ink making the snow more white… She longed to get closer up; to make her way through the trees, perhaps to the edge of the snow itself. She went for long walks up winding mountain paths which sometimes ended unexpectedly in a precipice, so that she had to retrace her steps. Sometimes the path ended at a hut and Manya and her cousins would go in and ask to see the owner's work; for all the mountaineers of that district were wood carvers and their simplest piece of furniture was a work of art. The peasants loved to show the things that they had made and when the children had admired the chairs and table and cuckoo clock and the coloured wooden bowls against the wall, they delved into cupboards and brought out little carved men or drinking cups or toys or even pictures carved in wood.

Once, in her wanderings, Manya came to a little mountain lake, a patch of water lying in the hills as blue as massed speedwell, and men called it “The sea's eye.” It was so lovely lying among the snow peaks that Manya thought it the gem of the whole country.

Within doors, life was quite riotously merry. Her uncle loved gaiety; so did his beautiful wife and as to his three daughters, they laughed all day and Manya with them. Guests arrived in plenty. Uncle and aunt would probably have been out shooting and have plenty of game to offer them. If they hadn't, there was nothing to do but slay a barn door chicken of which there were hundreds running about the yard. Then the girls flew to the kitchen and hastily baked the cakes. All was ready for the feast. For clothes, they hastily turned out cupboards and sewed together gay fancy dresses for charades, or if it was winter, for a “Kulig”—a winter fête.

Manya's first Kulig was a tremendous experience. The night was dark, but lit by the strange northern snow-light. Manya and her three cousins, wrapped in thick rugs, masked and dressed as Cracovian peasants, took their places in two sledges. Their outriders were boys in rustic costumes who lit the darkness with fantastic torches. Through the dark forest, they caught glimpses of other torches approaching. The cold night was suddenly filled with music, for the musicians were coming up, bringing four little Jews, who for two whole nights and two whole days Were to wring heart-stirring airs from their violins. They would play waltzes and mazurkas and all the world would catch up the refrains and sing them in chorus, making the night tuneful and noisy.

As the Jews played, other sledges joined them out of the darkness, three, five, ten sledges. In spite of hair-raising bends and glassy slopes those little musicians never missed a note as they led the fantastic troop under the frosty stats.

At the first lone farmhouse the sledges stopped with jingling bells and harness and all the company, laughing, shouting, and knocking loudly on the door, awakened the inmates, who were only pretending to be asleep. In a few moments the musicians were hoisted on to a table and the ball began in a room lit by torches.

Presently supper was brought and then, at a signal, suddenly the whole house was empty—empty of casks, of inhabitants, of horses, of sledges, of everything. A larger procession, with all the sledges of the new homestead, was wending its way through the forest to another farm.

A sledge with fresh horses, trying to pass another, went out of the beaten road, failed to get back and overturned in the snowdrift. The procession halted, torches waving in the wind, and gathered into a semicircle while willing hands brushed the snow from the occupants and righted their sledge. Again the bells rang out a wild peal of jingling speed in the night. But what had become of the musicians? Nobody knew. The leading sledge went faster and faster, hoping to catch them up; but it was soon apparent that they were not on that road; they had not gone on! A halt was called, a fork in the road was remembered. There was nothing for it but to go back and look for the little Jews along the other road. Everyone was worried. How would the dance go at the other farms if the musicians could not be found? But presently someone caught the joyful cry of violins above the sound of bells and the procession was complete again and growing in length as they stopped to dance at yet another farmhouse, and yet another and another.

The sun rose… the sun went down… the sun rose. The fiddlers had scarcely any time to eat or sleep. On the second night the vast train of sledges stopped with snorting horses and jingling bells before the biggest homestead for the real ball.

The little fiddlers played louder. The guests took their places for the famous figure dances. The chief boy, handsome and elegant, in his embroidered white costume advanced to lead out the best dancer of all the company. It was Manya Sklodovska, in the dress of a mountain maiden with a velvet jacket, puffed linen sleeves and a star-like crown decked with long, brightly coloured streamers.

They danced through the night. They danced a mazurka at eight in the morning. Manya said that never in her life had she enjoyed herself so much and her aunt said that if she enjoyed Kuligs so much, she should have one to celebrate her wedding.

But the joys of holidays were not over. An old pupil of Madame Sklodovska's, who had become Countess of Fleury, invited Hela and Manya to stay with her. The house stood on a tongue of land between two rivers. Manya had a lovely view from her room across the meeting waters and there she learned to row. “We do anything,” she wrote home, “that comes into our heads. We sleep all night and sometimes in the day. We dance. We are mad. In fact only a lunatic asylum would suit us!”

They varied their sleeping and dancing with riding and mushroom gathering and practical jokes. Once Manya asked the Countess's brother to go to town on a message. The unsuspecting young man went. The town was far. He came home in the dark and went to his room where all the young people of the house had slung his bed,his table, his chairs, his trunks, his clothes from the beams of the roof. His possessions had become entirely aerial and slapped him in the face as he moved among them.

On another day, lunch had been prepared for distinguished guests and the children were not invited. They ate the whole lunch before lunch and placed, by the empty table, a scarecrow representing a most satisfied and well-fed count! The culprits? Where were they? Vanished into thin air!

On the anniversary of the Count and Countess's wedding day, the gay company sent them, by two of their number, a huge crown made of vegetables. It weighed a hundred pounds and was presented to the happy couple as they sat on a decorated throne. Then the youngest member recited a poem which had been written by Manya for the occasion and ended thus:

For Louis' blessed day
A picnic be our pay!
For every girl invite a boy
In your example let us joy
And follow to the altar soon.
Grant us, grant us now this boon!

The Count and Countess did their best with a ball instead of a picnic. Manya and Hela wanted to be especially ravishing that night. They were poor and their ball dresses well worn. They counted their money. They turned the dresses over and over. They ripped off the faded tulle and found the linings quite good. A little blue tarlatan would do, they decided, instead of the tulle, and a ribbon here, a ribbon there would create new dresses. Thin purses and a skilful needle would do wonders. Flowers would do the rest and there would be money enough for two new pairs of shoes. When the shopping was done and the needlework was done and the garden had done its share, the mirror said: “You'll do.”

And Manya danced her new shoes through and fêted the morning by throwing them away.

Chapter V　People

MANYA was back in Warsaw. Her big grey eyes looked out with a laugh in them at a changed world. Her firm upper lip often twitched with a merry smile, but her face was often serious. Like the fathers of most of the world, Mr. Sklodovski let his children know that they had their living to earn. He had given up taking students and the family again lived in a little house of their own. It was hard enough, while their father was still earning, to pay the rent, the daily girl and the house-keeping and they had to look forward to the time when he would have nothing but a teacher's small pension to live on. That worried him. Like the fathers of most of the world, he had hoped to make enough money to provide for his family. Sitting by the lamp in the evening, he would sigh deeply. Four pair of happy eyes, between periwinkle-blue and grey, would look up at him and guess his thought; his four children would all protest together: “Don't worry, Father, aren't we all young and strong and able to earn for ourselves?” Mr. Sklodovski must have wondered, as he smiled at their eagerness, whether they would succeed in life as he had not done. He had worked hard and been very gifted and yet had won very little reward in money from life. Would his children be like him? The baldheaded, short, fat, little man sat under the lamp in his dark, meticulously brushed, shabby coat. Everything about him was precise and neat: his handwriting, his thoughts, his expressions, even his actions. He had brought up his children with the same exquisite, neat care. When he took them on excursions he made out the itinerary beforehand, pointed out the beauties of the landscape to them, realising, perhaps, what few people know, that most people miss seeing beauty because nobody mentions it. If they came to an old or famous building, he would tell them its history. Manya saw no faults in her father. It never occurred to her to mock his precise little ways. She thought of him as a fount of universal knowledge. And, indeed, he knew many things. He kept up with the new discoveries in physics and chemistry by buying learned pamphlets with his hard-earned savings. He knew, without a thought of his own cleverness, Greek and Latin and five modern languages. He wrote verse and read aloud beautifully to his children every Saturday evening so that they grew to know great literature. When he wanted to read to them some foreign book, David Copperfield, for example, he read it in Polish though the copy in his hand was English.

“There's nothing new at home,” wrote Manya to a friend. “The plants are quite well, thank you! The azaleas are in flower and Lancet is asleep on the rug! I have had my dress dyed and Gucia, the daily maid, is altering it. She's just done Bronia's, which is a success. I have little time and still less money. A lady who was recommended to us for lessons came; but when Bronia told her they would cost her a shilling an hour, she fled as if the house were on fire.”

Yet, paid badly or not, Manya had to teach. Nothing else was open to girls in those days. But she didn't think: “How many pupils can I get? What can I earn?” That wasn't Manya! She had her dreams—not the girl dream of getting married, nor the boy dream of engine driving. Her dream was Poland. She, Manya Sklodovska, must help Poland. How could she do that with her sixteen years and the stuff her father and her school and books had put into her head? There were others who dreamed for Poland, Manya knew, and plotted to throw bombs at the Czar. There were those who dreamed that God would answer their prayers for Poland. But, though Manya lent her passport to a revolutionary, she dreamed neither of those dreams. She believed that the most practical dream is the best: do the thing that is just in front of you; teach the Poles whom the Russian government was doing its best to keep ignorant; teach and teach and teach till Warsaw should become a great centre for the things of the mind, till Poland should lead Europe by being best.

New ideas were spreading in England and France. Manya had a friend ten years older than herself who had got wind of them and had started a secret society called the “Winged University” to study them. Manya, Bronia and Hela joined it. The little company met at one another's houses to be taught, not some weird or wild study, but just anatomy, biology and natural history. Yet at the sound of a knock at the door, a mouse in the wainscot, everyone started and trembled. If the police had caught them, it would have been prison for everybody. The members had to teach as well as learn. Manya collected a little library of books to lend to poor people but she had to teach them their letters and how to read before the books could be of any use to them.

Sometimes a Polish shop would be glad to let its work girls gather after work to meet Manya and sit thumbing books and racking brains in order to become more worthy citizens of Poland. No one was afraid that a single girl would give the secret away. Gay, reserved, little Manya, among the older, rougher girls refused to allow a single slang word or a single cigarette. Finding her curls too attractive, she cut them off, not noticing that by so doing she made herself look still more childish. She was full of work, trying her hand at everything: lectures, meetings, drawing, writing poetry, reading the literature of half a dozen countries—above all, following the far thoughts of great writers.

But what occupied her thoughts most was what was she going to do with Bronia. Bronia was getting old, or at least so thought Manya, and no one would see to Bronia's career if she didn't. Morning after morning, in fair weather or foul, she went to give her paid lessons. The rich kept her waiting, to them she was just a poor teacher, in a draughty corridor. “So sorry, Miss Sklodovska, my little girl is late this morning; you'll be able to give her her full lesson, of course?” At the end of the month her pay was forgotten. “So sorry, my husband will pay the two months together.” But Manya was needing the money then. She had been longing for it to buy a few necessary things.

Bronia was looking pale and discouraged. Manya would have to set aside her own ambitions, her desire to go to a university to satisfy her great need of knowledge. She must get Bronia off her hands first.

“Bronia, I have been thinking it all out,” she said one day; “and I have spoken to father. I think I have found a way.”

“A way to what?”

Manya had to be very careful and tactful. “Bronia, how long, could you live in Paris on what you've saved?”

“I could pay the journey and one year's living, but Medicine needs five years,” answered Bronia quickly.

“Yes, and lessons at a shilling an hour won't take us far.”

“Well?”

“Well, if each of us is working for herself, neither of us will succeed. Whilst with my plan you can take your train this autumn.”

“Manya! You're mad!”

“No. At first you can spend your own money and afterwards I will send you some. So will father. I can save for myself at the same time. And when you are a doctor, it will be my turn to go and you can help me.”

There were tears in Bronia's eyes for she understood what the offer meant to Manya but she thought the arithmetic a little odd. “How are you going to keep yourself, to help me and to save all at the same time?” she asked.

“Ah! That's the way I am finding. I am going to get a resident post where I shall be kept by someone else and have no chance to spend anything! Isn't that perfect?”

“No,” said Bronia, “I don't see why I should go first. You are cleverer. If you go first, you will succeed quickly and afterwards I can go.”

“Why? Oh foolish Bronia, dear! Aren't you twenty and I only seventeen? You have been waiting centuries. I have time. The eldest must go first. When you have a practice, you can shower gold on me! Besides I have set my heart on it, so there!”

So in September, just a month before her eighteenth birthday, Manya found herself in the waiting room of the Governesses' agency, dressed as she was sure a governess should be dressed. Her hair which had grown again was neatly done under her faded hat; her dress was plain and severe; everything about her was ordinary and quiet.

Nervously she approached the lady at the desk, holding her certificate and testimonials very tight. The lady read the testimonials very attentively and then suddenly looked at Manya; she even stared at her. “You really mean that you know German, Russian, French, Polish and English perfectly?” she questioned.

“Yes” said Manya, “though my English is not so good as the others. Still, I can teach it up to examination standard. I won the High School gold medal.”

“Ah! And what salary do you want?”

“Forty pounds a year resident.”

“I will let you know if a post offers.” With that not-tooencouraging promise, Manya left the agency.

It was not long before Manya found herself a private governess. The family's name is secret, because they would not like to remember the trick fate played them. They opened a little door for Manya Slodovska, aged eighteen, and through it, as she tells us, she caught a little glimpse of hell and she wouldn't go through. Life meant Manya to be a great giver of gifts, not an unhappy, little despised slave. They were rich, the B—s; they kept the governess in her place, speaking to her as an iceberg might speak, could it creak out its thoughts. They threw their great wealth about in public, but they kept her six months without her salary and expected her not to read in the evenings in order to save lamp oil. Their speech to people's faces was honeysweet, but behind their backs so backbiting that Manya says they didn't leave their friends a dry thread to cover them.

“I have learnt from them,” she wrote, “that people in books are true and that one is wise not to mix with those whom wealth has spoilt.” Perhaps it was such knowledge, won when she was eighteen, that made Manya Sklodovska in the far future unspoilable by any offer of great wealth!

But Manya's plan was not working. Living at the B—s in town, she found that she spent a little money every day. It was very pleasant to be able to see her father sometimes and to be able to keep up with her friends of the winged university, but when you have made up your mind to a plan, you must carry it out whatever the cost. Manya found that she must leave home entirely, must get a post in the depth of the country, where she would be able to spend nothing. In that way, Bronia, who was already in Paris, would be able to have what she had planned for her.

The very post she was seeking turned up. It was far away in the country and it was a little better paid—fifty pounds a year this time. And, of course, fifty pounds went farther in those days than now. But it was with rather a sinking heart that Manya showed her new address to her father, though probably it did not look as outlandish and far away to him as it does to us.

Melle Marya Sklodovska
c/o Monsieur Z—
SZCZUKI,
near PRZASNYSZ

It was January when Manya set out for the country, a January in Poland where the snow lay thick for months together. As the train drew slowly out of the station, she realised that she could no longer see her father waving to her. For the first time in her life she was wholly alone and frightened. Those new people in a far away village, from which there was no escape might prove to be as unkind as her last employers. Or her father, who was getting old, might be taken ill. Ought she to have left him? The long fields of snow crept by in the gathering darkness, but they had long been blotted out by Manya's tears.

Three hours in the train and then a sledge to meet her. Warm fur rugs were tucked around her and out into the snowy majesty of the winter night she speeded through a silence broken only by the noise of sleigh bells.

Four hours in the sleigh. Iced and hungry, Manya wondered if the horses would ever stop. Then a yawning space of light, an open door and a whole family to meet her—the tall master of the house, the mistress, the shy children clinging to their mother's skirt, their eyes alive with curiosity. Madame welcomed her with warm, friendly words, gave her boiling tea, took her herself to her room, and left her alone to recover some warmth and to unpack her few shabby cases.

Manya was in the depth of the country. She looked round with satisfaction at her whitewashed, simply furnished room, with its warm stove in an alcove.

The next morning she drew her curtains, expecting to see snowy fields and forests bending under snow. Instead she was greeted with factory chimneys belching black smoke. She drew back and looked again—not one chimney but many, and not a tree to be seen, not a bush, not a hedge. She was in the sugar beet district. As far as the eye could see there was nothing but ploughed land waiting for beetroot. The whole country was devoted to beetroot. For beetroot the peasants ploughed and sowed and harvested. The factories were beetroot refineries. The village consisted of the cottages of the beetroot workers sheltering under factory walls. The house where she lived belonged to the director of beetroot. The river flowed coloured with beetroot.

The factories were a disappointment to Manya. So were the young men and maidens of the big houses round. They talked of nothing but what he said and she said, of the clothes they would wear, of who was giving the next ball and of how long the last had gone on. Manya was so horrified when Mr. and Mrs. Z— came home from a dance at one o'clock in the afternoon that she seemed to have forgotten how much she had once rejoiced at dancing till eight in the morning.”Give me the pen of a caricaturist,” she exclaimed, “for some of these people are really worthy of it. The girls are geese, who don't know how to open their mouths and so far my Bronka, the eldest daughter of the house, is a rare pearl for sense and interest in life.” Besides Bronka, there was another interesting person at Szczuki, her little brother Stas, aged three. He was the life of the long, one-storied house. His pattering feet went everywhere, down the long corridors, out into the glass verandahs that looked shabby under the leafless virginia creeper. His prattle amused Manya. Once his Nanny told him that God was everywhere. “Stas doesn't like that,” he replied; “I'm afraid he'll catch me! Will he bite me?”

Andzia, Manya's special pupil, was ten and a Fidgetty Phyllis, who ran away from her lessons whenever a visitor called. Manya was supposed to teach her for four hours a day, but what with her perpetual running away and being caught and brought back and having to go back to the beginning again, work did not get on, as one might say, fast. Andzia, too, was apt to lie in bed till Manya pulled her out by the arm, a proceeding that aggravated Manya particularly. On one of those mornings, it took her two hours to re-cover her temper. The best part of her day were the three hours in which she read with Bronka and those other hours of leisure when she wrote long letters home: “I am coming to Warsaw at Easter,” she said; “and at that thought everything in me rejoices so much that it is all I can do not to shout like a savage.”

Along the muddy village lanes, she met the village children, dirty little boys and girls, their bright eyes looking out at her from under their matted tow-like hair. “Aren't these Poles?” she said to herself. “I, who have vowed to enlighten the people, can I not do something for them?” Those ragamuffins either had never learnt anything or only knew the Russian alphabet. Manya thought that it would be fun to start a secret Polish school for them.

Bronka was delighted when she heard of the idea. “Not so fast,” said Manya. “If we are caught, it will be Siberia for us, you know.” They both knew what Siberia meant—exile in a terrible land of frozen plains. But Bronka was ready to take the risk. The two girls obtained the permission of Mr. Z— and the class began.

Fortunately, there was an outside staircase to Manya's room. Ten or eighteen small, grubby boys and girls began to tramp up it. Manya borrowed a deal table and some benches and spent some of her valuable savings on buying exercise books and pens for her pupils. Then the fun began. Clumsy fingers grasped the unaccustomed instruments and letters were scrawled on white paper. Slowly the mysterious fact that you can write the sounds you hear in black on white began to dawn on the urchins. The proud parents, who could not themselves read, came up the wooden stairs and stood overwhelmed and delighted at the back of the room watching the marvellous thing a son or a daughter was doing. The sons and daughters were not doing it easily. They twisted, they sniffed, they groaned as if making a letter was as hard as carrying beetroots up a mountain. Manya and Bronka moved among them, helping them in their painful trying. They were smelly, they were often inattentive, they weren't very clever, but for the most part, their bright eyes showed that they were excited about their lessons and longing to learn.

Chapter VI　Fortunate Misfortune

OTHER people's holidays come when the summer comes; but a governess stays at her post most of the year. She is even more useful when the boys come home, and little girls need getting out of bed winter and summer. Manya was bored. Nothing ever happened. Tomorrow was always twin sister to yesterday—work from eight to half-past eleven, work from two to half-past seven, walk and lunch from half-past eleven to two. In the evening, it was reading aloud to Andzia if she had been good; sewing and talking if she had not. At nine o'clock at last came freedom to read her own books and to study. But even then she was liable to be interrupted to do one of the hundred and one things required of a governess. For instance, Andzia's godfather needed someone to play chess with him and the governess would do quite well; or a fourth was wanted at whist and it did not matter if the governess liked whist or not. Manya grew hungrier for knowledge as the chance of it slipped farther and farther away. Her books were old fashioned and there was no one with whom she could discuss her difficulties. She hadn't an idea what she was going to do. She thought with envy of the thousands of girls flocking to colleges the world over, meeting the choice and master spirits of their age, being taught and working in laboratories. Vienna, Berlin, London, St. Petersburg, especially Paris, seemed so many Meccas to her! No, not Vienna, Berlin or St. Petersburg for they were the capitals of Poland's oppressors. But London and Paris! She was wild with longing to go to Paris, free generous Paris that oppressed no one, but welcomed exiles and invited everyone to come to her who wanted to think, who wanted to know. Despair was getting hold of Manya. It was so hard to work alone. Her money accumulated so intolerably slowly and Bronia would need help for so many years. Her father also would be wanting her to take care of him when he was really old. Would Manya ever get to the university?

She had grown deliciously pretty. Her broad, lofty brow had all the sternness taken from it by her ravishing, burnished hair; her grey eyes deepset under well-marked eyebrows seemed very large and gazed at one with gay and penetrating understanding; her wilful mouth with a suggestion of a smile forced one to look and think twice. Her skin was like a very peach. She was graceful, with exquisite wrists and ankles; and best of all her thoughtfulness gave her just that touch of mystery which makes people always want to know a girl.

Casimir, the eldest son of the house, was glad to find Manya there when he came home for the holidays. He came across her snipping off dead roses in the lovely garden. He had heard about her from his sister's letters, but he hadn't believed in her, and didn't he know all about the whole dull race of governesses?

“But… By the sword of Poland!” he exclaimed to himself, “This one is different!”

“You have given your ragged school a holiday this morning, Mademoiselle?”

“Oh, no!” said Manya, her face alive with interest as usual. “They don't come till five, when their other work, whatever it may be, is done.”

So, thought Manya, this was Bronka's adored brother, this tall, handsome, charming-mannered student, who spoke to her so friendlily and went on to take so lively an interest in her pupils whom he would insist on calling her “ragged school.”

That evening she did not go at nine to her heavy books. There was far more to be learnt by real talk with a university student about the subjects he was studying. To-morrow lost its resemblance to yesterday. Summer broke the order of work. Casimir insisted on boating picnics and Manya was especially good at the oar. She rode so that it was a delight to watch her and there was no lack of horses in the stable. There were some forty to choose from and the three chose well and rode whole days across the endless plain. There were driving picnics also and Casimir noticed that Manya's delicate wrists handled the reins of the second wagonette with skill. Casimir had sprained his left thumb so that the coachman had to drive his mother and the babies in the first wagonette.

Among the endless “geese” whom Casimir had hitherto met, none had the talk and mystery of this strange girl. When he returned to Warsaw for the autumn, he longed for Christmas.

“It ought always to be winter, Mademoiselle,” he said. And to Manya's unsuspecting “No! Why?” he laughed. “Aren't we told to worship beauty and is there anything lovelier than a girl with perfect ankles skating gracefully? And then there are the dances! You who dance so well, don't you love them and the long sledge drives under winter stars?”

Yes, Manya had returned to loving dancing, but still she preferred the summer—the summer holidays.

“The holidays? When I am here?”

Casimir had long guessed her answer. He said that he would go to his father at once. People did not generally marry governesses, but Manya was different, so entirely different. Everyone in his home loved her; his father chose her for his walking companion; his mother introduced her to all her friends; his sister adored her. They had often invited her father, her brother and her sister to stay in the home; they showered presents and flowers on her on her birthday; they were surely just waiting to welcome her with delight as a new daughter.

But about that, Casimir was mistaken. When he told his parents that he wanted to marry Manya, his father was furious and his mother nearly fainted. Should their eldest son, he on whom all their hopes were fixed, who could bring home as bride the richest, noblest girl of all the country, should he marry a penniless governess? Marry a woman who earned her living by selling her work in other people's houses!

“Casimir, you're mad! People don't marry governesses !”

“People don't marry governesses! What a good thing!” hummed the old Earth as it whizzed round the Sun bringing Summer after Winter and Marie Curie for all of us instead of Madame Manya Casimir Z—.

But Manya who could not foresee the future, was very unhappy. Everyone in the house grew cold to her; yet she could not throw up her post and go away, because she had to send Bronia twenty pounds a year. All she could do was to make up her mind that never, never again would she ever love any man. All the tomorrows took on again their resemblance to all the yesterdays. She gave her lessons, scolded Andzia, shook Julek awake, because every book sent him to sleep, taught her ragged school, read chemistry, played chess, danced, walked. Only one thing sometimes introduced a little excitement: the roads were so badly marked that they would disappear entirely under the snow and the sleigh and its occupants would find themselves buried in a snow-filled ditch. On such occasions, laughter would bring back some of the old gay friendliness.

At that time, her letters home grew longer, but she often hadn't a stamp to send them with or the money to buy one. “I haven't heard from Bronia,” she complained, “but perhaps she hasn't a stamp either.” Because of her own sadness she was more able to enter into the troubles of her father, her brother and Hela. To her father she wrote: “Don't worry about us; you have done everything a father could do for us; after all, haven't you given us quite nice characters? We'll be able to earn a living all right, you'll see.” And to her brother: “Joseph, borrow a hundred roubles and stay in Warsaw. Don't bury yourself in the country and don't be angry if I do give you advice. Remember our agreement to say anything that comes into our heads. Everybody thinks that to practise in the country would be to bury yourself in a hole and have no career. A doctor without a chemist's shop, a hospital or books will just become a dud, however good his resolutions maybe. If that happened to you, darling, I should be desperately unhappy, because now that I have lost all hope of ever being anything myself, all my ambition is fixed on you and Bronia. You mustn't bury the gifts that our family undoubtedly possess. They must come out in one of us. The more I despair about myself, the more I hope for you.” Manya was also feeling great sympathy for Hela, who had been given up by her lover, and great indignation against young men in general: “Truly,” she wrote, “one is learning to have a good opinion of people! If they don't want to marry poor girls, they can go to the devil. No one asks them to do it, but why fall in love with them and then upset them?”

It was a bad moment in Manya's life. She said she was afraid she was catching stupidity from her pupils, which is a fear that comes to many teachers. Her great dreams seemed foolish. “The only dream I have now,” she wrote, “is to have a corner of my own where I can live with my father. to get a little independence and a home, I would give half my life. If by any possibility I can leave Z—s, which does not seem very likely, I will get a post in a boarding school in Warsaw and earn a little extra by private lessons. That's all I hope for. Life isn't worth bothering so much about.” It was, indeed, a bad moment. But a novel called On the Banks of the Niemen fortunately reminded her that ideas like that were not the real Manya. “Where have my dreams gone?”she wrote to Bronia. “I wanted to work for the people, and I have scarcely been able to teach a dzen village boys and girls to read. As to awakening in them a thought of what they are and of what they might do in the world! You couldn't dream of such a thing. Life is hard. I am becoming so mean, so common. Then suddenly a book like this novel gives me a shock and I am miserable about it all.” At the same time she wrote to her cousin: “I am in a black humour, for our daily company are frightful west winds, seasoned with rain, floods and mud. There's not a thought of frost and my skates hang sadly in the wardrobe. Perhaps you don't know that in our small hole frost and its advantages are as important as a debate between Conservatives and Liberals in Galicia! Don't think that your tales bore me. On the contrary it is a true delight to hear that there are places on the earth's surface where people move and even think! I feel things violently with a physical violence! Then I shake myself and get back to myself out of a nightmare and tell myself ‘Don't be crushed either by people or by events.’ But the need of new impressions, of change, of movement seizes me at moments with such force that I want to do something utterly, utterly foolish to put an end to this eternal sameness. Happily I have so much work that this folly doesn't get hold of me often.”

Chapter VII　Change

MANYA had desired change and she was to get change. She was to travel. She heard of another pupil who lived in Warsaw, but who was on holiday in far away Belgium and Manya was to join her there. Manya became suddenly doubtful whether she liked so much change as that. She would have to travel alone and have five changes of train. She would surely get lost; or thieves might come into her compartment at night while she slept. But none of these things happened. She found herself safely met by her new employers and introduced to an entirely new world—a world of great wealth which she was expected to share and to enjoy. Her pupil's mother was beautiful and charming. For the first time in her life Manya was close to lovely dresses made by Worth's; she was expected to finger and admire soft furs and brilliant jewels; she saw people who were becoming her friends looking at her from the walls where their portraits hung painted by the greatest painters. She moved among all the loveliest things that wealth can give and looked on at all the charm of parties and balls, gaiety and music. Moreover these rich people were human and kind. Mrs. F— liked her, took her everywhere, called her to her friends “The exquisite Miss Sklodovska.”

We have not heard what Manya thought of it all, because something far more exciting was about to happen to her. On the hall table lay a letter with the Paris post mark addressed to Miss Sklodovska in Bronia's handwriting—a letter written on squared exercise book paper, written hurriedly between two lectures. What news! Bronia was going to be married! Bronia was inviting Manya to share her home in Paris as soon as she had it! Paris! ... A

University… All her hopes fulfilled?

It was not as simple as that. Manya had known for some time that Bronia was engaged to the cleverest, handsomest, most delightful Polish student in Paris. His name, like that of Manya'sown lover, was Casimir, Casimir Dluski. He had been obliged to flee from Poland because he was suspected of having been connected with a plot. In Paris he was watched by request of the Czar's police and had all kinds of odd information entered against him in the books of the Paris Gendarmerie. But, in spite of that, he was a gay young doctor and he was going to marry Bronia. So Bronia would never be able to return to Warsaw to take care of her father. That would be Manya's part, for Hela was not muda use for taking care of anybody.

How lovely, how wonderful, how ideal shone the future according to Bronia! But Manya wrote back: “I have been a fool, I am a fool, I shall always be a fool my whole life through, or rather to translate into more fashionable language: I never had any luck! I haven't any luck! I never shall have any luck!” Thereupon the unlucky may take heart as they consider what was to happen to Manya. She went on: “I have dreamed of Paris as one dreams of salvation, but hope of getting there fled a long time ago and now that the possibility of getting there has come to me, I don't know what to do. I can't talk to father about it, because I think his heart is set on our plan of living together next year and I would like to give him a little happiness in his old age. On the other hand, my heart breaks when I think of how my gifts are being wasted and yet gifts ought to be used.” It was that feeling that gifts ought to be used that made her urge Bronia in the same letter to put pride in her pocket and beg, with all her most ingratiating skill, a rich friend to help Joseph to use his gifts. Manya argued that it would not be only Joseph who would be helped, but the world which would profit by his skill. All through her life Manya was to keep the opinion that one of the noblest works is to help the greatly gifted to use their gifts for the world. She ended her letter: “My heart is so black, so sad that I feel how wrong I am to talk to you of all this and poison your happiness.”

So Manya went home to live for at least a year with her father in a little home of their own. To some people it would have seemed dull, but Manya had a brain and found more sensible talk in her father's house than in any other. She also returned to the strange “winged” secret society and talked and studied.

But Chance had a trick up her sleeve. No one would have suspected, if he walked in May down the quiet tree-planted avenue of Cracow and smelt the purple lilacs in the grass-grown court of No. 66, that there was anything surprising or world-shaking there. In the court, beside the lilacs, there was a little one-storied building with tiny windows. Museum of Industry and Agricul-ture was written in large letters over its doors. Were old ploughshares or prehistoric spades kept there? Not a bit of it! Russia allowed museums to exist. They are always such properly dead places. But any intelligent person can teach in a museum. Manya's cousin was the Director of this one and, secretly, he taught science in it. He had a laboratory where the students could actually touch apparatus.

For the first time in her life Manya Sklodovska entered a laboratory! And that was to make a remarkable difference to the great world. She couldn't go there much, only in the evenings and on Sunday. There was no one to teach her when she got there. She worked all alone trying to reproduce experiments described in text books. Her results were sometimes unexpected, but sometimes a tiny success filled her with hope and sometimes a striking failure filled her with despair. But always, she found discovery, or even trying to discover, a wild delight.

When late at night she got home and rolled into bed, something seized her, something grabbed her mind, something spoke to her in the dark. She couldn't sleep. It was as if another someone in herself was talking to her, hammering at her thoughts, telling her what she must get up and do. Her work had found her and was insisting that she must do it. Those test tubes and retorts of the museum were friends and allies of her father's old physical apparatus which she had once loved. Manya Sklodovska had found herself—that self whose clever hands must for ever handle tubes and flames, elements and metals, while her clever brain drew conclusions from what her hands did and looked into the future.

But what should she do? Hands and brain said go! Love said stay with her father and brother and sister, with her lover Casimir Z—, who was still trying to win his parents' consent to his marriage. Manya met him in the holidays. They walked the mountains together, he told her in long talks of his difficulties and asked her advice.

“If you can't find a way out yourself,” exclaimed Manya, at the end of her patience, “don't ask me.” She at least knew her own mind at last. She wrote hurriedly to Bronia: “Give me a definite answer. I won't be any trouble to you. You can put me to sleep anywhere. But, I implore you, answer frankly.

Bronia answered frankly; she would have telegraphed if telegrams had not been too dear. Manya would have caught the next train if she had not had so many arrangements to make. She put all her savings on the table and counted them with her father. He added what he could to them. There, before their eyes, lay the round roubles that made Paris possible, only just possible.

Manya could not afford to travel third all the way. In Poland and France third was the cheapest, but Germany had a fourth. It did not matter that the fourth was like a succession of luggage vans. They had no separate compartments and they were bare, except for a bench round the four sides, and thoughtful people took their own stools and sat in the middle. Manya would do that. She would have to take a lot of luggage to save buying in France, but the bulkiest she could send in advance by luggage train—her own mattress, her blankets, her sheets, her table napkins. The only thing she had to buy was a cheap, strong, wooden trunk which she marked proudly M.S. Into it she put her strong, durable clothes, her shoes, her two hats. Then she did up the packages she would take with her in the truck for the journey: food and drink for three days in the train, the stool, her books, a bag of caramels and a rug.

Manya was off to Paris. She was twenty-four and her eyes literally shone with eagerness and joy. The long-hoped-for adventure had begun.

Chapter VIII　“I Take the Sun and Throw It...”

“I TAKE the Sun and throw it…” Manya laughed with joy at the words. Where was she? In the heart of Paris where joyous, free things happened, where in lightness of heart her great teacher, Paul Appell, could teach what he pleased, how he pleased; and, if he taught truth, crowds would flock to his teaching.

Manya had arrived early for the lecture and chosen a front seat in the great amphitheatre of the Sorbonne. She put her notebooks and her penholder neatly on the desk in front of her. All around her was the noise of the crowd getting into their places, but Manya did not hear them; she was absorbed in thought. Suddenly there was silence, for the master had come in and, as all his students were ardent mathematicians, they expected a treat.

Appell, with his square head, in his dark severe gown, explained so clearly that the very stars seemed to move obediently into their places as he spoke and the earth seemed at his mercy. He adventured boldly into the furthest regions of space, he juggled with figures and with stars. He said perfectly naturally and fitting the action to the word: “I take the Sun and throw it…”

Manya was happy. How could anyone find science dull? She thought how exquisite were the unchanging laws of the universe and how still more wonderful it was that the human mind could understand them. Was not Science stranger than a fairy tale, more delicious that a book of adventure? It was worth years of suffering she felt just to hear that phrase uttered by a savant: “I take the Sun and throw it…”

But how much else Manya had found in Paris! When she had first jumped from the train in the smoky, noisy North Station, she had thrown back her shoulders and breathed deep, not noticing the smoke. For the first time she was breathing the air of a free land. Outside the station everything seemed to her a miracle. The children in the gutter teased one another in the tongue they wanted to speak; what a miracle for the Polish girl who had had to speak Russian! The book shops sold the books they wanted to sell, the books of all the world; what a miracle!

But most miraculous of all, that road where she jumped on her first omnibus and scrambled to the cheap seats on top, was taking her, Manya Sklodovska, to a university that opened its doors to women! And what a university! The Sorbonne was the most famous university in the world. Even Luther, the German, had confessed that Paris had the most famous school in the whole world. The university was being rebuilt; workmen were everywhere; dust and noise were everywhere; classes moved from room to room as the workmen took possession. But that mattered nothing to Manya. At last she could learn what she wanted.

From that time on, she began to write her Christian name in French—Marie. With her surname she could do nothing. Her young associates found it too difficult to pronounce and a little on account of it left her alone. In the long corridors they turned to glance back at the simply, poorly-dressed stranger with the airy, fairy hair and intense eyes. “Who is she?” asked one. “A foreigner with an impossible name,” answered another. “They say she is always among the first in Physics, but she doesn't talk.”

Marie had to work very hard. She had had no idea how ignorant she would find herself in comparison with her companions. Her French turned out not to be as useful as she had expected. She missed whole phrases in a lecture. She found great chasms in her mathematics and physics. She set to work to correct all her defects.

It was well for her that in those first days she lived with Bronia and Casimir. Bronia was a genius for making things comfortable. She had taken a flat outside Paris where flats were cheaper and had furnished it with borrowed money. She was not the sort of person who lived just anyhow for fear of the risk of not being able to pay back. She had to have pretty things in her home, nicely draped curtains, graceful furniture, a piano and a few bright flowers in a vase. In her little kitchen she cooked exquisitely well-flavoured dishes and cakes, or made tea with tea sent especially from Poland, because she felt that there were some things Paris could not produce.

The quarter where she lived was, as in medieval times, almost reserved for butchers, and Doctor Dluski's patients were mostly sick butchers. They interviewed him in the little study which was set apart for his use during certain hours of the day. At other times it was Bronia's consulting room where she saw the butcher's wives about their babies. In the evenings work was strictly set aside and the two doctors tried to entice their newly arrived sister to all the fun of the fair. If there was a little money to spend they took her to a cheap seat at the theatre; if there wasn't, they gathered round their own piano or gave a tea party to their exiled Polish friends, when talk and laughter and teasing went on around the oil lamp and the tea-table set with Bronia's homemade cakes. Manya often withdrew early from those parties to work alone in her room, because she felt she had no time to play.

“Come out, Miss Bookworm!” called Casimir one evening; “it is Poland that calls; you have got to come this time. Hat and coat, quick! I've got complimentary tickets for a concert.”

“But . . .”

“But me no buts! It's that young Pole we were talking of and very few people have taken seats. We must go to fill the hall. I've got some volunteers and we are going to clap our hands off to give him the feeling of success. If you only knew how beautifully he plays!”

Marie could not resist her gay brother-in-law with his dark, sparkling eyes. Downstairs she hastened, dressing as she went, and ran to catch the old horse bus. She sat in the half-empty hall and watched the tall, thin man with the wonderful face and shock of copper-red hair walk up the platform and open the piano. She listened… Liszt, Schumann, Chopin lived again under his marvellous fingers. Marie was passionately moved. The pianist in his threadbare coat, playing to empty benches, did not seem to her an obscure beginner, but a king, almost a god.

The Dluskis asked him to their home. He went, taking with him his beautiful future wife whom Manya's mother had known. Mrs. Sklodovska used to say of the girl that she could never take her out because she was too beautiful. Sometimes the fiery-haired young man would go to the Dluski's piano, and at his touch, the common thing became sublime with heavenly music; for he who played was Paderewski, someday to be world famous, first as a pianist and then as President of a free Poland.

But those days were still far away. In 1891 Marie lived in Paris among a group of Polish exiles who seemed to make a little Polish island in the French city. They were young; they were gay; they were poor. On the fête days of the year, they met for parties in which everything was as Polish as they could make it. They ate Polish cakes, they acted Polish plays, they printed their programmes in Polish and decorated them with Polish scenes: a cottage in an expanse of snow, a dreamy boy bending over books, a Father Christmas throwing scientific textbooks down a chimney, an empty purse that rats had gnawed. When they acted plays, Marie was too busy to learn a part; but in a tableau, she once represented “Poland breatking her chains” Dressed in a long tunic such as the ancients wore, the colours of the Polish flag draped round her and her fair hair framing her Slav face, she was greeted by all the young people as a very vision of Poland.

Yet to show love for Poland, even in free Paris, was a dangerous thing. Mr. Sklodovski begged Manya not to be seen again in a Polish festivity which could get into the newspapers. “You know,” he wrote, “that there are people in Paris noting the names of those who take any part in Polish affairs and this might be a trouble to you and prevent you getting a post later on in Poland. It is wiser to keep out of the limelight.”

Marie scarcely needed that hint from her father. She wanted to give all her time to work, to live alone, free from the interruption of the piano, of her brother-in-law's evening chatter, of fiends dropping in. And she wanted to live nearer to the university to save her bus fares and the time the bus took.

Sadly, accompanied by both the Dluskis, she left the comfort and friendliness of her sister's home and set out to find her own work place, her own utter solitude.

She was going to live the life of her dreams, a life entirely given up to study. She would have to do it on one pound a week or rather less. Out of that she would have to pay for her room, her food, her clothes, her paper, her books and her university fees. Could it be done? That was her mathematical problem and, fortunately, she was good at mathematics, but that particular problem would take some doing. “Ah!” she thought, “I needn't eat much!” She had never had time to learn to cook. Her friends said that she didn't even know what went into soup. She didn't know and she hadn't time. She would never dream of taking time from physics to prepare a dinner. So she lived on bread and butter, cherries and tea, with an occasional egg or a piece of chocolate.

Her room was cheap—4s. 6d. a week. It was just an attic under the roof, lit by a sloping window, unheated, with no gas and no water. Her only furniture was a folding iron bedstead with her Polish mattress, a stove, a deal table, a kitchen chair, a washing basin, an oil lamp with a penny shade, a water bucket which she had to fill at the common tap on the landing, a spirit lamp to cook her food, two plates, one knife, a fork, a spoon, a cup, a saucepan, a kettle and three glasses for tea. When visitors came, her trunk was seat enough for two.

Two sacks a year of charcoal, which she bought on the street and carried up, bucket by bucket, all the six storey's, gave her all the warmth she allowed herself. Light she could almost do without. As soon as it began to get dark, she went to the St. Geneviève library and read there, her head in her hands, her elbows on the long table, till closing time at ten at night. After that she only needed oil in her lamp to last her till two in the morning, when she went to bed.

That was food, house, warmth and light settled. As to clothes, Marie could sew and brush and she meant to keep herself neat by brushing and mending, not by buying. She could do her own washing in her basin at the cost of a little soap.

That was a deliciously cheap life she planned in which nothing should interrupt her learning. But girls' bodies have a way of having something to say on their own account. Marie was surprised that often, when she left her books, she turned giddy. She even fainted sometimes on her way to bed before she had time to lie down. When she returned to consciousness, she told herself that she must be ill; but even of that she took no notice, merely thinking she would soon be better.

When her doctor brother-in-law told her she looked ill, she replied that she had been working and turned the conversation with a request for the baby. She had begun to make a great pet of Bronia's new baby and liked to turn attention from herself.

But luckily, one day, Marie fainted in public and the girl who saw it fetched Casimir. By the time he arrived, Marie was well again, but Casimir insisted on examining her. Then without a word he examined the room. Where, he asked, was the food cupboard? Manya hadn't got such a thing. Nowhere was there anything that showed any sign of eating and only a packet of tea to suggest that Marie drank anything.

“What have you eaten to-day?” asked the doctor.

“To-day?... I don't know... I lunched...”

“What did you eat?”

“'Cherries…Oh, all sorts of things…”

In the end Marie had to confess that since yesterday she had eaten a bunch of radishes and half a pound of cherries. She had worked till three in the morning and she had slept only four hours.

The doctor was furious, furious with the little fool, looking at him with innocent, cheerful grey eyes and more furious with himself for not having seen that his clever sister-in-law was a great silly in some things.

Sternly he ordered her to collect what she would want for a week and to come with him. He was so angry he wouldn't talk. At home, Bronia was sent out to buy beefsteak and Marie was ordered to eat it properly underdone in its red gravy and with its crisp potatoes. In less than a week she was again the healthy girl who had so lately come from Warsaw.

Because she was worried about her examination, she was allowed to go back to her attic on condition that she would feed herself sensibly. But alas, the very next day she was living on the air that blows.

Work!…Work! ... Marie was feeling her own brain growing. Her hands were getting cleverer. Soon Professor Lippman trusted her with a piece of original research and she had won her opportunity to show her skill and the originality of her mind. Any day of six she could be seen, in her coarse science overall, standing before an oak table in the lofty physical laboratory of the Sorbonne watching some delicate piece of apparatus or gazing at the steady boiling of some fascinating substance. Other similar workers were round her, men for the most part, utterly silent, doing a thing that was more absorbing than talk.

But when the experiments had come out, the boys looked at the girl, said a word at the door, pressed round her to make friends. She was growing a little less standoffish. Once the boys' eagerness to walk with her became so eager that her friend Mademoiselle Dydyuska had to shoo them away with her parasol. Marie had no time for friendship. With an iron will, a mad love for perfection and an incredible stubbornness she stuck to her work.

She won her licence in Physics in 1893 and in Mathematics in 1894, being top of the list in Physics and second in Mathematics. She was also working for perfection in French, refusing to allow any Polish accent to remain on her tongue; she intended to speak French like the French with only a little rolling of the “r,” which, though she did not intend it, only added to her charm.

She was not too busy to take note of flowers and springtime in Paris. She never forgot that she was a Polish peasant belonging to the fields. She spent Sunday in the country and talked of the lilacs and fruit trees in bloom and the air which was scented with flowers.

When the scorching days of July came, there was another examination. Marie was nervous. With thirty others shut into an airless room she gazed at the paper whose words danced and glimmered before her eyes. She pulled herself together and wrote. She waited, as so many others have done, with a sinking heart for the day of the result. When it came, she crept to listen to the announcement into a corner of the great amphi-theatre where she felt very insignificant in the crowd of students and their parents, for she was sure she had done badly.

The noise of talk and of a moving crowd suddenly became silence. The examiner had entered with his list. Marie had no time to listen. The examiner had already spoken the first name:

Marie Sklodovska.

So the holidays had come and Marie had the joy of taking home to Poland her wonderful result. She had other things to take home— presents! For this time she could spend all the money she had left, yes, everything, every penny. She could buy presents for her father, for Joseph, for Hela, and food for her 2,000 mile journey. It was the unbreakable custom with every Pole to arrive home penniless and laden with presents.

In the long summer, all over Poland, her relations feasted and fêted her. But the question that was eating at her heart was: what should she do about the autumn? Where and how could she raise a pound a week for another year at the university? Once more Mademoiselle Dydyuska turned up with her parasol. Whom she used it against this time, nobody knew, but she persuaded the authorities in Warsaw to grant a scholarship to the girl, who, she told them, would bring glory to their city. The great news came to Marie that she would have the Alexandrowitch bursary of £60. It meant another year's learning. Carefully she saved to make the bursary go as far as possible; carefully, after she was able to earn money for herself, she saved to return the bursary money, so that some other poor student might know the joy she had known. When, years after, the bursary secretary received the returned money he was greatly astonished, for no other student had ever thought of making such a return.

So back to work she went, to that work which was no drudgery, but the great love of her whole passionate being. That was the part of Marie's life she loved best, her hard student days, when, working in poverty and alone, with all the power of her youth, she was most herself. She has been called “the eternal student”—one of those people we meet in all the ancient stories of all the old universities: young, poor, greedy for knowledge, believing themselves gifted for some great purpose and driven to attain that purpose at any cost under high heaven.

Marie, working under her old oil lamp, knew herself one with the great scientists, the helpers of men. She had little to live on, but she lived greatly, gaily, thoughtlessly, rejoicingly. Truth was her daily fun, spoilt occasionally by a tragedy such as the final falling to pieces of a pair of shoes. to get a new pair would upset her spending for weeks; she would have to be hungrier than ever and colder. One night she was so cold that she took all her clothes out of her trunk and piled them on her bed. But she was still cold and there was nothing else movable to heap on her except the chair. So she dragged that on top and had to keep very still till morning lest her odd, warming scaffolding should fall off.

The water in her water jug might be ice in the mornings, but she loved those days so much that she wrote a verse about them:

Harsh and hard she lived to learn.
　Round her swirled the young who seek
Pleasures easy, pleasures stern.
　She alone, long week by week,
Happy, gay, made great her heart.
　When fleeting time took her away
From lands of knowledge and of art
　To earn her bread on life's gray way,
Oft times her spirit sighed to know
　Again the attic corner strait,
Still scene of silent labour slow,
　So filled with memory of fate.

Chapter IX　Marie's Love Story

MARIE was in a fix. It was not her first, and was not going to be her last. She had been given a most interesting piece of scientific work to do and she had nowhere to do it. The Society for the Encouragement of National Industry had asked her to make a thesis on the magnetic properties of different kinds of steel. It was just the work she loved. She had been getting on with it most successfully in Professor Lippmann's laboratory, but there simply wasn't room for all the heavy apparatus she needed. She had to analyse minerals and group examples of metals, and she hadn't any idea where she could get the loan of floor space. She told her trouble to a scientific Polish friend, M. Kowalski, who had come to Paris with his wife, partly on his honeymoon, partly to give scientific lectures.

Kowalski looked at her seriously. He saw that the matter was important, but what could he, a stranger in Paris, do about suggesting a room.

“I have an idea!” he exclaimed after a few moment's hesitation. “I do know a man of some importance who works in Lhomond Street at the School of Physics and Chemistry. He might have a room to lend, or at any rate he could give you some advice about it. Come and have tea to-morrow evening after dinner. I'll ask the young man to come along, too. He is well known; you must have heard his name, Pierre Curie.”

As Marie entered the sombre boarding-house room where the Kowalskis lodged she noticed at all young man standing in the embrasure of the balcony window. He looked very young, which surprised her because she was expecting to meet a man who had already made his mark. There was something original and very striking about the stranger, an ease, a grace, which seemed all the more marked under his loosely-fitting clothes. There was a clear transparency in the look with which he welcomed the girl to whom he was being introduced, which made him seem very honest, very simple, very young. She liked his grave, yet almost childlike, smile. They began at once to talk of science, for was not that why they had been brought together?

He was an unusual kind of man, the son of a doctor, who had realised, while Pierre was very young, that he was not the kind of boy who fits well into a mould that suits other people; Pierre wouldn't do for a public school, so he had a private tutor to himself. He had grown up a home-keeping boy, loving his father and mother's company and that of his only brother. He had taken to loving science, and also to delving into his own mind and writing down his opinions in his diary. “Women,” he wrote, when he was very young, “love life just for the mere sake of being alive far more than we men: women of genius are very rare. So when we give all our thoughts to some great work which separates us from the ordinary life around us, we have literally to fight against woman. The mother wants the love of her son even though, through loving her, he should make of himself an imbecile. A woman who loves would be ready to sacrifice the greatest genius in the world for the sake of the love of an hour.”

That was a bitter way to think of girlhood or of womanhood, but Pierre had his excuse. In addition to the fact that his observation was sometimes very true, he had had great grief connected with his first love, and he had made up his mind never to speak of it and never to marry. On that fateful evening when he talked science with Marie in the alcove, he was thirty-five. Inside France he was almost unknown, almost neglected, with that strange heart-breaking neglect with which France has the custom of greeting her greatest men, without all the same making them less great.

Outside France he was famous. A discovery that he and his brother had made which had helped to measure very minute quantities of electricity was used with gratitude by the greatest scientists of other countries. His own discovery of the principle of symmetry in crystals was to become a foundation of modern science. He had already given his name to a new balance and a new physical law. He was the honoured master of men like Lord Kelvin; but for all that he was getting only the wage of a superior workman, three pounds a week.

Still, his poverty was somewhat his own fault. He had been offered a post where money was the chief reward, but he had replied, “No, thank you, nothing is more unhealthy for the spirit than pre- occupations of that kind.” He had been suggested for government honours, and had begged to be excused and he had decided never to accept any decoration of any kind.

So this science-lover of stern and settled character stood before Marie and talked, his long, sensitive hand resting on the table, his still, clear eyes watching her with that deep, calm, detached inspection of theirs. Perhaps suddenly he remembered that old opinion of his—“Women of genius are rare.”

At first, conversation had been, as it would be when four people meet, quite general. Then Pierre and Marie had got on to science. Had she not come purely for scientific business? With a touch of deference, she questioned the great man who looked so young, and listened to his suggestions. Then he talked of himself, a thing he so rarely did, of his own aims and of his crystallography, which was puzzling and interesting him and whose laws he was seeking. A sudden thought darted through his mind: how strange it is to find one's self talking to a woman about the work one loves, employing technical terms and complicated formulas, and finding that woman, though charming and young, grow interested and keen, finding her understand, and finding her discuss details with faultless perception… What a delicious experience! He looked again at Marie, at her lovely hair, at her hands, made rough by chemical acids and housework, at her grace, at her absolute freedom from coquetry—so attractive and disconcerting a thing. That was the girl who had worked for years in Poland with the hope of reaching Paris, and was now there, working alone, penniless, in an attic.

“'Are you going to live in Paris always?” he asked.

“No, of course not,” replied Marie. “If I manage my examination this summer I shall return to Warsaw. I should like to come back in the autumn, but I don't know if I shall be able to afford it. In the end I shall teach in a Polish school and try to be useful. No Pole may desert her country.”

The conversation slipped off to the misery of Poland, to her oppressive masters. Pierre, whose one thought had been scientific discovery, listened surprised and distressed to a tale of human beings struggling to be free. Perhaps he thought of how great losses truth and knowledge may suffer when the scientists are obliged to give their thoughts away from science. Perhaps he began to dream that he must fight Poland and keep this rare genius for scientific Paris. At any rate, he was not going to lose touch with her. He took to meeting her at the Physics Society, where she went to hear about new discoveries. He sent her a copy of the limited edition of his own new book. He saw her from time to time at work in her linen overall among her apparatus in Lippmann's laboratory.

Then Pierre asked for Marie's address and called at 11 Rue des Feuillantines. Perhaps he remembered it as the street in which Pasteur had, also, once lived. As, after six flights of stairs, he entered the attic, the doctor's son was moved by the sight of the extreme poverty of the room. Yet how well it suited Marie! Never had she seemed so lovely as when she came to meet him in her threadbare frock across that almost empty room; so thin, so ascetic, so on fire, so stubborn, so self-willed she looked, so beautifully framed in emptiness.

All Pierre's bitterness went, like fog when the sun breaks through. They talked and he went back to work with quite another spirit; what had seemed to him little worth doing became more important and more clear. His new theory worked itself out into a most brilliant doctor's thesis and he made the discovery that one woman, at any rate, so far from killing genius in a man, had awakened it. He gave himself better to his high thoughts because he had given his heart to Marie.

But what of her heart? Pierre tried to find out. He took her into the lovely French country they both loved; together they gathered marguerites and brought them home to lend an air of whiteness and grace to the attic. He took her home to Sceaux, outside Paris, to meet his mother and his delightful old father. Marie found herself as if in a second home, a home oddly like hers in Warsaw, among calm, affectionate people who loved one another, loved books, loved nature and, above all, loved science. They talked of beautiful Poland, of Marie's long walks through its beautiful wide-spreading meadows, of her joy at the thought of the coming holidays there and among the Swiss mountains.

“But you are coming back in October?” exclaimed Pierre, a sudden chill clutching his heart! “It would be a sin on your part to abandon science.”

Marie was not deceived. She knew already that he meant it would be a sin to abandon him.

But Poland held her heart. Yet she said, looking shyly up at him, “I think you are right. I should very much like to come back.”

It was not long before Pierre felt brave enough to put his thought into words and to ask her to be his wife. But that she could never be, she said. She could never marry a Frenchman and turn her back on Poland. So many discussions followed that word, for Pierre knew that science was on his side and he could not believe that it was anyone's duty to give up science, which belonged to the whole world, for the sake of working for a mere country.

So Marie went home again for her holidays promising Pierre nothing but that he should always be her friend. He wrote her long persuading letters. He planned to meet her in Switzerland for a few days, but she was meeting her father there and he decided that his presence might spoil the girl's perfect holiday. He told her by post all his thoughts and his hesitations, never forgetting to slip in his opinion that the only dream that a man should live for was the scientific dream. “In politics,” said he, “you never know what you may be doing; you may be ruining your country while trying to help her. If you dream of helping humanity, you don't know how to do it. But science is solid. Any discovery, however small, that you make in that, remains made. Truth, once found, can't disappear and can never be wrong.

Believe me,

Your devoted,

Pierre Curie.”

Marie liked to write to him about her freedom.

“Talk!” he answered. “We're all slaves, slaves of our affections, slaves of prejudice, slaves when we have to earn a living, wheels in a machine, We have to yield something to the things around us! If we yield too much, we are poor mean things; if we don't yield enough, we are crushed.”

In October Marie returned to Paris, and it wasn't only she who was stubborn. What about that yielding to the things around one, about which Pierre spoke? He began to wonder if it should be he who should yield. The thought had no sooner come than he acted on it! He offered to give up Paris and to go to Poland. For a time he would give up science and teach French for a living; then somehow he would get back into scientific work.

Marie confided her hesitations to Bronia and asked her what she thought about that wonderful offer of Pierre's to give up his country. For herself, she felt that no one had the right to ask such a sacrifice of another. She was overwhelmed at the thought that Pierre had offered it to her. Pierre, too, went to the Dluskis. They were entirely on his side.

Bronia began to go with Marie to visit his parents, and heard from his mother so tender an account of the wonderful son Pierre was, that she knew that her sister's happiness would be safe in his hands.

Ten months more Marie hesitated, and then the two who had both promised themselves that they would never marry abandoned their high-flown ideas, and said yes to happiness.

Marie's brother wrote her a charming letter from Poland full of understanding. It was as if Poland itself spoke to tell the Polish girl that she could do more good to Poland by marrying a French scientist who happened to be Pierre Curie than she could by returning to be a schoolmistress in Warsaw. And, indeed, all that was about to happen showed that Marie had chosen the right.

So Marie could plan her wedding in all happiness; and what an odd wedding it was to be!

On the 26th of July, 1895, the sun rose in a clear sky, and Marie Sklodovska with it. Her beautiful face was lit with joy as she did her lovely hair and put on her new navy-blue dress with the striped blue blouse that Casimir Dluski's mother had given her. She hadn't wanted a real wedding dress; she was glad to have a new one because she only possessed one she wore every day, but she much preferred something useful that she could wear afterwards in the laboratory.

When she was dressed, Pierre fetched her and they left by the bus to catch the train to Sceaux, where the wedding was to be. Down the Boulevard St. Michel the heavy horses clop-clopped, passing the Sorbonne that the two looked at with loving eyes, for had it not brought them together?

At Sceaux there were to be no guests except Bronia and Casimir, Mr. Sklodovski and Hela, who had come all the way from Warsaw. They couldn't afford a gold ring or a wedding breakfast. For wedding presents, the most important were two shining bicycles, given them by a cousin, on which they were going to spend their honeymoon.

Said the one father to the other father, as they met the bride and bridegroom in the garden after the wedding, “You will have in Marie a daughter you can love, for since the day of her birth she has never given me a moment's pain.”

Chapter X　Madame Curie

PIERRE and Marie set out for an unusual honeymoon. They had no tickets to get and no rooms to reserve, because they were going off on bicycles just wherever their fancy led. They strapped a few clothes to the bicycles and, as the summer had been wet, two long rubber mackintoshes. Their tyres glided silently over the wet roads; bright, fitful sunshine flecked the tall trunks of the trees that make an avenue of all Frenck roads; overhead, the heavy summer leaves dappled the road with shade like a snakeskin and shook raindrops on the travellers from the last shower.

Upon what an adventure they were setting out, the two alone together! They couldn't see the end of it or imagine how exciting it was going to be, any more than they could see the end of the long avenue or know where they would sleep the night.

Pierre had always loved to wander in lonely woods. He liked them cool and wet, and, when he came out on to the rocky hillsides, he liked the smell of rosemary and marjoram and eglantine that made a wild jungle there. It was all one to him whether he walked by day or by night, by dawn or gloaming; whether he ate at eleven or three, seven or ten. Now all the things he cared for were lovelier still, because Marie was with him and she didn't bother him about time or punctuality.

They were not going to be extravagant; there should be no hotels for them. When they came to a village at evening, they found a simple inn, a place with one large tap-room, with a few tables and many chairs. The “Patron” spread a clean white cloth for them and brought them thick, hot soup. After dinner, they went up the creaking wooden stairs, along a rambling passage to a room where the light of one candle was not likely to show up the faded paper. French village inns are often like that; the supper is good, the bed is clean and delicious, and the charge small.

Next day after breakfast on coffee and rolls, they pedalled on along another highway under the trees with the forest on either hand. A long green ride that led into mysterious depths of trees tempted them; they dismounted and left their bicycles at a roadside cottage; saw that they had their compass safe, because it is easy to be lost in those great French forests; put apples in their pockets and found their feet sinking through soft moss into squelching mud. Lovely! For them, there was no such thing as direction, no such thing as time, and nobody to wonder when they would be back.

Pierre went in front, striding along absent-mindedly. Marie followed with shorter steps, but keeping up all the same. She was hatless, though at that time other women never walked without a hat. It wasn't the only fashion she was to set. Her skirt, which was meant to trail on the ground and plaster her shoes with caked mud, was gathered quite shockingly high into an elastic band, so that her ankles showed! Her shoes were thick and sensible and her leather belt had pockets for a knife, money and a watch. She could hear well enough what Pierre said, covering the ground there in front as if he had a train to catch. He was evidently talking to her, though, as he never turned his head, it might have been the tree she was addressing on the quaint customs of crystals. There is no conversation more learned or more difficult to follow than a conversation on crystals, or to put it more scientifically, on crystallography. Marie listened with joy, and her answers and remarks and suggestions were as clever as Pierre's, so that it seemed as if the two voices were the expression of one thought.

Marie was beginning to grow tired, when suddenly they came to an opening in the forest; and in the opening was a reedy pool. Marie threw herself down on the bank to bask in the sun, and Pierre went hunting like a small boy for what the pool might contain: dragonflies, tritons, salamanders. Far out in the water there were waterlilies; nearer at hand, yellow irises in bloom. He wanted them to decorate Marie, but there was no boat. A little way away a tree had fallen over the water—the very thing, a little slippery, perhaps, but what did a wetting matter to a lover? Luck was with him, however, and he was soon back arranging a crown of rather damp lilies and irises in his wife's hair.

Then, as if he had suddenly seen something to hunt, he crept on all-fours quietly close to the water again. Marie was not attending; it was so delicious to sit and do nothing in the August heat. Suddenly she screamed and looked with horror at her hand. A cold, wet frog was sitting in it!

“Don't you like frogs?” asked Pierre surprised; he had always liked them himself.

“Yes, but not in my hand.”

“What a mistake! They are such jolly things to watch. Look at him; isn't he handsome?”

But he relieved her of the handsome clamminess and let it go back to its pool to the joy of two of the party.

So they went on with the walk and the talk, Marie wearing her startling crown, till they reached the road again and their bicycles.

In mid-August, having gone round Paris by far woodland ways, they came to Chantilly in the north, a town buried in immense forests, where nowadays racehorses always peep at passers-by from their lordly stables. Marie and Pierre were due to join the family at a farm in the woods called “La Biche,” or The Hind. There they found Bronia, Casimir and baby Hélène, whom everyone called Lou; Grannie Dluska, Professor Sklodovski and Hela.

A farm in those woods has a charm of its own; never a sound comes near except the barking of a dog, the snapping of a branch, a woodman's distant axe against a tree-trunk, a hasty flutter of a startled pheasant or the skurry of a hare. Everywhere, as far as a man can walk or an eye can see, is an invitation to come in May, for the earth is hidden under the yellow, withering leaves of lilies-of-thevalley.

Inside the farm they talked apace, and often with Lou, who was beautiful, comic and gay and three years old. Sometimes they talked of solemn science with Professor Sklodovski and sometimes of the mysteries of bringing up children. Sometimes they discussed medicine and politics with Pierre's father and mother, who came from Sceaux on visits. France is the land for great talk, and often Marie was surprised to hear with what terrible vigour her French father-in-law and his friends talked politics. Politics were their very life; they cared intensely how their country was governed, and in free France they could say what they liked, which made their talk interesting. But Pierre was different. He disliked politics, because he said he was not clever at getting angry. But when a policy was unjust or cruel, he took sides—the side of the oppressed and persecuted.

So the honeymoon came to an end and Pierre and Marie settled to housekeeping in a Paris flat, and a strange, uncommon housekeeping it was! There were to be no visitors, so there were only two chairs. If a mistaken stranger toiled up the four storey's to pay a formal call and found the couple at home working, he had only to look round for a seat to see, without being told, that there was no place for him. The most pushing would beat a retreat in humbler mood. The Curies did not intend to have time to entertain. Marie, at any rate, would have, as it was, to do the work of two women: the work of a wife, which most wives find enough, and that of a scientist, which most scientists find more than enough.

She determined to make her home as simple and as little time-wasting as possible. There were to be no rugs to shake, no armchair or sofa to brush, nothing on the walls to dust, nothing to polish. The table, the two chairs and the bookshelf were of unpolished deal, which is a pleasant, untroublesome wood. The room depended on simplicity and a vase of fresh flowers for its beauty, while books, a lamp and piles of papers on physics showed it to be a scholar's den. Two people who loved one another, who loved Nature and learning, could desire nothing more. Yet they had to be fed. Doubtless that seemed a pity to them both, but Marie would not again neglect facts.

The first thing she bought to help her with her housekeeping was a black notebook with Accounts printed in letters of gold on the cover. She knew that faultless household arithmetic was a most important foundation of a happy home, especially of a home that had to be run on £240 a year exactly.

Her cooking would have to be faultless, too, or Pierre's digestion would go wrong. In addition, she had to find some scheme by which the dinner would cook itself while she spent most of the day at the laboratory doing science. Facts are fierce, strong things, but brains can use them against themselves. The first point was to make the day long. She got up early to go to market; she came home to make the bed and sweep the floor and prepare the evening dinner. Oh, that cooking! She had taken cooking lessons from Bronia and Madame Dluska before her marriage, but one doesn't learn much from lessons; mistakes are far better teachers. It was all very well that Pierre didn't know what he ate, and was as pleased when the dinner was wrong as when it was right, but Marie couldn't bear the idea that her French mother-in-law, a member of that famous cooking nation, might think that Polish girls couldn't cook. She read over and over again her book of recipes, she learned them as if they were science; she wrote notes in the margin and kept a record of her successes and failures. But there are things that printed recipes forget to tell you. Does one put beef to boil in hot or cold water? How long do beans take to boil? What keeps a stick of macaroni from sticking fast to the next piece? Those were mysteries needing a scientific experiment. Little by little, Marie grew clever; she invented dishes that could be left on the gas to cook while she was out; she calculated exactly the height of the gas flame that this or that stew would need for such and such hours; and, having set her burner exactly, she left the house and spent eight hours at the laboratory. Let no one say that a knowledge of science is no use for cooking.

When she walked home with Pierre in the evening, she bought the groceries or the fruit. Then at home, dinner over, her household work finished and expenditure entered in the notebook, she took out her books to study for another degree, and went on with it till two in the morning. It was a long day that stretched from 6.0 a.m. to 2.0 a.m. But still she was able to write to her brother: “All is well with us—health good and life kind. I am getting the flat gradually as I want it, but I intend that it shall be so simple it won't give us any worries or need any looking after, because I have very little help. A woman comes for an hour a day to wash-up and do the hardest part of the work.”

They had no excitements. They went frequently to see Pierre's parents at Sceaux, but they took their work with them and had two rooms set apart for them so that they might be just as if they were at home, just as hard-working. They scarcely ever went to the theatre and they went to nothing else. They could not even afford to go to Hela's wedding in Warsaw. They worked the year round with only a few days' holiday at Easter, till it was August again and Marie's examination in full swing.

Again she passed first on the list. Pierre threw an arm proudly round her neck and marched her home. No sooner had they arrived there than they pumped their bicycles, filled their bags, and set off for the mountains of Auvergne.

Marie wrote of that holiday: “What a radiant memory we have of a certain sunny day, when after a long, painful climb, we found ourselves crossing a fresh green Aubracian meadow in the clear air of those high tablelands. Another vivid memory is of an evening when we were caught by twilight in the gorge of the Truyère, and up the valley came, as by enchantment, a far-away melody from a boat disappearing down the stream. We had miscalculated our distances and couldn't get back to our beds before dawn. Then we met a string of carts whose horses took fright at our bicycles and obliged us to cut across ploughed fields. When we got back to the road high tableland was bathed in the moon's unreal light and the cows, in the paddock for the night, came gravely across one by one to gaze at us with their big, calm eyes.”

After holiday came work again, and life went on teaching Marie Curie as it had taught Manya Sklodovski, with great blows of hardship, that the best things in the world have to be paid for dearly.

Marie wanted a baby as much as she wanted Science, and as much as she wanted to be able to share everything with Pierre.

But she found that this time she just couldn't do everything. She could not stand eight hours studying the magnetization of steel, and she could not bicycle all day with Pierre among the blue bays of Brittany. She was surprised and disgusted to find that she had to yield to some things. When her father came from Poland on purpose to give her an early holiday, Pierre wrote her charming letters in simple Polish, because he was finding the language difficult, but was proud of his progress.

“My little girl, so dear, so sweet, whom I love so much. I got your letter to-day and I am very happy. Here, there is nothing new, except that I miss you; my very soul has fled with you.” And Marie answered, making her Polish easy for him: “It is fine. The sun is shining. It is hot. I am very sad without you. Come quickly. I sit watching from morn till eve and still you do not come. I am well. I work as much as I can, but Poincaré's book is harder than I expected. I must talk to you about it and we must go over together what I have found so hard.”

Then Irène came to add to Marie's work and joy. She called her her little queen; fed her herself; washed and dressed her, and would have done without a nurse had not the doctor ordered her to have one.

So now Marie had four things to take all her time instead of three: the laboratory, her husband, her house and her daughter. When she wanted to work, Irène was cutting her teeth and crying the house down; or Irène had a cold, or she had knocked her head, or she was a little feverish. Then both the great scientists, who happened to be her father and mother, had to sit up all night to watch a blue-eyed scrap. Sometimes, even when Irène was quite well, Marie, busy with science at the laboratory, would be seized with panic, leave her reports and rush off to the park to see if Nurse had mislaid her baby. No! There was Nurse pushing the pram with Irène safely inside. When Nurse left, Irène found a devoted slave in her grandfather, with whom Marie could leave her whenever the laboratory was having its turn.

But no one can wonder that Irène's mother grew thin. She was lucky, however, and thinness made her more beautiful than ever, with a sort of noble, ghostly beauty. She was almost unreal, as if the wind might have blown her away, except for her great brow and intense dreamy eyes.

Chapter XII　A Light in the Dark

SO the mysterious and radiant stranger had a name, but no one had yet seen its face, not even Pierre and Marie who had given it its name of Radium. It had not, like all respectable and real substances, been touched, seen, put in a bottle, or even weighed. That question of weighing was very important. Weight—“atomic weight” —was to a scientist the very proof of existence. Something existing in the mind of Pierre and Marie, whose atomic weight even they did not know, was not scientifically there at all in the opinion of the scientists. No, Pierre and Marie had to get hold of Radium and weigh it. When they had done that, scientists would believe in it.

“It is in pitchblende,” thought the Curies, “and it is too small to be seen; but perhaps if we could get hold of an enormous quantity of pitchblende and extract all the Radium from it, we should have a piece large enough to see.”

But how were they to get hold of a really enormous quantity of pitchblende, say a hundred tons? And where could they put it if they had it? And how could they work on it even if they could house it?

The scientist takes one step at a time. First let them get hold of the pitchblende. They knew where great quantities were to be found, because the Bohemians used it in the manufacture of their beautiful glass; but it was expensive and the Curies had no money worth talking about. But the Bohemians did not, of course, make glass of pitchblende itself; they extracted Uranium from it for the manufacture of glass and threw out the useless dust in mighty powdery heaps in the forest of St. Joachimsthal. “Radium and Polonium,” said the Curies, “are not in Uranium; so they must be in that waste dust. Perhaps the manufacturers could be persuaded to sell their waste dust cheap.”

“Sell?” said the manufacturers kindly. “We'll give it to you if you will pay for taking it away.”Even that transport was expensive enough, but the Curies poured out their savings and sent them to Bohemia.

That was settled. The dust would be arriving, whole railway trucks of it. Where in the world would they put it?

Pierre and Marie went round to the great home of Science, the Sorbonne. Surely in that vast set of buildings, some unwanted room could be found for their valuable and exciting dust; but no! They had to go back to their own school of physics and even there nothing satisfactory could be spared them. The only place available was a shed on the other side of the courtyard from their laboratory. And what a shed! The glass roof was broken and the rain would rain through and upset any experiment that had to be kept dry. There was no floor, only a badly tarred surface; there was no furniture, except an old kitchen table or two, a blackboard and an old stove with a rusty iron chimney. In summer the workers would be cooked, because the roof was of glass. In winter, they would freeze when the outside world froze, because the stove gave no heat; or they would be soaked if it happened to rain. Not that that mattered much, for the room was not fitted with a fume cupboard to carry away the poisonous fumes, so that most of their work would have to be done out of doors. Still “Beggars can't be choosers,” says an old adage, so the Curies settled down to making the shed do.

The great morning came. The heavy cart horses with their bells and pointed black fur collars, brought their big coal cart to rest outside the school of physics. Perhaps they looked round surprised at the eager pair who rushed out hatless, in science overalls, with exclamations of joy to welcome their load. Not so was coal generally received.

But the load was not coal; it was sacks of brown dust. Marie could not wait for the sacks to be carried in; excitedly, in the street under the horses' solemn eyes, she seized the string with which one was tied and began to tear it undone. This was pitchblende! Her pitchblende! Or rather the part of pitchblende that mattered. Curiosity was in her heart, her eyes, her tingling, working fingers. At last, she was able to plunge both hands into the brown, dullcoloured dust and pine-needles from the Bohemian pine forest. Was Radium, the radiant stranger, really in that? Would she tind stars in the dust? Marie was going to get it out, even if she had to boil down mountains of that dingy dust.

The first ton of sacks was carried into the shed and the work began, four years' work, the best and happiest and hardest years of Marie's life.

In a great iron cauldron, she boiled down the dust, stirring it perpetually with an iron rod nearly as tall as herself. She stuck to her work all day long, even eating at the shed so as not to interrupt her task. She might have been seen any day, her hair blowing in the wind, her dusty overall flecked and tattered with acids, stirring her ill-tempered mud. She had chosen the man's work of hard manual labour out of doors, while Pierre sat at the table indoors trying to discover the properties of Radium by means of delicate, precise experiments. Sometimes she worked more than forty pounds of dust at a time, filling the shed with great pots of precipitates and liquids. She carried heavy weights, lifted pots to pour their contents into others and stirred and stirred the boiling cauldron.

After an entire day spent at the shed, with such hard work as that, Marie had her nursery work at home. She washed Irène and put her to bed and hoped to be able to go and sit in the study with Pierre. But Irène thought differently. No sooner was Marie's back turned, than a little piteous “Mé” came from the nursery… “Mé!” So back went Marie to sit with her baby till she slept. Pierre was not pleased about that; he wanted Marie's time too. But when Irène was asleep husband and wife sat together studying far into the night.

When to-morrow came, they worked again. Where was that Radium? Would they never see it? The days lengthened into months; the months were more than twelve and the second year was slipping into the third, and the third into the fourth. They worked as in a dream, thinking only of one thing, talking only of one thing.” What will it be like when we do see it?” asked Marie one day when she was taking a little time off to pace up and down the courtyard with Pierre.

“'I hope it will be a beautiful color,” said Pierre.

In 1900, a French chemist, André Debierne, came to help them and discovered, before ever. they had caught a glimpse of Radium or Polonium, a “brother” element which he called Actinium.

Time after time, the heavy horses brought more tons of pitchblende waste to the gate. Every day with her terrible patience, Marie was extracting from it a substance in which Radium was more and more concentrated. But still it hid, still it kept itself to itself and preserved its secret.

She had terrible patience, but difficulties were crowding in on the two. She and Pierre had not enough money to live and they had not enough time to work. Pierre had to do a great deal of teaching to earn the £240 on which they lived and that took time from Radium and still was not enough to pay their expenses and those of Irène's nurse. So Pierre tried to get a university post where his work would be more advanced and better paid; where, perhaps, he would have a real laboratory, equipped with electricity for his experiments and where he would not have so many lessons a day and so many wearying corrections at night.

But, unfortunately, posts are not always given to those who do the best work; they often go to the friends of the principal or to those who know the art of praising themselves. When an opportunity came to apply for such a post, Pierre was told that, according to custom, he must go and call on each member of the appointing commit-tee. He hated doing so. Shyly he rang the door bell, asked for the member, was shown in and sat down, but when the member came, Pierre was so shy that he praised his rival and not himself in the most glowing terms. Naturally, when the day of election came, it was the rival who was elected.

But something had to be done in order to live. Pierre was able to add to his salary by obtaining a humble post of £100 a year as tutor at the Poly-technique, one of the two most famous schools of France.

Just as he did this, the University of Geneva offered him his very heart's desire, a lectureship at the university, a beautiful laboratory, all the instruments and equipment he chose to ask for. He accepted and he and Marie went to Geneva. But when they got there, they knew that they could not desert Paris, could not, simply could not, abandon Radium, that child of theirs. However badly Paris treated them, only in Paris could they work at Radium. So with apologies, Pierre abandoned his wonderful post at Geneva and returned to Paris, poverty and Radium.

We next find the two rejoicing because Pierre had obtained a post in the School of Physics, Chemistry and Natural Science and Marie one to teach girls in the Sèvres training school for elementary teachers. They were lucky young women who had Marie Curie to teach them, but it was sad that the world did not realise that the work she was doing on Radium could only be done by her, while many people might have taught Science at Sèvres. Marie prepared her lessons with the greatest care and won much praise, because they were the most original and the most fascinating lessons any of the girls had known. But her long tram rides several times a week tried her and wasted precious hours; so did the preparation of schoolgirl lessons and the weary marking of papers. It was like setting Rembrandt to paint gate-posts. Both Pierre and Marie were wearing themselves out. Would they ever see Radium?

Marie also had forgotten her good resolution to feed well after her marriage. “You scarcely eat, either of you,” wrote their doctor to Pierre. “I have more than once seen Madame Curie nibbling two thin rounds of sausage and washing it down with a cup of tea. Do you think that even a strong constitution won't suffer from such starvation?… I know what your excuse will be: ‘she is not hungry and is old enough to know what is good for her.’ She isn't! She's behaving like a baby. I am speaking with all the conviction of my friendship. You don't spend enough time on your meals…You mustn't read while you eat, or talk Physics...

One gets the impression that neither Pierre nor Marie paid the slightest attention to the doctor's good advice. There was that Radium to be brought to life in the shed of the Rue Lhomond and nothing else mattered.

At one moment Pierre suggested that they should devote themselves to a study of the proper-ties of Radium and abandon the effort to see the thing itself, but Marie would not listen.

She was getting nearer. She had ceased to boil down the rough dust. She had obtained from it something which could be kept indoors, something which, in a small space contained all the Radium of the many tons. to work upon it further, she needed delicate instruments, a science room in which there was neither dust nor damp, neither cold nor heat, nothing to upset an accurate experiment. But she had no such room, and dust, heat, cold, wind constantly undid what she did and forced her to waste time and energy doing it again. She had terrible patience.

It was the year 1902. Three years and nine months had passed since Marie had announced the probable existence of Radium. At last she had conquered the radiant stranger. She had seen stars in that dust; she had seen Radium. She had made one decigramme of it. It had weight. It had the atomic weight of 226. Chemists bowed to it.

Marie and Pierre were sitting at home in the evening and Irène had been put to bed. That four year old tyrant had consented to shut her eyes and let Mé go back to Pierre to finish making the tyrant's dress, for Mé made all Irène's clothes. Suddenly Marie put down her work: “Let's go back!” she said.

Pierre needed no asking. They had left their Radium only two hours but they longed to see it again. They wanted it as if it were a new baby. They called to Grandfather Curie that they were going out and then, arm-in-arm, through the crowded streets, past the factories of their un-fashionable district, they made their way back to Rue Lhomond and their shed.

“Don't light up,” said Marie. “Do you remember the day when you said you would like Radium to have a beautiful colour?”

In the dark of the shed, Radium had something even more lovely than colour. It had light!

“Look! look!” whispered Marie, as she felt her way to a chair and sat gazing round her.

There were tiny points of light in the dark room, like pale blue moonlight dancing on water, specks of light that were never still. On the table, on the shelves were those strange, mysterious radiances. In its little receptacles there was Radium visible at last, visible by its own light in the dark.

Chapter XIII　Not for Sale

THE whole world was excited! Something entirely new had come into people's everyday life, something that made them change their thoughts about many things. It was not only scientists who talked about Radium: children discussed it on their way home from school; women, who had been disappointed for long, long ages because men had made all the greatest discoveries, rejoiced aloud, that at last it had happened to a woman to discover a new and wonderful thing. But, at first, no one dreamed how wonderful Radium was going to be.

Letters came in packed masses to the two Curies from famous scholars in England, Denmark, Germany and Austria, asking for information about the new discovery. Scientists everywhere took up the study of Radium and found out more about its characteristics and those of its near relations. Two Englishmen, Ramsay and Soddy, found that it threw off from itself tiny quantities of a new gas, which they called Helium. In other words, Raduim had the capacity of becoming Helium. That was something very startling. Scientists had been accustomed to laugh at the Medieval Alchemists who believed that they could turn iron into gold. A picture of the alchemist's mysterious smoky cave was a picture of a dream of the impossible. Things, the scientists had said, were themselves, with their own chemical composition and their own atomic weight. Now they had to face the fact that Radium made Helium out of itself, and they wondered what other things might also be occupied with creating new substances. Perhaps the ghosts of the alchemists were laughing at the chemists.

At any rate, to turn iron into gold was no more remarkable a feat than the feats of which this Radium was capable. It looked like dull table salt, but it was two million times more radiant than Uranium. The rays that it gave out could go through every solid metal except lead. It was accompanied by its shadow—a spirit that was so alive and active that even when it was shut up in a glass tube, it destroyed a quarter of itself in a day. It could produce heat of itself, enough heat to melt in an hour a piece of ice of its own weight. If you shut it away from the cold, it would grow hotter than the day. If you shut it in glass, it would turn the glass mauve or violet. If you wrapped it in paper or cotton wool, it ate them. If you had no candle in the dark, it gave you enough light to read by.

One of the most wonderful things about this Radium was that it did not even stick to its own light; it handed it on to everything, that came in its way, even though such generosity was often most inconvenient.

It showed a sudden interest in human affairs in that it lent its luminosity to real diamonds, but turned its nose up at paste. Diamond buyers could use it to test the genuineness of their purchases.

Poor Marie found its interference in all her experiments most distracting. Nothing could be left near a tube of Radium without becoming radio-active; it presented its luminosity to the air, the dust, Marie's clothes, her instruments, her notebooks. Those last kept the luminosity they had not been able to refuse, long after she was dead.

Scientists probably enjoy having their ideas upset, so those early years of the baby Radium must have been happy ones for them. Not only did that strange Radium create a new element out of itself, but that new element again made something new, and so on. The radio-elements formed strange faculties in which each member was created by the transformation of the substance of its mother. But the scientists' shocks did not end there. They found that each radio-element lost half of itself in a given time, a time which was always the same, a time so long that we need not worry about finding ourselves bereft of the radio elements. Uranium, to lose half of itself, takes a few milliards of years, and a milliard is a million-million. To do the same thing, Radium takes only 1,600 years, while its spirit takes only four days and its spirit's children only a few seconds.

You could look at Radium and see it lying quite still and yet know that, while you were gazing at it; its strange children were being born, were being murdered or committing suicide, or merely colliding with one another.

Then suddenly something altogether new happened to this active stranger as if enough things hadn't happened already. Pierre, exploring still, let it burn him. The skin of his hand became red but didn't hurt. It became redder. On the twentieth day a crust formed as on an ordinary fire burn. Then a sore appeared. On the forty-second day the sore began to heal on the outside edge.

Then Marie, though she had not meant to burn herself, found that her Radium had burnt her, though it was in a glass tube and the tube was in a tin box.

Then their friend Becquerel, going home with a tube of it in his jacket pocket, was quite seriously burnt.

“Your abominable child.” he exclaimed to Marie. “What has it burnt me for? I love the thing, but I've a bone to pick with it.” Marie, too, might have had a bone to pick with the thing she loved, because the tips of her fingers hurt horribly and lost their skin.

But soon people began to look kindly on Radium's burns because they healed so well. Doctors became immensely interested in it. They set it to burn away terribly sick skin and, when the burn was healed, the illness had gone too. A wild great hope began for the world. Perhaps Radium could be persuaded to burn away cancer.

At any rate, Radium had been proved to be useful People were wanting to buy it. Marie, out of eight tons of pitchblende had made one gramme of Radium. It was worth £30,000, but it was not for sale. Marie would treasure it while she lived and leave it to her laboratory as a precious symbol of years of great work and a great triumph.

One Sunday morning as Pierre and Marie were sitting at home in the Boulevard Kellerman, the postman left a letter with an American stamp for Pierre. He read it carefully, folded it, and put it on his desk.

“We'll have to talk,” he said, “about this Radium. It is going to be manufactured on a large scale. They have written from Buffalo to ask for information about it.”

“Well?” Marie was a little bored.

“Well, we can choose… We can describe quite openly and frankly all our results and methods of making it…”

“Of course,” smiled Marie.

“'Or,” went on Pierre, paying no attention to the interruption, “we can consider ourselves as the owners of our knowledge, the inventors of Radium. If we do that, before we publish our method of extracting Radium from pitchblende, we must take out a patent and draw a profit from the manufacture of Radium in the whole world.”

As he spoke, it was quite clear to them both that immense wealth was theirs for the accepting. A patent on the manufacture of Radium would give them enough money to build a great laboratory and to buy Radium for research. What things they could do if they were rich!

Marie thought for a little, and then said: “That is impossible; that would be against the spirit of science.”

Pierre agreed, but he told her to think carefully, because the decision once made could not be reconsidered. He reminded her about the laboratory they both wanted and about the future of their daughter. Was she sure she did not want to be rich?

Marie knew the great old custom of the scientists, the custom that people like Pasteur had followed, and she said: “Physicists always publish their researches. It is only a chance that our discovery has a money value. We can't use a chance like that for profit. And Radium is going to help the sick. It seems impossible to me to seek any profit from it.”

Again Pierre agreed that it would be contrary to the scientific spirit to sell their knowledge of Radium. He wrote that very night and gave the Americans all the information they wanted.

So, without a moment's regret, Pierre and Marie turned their backs for ever upon the millionaire's faery fortune. Their Radium was not for sale.

The scientific spirit had given Radium to them and to the world, and however low the spirit of the world sinks, it still loves the scientific spirit which gives all its knowledge freely to all men without price. Having chosen poverty when they might have chosen fortune, Marie and Pierre took their bicycles and went for thier ordinary ride through the summer woods to gether wild flowers for their room.

Chapter XIV　Darkness

MARIE and Pierre were famous. France offered them prizes. England sent them an invitation. They carried from France a gift for their English friend, Lord Kelvin, a gift of a tiny particle of radium in a glass phial, which he showed with childish glee to his scientific friends. Pierre was to lecture on Radium to the Royal Institute, and Marie was to be the first woman ever to be admitted to a meeting of that severe and splendid Society. Never had there been so gay a lecture there, for Pierre made the wizard Radium show its strange tricks to the solemn assembly of all the most learned Englishmen. The Royal Society was enchanted, and all London was agog to see the two “parents” of radium. There were banquets in their honor, and the noble and the rich glimmered in pearls and diamonds as they gazed in astonishment at that strange thing—a woman scientist, who dined at night in a simple black dress unrelieved by a single jewel, and whose hands, scarred with acids, were bare of any ring; but she looked no less distinguished than they, with her thin figure, her inspired face, and her great pale forehead over those intense eyes. Marie, herself, loved the glitter around her, but she was a little surprised to see the usually indifferent Pierre apparently absorbed in the dazzling scene.

“Aren't jewels pretty things?” she asked him. “I never dreamed such lovely ones existed.”

Pierre laughed. “Do you know,” he said, “at dinner I hadn't anything to do with my mind so I spent the time working out how many laboratories could have been built and equipped with the price of those jewels!”

No! The Curies were certainly “different.” They understood a substance that gave out its own light, but not jewelled reflectors. They didn't even know what to do with a gold medal when the Royal Society honoured Marie with the Davy Medal. Pierre gave it to Irène as a thoroughly safe and biteable plaything, and she adored it.

They knew still less what to do with fame and crowds and applause and journalists. Marie could only be miserable about them.

On December 10th, 1903, she was awarded half the Nobel Prize for Science. Henri Becquerel had the other half. She was the first woman to be thus honoured in science, but not a word of excitement escaped her. She rejoiced in the real part of the prize: the recognition by her fellow-scientists of her work and the gentle pleasure of having some money to spend; but the glitter and the tinsel, fame, letters of congratulation from strangers, demands for autographs, requests for interviews from photographers and journalists—those things she hated. “I would like to bury myself to get a little peace,” she wrote.

She enjoyed spending the money, and how she spent it showed her in all her sincerity and charm. She banked some of it, so that the family income from it might pay someone to help in the laboratory and also enable Pierre to give up his teaching at the School of Physics and so have time to do research. She gave a large gift to the sanatorium which the Dluskis had founded in Poland. She gave presents to Pierre's brother and her own sisters; she paid subscriptions to scientific societies; she helped some Polish students, her laboratory boys, and a Sèvres girl who was in need. Then she remembered an old French teacher of her own who lived in Poland, who had a lovely, impossible day-dream—that of visiting just once again her dear France. Marie wrote to her, sent her the money for her journey, and invited her to come and stay with her. The old woman wept with joy at the immense unexpected pleasure. Last of all, Marie gave herself a present—a modern bathroom in her house in the Boulevard Kellerman, and new paper for one of her sitting-rooms.

But oh! The foolish crowd! Instead of collecting money to build a laboratory so that the Curies might find out more about Radium, they wasted Marie's time, forced her to play hide-and-seek in the street in order to get into her own house unmolested; published in the newspapers all the little details of their home-life that the Curies loved and would have liked to keep to themselves, even the baby-words that Irène said to her nurse, even the colour of the roof cat. Marie exclaimed, “They prevent our working. Our life is spoilt with honour and glory!” And she meant it. She was shy, and very busy, and the senseless crowd was making her really ill. Once, when the Curies were dining with the French President, a lady went up to Marie and asked if she should present her to the King of Greece. “I don't see the necessity,” said Marie, gently, and then perceived, in an overwhelming glance, that the lady was Mme. Loubet, the wife of the President, and that she was very surprised indeed. “Of course… of course, naturally I'll do anything you like,” she stammered, blushing. To meet kings is a pleasure to so many people, but Marie was different. She was tired and she was young. She wanted a holiday, just to be gay and free and happy, and to be an ordinary mother and an ordinary wife. She wished Irène's whooping-cough wouldn't take so many months to go away and that Pierre's illness wouldn't frighten her. Since she had danced in Poland twenty years before, her life had been nothing but work, and never had she so longed to do nothing, to forget that she was the famous Mme. Curie, and to be mere Manya again and eat too many strawberries and sleep and do nothing.

But Pierre was in a hurry. There was so much work to do. He couldn't understand Marie's holiday spirit—that was something altogether too girlish, altogether too unscientific. They must devote themselves to science, he told her, and she obeyed. She always obeyed him. But she was terribly tired, so tired that she almost didn't want her new baby, Eve. “Poor little thing,” she said, “to have to live in so hard a world as this.” It was indeed a cruel thing that the hunters and pursuers should have taken all her gaiety and courage, even from Manya.

But Eve did her good, for she loved very new babies, and she was obliged to have the month's holiday that Eve gave her—Eve, with the dark hair and blue eyes, who was so different from Irène, of the fair hair and hazel eyes. Eve wouldn't lie in her cradle, but protested vigorously, and Marie was not a model mother who left her to cry, but a soft-hearted one who took her up and carried her about till she slept.

Just before the coming of Eve, an odd privilege had been granted to Marie by the University of Paris, the right to work in Pierre's laboratory. She had been working there all the time, but suddenly the University woke up and gave her an appointment which allowed her to do so—the appointment of “Physics Organiser” under M. Curie at a salary of £96 a year. The University acknowledged, what everyone else had known for a long time, that the Curies always worked together. All their time and their thoughts and their work were quite naturally shared, just as if they were one happy person.

In June, 1905, Pierre and Marie went to beautiful Stockholm, where Pierre had to make a speech, in both their names, in connection with the Nobel Prize. He described Sweden rather. charmingly, as composed of lakes and fjords surrounded by a little dry land, and the two enjoyed the uncrowded calm of the vast spaces and the courtesy of a nation which did not press upon them.

But Marie sometimes made friends with strangers. There was an American baller dancer, Loïe Fuller, who used strange lighting to make her dancing more beautiful. She wrote to Marie to ask how she could use Radium to light her butterfly wings. Pierre and Marie laughed at the wild idea, but wrote back very gently explaining the queer thing that was Radium. Loïe replied that she had only one way of thanking them for their letter—to come and dance to them in their own home. The Curies accepted that uncommon thanks, and on the day there appeared at their door an odd-looking girl with baby-blue eyes and an army of electricians. All day the electricians worked. By the evening the Curies' dining-room was transformed into a fairyland of strange lights, and Loïe danced, making herself by turns flame, flower, bird, and witch.

The little music-hall dancer became a great friend, and took the Curies to introduce them to her friend, Rodin, the great sculptor, and there, in his studio, among the casts and marbles, Science, Sculpture and Dance would sit and talk the evening out.

Then came April, 1906. The hot sun of April in France drew their scent from the violets, purple and white, that coloured the hedgerows in the valley of the Chevreuse. Marie and Pierre, Irène and Eve, were on holiday. In the evening they fetched the milk from the farm; Eve, the little mountebank, making them all laugh as she tottered in the dry cart-ruts. In the mornings, Pierre and Marie, on their bicycles, hunted flowers through the woods and revisited the pond, which they had met on their honeymoon. It was dry and the water-lilies had gone, but yellow-flowering reeds circled the mud with a bright startling crown. And Marie and Pierre, wandering home, gathered violets and powder-blue periwinkle from the banks of the sunken lanes.

At noon on another day they lay in the sun and dreamed, while Irène chased butterflies with a green net, greeting them with high-pitched cries and squeals of glee.

“Life has been sweet with you, Marie,” murmured Pierre.

Then, after dinner, he caught the train to Paris and work, carrying with him the yellow ranunculus they had gathered by the pond. The others joined him the next day, and April, as is the way with April, had turned wet and cold.

The day after Marie and the children came home was April the 19th, 1906—a wet day, with muddy, slippery streets, a cloudy day and dark. Pierre had several engagements in the city; Marie had to get the house in order after the holidays, and many things to do in town. Busily, gaily, she went hither and yon. Six o'clock found her back on her own doorstep, happy to be home again, eager to meet Pierre and to begin another of those delicious evenings working with him at scientific calculations.

She opened the drawing-room door. Three men rose and stood, with deep respect in their attitude; just that, as if she had been a queen; and in their eyes she read a terrible pity. Paul Appell, her old teacher, had to tell her that Pierre had slipped in the street and the wheel of a heavy horse-drawn dray had crushed his head.

“Pierre is dead?… dead? Really dead?” she said.

When Eve grew up, she told us, in the lovely life she wrote of her mother, that from the moment she spoke the words “Pierre est mort,” a cloak of solitude and secrecy enveloped Marie, and that from that April day for ever she was a person apart and lonely.

Chapter XV　Whatever Happens

MARIE was born to have glorious courage. All her life she had had to call upon her valiancy, and it had grown strong and would not fail her. Moreover, she had truly loved a great man, and Pierre had left her a word to remember and to obey when her world fell to pieces around her. “Whatever might happen,” he had said, one day when they were talking of death, “whatever might happen, and even though one might be like an empty body, whose spirit was dead, it would be one's duty to go on working all the same.” So Marie, fortunately, had to go on working. When a pension was offered her, she refused it, saying she was young enough to earn for herself and her children.

She found an odd little way of comfort which seems to make her all the dearer to us: she wrote her diary as if she were speaking to Pierre:

“They have offered to let me take your place, my Pierre: your lectures and the direction of your laboratory. I have accepted. I don't know if I have done right or wrong. You have often told me that you would like me to give a course of lectures at the Sorbonne. And I would at least like to try to continue your work. At one moment that seems the easiest way to go on living; at another I seem a fool to undertake it.”

“May 7th, 1906:

“My Pierre, I think of you all the time; my head is bursting with the thought of you, and my reason fails. I can't understand that I have to live without you and that I can't smile at my dear life's companion. The trees have been in leaf two days now and the garden is beautiful. This morning I was admiring the children in it. I thought how beautiful you would have thought them and that you would have called me to show me that the periwinkles and narcissus were out…

“May 14th: I want to tell you that they have nominated me to your chair of Physics at the Sorbonne and that there are people imbecile enough to congratulate me on it.” Marie was not too crushed to feel fierce rage at fools.

No woman had ever had the honour of a university chair at the Sorbonne; that is, no woman had been made head of a teaching staff in any subject. But there was no man in France capable of taking over Pierre's work, so it fell naturally to Marie. She alone of living scientists had the genius for it. She determined that her lectures should be worthy of Pierre, so she sent the children to the country and stayed all summer in Paris working on Pierre's subject, on Pierre's notes.

She needed another house and decided to go and live at Sceaux where Pierre was buried. The children's grandfather was a little scared that, when she moved to a smaller house, she would not want him. How could he ask the question? Marie was also a little scared that he would not want to live with a mere daughter-in-law now that his son was dead. The old man tackled the difficult question: “Now that Pierre isn't here, Marie, you have no reason for living with an old man. I can quite well go and live with my eldest son. It is for you to decide.”

“No, you must decide,” Marie whispered. “If you go, you will grieve me. But you must choose what you prefer.”

“What I prefer, Marie, is to stay with you always.”

But the day had to come when Marie would have to go outside her home again where everyone treated her grief with tenderness and respect, and face the outside world where she was now an exciting and famous widow. She knew that the newspapers were asking the Sorbonne to change its rules and make her lecture in the great amphitheatre so that many thousands might hear the first woman to lecture in the Sorbonne. She was probably glad that the Sorbonne was one of the most conservative places on earth and was not likely to change its rules. She had heard that the fashionable crowd, that wished to be present, were discussing what she would say and how she would refer to her husband, because it was the university custom for every new holder of a chair to praise his predecessor. It was the custom to thank the Minister, to thank the university. When the day of its inaugural lecture came, the crowd was waiting, like birds of prey, to hear Marie say something moving, perhaps to see her break down. It was the small amphitheatre, but they thronged it, crushing the real students who were there to learn, even pushing them out of their seats.

Marie entered quickly amid deafening applause. As soon as there was silence, she began her lecture in advanced Physics simply at the place where Pierre had left off: “When we consider the progress which has taken place in physics during the last ten years, we are surprised at the change in our ideas concerning electricity and matter…

The audience was surprised indeed, but at the change in their ideas about something other than electricity. They had gone to see a show; they found themselves meeting a woman, who was no show, but a truly sincere human being who thought more about her work than about herself. They were touched. Tears welled up into their eyes. Marie spoke of the new theories of the structure of electricity, of the disintegration of the atom and of radio-active bodies. At the end of her lecture, which was addressed purely to the students, she left the hall as quickly and as simply as she had entered it.

If her work had been hard before, it became harder. She had to think out how to educate the little girls. She had her work of discovery in the laboratory and her lectures at the Sorbonne. She had her house and garden to see to and, above all, she had a special work of her own to do. She had by some means to get a laboratory built in honour of Pierre, something wonderful and perfect it was to be—the laboratory of his dreams.

Eve and Irène played with their blue-eyed grandfather in the new house at Sceaux. He taught Irène botany and natural history and poetry, and helped her to dig her own garden patch and to plant the right flowers, while Eve made friends with her pet tortoise in the grass or romped with the black or with the tabby cat.

But Marie hastened early in the morning, with that quick, business-like step of hers, to catch the Paris train and did not return till the lights were lit in the evenings. The children did not see much of their mother, but it was she who planned the day the children spent. They had to work for an hour at the beginning of the morning. Irène loved figures and Eve music. After that, they went for a walk in all weathers and then to gym, which they loved. Then they cooked or modelled or sewed or gardened or, on a Saturday and Sunday, or in the holidays, they went out bicycling or swimming with their mother. She meant them to be strong and fearless. They were not allowed to be afraid of the dark or of accidents or of climbing, or of riding, or of animals or of anything. Brave and bold they should be and French. She taught them Polish, but she did not want them to have the unhappiness she had had of feeling themselves part of two nations and one a sad and persecuted country. Only one thing she left out of their educationm—the art of welcoming strangers and being charming at parties. In those things, they had no practice.

Marie did not want her children overworked and hours in French schools are very long, sometimes six hours at school followed by three hours' homework.

Marie and her university friends often talked on the subject and they decided to pool their children and teach them themselves. It was a glorious idea. Those lucky children were to have one lesson a day, but it was to be given by the greatest specialist in Paris. On the first morning they were to go to the Sorbonne laboratory where Jean Perrin taught them chemistry. “The Sorbonne hasn't yet been blown up,” said the newspaper, “but we haven't yet lost all hope.” On the next day they went into the country to be taught mathematics by Paul Langevin; on the next to the sculptor, Magrou, to learn modelling; on another to a professor of modern languages and literature, and on Thursday afternoon to the School of Physics to be taught by Marie Curie. Lucky brats!

In that stately place which had never before heard an easy lesson, they dropped inky bicycle bearings on sloping white boards to see with their own eyes the curves that falling bodies make. Or, Marie asked them such dark questions as: “What must I do to keep the heat in this liquid in this pan?”

“Wrap it in wool,” said one.

“Isolate it,” suggested another.

“I,” smiled Marie, “would begin by putting on the lid.”

Unfortunately however, parents have to be busy earning the family income and have no time to give their own children enchanting lessons. Those delicious lessons ceased, and Eve and Irène went to school where the hours were not quite so long as in most schools. They said in after-life that from those early lessons they learnt to like work, to be indifferent to money and to be so independent that they were convinced that they could pull themselves out of any difficulty.

In the laboratory, among many new triumphs, Marie had one very great triumph. Up to that time she had made only the salts of Radium. On one occasion she and André Debierne succeeded in making Radium metal. They succeeded once. Neither they nor anyone else has ever done it again.

In 1911 Marie was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry. No person before her had ever received two Nobel prizes.

One would have thought that all the world would have gloried in her as a scientist and treated her gently as a sad woman. But, unfortunately, there is a strange disease which causes certain people to feel very cruel when they hear of someone being very successful or very beautiful. Marie was both, and suddenly people began to write her anonymous letters and to tell extraordinary lies about her and to accuse her of doing wrong. things of which she had never dreamed. Her friends tried to protect her; but it is difficult to fight against enemies who hide. They felt that the best protection would be for the Academy of Science to give her an open honour by making her a member. It was her due, but no woman had ever been a member. The liars redoubled their efforts to prevent the election. They even went the length of putting a false voting paper into the hand of a blind man, her friend, so that he might seem to oppose her. The Academy of Science, to its lasting disgrace, rejected her by one vote.

Marie was terribly unhappy about the lies. For a time she had to borrow her sister's name to escape from her enemies. She was as open as the day and this attack from the people who skulked in darkness made her ill. It almost destroyed that famous courage of hers, but not quite. She was very ill and in great pain. The surgeons said an operation would save her from pain, but she told them to wait till after she had attended the next Physics Congress. Her courage was still there.

Then when she was still ill there came to her a great decision to make. She was tired and wanted not to have to think, but Poland had decided to build a great laboratory of radio-activity at War-saw, and invited her to be the head of it. How she longed to accept! What an invitation it was! She was told that Poland needed her, that her country was growing discouraged and needed something to make it believe in itself again.

But long years before Marie had decided that greatly though she loved Poland, she loved Pierre Curie more. She still loved him more, and Poland and he were still pulling in opposite directions. If Marie gave herself to Poland, she would have to give up the hope of building Pierre's laboratory. Without her presence in France, Pierre's dream would never come true. She refused Poland sadly.

But Poland insisted that she should direct the new laboratory from a distance and go to the opening of the new building. Many exciting things befell her during that visit. First, she gave an address on Science in Polish, and it was the first time in her life that she had ever used her own tongue for a scientific speech. Secondly, she attended a great ceremony in the museum where she had done her first Physics experiments. Thirdly, at a banquet given in her honour by Polish women, she discovered the old headmistress of her first school. Hurriedly, Marie made her way through the crowd to the old lady and kissed her on both cheeks. What joy that old head-mistress must have felt at the thought that her “old girl” was without question the most famous woman!

Marie had earned a holiday. She was going to spend it walking in Switzerland with a rucksack on her back and teaching Eve and Irène to climb and to treat crevasses with proper respect.

They had a friend with them who talked Physics so enthusiastically with Marie, that the children had to keep watch over him lest he, not they, should fall into a crevasse. They listened with surprise to the odd things he said to their mother, and laughed so much that there was no one to look after the crevasses.

“You see, Madame,” they heard him say, “what I need to know is: what exactly happens to the passengers in a lift when it falls in a vacuum?” The question seemed easy to answer to Eve and Irène and very amusing. They did not guess that they were listening to that incomprehensible subject called “Relativity,” for the careless friend was none other than the great Einstein.

At that time, Marie was becoming happier again, because the walls of Pierre's Radium Institute were growing in the Rue Pierre Curie. Dr. Roux, the head of the Pasteur Institute, had pro-posed two years before to raise the money for a laboratory for Madame Curie. That made the Sorbonne wake up to the fact that the Pasteur Institute was thinking of snatching their Madame Curie from them, and, to prevent such a catastrophe, they agreed with the Pasteur Institute to share in the building of the new laboratory.

Marie was full of joy. She helped to make the plans, discussed the shape of all the rooms and windows with the architect, and insisted on having immense windows and overflowing light. She also insisted on the garden and planted the trees and roses with her own hands before the building began, so that they might be making a little show when it was opened.

In July, 1914, she was able to read on the stone over the door:

Institut du Radium Pavillon Curie.

She tells us that she thought of Pasteur's words: “If you care for those conquests that are useful to men… if you are jealous of the part which your country may claim to have played in the spread of these marvels, take an interest, I implore you, in these sacred dwellings which we call laboratories. Ask that their numbers be increased, that they may be spler lid. They are the temples of the future, temples of true wealth and well-being. It is in them that man grows great, grows strong, and grows good. There he learns to read the works of Nature, which are the works of progress and universal peace; while his own works are too often barbaric and destructive.”

So thought Marie Curie, remembering Pasteur, as she watched Pierre's completed Institute of Radium, in July, 1914. The building was ready, but Marie would have to wait four years, four years of war, before she could see work begin in the Institute of Radium and Pierre's dream come true.